<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="36"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 14  I  AUGUST 16 2024      ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





               5



                                                            30













                                                            22                                        26
















           4-Editorial: Women’s equality in focus          30-Disqualification and the fight for
           5-The Journey of Equality                       clarity

           9-A visionary leader and champion of            33-Horoscopes

           harmony                                         34-Letters

           13-Unsung heroes in crisis zones
           18-The global fight against slavery

           22-Small bite, big Impact

           26-Man's best friend through the ages












           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[A Century of Change
     EDITORIAL  Women’s equality                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           in focus                                                               Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           ntaernational Women’s Equality Day,   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           observed annually on August 26th, is
                                        Imore than just a date on the calendar—     Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        it’s a powerful reminder of the strides
                                        women have made in the pursuit of equality   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        and the challenges that remain. This day     Sushil Kumar
                                        commemorates the historic moment in 1920
                                        when women in the United States won the   Social Media Editor
                                        right to vote, a monumental victory after   Vishakha Sharma
                                        decades of tireless advocacy. However, its
                                        significance transcends national borders,   Art & Graphics Director
                                        echoing the global struggle for gender       Vipin Agarwal
                                        equality that continues to this day.
                                           Over the past century, women have
           shattered countless barriers in every sphere—politics, education, business, science,
           and the arts. Their achievements are a testament to resilience, determination, and an   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           unwavering commitment to justice. From the suffragettes who marched for the right
           to vote to modern-day activists fighting for equal pay and reproductive rights, women   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           have consistently demonstrated the power of collective action. Their efforts have not   Editor, United News of India, New
           only changed laws but also transformed societies, challenging deep-rooted   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           stereotypes and opening doors for future generations.             Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
             Women’s voices are now louder and more influential than ever, shaping policies,   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           driving economies, and leading communities. We see women at the helm of nations,   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           corporations, and social movements, using their platforms to advocate for a more   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           equitable world. These successes, however, should not overshadow the ongoing
           struggles that women face. The path to true equality remains fraught with obstacles,   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           both visible and invisible.                                            Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             Gender-based violence continues to plague societies worldwide, affecting millions
           of women and girls. Economic disparities persist, with women often earning less than   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           men for the same work and facing barriers to career advancement. Women are still
           underrepresented in leadership roles, whether in government, business, or academia.   Phone +91 20 40199102
           Additionally, threats to reproductive rights are ever-present, with many women still   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           lacking access to essential healthcare services.                          Baner Road,
             International Women’s Equality Day is not only a celebration of the progress   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           women have made but also a poignant reminder of the work that remains. It urges us   Email revoir@post.com
           to reflect on the persistent inequalities that continue to hold women back and to   Website www.revoir.in
           renew our commitment to creating a world where every woman, regardless of her
           background, has the opportunity to thrive.
             When women succeed, societies flourish. Gender equality benefits everyone—  Legal Advisor
           families, communities, and nations. As we honor the courage and contributions of   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           women past and present, we must also look forward, envisioning a future where
           equality is not just an aspiration but a reality. On this International Women’s Equality   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           Day, let us celebrate the victories, acknowledge the work that still lies ahead, and   all rights reserved. This publication
           unite in our resolve to achieve a world where equality is the norm, not the exception.   may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH



































           TRIUMPHS AND TRIALS



           The Journey of








           Equality








           By Naina Kapoor

             nternational Women’s Equality Day,   struggle for women's suffrage, equal   during immense social and political re-
             celebrated annually on August 26th,   rights, and opportunities in all spheres   sistance. Their dedication culminated in
           Iis a day dedicated to recognizing the   of life.               the ratification of the 19th Amendment
           progress made in the fight for women's                          on August 18, 1920, with the official
           rights and highlighting the ongoing ef-  Historical background: The fight   proclamation on August 26, 1920, fi-
           forts to achieve gender equality globally.   for suffrage       nally enfranchising women and marking
           This day commemorates the adoption of   The roots of International Women’s   a monumental victory for gender equal-
           the 19th Amendment in the United   Equality Day are deeply entwined with   ity.
           States in 1920, which granted American   the early 20th-century suffrage move-
           women the right to vote. However, its   ment. In the United States, women like   Global perspective
           significance extends far beyond the bor-  Susan B. Anthony, Elizabeth Cady Stan-  While the 19th Amendment was a
           ders of the U.S., symbolizing the global   ton, and Alice Paul led the charge, en-  significant milestone in the United

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[States, the struggle for women's suffrage
           and equality was a global phenomenon.
           Countries like New Zealand and Finland
           had already granted women the right to
           vote by the early 20th century, while
           others followed suit in the ensuing dec-
           ades. Each nation's journey was unique,
           yet all shared a common goal: ensuring
           that women had an equal voice in shap-
           ing their societies.

           Achievements and milestones:
           Political representation
             Since the early suffrage victories,
           women have made significant strides in
           political representation. Today, women                                                            Right: Elizabeth Cady Stanton
           hold prominent positions in govern-                                                             Left: Mother Teresa
           ments worldwide, from heads of state to
           parliamentary representatives. The pres-
           ence of women in political arenas has
           led to more inclusive policies and a
           greater focus on issues such as gender-
           based violence, healthcare, and educa-
           tion.

           Economic empowerment
             Economic empowerment is another
           critical aspect of gender equality.
           Women have made substantial gains in
           the workforce, entrepreneurship, and
           leadership roles. Efforts to close the
           gender pay gap and ensure equal oppor-
           tunities for career advancement have                                                            Suffragettes marching and protesting, New York, 1920
           shown progress, although challenges re-
           main. Initiatives like microfinance pro-
           grams have empowered women in de-
           veloping countries to start businesses
           and achieve financial independence.

           Education and healthcare
             Access to education and healthcare is
           fundamental to women's equality. Over
           the past century, there have been re-
           markable improvements in these areas.
           Literacy rates among women have risen
           dramatically, and more girls are attend-
           ing school than ever before. Ad-
           ditionally, advancements in healthcare
           have reduced maternal mortality rates
           and improved reproductive health serv-
           ices, giving women greater control over
           their bodies and futures.

           Ongoing challenges
             Despite the progress made, signifi-
           cant challenges persist in the quest for
           gender equality. International Women’s                                                          International Women’s Equality Day march
           Equality Day serves as a reminder that
           the fight is far from over.
           Gender-based violence
             Gender-based violence remains a
           pervasive issue affecting women world-

           6                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[wide. From domestic abuse to human   proportional in many countries. Women
                                           trafficking, millions of women and girls   often encounter barriers such as gender
                                           face violence and exploitation. Address-  bias, lack of support networks, and lim-
                                           ing this issue requires comprehensive   ited access to political financing. En-
                                           strategies, including legal reforms, pub-  couraging more women to participate in
                                           lic awareness campaigns, and support   politics and implementing policies to
                                           services for survivors.         support their candidacies can help
                                                                           achieve a more balanced representation.
                                           Economic inequality
                                             The gender pay gap and unequal ac-  Reproductive rights
                                           cess to economic opportunities continue   Reproductive rights are fundamental
                                           to hinder women's progress. Women are   to women's equality. Access to contra-
                                           often concentrated in lower-paying jobs   ception, safe abortion services, and
                                           and face barriers to leadership positions.   comprehensive reproductive healthcare
         Feminist equality protest         supporting female entrepreneurs are cru-  lives. However, these rights are often
                                           Ensuring equal pay for equal work, pro-
                                                                           are essential for women to make in-
                                                                           formed decisions about their bodies and
                                           moting women in STEM fields, and
                                                                           under threat due to political, religious,
                                           cial steps toward economic equality.
                                                                           and cultural opposition.
                                           Political underrepresentation
                                                                           The role of international women’s
                                             While women’s political representa-
                                                                           equality day
                                           tion has improved, it is still far from
                                                                              International Women’s Equality Day
                                                                           plays a crucial role in raising awareness
                                                                           about gender equality issues and cele-
                                                                           brating the achievements of women
                                                                           worldwide. It serves as a platform for
                                                                           advocacy, education, and reflection.

                                                                           Advocacy and activism
                                                                              On this day, activists and organiza-
                                                                           tions worldwide rally to highlight the
                                                                           importance of gender equality. Cam-
         Iconic leaders and crusaders                                      lence, pay equity, and reproductive
                                                                           paigns and events draw attention to spe-
                                                                           cific issues, such as gender-based vio-
                                                                           rights. These efforts help galvanize pub-
                                                                           lic support and push for policy changes.

                                                                           Education and awareness
                                                                              Education is a powerful tool for
                                                                           change. International Women’s Equality
                                                                           Day provides an opportunity to educate
                                                                           people about the history of women's
                                                                           rights, the progress made, and the chal-
                                                                           lenges that remain. Schools, universi-
                                                                           ties, and community organizations often
                                                                           host lectures, workshops, and discus-
                                                                           sions to foster a deeper understanding of
                                                                           gender equality.

                                                                           Celebration of achievements
                                                                              Celebrating the achievements of
         Swedish activist Greta Thunberg                                   in various fields—science, politics, arts,
                                                                           women is an essential aspect of this day.
                                                                           Recognizing the contributions of women
                                                                           business—serves as an inspiration for
                                                                           future generations. Awards, honors, and
                                                                           public acknowledgments spotlight the
                                                                           impact women have made on society.
                                                                              Moving forward: The future of

                                                                              As we celebrate International

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                           gender equality              7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Left: Nobel Peace Prize laureate Malala Yousafzai  Right: Feminist march for women’s equality














           Women’s Equality Day, it is crucial to
           look forward and envision a future
           where gender equality is a reality.
           Achieving this goal requires concerted
           efforts from individuals, communities,
           governments, and international organi-  dress local issues and provide support to   ity. Challenging stereotypes, promoting
           zations.                        women in need. These movements often   positive representations of women in
                                           lead to innovative solutions and foster a   media, and encouraging men to support
           Policy and legal reforms        sense of solidarity and empowerment.   gender equality are essential steps to-
             Governments must enact and enforce                            ward creating a more inclusive society.
           laws that protect women's rights and   Education and mentorship    International Women’s Equality Day
           promote gender equality. This includes   Investing in education and mentor-  is more than a celebration; it is a call to
           laws against gender-based violence, pol-  ship programs for girls and young   action. It reminds us of the progress
           icies to ensure equal pay, and measures   women is crucial for building future   made and the work that still lies ahead
           to support women in leadership posi-  leaders. Encouraging girls to pursue ca-  in the fight for gender equality. By hon-
           tions. International cooperation and   reers in STEM, providing scholarships,   oring the past, addressing current chal-
           agreements can also help standardize   and creating mentorship networks can   lenges, and working toward a more
           and strengthen these efforts globally.   help break down barriers and open   equitable future, we can ensure that the
                                           doors to new opportunities.     vision of true equality for all women be-
           Grassroots movements                                            comes a reality. Let this day inspire us
             Grassroots movements play a vital   Cultural change           to continue striving for a world where
           role in driving change. Community-  Cultural norms and attitudes play a   every woman has the freedom, opportu-
           based organizations and activists can ad-  significant role in shaping gender equal-  nities, and rights she deserves. ■





















                                                                                                           Women’s equality rally









           8                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[PROFILE








































           Rajiv Gandhi




           A visionary leader





           and champion of harmony





           By Aarav Sharma

                 ugust 20 marks the birth anni-  mative, as he sought to propel India into   College and Cambridge University. Ra-
                 versary of Rajiv Gandhi, the 6th   the information age and bridge divides   jiv's initial interest lay in engineering
           APrime Minister of India, a piv-  within its vast populace.     and aviation, which led him to become a
           otal figure in Indian politics and a vi-                        professional pilot with Indian Airlines.
           sionary leader who championed mod-  Early life and education
           ernity, progress, and communal    Born on August 20, 1944, in Bombay   Entry into politics
           harmony. This day is also celebrated as   (now Mumbai), Rajiv Gandhi was the   Rajiv Gandhi's entry into politics was
           Communal Harmony Day, reflecting   eldest son of Indira Gandhi and Feroze   not premeditated. It was the tragic de-
           Gandhi's enduring commitment to fos-  Gandhi. His early education took place   mise of his younger brother, Sanjay
           tering peace and unity in a diverse na-  in prestigious institutions like Welham   Gandhi, in a plane crash in 1980 that
           tion. Rajiv Gandhi's tenure as Prime   Boys' School, the Doon School, and   compelled him to step into the political
           Minister, though brief, was transfor-  later in the United Kingdom at Eton   arena. Rajiv was reluctant initially, pre-

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Rajiv Gandhi taking the oath of office as Prime Minister of India
















                                                                                                           Young Rajiv Gandhi

















         Rajiv and Sonia Gandhi getting off the aircraft                                                   Rajiv Gandhi addressing a public meeting


















           ferring his career as a pilot and a private   Technological and economic   policies of the 1990s, which transformed
           life with his wife, Sonia, and their chil-  reforms             India into one of the fastest-growing
           dren, Rahul and Priyanka. However, his   Rajiv Gandhi's tenure is often cred-  economies globally.
           mother, then Prime Minister Indira Gan-  ited with laying the foundation for In-
           dhi, persuaded him to join politics,   dia's technological and economic trans-  Promoting communal harmony
           marking the beginning of his political   formation. Recognizing the potential of   One of Rajiv Gandhi's enduring leg-
           journey.                        information technology, he initiated pol-  acies is his emphasis on communal har-
                                           icies that liberalized the telecom sector   mony. His leadership was marked by ef-
           Ascension to Prime Ministership   and promoted computerization. The es-  forts to bridge the communal divides
             The assassination of Indira Gandhi in   tablishment of MTNL and the push for   that had plagued India since independ-
           1984 thrust Rajiv Gandhi into the na-  digital communication were part of his   ence. Rajiv was acutely aware of the de-
           tion's highest office. At 40, he became   broader strategy to modernize India's in-  structive potential of communalism,
           the youngest Prime Minister of India.   frastructure.           especially in the aftermath of the anti-
           His ascent was marked by a wave of   Economically, Rajiv advocated for   Sikh riots of 1984, which followed his
           sympathy and a resounding electoral   liberalization and globalization. His ad-  mother's assassination by her Sikh body-
           victory for the Congress party. Rajiv's   ministration reduced import quotas, tar-  guards.
           tenure from 1984 to 1989 was a period   iffs, and taxes to encourage investment   To promote peace and unity, Rajiv
           of significant change, driven by his vi-  and industrial growth. These measures,   Gandhi championed policies that fos-
           sion of a modern, technologically ad-  though controversial at the time, set the   tered communal harmony and national
           vanced, and economically robust India.   stage for the economic liberalization   integration. He supported the passage of

           10                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[policy that balanced non-alignment with
                                                                           pragmatic engagement. Rajiv advocated
                                                                           for nuclear disarmament and played a
                                                                           significant role in global peace initia-
                                                                           tives. His efforts to mediate in regional
                                                                           conflicts, such as sending the Indian
                                                                           Peace Keeping Force (IPKF) to Sri
                                                                           Lanka, underscored his commitment to
                                                                           regional stability, although the mission
                                                                           had mixed outcomes.
                                                                              Rajiv also worked towards strength-
                                                                           ening India's relations with superpowers
                                                                           like the United States and the Soviet
                                                                           Union, as well as with neighboring
                                                                           countries. His tenure saw an increase in
                                                                           diplomatic and economic cooperation,
                                                                           which helped position India as a key
                                                                           player in global affairs.

                                                                           Challenges and controversies
                                                                              Rajiv Gandhi's tenure was not with-
                                                                           out challenges and controversies. The
                                                                           Bofors scandal, involving allegations of
                                                                           kickbacks in a defense deal, marred his
                                                                           image and eroded public trust in his ad-
                                                                           ministration. Additionally, his decision
           the Muslim Women (Protection of
         Top: Rajiv Gandhi and Mikhail Gorbachev, 1986  within the framework of Islamic law.               Rajiv Gandhi and Benazir during the SAARC Summit
           Rights on Divorce) Act in 1986, which
           aimed to safeguard the rights of Muslim
           women and address their concerns
           This move, however, was met with
           mixed reactions, reflecting the complex
           interplay of religion and politics in
           India.

           Vision for education and youth
           empowerment
             Rajiv Gandhi believed that India's fu-
           ture lay in the hands of its youth. He
           emphasized the need for modern educa-
           tion and vocational training to empower
           young Indians. His government
           launched initiatives to expand higher
           education and improve the quality of
           primary and secondary education. The
           establishment of Jawahar Navodaya Vi-  education to rural children, is a testa-  to send the IPKF to Sri Lanka was criti-
           dyalayas, aimed at providing quality   ment to his vision for an inclusive edu-  cized both domestically and inter-
                                           cational framework.             nationally, leading to significant casual-
                                             Furthermore, Rajiv's policies encour-  ties and straining Indo-Sri Lankan
                                           aged scientific temper and innovation.   relations.
                                           He was instrumental in setting up insti-  Despite these challenges, Rajiv's con-
                                           tutions like the National Institute of   tributions to India's modernization and
                                           Fashion Technology (NIFT) and pro-  his vision for a united, progressive na-
                                           moting the Indian Institutes of Technol-  tion remain significant. His assassina-
                                           ogy (IITs) and Indian Institutes of Man-  tion on May 21, 1991, by the Liberation
                                           agement (IIMs) as centers of excellence.   Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE) was a
                                                                           tragic end to a promising political ca-
                                           Foreign policy and international   reer.
         Rajiv Gandhi                      dhi sought to enhance India's stature on   Legacy and commemoration
                                           relations
                                             On the international front, Rajiv Gan-
                                                                              Rajiv Gandhi's legacy is celebrated
                                           the global stage. He pursued a foreign
                                                                           every year on his birth anniversary, Au-
           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[outstanding contributions to promoting
                                                                           communal harmony and peace.
                                                                              Rajiv Gandhi's birth anniversary is a
                                                                           day to reflect on the legacy of a leader
                                                                           who envisioned a modern, progressive,
                                                                           and harmonious India. His contributions
                                                                           to technological advancement, economic
                                                                           liberalization, education, and communal
                                                                           harmony have left an indelible mark on
                                                                           the nation. As India continues to navi-
                                                                           gate its path towards development and
                                                                           unity, the principles and vision of Rajiv
                                                                           Gandhi remain relevant and inspiring.
                                                                              Communal Harmony Day serves as a
                                                                           poignant reminder of the need for peace,
                                                                           tolerance, and unity in a diverse nation.
                                                                           It is a day to honor the memory of a
                                                                           leader who, despite his challenges and  Left: Rahul Gandhi carrying his father's body
                                                                           controversies, worked tirelessly to build
                                                                           a better future for India and its people.
                                                                           Rajiv Gandhi's life and legacy continue
                                                                           to inspire generations, reaffirming the
                                                                           timeless values of harmony and pro-
                                                                           gress. ■





























           gust 20, which is observed as Com-
           munal Harmony Day. This day serves as
           a reminder of his efforts to promote
           peace and unity in a diverse and often
        Left: supporters paying their last respects  Right: Rajiv Gandhi making his final journey   to honor his memory and reaffirm the
           divided nation. Various events and pro-
           grams are organized across the country
           values of communal harmony and na-
           tional integration.
             Educational institutions, social or-
           ganizations, and government bodies
           conduct seminars, workshops, and cul-
           tural programs to propagate the ideals of
           tolerance and unity. The Rajiv Gandhi
           National Sadbhavana Award, established
           in his honor, is awarded annually to in-
           dividuals or institutions that have made

           12                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT











































           UNSUNG HEROES IN





           CRISIS ZONES






           Honoring the unseen sacriﬁces and relentless efforts of
           humanitarian workers on the frontlines of global emergencies



           By Pooja Mehta


                  orld Humanitarian Day, ob-  lost their lives in the 2003 bombing of   The significance of World
                  served annually on August   the UN headquarters in Baghdad, Iraq.   Humanitarian Day
           W19th, is a day dedicated to    Over the years, World Humanitarian   The primary purpose of World Hu-
           recognizing the tireless efforts of hu-  Day has evolved to not only honor those   manitarian Day is to draw attention to
           manitarian workers who risk their lives   who have fallen but also to celebrate the   the millions of people affected by con-
           to provide aid to those in need. Estab-  spirit of humanitarianism that drives   flicts, natural disasters, and other crises,
           lished by the United Nations General   thousands of individuals around the   and to highlight the critical work of hu-
           Assembly in 2008, this day commem-  world to provide assistance in the most   manitarian organizations and their staff.
           orates the 22 humanitarian workers who   challenging conditions.   These workers operate in some of the

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[cludes efforts to restore infrastructure,
                                                                           support livelihoods, provide education,
                                                                           and promote social cohesion. In many
                                                                           cases, humanitarian workers also advo-
                                                                           cate for the rights and dignity of affected
                                                                           populations, ensuring that their voices
                                                                           are heard and their needs are met.

                                                                           Challenges faced by humanitarian
                                                                           workers
                                                                              The work of humanitarian workers is
                                                                           fraught with challenges. In many crisis
                                                                           zones, they face threats from armed
                                                                           groups, unstable governments, and local
                                                                           populations who may view them with
                                                                           suspicion. The 2003 Baghdad bombing,
                                                                           which led to the creation of World Hu-
                                                                           manitarian Day, is a stark reminder of
                                                                           the dangers these workers face. Unfor-
                                                                           tunately, such attacks are not isolated in-
                                                                           cidents. In recent years, there has been



















           most dangerous environments, often
           putting their own lives at risk to save
           others. The day serves as a reminder of
           the need for greater global solidarity and
           cooperation to address the challenges
           faced by vulnerable populations and to
           ensure that humanitarian aid reaches
           those who need it most.

           The role of humanitarian workers
             Humanitarian workers are the back-
           bone of the global response to crises.
           Whether responding to natural disasters,
           conflicts, epidemics, or other emer-
           gencies, these individuals are often the
           first on the scene, providing lifesaving
           assistance such as food, water, shelter,
           medical care, and protection. Their work
        Top: Lakkidi view point, Wayanad  Middle: Scene of devastation in Wayanad   neutrality, impartiality, and independ-  A foggy climate in Wayanad during the monsoon
           is guided by principles of humanity,
           ence, ensuring that aid is provided based
           on need alone, without discrimination.
             Humanitarian work is not just about
           immediate relief; it also involves long-
           term recovery efforts. After the initial
           emergency phase, humanitarian workers
           play a crucial role in helping com-
           munities rebuild their lives. This in-

           14                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[sential in preventing the escalation of
                                                                           crises and in promoting sustainable de-
                                                                           velopment.

                                                                           The role of the united nations and
         A rescuer consoles a man who has lost his home                    tarian efforts around the world. The UN
                                                                           international organizations
                                                                              The United Nations and other inter-
                                                                           national organizations play a central role
                                                                           in coordinating and supporting humani-

                                                                           Office for the Coordination of Humani-
                                                                           tarian Affairs (OCHA) is responsible for
                                                                           mobilizing and coordinating humanitar-
                                                                           ian action in partnership with national
                                                                           and international actors. OCHA ensures
                                                                           that humanitarian assistance is delivered
                                                                           effectively and efficiently, and that the
                                                                           rights of affected populations are pro-
                                                                           tected.
                                                                              In addition to OCHA, various UN
                                                                           agencies such as the World Food Pro-
           an alarming increase in the number of   The impact of humanitarian work   gramme (WFP), the United Nations
           attacks on humanitarian workers. Ac-  The impact of humanitarian work   High Commissioner for Refugees
           cording to the Aid Worker Security Da-  cannot be overstated. Every year, mil-
           tabase, 2022 saw one of the highest   lions of lives are saved through the ef-
           numbers of recorded incidents, with   forts of humanitarian organizations and
           more than 300 humanitarian workers   their staff. In conflict zones like Syria,
           killed, kidnapped, or seriously injured.   Yemen, and South Sudan, humanitarian
             In addition to security risks, humani-  workers provide essential services that
           tarian workers often operate in ex-  would otherwise be unavailable. In areas
                                           affected by natural disasters, such as
           tremely challenging environments.
         Bottom: Aid delivery by helicopter  astated by natural disasters or working   their swift response helps to prevent the   A child in a refugee camp
                                           earthquakes, floods, and hurricanes,
           Whether navigating through areas dev-
           in conflict zones where access to basic
                                           loss of life and alleviate suffering.
           necessities is limited, the physical and
                                             Beyond immediate relief, humanitar-
                                           ian work also contributes to long-term
           emotional toll of this work can be im-
           mense. Despite these challenges, hu-
                                           peace and stability. By addressing the
           manitarian workers continue to show ex-
                                           root causes of conflict and providing
           traordinary resilience and dedication,
                                           support to vulnerable populations, hu-
                                           manitarian workers help to build more
           driven by a deep commitment to helping
                                                                           (UNHCR), and the World Health Organ-
                                           resilient communities. Their work is es-
           those in need.
                                                                           ization (WHO) are deeply involved in
                                                                           humanitarian work. These agencies pro-
                                                                           vide specialized support in areas such as
                                                                           food security, refugee protection, and
                                                                           health services. Their efforts are often
                                                                           complemented by the work of non-gov-
                                                                           ernmental organizations (NGOs), which
                                                                           play a critical role in delivering aid on
                                                                           the ground.
                                                                           World humanitarian day 2024: A
                                                                           call to action
                                                                              Each year, World Humanitarian Day
                                                                           focuses on a specific theme to raise
                                                                           awareness and inspire action. The theme
                                                                           for 2024, "No Matter What," highlights
                                                                           the unwavering commitment of humani-
                                                                           tarian workers to provide aid in the most
                                                                           challenging circumstances. This theme
                                                                           underscores the importance of standing
                                                                           in solidarity with those affected by
                                                                           crises and recognizing the sacrifices

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[made by humanitarian workers.   ment representatives, participating in
                                           awareness campaigns, or using social
             In the face of increasing global chal-
        Top Right: Humanitarian workers   assisting in rebuilding a home   ian assistance has never been greater.   challenges faced by humanitarian
                                           media to spread the word.
           lenges, from climate change to pro-
                                             Educate: Learning more about the
           tracted conflicts, the need for humanitar-
           World Humanitarian Day 2024 calls on
                                           workers and the people they serve is a
                                           crucial step in becoming an informed
           individuals, communities, and govern-
           ments to support humanitarian efforts
                                           advocate. Many organizations offer re-
           and to advocate for the protection of aid
                                           sources and information to help individ-
                                           uals better understand humanitarian is-
           workers. It also serves as a reminder that
           everyone has a role to play in alleviating
                                           sues.
           human suffering, whether through vol-
                                             World Humanitarian Day is a power-












                                                                           ful reminder of the courage, dedication,
                                                                           and resilience of humanitarian workers
                                                                           around the world. It is a day to honor
                                                                           their sacrifices and to recognize the pro-
                                                                           found impact of their work on the lives
                                                                           of millions of people. As global chal-
                                                                           lenges continue to evolve, the need for
                                                                           humanitarian assistance will only grow.
                                                                           By supporting humanitarian efforts and
                                                                           standing in solidarity with those affected
                                                                           by crises, we can all contribute to a
                                                                           more just and compassionate world. ■
           unteering, donating, or simply raising
           awareness about the issues faced by vul-
           nerable populations.

           How to get involved
             There are many ways to get involved
           in World Humanitarian Day and support
           humanitarian efforts:
             Donate: Financial contributions to
           humanitarian organizations can make a
           significant difference. Many organiza-
          Right: Rescuers crossing a river at Wayanad  Top: A rescue worker walking past after the landslides   nationally, volunteering with humanitar-
           tions rely on donations to fund their op-
           erations and provide critical assistance
           to those in need.
             Volunteer: Whether locally or inter-
           ian organizations can be a rewarding
           way to contribute. Many organizations
           offer opportunities for individuals with a
           wide range of skills to get involved.
             Advocate: Raising awareness about
           humanitarian issues and advocating for
           policies that support humanitarian work
           is another important way to make an im-
           pact. This can include writing to govern-

           16                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[IN FOCUS









































           From Chains to Liberation




           The global






           fight against slavery








           By Rajeev Khanna

                he International Day for the Re-  day also commemorates the Haitian   bonded labor, this day is an opportunity
                membrance of the Slave Trade   Revolution, where enslaved Africans in   to draw parallels, reflect on shared his-
           Tand its Abolition, observed on   Saint-Domingue (now Haiti) rose   tories of oppression, and renew commit-
           August 23rd, holds deep historical and   against the French colonial powers, ulti-  ments to human rights and social justice.
           moral significance. It serves as a global   mately leading to the abolition of slav-
           reminder of one of humanity’s darkest   ery in the colony.      The transatlantic slave trade: A
           chapters and the ongoing impact of the   For India, a country with its own   global crime against humanity
           transatlantic slave trade, as well as other   complex history of colonialism, caste-  The transatlantic slave trade, span-
           forms of slavery across the world. The   based discrimination, and forms of   ning over 400 years, was one of the

           18                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[National Museum of Slavery, Angola














                                                                           mous wealth from India, often through
                                                                           the exploitation of labor and natural re-
                                                                           sources, leading to widespread poverty
                                                                           and suffering among the Indian pop-
                                                                           ulation.
                                                                              India’s caste system, though distinct
                                                                           from slavery, also institutionalized a
         Child labor in Asian countries                                    particularly those belonging to the so-
                                                                           rigid hierarchy that denied basic human
                                                                           rights and dignity to millions of people,
                                                                           called “lower” castes or Dalits. The
                                                                           practice of bonded labor, where individ-
                                                                           uals were forced to work to repay debts,
                                                                           often under brutal conditions, was
                                                                           another form of exploitation that mir-


           most brutal and extensive systems of   global movement against slavery, inspir-  rored slavery in many ways. Though
           human exploitation in history. It in-  ing other uprisings and contributing to
           volved the forced transportation of mil-  the eventual abolition of the transatlantic
           lions of Africans to the Americas and   slave trade.
           Europe, where they were subjected to
           inhumane conditions, forced labor, and   India's historical context:
           unimaginable suffering. This trade was   Colonialism and caste-based
           driven by European colonial powers and   oppression
           had profound economic, social, and cul-  While India was not directly in-
           tural impacts on the world, particularly   volved in the transatlantic slave trade, it
           in Africa, the Americas, and Europe.   has its own history of colonial exploita-
             The abolition of slavery did not   tion and forms of social oppression that
           happen overnight; it was the result of re-  bear similarities to slavery. The British
           lentless resistance by the enslaved   colonial rule in India was marked by
           people themselves, coupled with the ef-  economic exploitation, cultural suppres-
           forts of abolitionists worldwide. The   sion, and widespread human rights                       A child laborer
           Haitian Revolution, which began in   abuses. The East India Company and
           1791, was a landmark event in the   later the British Crown extracted enor-

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[International day for the
                                                                           remembrance of the slave trade
                                                                           and its abolition: India's role
                                                                              As the world observes the Inter-
                                                                           national Day for the Remembrance of
                                                                           the Slave Trade and its Abolition, it is
                                                                           important for India to engage with this
                                                                           global history and its contemporary im-
                                                                           plications. This day offers an opportu-
                                                                           nity for reflection on the shared histories
         A painting depicting the Battle for Palm Tree Hill                rights for all.
                                                                           of oppression, the interconnectedness of
                                                                           global struggles for freedom, and the on-
                                                                           going challenges of ensuring human
                                                                              India, with its rich cultural heritage
                                                                           and history of resistance against colo-
                                                                           nialism, has a unique role to play in the
                                                                           global discourse on slavery, colonialism,
                                                                           and human rights. The country’s experi-
                                                                           ence with colonial exploitation and its
                                                                           own internal struggles with caste-based

                                                                           important perspectives on the broader is-
                                                                           sues of social justice and human dignity.

           bonded labor is officially illegal in India                     discrimination and bonded labor provide
           today, it continues in various forms, par-
           ticularly in rural areas.

           India's struggle against
           oppression
             India's struggle for independence
           from British rule can be seen as a paral-
           lel to the global struggle against slavery
           and colonialism. The Indian independ-
           ence movement, led by figures like Ma-
           hatma Gandhi, Jawaharlal Nehru, and
           B.R. Ambedkar, was not just a fight for
           political freedom but also a broader
           struggle for social justice, equality, and                                                      Left: A woman laborer in a brick kiln
           human dignity.                                                                                    Bottom: Bonded labor in India
             Mahatma Gandhi’s concept of “Swa-
           raj” (self-rule) went beyond mere politi-
           cal independence; it encompassed the
           idea of freedom from all forms of op-
           pression, including economic exploita-
           tion and social injustice. B.R. Ambed-  violence against Dalits and other mar-
           kar, one of India’s most prominent social   ginalized groups. Bonded labor, despite
           reformers, dedicated his life to fighting   being outlawed, persists in various
           caste-based discrimination and advocat-  forms, particularly in industries like ag-
           ing for the rights of Dalits and other   riculture, brick kilns, and domestic
           marginalized communities.       work.
                                             Moreover, the global legacy of slav-
           The legacy of slavery and caste in   ery is not entirely disconnected from
           contemporary India              India. The country has its own history of
             While India has made significant   “coolie” labor, where Indian laborers
           progress since independence, the legacy   were transported to various British col-
           of both colonialism and caste-based op-  onies under conditions that often resem-
           pression continues to affect the country.   bled slavery. These laborers were sub-
           The caste system, though legally abol-  jected to harsh conditions, long working
           ished, still exerts a powerful influence   hours, and little pay, and their plight is
           on Indian society, manifesting in social   an important but often overlooked part
           discrimination, economic inequality, and   of India’s colonial history.

           20                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Map of the slave trade








           Education and awareness: The    social justice                     The International Day for the Re-
           need for historical reflection    The observance of the International   membrance of the Slave Trade and its
             One of the key ways to honor the In-  Day for the Remembrance of the Slave   Abolition is a day of global significance,
           ternational Day for the Remembrance of   Trade and its Abolition is not just about   reminding us of the horrors of slavery
           the Slave Trade and its Abolition is   looking back at the past; it is also about   and the ongoing struggle for human
           through education and awareness. In   looking forward and renewing commit-  rights and social justice.
           India, there is a need to integrate the his-  ments to human rights and social justice.   For India, this day is an opportunity
           tory of slavery, both global and local,   For India, this means continuing to ad-  to reflect on its own history of oppres-
                                           dress the legacies of colonialism and   sion, to draw connections with global
                                           caste-based oppression, ensuring that all   struggles for freedom, and to renew its
                                           citizens have access to basic human   commitment to creating a just and equi-
                                           rights, and working towards a more just   table society.
         Key abolitionist Toussaint Louverture  human dignity, provides a strong foun-  India too must honor its own history of
                                           and equitable society.
                                                                              As the world remembers the victims
                                             India’s constitution, which enshrines
                                                                           of the transatlantic slave trade and the
                                           the principles of equality, justice, and
                                                                           heroes who fought for its abolition,
                                                                           resistance and continue the fight against
                                           dation for this work. However, realizing
                                                                           all forms of oppression. This is not just a
                                           these principles requires ongoing efforts
                                           to address the social, economic, and cul-
                                                                           historical responsibility but a moral im-
                                                                           perative that resonates with the values of
                                           tural factors that perpetuate discrim-
                                           ination and inequality.
                                                                           humanity, dignity, and justice that lie at
                                                                           important day. ■
           into educational curricula. This includes   A Shared Global Responsibility   the heart of the global observance of this
           not only the transatlantic slave trade but
           also the history of bonded labor, caste-
           based oppression, and other forms of ex-
           ploitation that have existed in India.
             Educational institutions, civil society
           organizations, and the media have a crit-
           ical role to play in raising awareness
           about these issues and encouraging pub-
           lic discourse. By understanding the his-
           tory of slavery and its abolition, as well
           as the parallels in India’s own history,                                                        Mahatma Gandhi: India’s Fight for Freedom and Justice
           people can better appreciate the impor-
           tance of human rights and the need to
           continue the struggle against all forms
           of oppression.
           Moving forward: India’s
           commitment to human rights and


           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[INSIGHT


































           Outsmarting Mosquitoes




           Small bite, big Impact






           By Aditya Joshi


                  orld Mosquito Day, observed   tures on Earth. Responsible for spread-  torical breakthrough and an opportunity
                  annually on August 20th,   ing diseases that kill over a million   to galvanize global efforts toward eradi-
           Wcommemorates the discovery     people each year, their impact on global   cating these deadly diseases.
           by British doctor Sir Ronald Ross in   public health cannot be overstated.
           1897 that female mosquitoes transmit   World Mosquito Day is not just a day of   Understanding mosquito-borne
           malaria between humans. This day   remembrance but also a day of action. It   diseases
           serves as a reminder of the devastating   is a call to the global community to ac-  Mosquitoes are vectors for various
           impact of mosquito-borne diseases and   knowledge the progress made in the   diseases, each with unique characteris-
           highlights ongoing global efforts to con-  fight against mosquito-borne diseases   tics and challenges. Below are some of
           trol and eliminate them. While malaria   and to renew commitments to research,   the most significant mosquito-borne dis-
           remains a central focus, World Mosquito   prevention, and treatment.   eases:
           Day also draws attention to other mos-  Sir Ronald Ross’s discovery over a   Malaria: Caused by the Plasmodium
           quito-borne illnesses, such as dengue,   century ago was a watershed moment in   parasite, malaria is transmitted to hu-
           Zika, yellow fever, and chikungunya,   medical history. It laid the foundation   mans through the bite of an infected fe-
           which affect millions worldwide.   for modern malaria research and control   male Anopheles mosquito. It remains a
                                           strategies, leading to the development of   major public health challenge, particu-
           The significance of world       prevention methods, treatments, and   larly in sub-Saharan Africa, where the
           mosquito day                    public health campaigns that have saved   majority of cases and deaths occur. De-
             Mosquitoes, often considered mere   millions of lives. Celebrating World   spite significant progress in reducing the
           nuisances, are among the deadliest crea-  Mosquito Day is an homage to this his-  global malaria burden, the disease still

           22                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Top Left: Malaria vaccine  Top Right: Lab Research on Mosquitoes   poses a severe threat, especially to chil-
           dren under five and pregnant women.
             Dengue Fever: Transmitted by
           Aedes mosquitoes, dengue fever is a
           viral infection that causes flu-like symp-
           toms and can develop into severe
           dengue, a leading cause of serious ill-
           ness and death in some Asian and Latin
           American countries. The incidence of
           dengue has increased dramatically in re-
           cent decades, with about half of the
           world's population now at risk.
             Zika Virus: Zika virus is also trans-
           mitted by Aedes mosquitoes. While the
           symptoms are generally mild, Zika
           gained international attention due to its
           association with severe birth defects, in-
           cluding microcephaly in newborns. The
           2015-2016 Zika outbreak in the Ameri-
           cas highlighted the global vulnerability
           to emerging mosquito-borne diseases.
             Chikungunya: Another disease
           spread by Aedes mosquitoes, chikung-
           unya causes fever and severe joint pain.
           While it is rarely fatal, the debilitating
           joint pain can last for months or even
           years, significantly impacting the quality
           of life of those affected.
             Yellow Fever: A viral disease trans-
           mitted by both Aedes and Haemagogus
        Right Middle: Health worker spraying insecticide  Right Bottom: Health worker conducting a malaria test   cine exists, yellow fever remains a threat   quito population and preventing bites   these efforts.
           mosquitoes, yellow fever causes jaun-
           dice and hemorrhagic symptoms and can
           be fatal. While a highly effective vac-

           in parts of Africa and South America,
           particularly in areas with low vaccina-
                                             Vector Control: Reducing the mos-
           tion coverage.
                                                                              Vaccination: Vaccines have been a
           Global efforts to combat mosquito-
                                           are crucial in controlling the spread of
                                                                           game-changer in the fight against mos-
           borne diseases
                                           diseases. This includes the use of insec-
                                                                           quito-borne diseases. The RTS,S/AS01
                                           ticide-treated bed nets, indoor residual
                                                                           malaria vaccine, piloted in several Afri-
             The fight against mosquito-borne dis-
                                                                           can countries, represents a significant
           eases is multi-faceted, involving vector
                                           spraying, and environmental manage-
           control, vaccination, treatment, public
                                           ment to eliminate mosquito breeding
           education, and research. Here are some
                                           sites. However, the rise of insecticide re-
                                                                           larly, vaccines for yellow fever and
                                                                           dengue have proven effective in reduc-
                                           sistance poses a significant challenge to
           of the key strategies and initiatives:
           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                           milestone in malaria prevention. Simi- 23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Stagnant water in the garden



















         Mosquito-killing racket                                                                           Mosquito breeding









           ing disease incidence in high-risk areas.
             Treatment and diagnosis: Early dia-
           gnosis and prompt treatment are essen-
           tial in reducing the mortality and mor-
           bidity associated with mosquito-borne
           diseases. The development of rapid dia-
           gnostic tests and effective antimalarial
           drugs has been instrumental in control-
           ling malaria. For other diseases like
           dengue and chikungunya, supportive
           care remains the primary treatment, as
           no specific antiviral drugs are available.
             Public education and awareness:
           Educating communities about mosquito-
           borne diseases, prevention methods, and
           the importance of seeking early treat-
           ment is vital. Public health campaigns
           often focus on promoting the use of bed
           nets, encouraging indoor spraying, and
           advising people to eliminate standing
           water where mosquitoes breed.
             Research and innovation: Ongoing
           research is crucial in developing new
           tools and strategies to combat mosquito-
           borne diseases. Innovations such as ge-
           netically modified mosquitoes, which
           are designed to reduce mosquito pop-
           ulations or interfere with disease trans-
           mission, are being explored. Ad-
           ditionally, research into new
           insecticides, drugs, and vaccines con-
           tinues to be a priority.                                                                        Mosquito net in the garden area
           Challenges in the fight against
           mosquito-borne diseases
             Despite significant progress, several

           24                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[challenges remain in the global fight
           against mosquito-borne diseases:
             Insecticide resistance: The wide-
           spread use of insecticides has led to the
           development of resistance in mosquito
           populations, undermining the effective-
           ness of vector control efforts. This has
           prompted the need for new insecticides
           and alternative strategies to manage re-
           sistance.
             Access to healthcare: In many parts
           of the world, particularly in rural and re-
           mote areas, access to healthcare remains
           limited. This includes access to diagnos-
           tic services, treatment, and preventive
           measures like bed nets and vaccines.
           Strengthening health systems is critical
           to ensuring that everyone at risk can ac-                                                       Beautiful mosquito net over a bed
           cess the care they need.
             Climate change: Changing climate
           patterns are altering the distribution and
           behavior of mosquitoes, potentially ex-
                                           ing long-term success.             The lessons learned from past suc-
                                             World Mosquito Day is a powerful   cesses and failures in controlling mos-
                                           reminder of the ongoing battle against   quito-borne diseases must guide future
                                           some of the world’s deadliest diseases. It   efforts. With continued research, invest-
                                           celebrates the scientific achievements   ment, and community engagement, the
                                           that have brought us closer to control-  goal of a world free from the burden of
                                           ling and eliminating mosquito-borne   mosquito-borne diseases is within reach.
                                           diseases while acknowledging the chal-  World Mosquito Day serves as a call to
                                           lenges that remain. As we mark this day,   action, urging governments, organiza-
                                           it is important to recognize that the fight   tions, and individuals to redouble their
                                           against these diseases requires global   efforts and work together to protect the
                                           cooperation, sustained commitment, and   health and well-being of millions around
                                           innovative solutions.           the world. ■




           panding the range of mosquito-borne
           diseases. Warmer temperatures and
           changing rainfall patterns can create
           more favorable conditions for mosqui-
           toes, leading to increased transmission
           in new areas.
             Political and economic instability:
           Conflicts, economic downturns, and po-
           litical instability can disrupt public
           health efforts and exacerbate the spread
           of mosquito-borne diseases. In such set-
           tings, weakened health systems and dis-
           placement of populations can lead to
           outbreaks and hinder control efforts.
             Funding and resources: Sustained
           funding and resources are essential for
           the ongoing fight against mosquito-
           borne diseases. However, competing
           global health priorities, economic chal-
           lenges, and donor fatigue can lead to                                                           Mosquito-killing waves
           funding gaps, threatening progress. Con-
           tinued investment in research, preven-
           tion, and treatment is crucial to achiev-

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE  Man's best                                           companions to serving as therapy dogs,



                                                                           service dogs, and working dogs in var-
                                                                           ious fields such as law enforcement and
                                                                           the military.


           friend through                                                  The role of dogs in society
                                                                              Dogs have been an integral part of
                                                                           human society for millennia. From the
                                                                           early days of domestication, when dogs
                                                                           were primarily used for hunting and pro-
                                                                           tection, to their current roles as compan-
                                                                           ions, service animals, and working dogs,
           the ages                                                        immeasurable.
                                                                           their contributions to human society are
                                                                              Companionship: Perhaps the most
                                                                           common role of dogs is that of a com-
                                                                           panion. Dogs provide emotional sup-
                                                                           port, reduce feelings of loneliness, and

           By Ishita Desai


             nternational Dog Day, celebrated an-
             nually on August 26th, is a global
           Ievent dedicated to honoring the
           unique bond between humans and dogs.
           Established in 2004 by pet and family
           lifestyle expert Colleen Paige, this day
           serves as a reminder of the deep and en-
           during connection we share with our ca-
           nine companions. Dogs have been by
           our side for thousands of years, provid-
           ing companionship, protection, and un-
           conditional love. This special day not
           only recognizes the joy and comfort
           dogs bring into our lives but also raises
           awareness about the importance of
           adoption, rescue, and the humane treat-
           ment of these loyal animals.
           History of international dog day
             Colleen Paige, an animal advocate
           and pet lifestyle expert, founded Inter-
           national Dog Day to raise awareness
           about the plight of dogs and to encour-
           age adoption. The date, August 26th,
           was chosen because it was the day
           Paige’s family adopted their first dog,
           Sheltie, when she was just 10 years old.
           Since its inception, International Dog
           Day has grown into a worldwide cele-
           bration, with people from all walks of
           life coming together to honor dogs and
           promote their well-being.
             Over the years, International Dog
           Day has become more than just a cele-
           bration. It has evolved into a movement
           that encourages responsible pet own-                                                            A dog being hugged by its owner
           ership, promotes the adoption of dogs
           from shelters and rescues, and advocates
           for stronger animal welfare laws. The
           day also highlights the various roles
           dogs play in society, from being loyal

           26                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[cal professionals to potential health is-
                                                                           sues before they become critical. In re-
                                                                           search, dogs have contributed to the un-
                                                                           derstanding of genetics, behavior, and
                                                                           even the development of new therapies
                                                                           for various diseases.

                                                                           The importance of adoption and
                                                                           rescue
                                                                              One of the primary goals of Inter-
                                                                           national Dog Day is to promote the
                                                                           adoption of dogs from shelters and res-
                                                                           cue organizations. Every year, millions
                                                                           of dogs end up in shelters, and unfor-
                                                                           tunately, many are euthanized due to
                                                                           overcrowding and lack of resources. By
                                                                           choosing to adopt a dog from a shelter
                                                                           or rescue, individuals can help reduce
                                                                           the number of homeless animals and
                                                                           provide a loving home to a dog in need.
                                                                              Adoption also offers several benefits
                                                                           to prospective dog owners. Shelter dogs
                                                                           are often already house-trained, and
                                                                           many have been socialized with other
                                                                           animals and people. Additionally, adop-
         Top: Volunteer with a rescue dog





















           help improve mental health. Studies   prove overall well-being.
           have shown that dog owners tend to   Working dogs: Dogs are employed
           have lower blood pressure, reduced   in various fields, including law enforce-
           stress levels, and increased physical ac-  ment, search and rescue, and the mili-
           tivity, thanks to the daily walks and   tary. Police dogs are trained to detect
           playtime that come with dog ownership.   drugs, explosives, and firearms, as well
             Service and therapy dogs: Service   as to apprehend suspects. Search and
           dogs are trained to assist individuals   rescue dogs play a crucial role in locat-
           with disabilities, such as guide dogs for   ing missing persons, whether they are
           the visually impaired, hearing dogs for   lost in the wilderness or trapped under
           the deaf, and mobility assistance dogs   rubble following a natural disaster. Mili-
           for those with physical disabilities.   tary dogs are trained for tasks such as                 Bond between humans and their canine companions
           These dogs undergo extensive training   detecting explosives, scouting for enemy
           to perform tasks that help their owners   forces, and protecting their handlers.
           lead more independent lives. Therapy   Detection and research: Dogs have
           dogs, on the other hand, provide comfort   an extraordinary sense of smell, which
           and emotional support to people in hos-  makes them invaluable in detection
           pitals, nursing homes, schools, and dis-  roles. Some dogs are trained to detect
           aster areas. Their calming presence has   diseases such as cancer, diabetes, and
           been shown to reduce anxiety and im-  seizures, alerting their owners or medi-

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Dogs participating in an event












                                                                           sizes the importance of responsible dog
                                                                           ownership. Owning a dog is a long-term
                                                                           commitment that requires time, effort,
                                                                           and financial resources. Prospective dog
                                                                           owners should carefully consider
                                                                           whether they can provide the necessary
                                                                           care, including regular veterinary check-
                                                                           ups, proper nutrition, exercise, groom-
                                                                           ing, and training.
                                                                              Spaying and neutering are essential
                                                                           aspects of responsible dog ownership.
                                                                           These procedures help control the pet
         Indian Army dog on duty                                           diseases, and can prevent behavioral is-
                                                                           population, reduce the risk of certain
                                                                           sues. Microchipping and ensuring that
                                                                           dogs wear identification tags are also
                                                                           crucial for keeping dogs safe and reuni-
                                                                           ting them with their owners if they be-
                                                                           come lost.
                                                                              Training and socialization are vital
           ting a dog is usually less expensive than
           purchasing one from a breeder, and it
           provides the satisfaction of knowing that
           you’ve given a second chance to a de-
           serving animal.
             Rescue organizations play a critical
           role in saving dogs from dire situations,
           such as abusive homes, puppy mills, and
           natural disasters. These organizations
           often operate on limited budgets and
           rely heavily on volunteers and dona-
           tions. International Dog Day is an op-                                                          Military working dogs undergoing aviation training
           portunity to support these organizations
           by donating, volunteering, or even fos-
           tering a dog in need.
           Promoting responsible dog
           ownership
             International Dog Day also empha-

           28                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[for a dog’s well-being and safety. Prop-
           erly trained dogs are less likely to de-
           velop behavioral problems and are better
           equipped to interact with people and
           other animals. Socialization, which in-
           volves exposing dogs to various envi-
           ronments, people, and other animals,
           helps them become well-adjusted and
           confident.

           Celebrating international dog day
             There are countless ways to celebrate
           International Dog Day, whether you’re a
           dog owner or simply a dog lover. Here
           are some ideas to make the day special
           for the dogs in your life:
             Adopt a dog: If you’re considering
           getting a dog, International Dog Day is
           the perfect time to visit your local
           shelter or rescue organization. Adopting
           a dog not only gives them a loving home
           but also frees up space for another dog
           in need.
             Volunteer or donate: Support your
           local animal shelter or rescue organiza-
           tion by volunteering your time or mak-
           ing a donation. Many shelters need help
           with walking dogs, cleaning, and organ-
           izing events. Donations of money, food,
           toys, and supplies are always appreci-
           ated.
             Spoil your dog: Treat your dog to a
           special day filled with their favorite ac-
           tivities. Take them for a long walk, play
           their favorite games, or give them a new
           toy. You could also prepare a homemade
           meal or bake some dog-friendly treats.
             Host a dog party: Invite your
           friends and their dogs over for a dog-
           themed party. Set up an obstacle course,                                                        Left: Therapy dog comforting a patient
           have a costume contest, or simply let the
           dogs play together. Don’t forget to pro-                                                          Top: Dogs in a shelter
           vide plenty of water and dog-friendly
           snacks.
             Raise awareness: Use social media
           to spread the word about International
           Dog Day and the importance of adop-  and to advocate for their well-being.
           tion and responsible pet ownership.   Whether through adoption, volunteer
           Share stories and photos of your dog, or   work, or simply spending quality time
           highlight a local shelter or rescue organ-  with your dog, there are many ways to
           ization that’s doing great work.   make a positive impact on this special
             Support pet-friendly legislation:   day.
           Advocate for stronger animal welfare   As we honor our loyal companions,
           laws in your community. This could in-  let’s also remember the millions of dogs
           volve supporting legislation that pro-  around the world who are still in need of
           motes spaying and neutering, cracking   loving homes. By raising awareness and
           down on puppy mills, or improving con-  promoting responsible pet ownership,
           ditions for dogs in shelters.   we can ensure that every dog has the
                                           chance to live a happy, healthy life. So,
           A day to cherish and advocate   this International Dog Day, take a mo-                          A child playing with a dog
             International Dog Day is more than   ment to appreciate the dogs in your life
           just a celebration of dogs; it’s a day to   and consider how you can help make the
           reflect on the roles they play in our lives   world a better place for all dogs. ■

           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[The official reason cited for her disqual-
                                                                           ification was a "violation of the athlete's
                                                                           code of conduct," a broad and somewhat
                                                                           ambiguous charge that has left room for
         REPORT                                                            speculation and controversy. While the
                                                                           IOC has been tight-lipped about the spe-
                                                                           cifics, insiders suggest that the issue
                                                                           might relate to anti-doping regulations
                                                                           or other compliance-related concerns.
                                                                           However, without clear and transparent
                                                                           communication from the IOC, these
                                                                           speculations remain just that—specula-
                                                                           tions.
                                                                              The decision to disqualify Vinesh
                                                                           Phogat has effectively ended her hopes
                                                                           of securing an Olympic medal in Paris,
                                                                           dashing not only her dreams but also the
                                                                           aspirations of millions of Indians who
                                                                           were rooting for her success. For an ath-
                                                                           lete of Vinesh's caliber, who has spent
                                                                           years training rigorously, overcoming
                                                                           injuries, and battling the odds to reach
                                                                           the pinnacle of her sport, the disqual-
                                                                           ification is nothing short of a catastro-
                                                                           phe.
                                                                           Family alleges foul play: A
                                                                           disgusting conspiracy?
                                                                              In the wake of the disqualification,
           Paris 2024                                                      Vinesh Phogat's family has come for-
                                                                           ward with explosive allegations, accus-
                                                                           ing unnamed figures within the sports
                                                                           establishment of orchestrating a cal-
           Disqualification                                                culated and malicious conspiracy
                                                                           against her. These allegations, if true,
                                                                           paint a disturbing picture of the politics
                                                                           and power struggles that can plague
           and the fight for                                               even the most prestigious sports events.
                                                                              Mahavir Singh Phogat, Vinesh's
                                                                           father and a renowned wrestling coach,
                                                                           has been particularly vocal in expressing
                                                                           his disbelief and outrage. "This is noth-
           clarity                                                         ing short of a disgusting conspiracy," he
                                                                           declared in an emotional press confer-
                                                                           ence. "Vinesh has always been a ded-
                                                                           icated and disciplined athlete. She has
                                                                           never compromised on her ethics or her
           By Riya Verma                                                   commitment to the sport. We believe
                                                                           there are powerful people who wanted
                                                                           to see her fail, and they have used their
             n a dramatic and unexpected turn of   was expected to be a crowning achieve-  influence to make that happen."
             events, Vinesh Phogat, one of India's   ment in her illustrious career. However,   Vinesh's uncle and mentor, Mahavir
           Imost celebrated athletes and a sym-  the abrupt end to her Olympic journey   Phogat, who has been instrumental in
           bol of female empowerment in the   has ignited a firestorm of controversy,   shaping her career, echoed these sen-
           world of sports, has been disqualified   with her family alleging a nefarious con-  timents. He pointed out that Vinesh has
           from participating in the Paris Olympics   spiracy aimed at ruining her career and   been an outspoken critic of the way ath-
           2024. The decision, handed down by the   tarnishing her legacy.   letes are treated by sports federations
           International Olympic Committee                                 and has never shied away from high-
           (IOC), has not only shocked her fans but   The disqualification: A bolt from   lighting the flaws in the system. This, he
           also sent shockwaves through the entire   the blue              suggested, might have made her a target
           Indian sports community. Vinesh, who   Vinesh Phogat's disqualification was   for those who felt threatened by her
           was seen as a strong medal contender,   announced by the IOC under circum-  boldness and willingness to challenge
           had been diligently preparing for what   stances that remain shrouded in mystery.   the status quo.

           30                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[The context: A history of adversity   could have ended her career. However,   According to the family, Vinesh has
           and triumph                     Vinesh's indomitable spirit saw her   faced hostility and discrimination from
             To understand the gravity of these al-  bounce back stronger, and she quickly   certain quarters within the sports admin-
           legations, it is essential to delve into Vi-  re-established herself as one of the top   istration for years. They allege that her
           nesh Phogat's background—a story of   wrestlers in the world.   success and outspokenness have made
           struggle, resilience, and triumph against   Given this context, the disqualifica-  her a target for those who feel threat-
           all odds. Born into a family of wrestlers   tion from the Paris Olympics is not just   ened by her influence. Mahavir Singh
           in a small village in Haryana, Vinesh   a personal setback for Vinesh; it is a   Phogat has hinted at the involvement of
           was introduced to wrestling at a young   blow to the entire Phogat family and to   rival camps within the wrestling frater-
           age by her father and uncle, both of   the millions of Indians who see her as a   nity, suggesting that individuals who
           whom were determined to defy societal   beacon of hope and inspiration.   harbor jealousy or resentment towards
           norms and push their daughters into a                           Vinesh may have played a role in her
           male-dominated sport. The Phogat   Allegations of conspiracy:   downfall.
           family, famously depicted in the Bolly-  examining the claims      Moreover, the timing of the disqual-
           wood film Dangal, became a symbol of   The Phogat family's allegations of a   ification, just as Vinesh was peaking in
           women's empowerment in India, with   conspiracy have added a new layer of   her training and preparation for the
           Vinesh and her cousins leading the   complexity to the disqualification saga.   Olympics, has raised eyebrows. The
           charge.                         While such claims are difficult to prove   family questions why the IOC chose to
             Over the years, Vinesh Phogat has   without concrete evidence, the family   act so close to the event, rather than ad-
           built an impressive career, winning mul-  believes that Vinesh's disqualification is   dressing any concerns well in advance.
           tiple medals at the Commonwealth   the result of a deliberate attempt to de-  They believe that this was a calculated
           Games, Asian Games, and World Cham-  rail her career. They argue that the vague   move to destabilize her mentally and
           pionships. Her journey has been far   nature of the charges against her, cou-  prevent her from competing at her best.
           from easy; she has battled serious in-  pled with the lack of transparency from
           juries, including a devastating knee in-  the IOC, lends credence to their sus-  The broader implications: Politics,
           jury at the Rio Olympics in 2016, which   picions.              power, and the Olympic dream
                                                                              The allegations of a conspiracy
        Bottom: Vinesh is requesting to be awarded the silver
                                                                           against Vinesh Phogat highlight the
                                                                           darker side of sports—a world where
                                                                           politics, power struggles, and personal
                                                                           vendettas can sometimes overshadow
                                                                           the spirit of fair competition. If the Pho-
                                                                           gat family's claims are true, they reveal
         Left: Mahavir Phogat's daughters








































           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[a troubling reality where athletes are
           vulnerable to forces beyond their con-
           trol, and where merit and hard work can
           be undermined by behind-the-scenes
           machinations.
             This is not the first time that allega-
           tions of foul play have marred the
           Olympics. Over the years, there have
           been numerous instances where athletes
           have been disqualified or sidelined
           under dubious circumstances, leading to
           accusations of bias, corruption, and po-
           litical interference. In some cases, these                                                      Bajrang Punia, Vinesh Phogat, and Sakshi Malik are protesting
           allegations have been substantiated,
           while in others, they have remained un-
           resolved, leaving a cloud of suspicion
           over the proceedings.
             For Vinesh Phogat, the disqualifica-
           tion is not just a personal tragedy; it is
           also a symbol of the challenges that ath-
           letes, especially women, face in navigat-
           ing a system that is often stacked against
           them. The Phogat family's fight for jus-
           tice is not just about clearing Vinesh's                        Some have called for greater transpar-
           name; it is also about challenging the                          ency from the IOC, while others have
           structures that allow such injustices to                        expressed solidarity with Vinesh and her
           occur.                                                          family, urging the Indian government
                                                                           and sports authorities to take up her case
           The road ahead: A fight for justice                             at the highest levels.
             Despite the devastating blow of her                              The disqualification has also become
           disqualification, Vinesh Phogat and her                         a political issue, with several politicians
           family are not backing down. They have                          and public figures demanding accounta-
           vowed to fight the decision with all the                        bility and action. The Ministry of Youth
           resources at their disposal, exploring                          Affairs and Sports has reportedly sought
           every legal avenue to challenge the                             a detailed report on the matter, and there
           IOC's ruling and seek justice. Mahavir                          are growing calls for an independent in-
           Singh Phogat has indicated that they are                        quiry to ensure that justice is served.
           considering filing an appeal with the
           Court of Arbitration for Sport (CAS), an                        The battle for truth and fairness
           independent body that resolves disputes                            As the controversy continues to un-
           related to sport.                                               fold, Vinesh Phogat's disqualification
             The family's determination to fight                           from the Paris Olympics 2024 remains a
           back is rooted in their belief that Vinesh                      deeply contentious issue. The allega-
           has been wronged and that the truth                             tions of a conspiracy have cast a dark
           must come to light. "We will not let this                       shadow over what should have been a
           injustice stand," Mahavir Phogat as-                            moment of pride and achievement for
           serted. "Vinesh has worked too hard and                         the athlete and her country. For Vinesh,
           sacrificed too much to let her career be                        the battle is now not only about regain-
           destroyed by false accusations and back-                        ing her right to compete but also about
           room politics. We will do whatever it                           reclaiming her dignity and honor.
           takes to clear her name and restore her                            The coming days will be crucial as
           honor."                                                         the Phogat family prepares to challenge
                                                                           the disqualification and seek justice.
           Public and media reaction: A                                    With the world watching closely, the
           nation in shock                                                 case has the potential to become a land-
             The news of Vinesh Phogat's disqual-  supporters have expressed their disbelief   mark moment in the fight for fairness
           ification and the subsequent allegations   and anger, calling for a thorough investi-  and transparency in sports. Whether Vi- Bottom: Mahavir Phogat (Uncle & Trainer)
           of a conspiracy have sparked wide-  gation into the circumstances surround-  nesh Phogat can clear her name and re- Middle: Vinesh Phogat in a hospital
           spread outrage across India. Social   ing her disqualification.   turn to the mat remains to be seen, but
           media platforms have been flooded with   Prominent figures from the sports   one thing is certain: her courage and re-
           messages of support for the wrestler,   community, including fellow wrestlers,   silience in the face of adversity will con-
           with hashtags like #JusticeForVinesh   former Olympians, and sports analysts,   tinue to inspire millions, both in India
           trending nationwide. Many fans and   have also weighed in on the controversy.   and around the world. ■

           32                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                    August 16-31, 2024






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     You’ll find yourself making strides in both     Libra, balance and harmony will be your focus
                     personal and professional areas. Embrace this   during this period. Seek out activities that bring
                     momentum and keep pushing forward.              you peace and joy. In your professional life, col-
                     Relationships may require some attention; make   laboration will lead to success, so be open to
                     sure to communicate openly with loved ones.     working with others.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Patience will be your ally during this time. Some   Scorpio, your determination and focus will help
                     projects may require more time to reach fruition,   you achieve your goals. This is a time for taking
                     but your persistence will pay off. Relationships   action and making things happen. Relationships
                     will be stable and supportive, providing a solid   may require some extra attention, so make sure
                     foundation. Focus on saving.                    to communicate openly and honestly.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Your social life will be buzzing with activity.   Sagittarius, your adventurous spirit will lead you
                     This is a great time to network and build connec-  to new opportunities. Embrace change and be
                     tions that can benefit you in the long run. In your   open to exploring new paths. In your profes-
                     personal life, make sure to balance social en-  sional life, think outside the box and don’t be
                     gagements with some quiet time for yourself.    afraid to take risks.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Cancer, this period brings a focus on home and   Capricorn, your discipline and hard work will
                     family. You may feel the urge to make changes   pay off during this period. Focus on building a
                     in your living environment or reconnect with    strong foundation in both your personal and pro-
                     family members. Professionally, stay organized   fessional life. Relationships will be supportive
                     and focused to achieve your goals.              and provide you with the stability you need.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, your confidence and creativity will be at an   Aquarius, your innovative ideas will set you
                     all-time high. This is the perfect time to take on   apart from the crowd. This is a great time to
                     new challenges and showcase your talents. In re-  think creatively and explore new projects. In re-
                     lationships, be open to new experiences and     lationships, be open to new perspectives and
                     enjoy the excitement they bring.                enjoy the diversity they bring.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, this period is ideal for planning and or-  This period is perfect for introspection and self-
                     ganizing. Focus on setting clear goals and work-  care. Take time to connect with your inner self
                     ing methodically towards them. Relationships    and focus on your emotional well-being. Rela-
                     will benefit from your attention to detail and   tionships will be supportive, providing you with
                     thoughtfulness.                                 the comfort and understanding you need.


           AUGUST 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Justice for Kolkata doctor
             The brutal rape and murder of a 31-
                                           potentially undermining investor con-
                                           fidence.
           year-old postgraduate trainee doctor at
           RG Kar Medical College in Kolkata has   Securities and Exchange Board of India,   could have profound implications for
                                             Such allegations, if proven true,
                                                                           South Asia's geopolitical dynamics. It is
           sent shockwaves across the nation.   could have far-reaching implications for   essential for both countries to prioritize
           Found on August 9, her body bore horri-  the financial markets and regulatory   dialogue and cooperation to ensure
           fic signs of violence, including bleeding   frameworks. It is crucial for SEBI to ad-  peace and stability in the region during
           from her eyes, mouth, and private parts,   dress these claims transparently to main-  this uncertain time.
           as detailed in the autopsy report. This   tain public trust and uphold the princi-  Naveen Kumar, Mumbai, Maharash-
           heinous act has ignited widespread pro-  ples of accountability and governance.   tra, India
           tests among medical professionals de-  As stakeholders in the financial eco-
           manding justice and enhanced safety   system, we must demand a thorough in-
           measures in healthcare institutions.   vestigation into these allegations. Ensur-  Controversy over Waqf bill
             The accused, Sanjay Roy, was ar-  ing that our regulatory bodies operate   The referral of the Waqf (Amend-
           rested shortly after the incident, with ev-  without bias is essential for fostering a   ment) Bill to the Joint Parliamentary
           idence linking him to the crime. The   fair and equitable market environment.   Committee (JPC) has ignited signifi-
           public outcry reflects a deep-seated fear   The integrity of our financial systems   cant debate regarding its implications
           for the safety of women and healthcare   depends on it.         for the Muslim community in India.
           workers in India. As doctors across the   Ashok Sharma, Delhi, India   While the government argues that the
           country unite in protest, it is imperative                      bill aims to enhance transparency and
           that authorities respond with urgency,                          inclusivity within Waqf management,
           ensuring that such atrocities are met   Bangladesh Coup         critics contend that allowing non-Mus-
           with the strictest punishment and that   The recent turmoil in Bangladesh,   lims on the Waqf Board undermines
           systemic changes are implemented to   culminating in former Prime Minister   the autonomy of the Muslim com-
           protect vulnerable individuals in our so-  Sheikh Hasina's flight to India amid a   munity.
           ciety. Justice must prevail for the victim   military coup, raises critical concerns   Opposition leaders have labeled the
           and her grieving family.        about regional stability. Hasina's resig-  bill as unconstitutional and politically
           Akash Banerjee, Kolkata, West Ben-  nation, prompted by violent protests   motivated, raising concerns about its
           gal, India                      against her government, marks a signifi-  potential impact on religious freedoms.
                                           cant shift in Bangladesh's political land-  The introduction of the district collec-
                                           scape.                          tor as an arbiter in property disputes
           Investigate allegations against   Her arrival in India, reminiscent of   further complicates the governance of
           SEBI chief                      her asylum during the 1975 coup, under-  Waqf assets.
             The recent report by Hindenburg Re-  scores the historical ties between the two   As the JPC reviews this contentious
           search alleging misconduct by SEBI   nations. As she seeks refuge, it is vital   legislation, it is crucial to ensure that
           Chief Madhabi Puri Buch has raised se-  for India to navigate this situation care-  any amendments truly reflect the inter-
           rious concerns regarding the integrity of   fully, balancing support for Hasina with   ests of all stakeholders, preserving the
           regulatory oversight in India. The report   the need to engage with the new mili-  integrity of Waqf properties and the
           claims that Buch's actions may have   tary-led regime.          rights of the Muslim community.
           compromised the independence of the   The unfolding events in Bangladesh   Rashid Khan, Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           34                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                                       36
                                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 01 2024
           36                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           36
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>