<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 06 I  MARCH 16 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: BRUNA FOSSILE





               5



                                                            11













                                                           26                                        20
















           4-Editorial: Why social media leaves us  23-Before the Keyboard
           restless                                        26-Whiskey and the art of drinking

           5-Is social media stealing our happi-           alone

           ness?                                           28-Horoscopes

           8-When words flow like rivers                   29-Letters
           11-The changing soul of poetry                  31-Frame of thought

           15-Theatre in the age of streaming

           18-The future under the skin

           20-Lohiya’s lens on modern India









           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Algorithmic Emotions
     EDITORIAL  Why social media                                                    Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           leaves us restless                                                   Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                hen was the last time you         Art & Culture Editor
                                                checked your phone without         Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Wthinking about it? For many of
                                        us, the answer is uncomfortable. A quick   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        glance becomes ten minutes. One notifica-  Vishakha Sharma
                                        tion leads to another. Before we know it,
                                        we’ve slipped into a quiet ritual of scroll-
                                        ing, liking and comparing.                Social Media Editor
                                           Platforms like Meta Platforms and Tik-    Sushil Kumar
                                        Tok are designed to feel effortless. Swipe
                                        up, watch, repeat. The experience is    Art & Graphics Director
                                        smooth, even pleasurable. But beneath that   Vipin Agarwal
                                        simplicity lies a carefully engineered sys-
                                        tem that keeps us coming back for tiny
           bursts of satisfaction, the kind psychologists often describe as “digital dopamine.”   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             At first glance, social media promises connection. Friends across continents. Old
           classmates resurfacing. New ideas arriving every minute. Yet something curious   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           happens along the way. The same platforms that connect us also quietly cultivate   Editor, United News of India, New
           comparison. Someone’s vacation photo. Another person’s promotion. A perfectly ed-
           ited moment that suggests life elsewhere is always brighter, richer, happier.   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             It’s not just envy. It’s something subtler. Algorithms learn what excites us, what   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           annoys us, what keeps our eyes on the screen. The result is a kind of emotional roller   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           coaster. One moment you’re laughing at a meme. The next, you’re reading alarming   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           news or watching an influencer’s flawless life. These algorithmic mood swings can   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Shahid
           leave users oddly restless, even after hours of scrolling.            A Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             The paradox of hyper-connectivity is that people have never been more digitally
           linked, yet loneliness remains stubbornly high. Studies across several countries sug-
           gest that heavy social media use often correlates with increased anxiety and lower   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           self-esteem, particularly among younger users. The question then becomes difficult
           to ignore. Are we choosing these platforms freely, or are we being subtly nudged to-
           ward dissatisfaction?                                                Phone +91 20 40199102
             Of course, social media is not purely villainous. Activism, creativity and com-  Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           munity have flourished online. For many young creators, these platforms provide op-  Baner Road,
           portunity and voice. The problem is less about technology itself and more about how   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           it quietly shapes our attention and expectations.                  Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             Perhaps the real challenge is learning to step back. To notice when the scroll stops   Website www.revoir.in
           serving us. To remember that happiness rarely arrives through an algorithm.
             Maybe the simplest test is this. Put the phone down for a while and look around.   Legal Advisor
           The world offline still moves at a human pace. And sometimes, that’s exactly the   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           speed happiness needs.
             And perhaps happiness, in the end, isn’t something to chase through endless feeds.
           It’s something quieter, found in moments that no algorithm can curate.
                                                                            Copyright © 2026 REVOIR (eZine),
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.

         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                   www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[COVER STORY








































           Digital Dopamine                                                ness has become strangely entangled
                                                                              In today's attention economy, happi-
                                                                           with notifications, likes and endless
                                                                           scrolling. Social media promises con-
           Is social media                                                 nection and entertainment, yet many
                                                                           users walk away feeling restless or
                                                                           vaguely dissatisfied. The question feels
                                                                           uncomfortable but unavoidable: are
                                                                           these platforms simply tools we use, or
           stealing our                                                    systems quietly shaping how we feel?

                                                                           The science of the digital reward
                                                                           loop
                                                                              At the heart of social media lies a
           happiness?                                                      powerful psychological trigger: dopa-
                                                                           mine.
                                                                              Dopamine is often described as the
                                                                           brain's “feel-good” chemical, though
                                                                           neuroscientists say it's really a moti-
           The deeper challenge may not be abandoning social               vator. It pushes us to seek rewards. In
                                                                           healthy doses, it fuels curiosity, learning
           media but learning to use it without surrendering               and pleasure. But when that reward sys-
                                                                           tem is repeatedly stimulated in unpre-
           emotional autonomy. By Naina Kapoor                             dictable ways, it can become habit-
                                                                           forming.
                                                                              Social media platforms tap directly
             t begins almost unconsciously. You   inadequate. Ten minutes later, you're   into this dynamic.
             wake up, reach for your phone and   still there, chasing something you can't   Every notification, like, comment or
           Istart scrolling. A friend's vacation   quite name.             share acts like a tiny reward. Sometimes
           photos. A stranger's fitness transfor-  Maybe it's connection. Maybe dis-  a post receives dozens of reactions.
           mation. A video that makes you laugh.   traction. Or maybe it's something closer   Sometimes none at all. That unpredict-
           Another that leaves you feeling oddly   to a chemical reward.   ability is crucial. It mirrors the mechan-

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             In the endless scroll
                                                                             of curated

                                                                             happiness, ordinary

                                                                             life can begin to feel
                                                                             strangely

                                                                             inadequate.”



                                                                           becomes familiar. Someone is always
                                                                           fitter. Someone richer. Someone appears
                                                                           happier, more successful or more pro-
                                                                           ductive.
                                                                              Of course, these images rarely show
                                                                           the full story. Most posts represent high-
                                                                           light reels rather than ordinary life. But
                                                                           emotionally, the brain often forgets that
                                                                           distinction.
                                                                              Young adults and millennials are
                                                                           especially vulnerable to this comparison
                                                                           culture. For many, social media isn't just
                                                                           entertainment. It's tied to identity,
                                                                           friendships and career ambitions. A
                                                                           travel influencer's sunset photo might
                                                                           quietly trigger doubts about one's rou-
                                                                           tine life. A viral success story can create
                                                                           subtle pressure to achieve more, faster.
                                                                              None of this is deliberate cruelty. Yet
           ics used in casinos and slot machines.   lored to individual tastes.   the cumulative effect can be exhausting.
           Your brain keeps checking because the   The experience feels magical. Some-  Inspiration motivates us in small
           next reward might arrive at any moment.   times unsettling.     doses. In constant streams, it can make
             Apps run by companies such as Meta   One moment you see uplifting travel   ordinary life feel insufficient.
           Platforms and TikTok refine this loop   videos. The next moment you're watch-
           constantly. Engineers analyze vast   ing clips about burnout, loneliness or fi-  The paradox of hyper-connectivity
           amounts of user data to determine what   nancial stress. The algorithm isn't delib-  Social media promised to bring the
           keeps people engaged the longest. The   erately trying to make anyone unhappy.   world closer together. In many ways, it
           result is a personalized stream of content   It simply prioritizes engagement. And   has succeeded. Families separated by
           that feels almost impossible to leave.   emotionally charged content tends to   continents share everyday moments in-
             And once that loop begins, it rarely   keep people watching longer.   stantly. Activists mobilize communities
           ends with a single glance.        Some researchers now refer to this   within hours. Friendships survive across
                                           phenomenon as algorithmic mood   time zones.
           Algorithms that know our moods   swings. Your emotional state can shift   Yet something strange has happened
             If early social media felt like brow-  depending on what the feed decides to   along the way.
           sing a newspaper, today's platforms be-  show next. It's a subtle influence, but a   Despite being more digitally con-
           have more like mood-reading machines.   powerful one.           nected than ever, many users report feel-
             Algorithms track how long we watch                            ing lonelier offline.
           a video, whether we pause on a photo,   The comparison trap        Part of the paradox lies in how inter-
           what posts make us react emotionally.   Humans have always compared   actions have changed. Online communi-
           Over time they build detailed profiles of   themselves with others. Social media   cation often replaces deeper conver-
           our interests, habits and even our vulner-  has simply multiplied the scale.   sations rather than adding to them.
           abilities.                        Earlier generations compared them-  Quick reactions, emojis and short com-
             TikTok's recommendation engine is   selves with neighbors or colleagues.   ments substitute for more meaningful
           often described as one of the most so-  Today we measure our lives against in-  dialogue.
           phisticated in the digital world. Within   fluencers, celebrities and carefully cu-  There is also what sociologists call
           minutes of opening the app, the “For   rated lifestyles from across the globe.   ambient intimacy. We know what ac-
           You” page begins delivering content tai-  Scroll long enough and the pattern   quaintances ate for breakfast, where col-

           6                                                   www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[tal reward loop replaces more grounded
                                                                           experiences.
                                                                              Researchers increasingly recommend
                                                                           small behavioral adjustments rather than
                                                                           extreme digital detoxes. Turning off
                                                                           non-essential notifications reduces im-
                                                                           pulsive checking. Limiting scrolling be-
                                                                           fore bedtime improves sleep. Even short
                                                                           breaks from social feeds can reset emo-
                                                                           tional perspective.
                                                                              Some users curate their timelines
                                                                           carefully, unfollowing accounts that
                                                                           trigger comparison or anxiety. Others
                                                                           practice mindful scrolling, asking a sim-
                                                                           ple question before opening an app:
                                                                           What am I here for? It's a small act of
                                                                           awareness, but surprisingly powerful.

                                                                           Learning to reclaim our attention
                                                                              The deeper challenge may not be
                                                                           abandoning social media but learning to
                                                                           use it without surrendering emotional
                                                                           autonomy.
                                                                              Attention is a limited resource. Every
                                                                           minute spent scrolling is a minute not
                                                                           spent elsewhere. That doesn't make so-
                                                                           cial media inherently wasteful, but it
                                                                           does invite reflection.
                                                                              What if we treated our digital habits
                                                                           the way we treat our diets?
                                                                              Occasional indulgence is harmless,
                                                                           even enjoyable. But a constant stream of
                                                                           emotional junk food eventually affects
                                                                           how we feel.
                                                                              Reclaiming attention doesn't require
           leagues vacationed and which concerts   were completely content with their lives,   deleting every app. Sometimes it simply
           friends attended. Yet that knowledge   they might spend less time browsing as-  means pausing long enough to notice the
           doesn't necessarily create emotional   pirational lifestyles or seeking validation   difference between connection and com-
           closeness.                      through likes.                  pulsion.
             The result can feel like social prox-  Others believe the issue is less inten-
           imity without genuine connection.   tional and more structural. Engineers   A final scroll
             A crowded digital room where every-  optimize algorithms for engagement be-  Close your phone for a moment and
           one is present, but not always truly en-  cause that's what the system rewards.   look around. The room is quieter than
           gaged.                          Emotional consequences become unin-  the internet. Conversations are slower.
                                           tended side effects. The truth probably   Emotions feel less amplified.
           Are we being engineered to feel   lies somewhere in between.       Real life rarely delivers the constant
           dissatisfied?                     Few designers set out to harm mental   stimulation of a social feed. It moves
             This question often surfaces in de-  health. Yet platforms optimized solely   unevenly, sometimes awkwardly, some-
           bates about digital well-being.   for engagement can shape emotional   times beautifully. And perhaps that's the
             Social media platforms are, funda-  habits in ways nobody fully anticipated.   point.
           mentally, businesses. Their revenue de-                            The digital world is designed to cap-
           pends heavily on advertising, which in   The human response: awareness   ture our attention. But happiness, in its
           turn depends on attention. The longer   and balance             quieter form, rarely demands constant
           users remain on the platform, the more   Despite these concerns, social media   scrolling.
           valuable that attention becomes.   itself isn't inherently harmful. For many   It appears in small, unfiltered mo-
             In that environment, engagement be-  people, it remains a powerful tool for   ments. A conversation that lingers. A
           comes the ultimate metric.      creativity, community and information.   walk without notifications. A day that
             Content that provokes strong reac-  Artists find audiences. Small busi-  doesn't need to be posted.
           tions performs better. Outrage spreads   nesses grow. Social movements gain   Social media isn't stealing happiness
           quickly. Envy spreads quietly. Both keep   visibility. Conversations about mental   entirely. Yet if we're not careful, it can
           people scrolling.               health that once felt taboo now reach   convince us that happiness is always
             Some critics argue the system subtly   millions.              somewhere else. Just one more scroll
           benefits from dissatisfaction. If users   The problem emerges when the digi-  away. ■

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[INSIGHT



































           Water & Language                                                Rivers have nurtured civilizations,

                                                                           droughts have shaped migrations and
                                                                           rain has determined whether com-
           When words                                                      munities thrive or struggle. Over time,
                                                                           these realities have seeped into the way
                                                                           people speak.
                                                                              In many ways, water doesn’t just sus-
                                                                           tain life. It shapes language itself.
           flow like rivers                                                When rain needs many names

                                                                              Consider the languages of northern
                                                                           Europe. In English alone, rain appears in
                                                                           a surprising variety of forms: drizzle,
                                                                           shower, downpour, cloudburst, sprinkle,
           It’s a small reminder that language, like water, flows          mist, sleet. Each word paints a slightly
                                                                           different picture of the sky.
           through human history. It gathers meaning along the                Move further north to Scotland and
                                                                           the vocabulary becomes even richer.
           way, carving paths through culture, memory and                  Scots reportedly has dozens of terms re-
                                                                           lated to rain, including dreich for dull,
           everyday life. By Aarav Sharma                                  wet weather and smirr for a fine, persist-
                                                                           ent drizzle. These distinctions matter in
                                                                           a landscape where rain is almost a daily
                 ow many words do you have for   touches the earth. A relentless downpour   companion. The language mirrors the
                 rain? It sounds like a simple   that floods fields. A sudden burst of   weather's endless variations.
           Hquestion, yet it quietly reveals   monsoon rain that transforms dry streets   Across the Atlantic, in parts of the
           something profound about how people   into rivers within minutes.   Caribbean, rainfall also invites expres-
           live. In some languages, rain has only a   Language, after all, is not just a sys-  sive language. Islanders speak of
           handful of names. In others, it arrives in   tem of grammar and vocabulary. It is a   “squalls” that appear suddenly and va-
           dozens of shades and expressions, each   reflection of human experience. And   nish just as quickly. Farmers, fishermen
           describing a slightly different mood of   water, in its many forms, has shaped that   and sailors often rely on these nuanced
           the sky. A soft drizzle that barely   experience for thousands of years.   descriptions to understand what kind of

           8                                                   www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[“



            The number of
            words a culture has

            for rain often reveals

            how closely its
            people have listened

            to the sky.”



           weather they are facing.
             Meanwhile, in Japan, rain occupies a
           deeply poetic space in language. Words
           like kosame describe light rain, while ni-  tions.
           waka-ame refers to a sudden shower.
           Even seasonal rains have names. The   Desert societies: Words for the
           early summer rainy season, known as   absence of water
           tsuyu, carries not only meteorological   If rainforest cultures develop lan-
           meaning but also cultural associations   guage around abundance, desert so-
           with reflection, patience and the rhythm   cieties often shape their vocabulary
           of nature.                      around scarcity.
             These words are more than linguistic   In many Arabic dialects, there are nu-
           decoration. They reflect a long history   merous words describing different states
           of living closely with the sky.   of dryness, thirst or drought. This is
                                           hardly surprising in landscapes where
           Rainforest languages: A         water can determine survival.
           vocabulary of Abundance           Bedouin traditions also include nu-
             In tropical rainforest regions, where   anced terminology for clouds and the
           rain can shape daily life in dramatic   promise of rain. A certain kind of cloud
           ways, language often evolves with re-  formation may signal hope after months
           markable specificity.           of dryness. Another might suggest dis-
             Communities in the Amazon basin,   appointment. Language captures these
           for example, frequently distinguish be-  subtle expectations.
           tween several kinds of rainfall depend-  Similarly, in parts of North Africa
           ing on intensity, duration and timing.   and the Middle East, classical Arabic
           For people whose livelihoods depend on   poetry contains rich imagery about rain
           hunting, fishing or small-scale farming,   arriving after long droughts. The arrival
           such differences are not trivial. A gentle   of water is often portrayed almost as a   Across Asia, water metaphors are
           morning rain might be welcome for   spiritual event. Words associated with   equally powerful. In Chinese philoso-
           crops, while a prolonged storm could   rain carry emotional weight because   phy, water often symbolizes adaptability
           threaten river travel or flood fields.   they represent relief, renewal and life it-  and resilience. A famous saying inspired
             Anthropologists have often noted   self.                      by Taoist thought suggests that water is
           how indigenous languages in rainforest   In these regions, it is not just rain that   soft and yielding, yet capable of wearing
           regions tend to include detailed environ-  has names. The waiting for rain does   down stone. The message is simple but
           mental vocabularies. These words do not   too.                  profound: gentleness can hold great
           simply describe weather. They encode                            strength.
           practical knowledge about seasons, soil   Proverbs that flow through   African proverbs also draw deeply
           conditions and animal behaviour.   cultures                     from water imagery. In some West Afri-
             Even the sound of rain can carry   Water does not only influence vocab-  can traditions, people say that “rain does
           meaning. Some languages use onomato-  ulary. It flows into proverbs, metaphors   not fall on one roof alone,” a reminder
           poeic expressions that mimic the way   and everyday expressions across civ-  that hardship and fortune are shared by
           rain hits leaves, rivers or rooftops. The   ilizations.         communities.
           rhythm of rainfall becomes part of the   In English, phrases like “still waters   In India, water appears frequently in
           spoken world.                   run deep” suggest quiet strength beneath   everyday sayings as well. Expressions
             In such communities, language func-  calm appearances. “You can lead a horse   about rivers, wells and monsoon rains
           tions almost like an environmental   to water but you can’t make it drink” re-  often convey patience, humility or the
           guidebook passed down through genera-  flects the limits of persuasion.   unpredictable nature of life.

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             In deserts people
                                                                             learn to name the

                                                                             waiting for rain,

                                                                             while in rainforests
                                                                             they name its many

                                                                             voices.”



                                                                           bedded within them. Words that describe
                                                                           specific winds, currents or rainfall pat-
                                                                           terns might vanish along with the com-
                                                                           munities that created them.
                                                                              And with them, a certain way of un-
                                                            of landscapes   derstanding nature could quietly fade.
                                                            that people have
                                                            lived with for   Listening to the language of water
                                                            centuries.        Despite these changes, water con-
                                                              A community   tinues to shape human imagination.
                                                            that depends on   Writers still describe rain to set
                                                            rivers develops   moods in novels. Poets still use rivers as
                                                            terms for cur-  symbols of time, change and memory.
                                                            rents, floods and   Even in everyday conversation, people
                                                            seasonal       talk about emotional “waves,” “floods”
                                                            changes. Fish-  of information or ideas that “flow.”
                                                            ermen may dis-    Water provides a language for experi-
                                                            tinguish between   ences that can otherwise feel difficult to
                                                            different types   describe.
                                                            of tides. Farmers   Perhaps that is why water metaphors
                                                            might have mul-  appear so naturally across cultures. We
                                                            tiple expressions   all understand what it means to see a
                                                            for soil moisture   river move slowly toward the sea or to
                                                            or irrigation.   watch rain gather in dark clouds before
                                                              Over time,   falling. These images connect people re-
                                                            these words be-  gardless of geography.
                                                            come part of      And language quietly carries those
                                                            identity.      shared experiences forward.
                                                              Yet modern
                                                            life is slowly   A quiet reflection
                                                            changing this re-  Next time rain taps gently on a win-
                                                            lationship. Ur-  dow, it might be worth pausing for a
                                                            banization and   moment.
                                                            technological     Somewhere in the world, another lan-
             These proverbs reveal something fas-  lifestyles often distance people from the   guage may have a very specific word for
           cinating. Even cultures separated by ge-  environments that once shaped their vo-  that exact kind of rain. A word shaped
           ography often turn to water when ex-  cabulary. Many city dwellers rarely no-  by generations who noticed its sound, its
           plaining human behaviour. Perhaps it is   tice the subtle differences between types   timing and the way it changed the land
           because water is both familiar and mys-  of rain. A downpour or a drizzle may   around them.
           terious. It sustains life, yet it can also re-  simply be described as “rain” and noth-  It’s a small reminder that language,
           shape landscapes with quiet persistence.   ing more.            like water, flows through human history.
                                             When environmental knowledge   It gathers meaning along the way, carv-
           Language as environmental       fades, language sometimes simplifies as   ing paths through culture, memory and
           memory                          well.                           everyday life.
             Linguists and anthropologists some-  Some linguists worry that as indige-  And sometimes, the words we use to
           times describe language as a kind of cul-  nous languages disappear, we may also   describe water tell us just as much about
           tural memory. Words carry the imprint   lose detailed ecological knowledge em-  ourselves. ■

           10                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE



































                                               Metaphor and Machine

               or centuries, poetry has been one
               of the most intimate forms of
           Fhuman expression. A few care-
           fully chosen lines could capture grief,   The changing
           longing, rebellion or love. Poems carried
           the rhythm of breath, the hesitation of
           thought and the emotional tremor of the
           person who wrote them. Yet today po-
           etry finds itself in an unexpected conver-
           sation with technology.          soul of poetry
             Scroll through social media and po-
           etry appears everywhere. Short verses
           sit between travel photos, news updates
           and memes. Some are written by people.
           Others are generated by artificial intelli-  In an age of algorithms, the most powerful lines may
           gence. Increasingly, it’s becoming har-
           der to tell the difference.     still come from the fragile, complicated and beautifully
             Poetry remains a cultural treasure,   imperfect human heart. By Anaya Gupta
           but in the digital age it also competes
           with algorithms that decide what we see,
           like and share. The question is no longer   carried history, emotion and identity.   The digital era has altered this
           whether machines can write poems.   Consider the Persian ghazals of   rhythm.
           They already do.                Hafez, the haiku traditions of Japan, the   Poetry now lives inside timelines and
             The deeper question is whether those   romantic reflections of William Words-  social feeds, surrounded by the restless
           poems can truly mean something.   worth or the passionate lines of Pablo   pace of online life.
                                           Neruda. Each poet wrote from a deeply
           Poetry before the algorithm     personal place shaped by culture, mem-  The rise of algorithmic poetry
             Long before screens and scrolling   ory and experience.          Today algorithms influence which
           feeds, poetry travelled through human   Poetry was slow art. A poem could   poems reach readers.
           voices.                         take months or even years to refine.   Social media platforms study behav-
             Ancient poets recited verses in mar-  Readers approached it with patience, re-  iour. They track what users pause on,
           ketplaces and royal courts. In many cul-  turning to the same lines again and   share and react to. Content that gener-
           tures, poems were memorised and   again, discovering new meanings over   ates quick engagement rises to the top.
           passed down through generations. They   time.                   Poetry, once a quiet and reflective form,

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[“



            Algorithms can
            imitate the rhythm

            of poetry, but they
            cannot remember

            the silence that
            gives a poem its

            soul.”


                                                                              The question of authenticity
                                                                              This raises an important question
                                                                           among writers and readers.
                                                                              If a poem moves us, does it matter
                                                                           who wrote it?
                                                                              Some argue that poetry should be
                                                                           judged purely by its effect. If a reader
                                                                           feels comfort or inspiration from lines
                                                                           written by a machine, perhaps the origin
                                                                           is irrelevant.
                                                                              Others strongly disagree. For them
                                                                           poetry is fundamentally a human act. It
                                                                           is not simply arranging beautiful words
                                                                           but sharing a fragment of consciousness.
                                                                              Imagine reading a powerful love
                                                                           poem and later discovering it was
                                                                           written by a program that has never felt
                                                                           love. The words might still sound con-
                                                                           vincing, but the emotional connection
           now competes with entertainment, news   By analysing vast collections of writ-  may shift.
           and viral trends.               ing, AI systems learn patterns of lan-  Readers often look for the voice be-
             This environment has produced a   guage, rhythm and metaphor. With a   hind the poem, the life that shaped its
           new style of poetry. It is often short,   simple prompt such as “write a poem   language. When machines enter that
           visually simple and emotionally imme-  about loneliness,” the machine can pro-  space, the boundaries of authorship
           diate. A few lines that can be read in   duce verses in seconds.   begin to blur.
           seconds and easily shared.        Sometimes the results are surpris-  Faster reading, shallower feeling?
             In some ways this shift has expanded   ingly graceful. The imagery feels famil-  Another change in the digital age is
           poetry’s audience. Young readers who   iar. The structure resembles traditional   the speed at which poetry is consumed.
           might never open a traditional poetry   poetry. Occasionally, the lines even   A poem that once invited quiet re-
           book now encounter verses online.   carry emotional resonance.   flection might now be read in a few sec-
           Some even begin writing their own   Yet something subtle feels different.   onds. A reader pauses briefly, taps a
           poems and sharing them with a global   A machine has never experienced   heart icon and moves on.
           community.                      heartbreak. It does not remember child-  Poetry has become both more visible
             But the same system that amplifies   hood streets or late-night conversations   and more fleeting.
           poetry can also flatten it.     with friends. It has never watched a   Millions of people encounter verses
             Algorithms reward speed more than   storm roll across the sea.   every day through their screens. At the
           depth. A poem that demands reflection   When AI writes about the ocean or   same time, the constant flow of online
           may struggle in a culture built around   the sky, it draws from patterns in data   content makes it difficult to linger with a
           rapid scrolling. Virality often depends   rather than from memory.   poem.
           on simplicity rather than complexity.   That difference matters.   Are we reading more poetry but feel-
             And within this digital landscape, ar-  For centuries poetry has been rooted   ing it less deeply?
           tificial intelligence has quietly entered   in lived experience. Even the most   The answer is complicated. Some
           the creative process.           imaginative poems grow out of emo-  readers discover powerful poems online
             When machines write poems     tional landscapes shaped by life.   that stay with them for years. Others ex-
             Artificial intelligence can now gener-  A machine, no matter how sophisti-  perience poetry as a passing moment in
           ate poetry with remarkable fluency.   cated, does not live inside that world.   an endless digital stream.

           12                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Poetry requires stillness. Digital cul-                       emotion and consciousness.

           ture thrives on movement.        “                                 That distinction may seem subtle, yet
             The tension between these two forces                          it defines the essence of poetry.
           shapes how poetry is experienced today.   We may be reading        Poetry is not merely about words.
             When technology supports poetry                                  It is about presence.
             Despite these concerns, technology   more poetry than            The future of poetry
           has also opened new doors for poetry.                              The future will likely include both
             Online platforms allow poets from   ever online, yet the      poets and machines.
           different countries to share their work                            Artificial intelligence will continue to
           instantly. Writers who once struggled to   real challenge is    generate verses and assist writers. Algo-
           find publishers can now reach readers                           rithms will shape what readers en-
           directly. A poem written in one corner of   whether we still    counter online. Digital platforms will in-
           the world can travel globally within mi-  pause long enough     fluence how poetry spreads across the
           nutes.                                                          world.
             Digital archives have also made clas-  to truly feel it.”        Yet the core impulse behind poetry
           sical poetry more accessible than ever.                         may remain deeply human.
           Students can explore centuries of litera-                          People will still write poems after
                                                                           heartbreak. They will scribble lines in
                                                                           notebooks during quiet moments. They
                                                                           will search for words that capture feel-
                                                                           ings too complex for ordinary speech.
                                                                              Poetry has survived every techno-
                                                                           logical shift in history. Printing presses,
                                                                           radio and the internet all changed how
                                                                           poems travelled, but none erased the
                                                                           human desire to write them.
                                                                              Perhaps the real question is not
                                                                           whether machines can create poetry.
                                                                              It is whether humans will continue to
                                                                           need it.
                                                                              A quiet reflection
                                                                              Somewhere tonight, a young writer
                                                                           may still be staring at a blank page.
                                                                              No algorithm can fully predict what
                                                                           will happen next. A line will slowly ap-
                                                                           pear, shaped by memory, uncertainty
                                                                           and hope. It may not become viral. It
                                                                           may not even be perfect.
                                                                              But it will be unmistakably human.
           ture with a few clicks.
             Artificial intelligence itself can be-
           come a creative tool rather than a re-
           placement. Some poets experiment with
           AI to generate unexpected phrases or
           structures. Others use it as a starting
           point for new ideas.
             When used thoughtfully, technology
           can expand the creative possibilities of
           poetry.
             The challenge is ensuring that effi-
           ciency does not replace imagination.
             Can a machine feel a metaphor?
             At the heart of this debate lies a
           deeper philosophical question.
             Can a machine truly understand
           metaphor?
             Metaphor is not just a literary tech-
           nique. It is a bridge between emotion   They can produce new metaphors and   And perhaps that is what poetry has
           and language. When a poet writes, “my   poetic images. But understanding them   always been about.
           heart is a locked room,” the image   in a human sense is another matter.   In an age of algorithms, the most
           carries emotional weight shaped by per-  Machines analyse language through   powerful lines may still come from the
           sonal experience.               patterns and probabilities. Humans un-  fragile, complicated and beautifully im-
             Algorithms can imitate such patterns.   derstand language through memory,   perfect human heart. ■

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY








































           Stage vs Screen


           Theatre in the


                                                                           The rise of binge culture
                                                                              Streaming has changed how people
           age of streaming                                                Netflix and Amazon Prime Video trans-
                                                                           experience stories. Platforms such as
                                                                           formed entertainment from a scheduled
                                                                           event into an on-demand habit.
                                                                              Not long ago, viewers waited a week
           Streaming gives us convenience and endless choice.              for the next episode of a television show.
                                                                           Today entire narratives arrive in a single
           Theatre gives us presence and connection. One fills             drop. Watching five episodes in one
                                                                           evening is normal. In fact, many viewers
           our evenings; the other reminds us why stories matter           feel slightly impatient when content is
                                                                           released slowly.
           in the first place. By Pooja Mehta                                 This shift has shaped expectations
                                                                           about storytelling itself. Audiences are
                                                                           used to high production values, cine-
                  hat is it about a dark theatre   Prime Video, that question feels more   matic visuals and constant narrative mo-
                  hall that still feels different   relevant than ever. Our screens offer   mentum. Algorithms recommend what
           Wfrom watching a show at        endless entertainment at the tap of a   to watch next. The experience is per-
           home? Maybe it’s the hush that falls be-  finger. Entire seasons appear overnight.   sonal, curated and private.
           fore the curtain rises. Maybe it’s the   Viewers binge-watch late into the night   Compared with this, theatre can seem
           faint rustle of an audience settling into   and pause whenever they like.   slower, even demanding. It asks people
           their seats. Or perhaps it’s the simple   Against this convenience, live theatre   to leave their homes, travel to a venue
           awareness that whatever unfolds on   might seem almost fragile. It cannot be   and sit among strangers for two hours
           stage will happen only once in exactly   paused. It cannot be replayed instantly.   without checking their phones.
           that way.                       It demands time, presence and attention.   So the obvious question emerges:
             In an age dominated by streaming   Yet strangely, it continues to survive.   why would audiences still choose live
           platforms like Netflix and Amazon   And sometimes, it even thrives.   theatre?

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[The answer lies in something stream-  series they might never have seen other-
           ing cannot easily replicate.    wise.
             Presence.                       When theatres reopened, something
                                           had changed.

           The power of being there          Some people returned eagerly, almost   “
             A live performance carries an unpre-  with relief. They missed the atmosphere,
           dictability that no screen can reproduce.   the applause, the feeling of shared atten-  Streaming may offer
             Actors breathe the same air as the au-  tion.                   endless stories, but
           dience. A line delivered with unexpected   Others hesitated. Habits had shifted.
           emotion can change the rhythm of a   Convenience had won ground.   theatre offers
           scene. A laugh spreads across the room   Producers suddenly faced a new
           like a small wave. Even silence feels dif-  question: how do you persuade au-  something rarer: a
           ferent when hundreds of people share it.   diences to return to a space that requires
             These moments are fragile. They ex-  effort, when entertainment is available   story that breathes
           ist only once.                  instantly at home?
             For theatre lovers, that ephemerality   The answer, interestingly, has in-  in the same room as
           is precisely the point. Watching Hamlet   volved borrowing ideas from the digital
           on a laptop may offer convenience, but   world itself.            its audience.”
           watching it unfold on stage creates a
           communal experience. The story be-  The rise of hybrid theatre
           comes something people feel together.   In recent years, theatres have experi-  stage production online, the next step
             Directors often describe theatre as a   mented with hybrid models that com-  may be seeing one in person.
           conversation between performers and   bine stage performance with digital ac-  Not everyone in the theatre com-
           audience. When spectators lean forward,   cess.                 munity embraces this shift. Some worry
           actors sense it. When attention drifts, the   Some productions are now filmed   that filmed performances dilute the im-
           energy shifts.                  and streamed online after their live run.   mediacy of the art form. Others see it as
             Streaming platforms offer extraordi-  Others offer simultaneous broadcasts,   a necessary evolution.
           nary storytelling. But they cannot rep-  allowing viewers in different cities or   After all, theatre has adapted before.
           licate that feedback loop of human pres-  countries to watch the performance re-
           ence.                           motely.                         When screens inspire the stage
             Still, theatre’s survival has not been   The National Theatre in London, for   Ironically, the streaming boom has
           without challenges.             example, launched a digital platform   also influenced what appears on stage.
                                           where professionally recorded produc-  Many modern theatre productions in-
           The shock of the pandemic       tions are streamed globally. Broadway   corporate cinematic elements such as
             When theatres around the world went   shows have followed similar paths, re-  projection screens, digital scenography
           dark during the pandemic, the fragility   leasing filmed versions on streaming   and multimedia storytelling. Lighting
           of the art form became painfully clear.   services.             design and sound technology now create
             Broadway shut down. London's West   These initiatives serve multiple pur-  immersive environments that rival vi-
           End went silent. Small community the-  poses.                   sual experiences on screen.
           atres struggled to stay afloat. For   They expand audiences beyond geo-  Some plays even draw directly from
           months, stages stood empty while   graphical limits. They allow students   the world of digital culture.
           streaming platforms experienced record   and theatre lovers to watch productions   Stories about social media, online
           growth.                         that might otherwise be inaccessible.   identity and virtual relationships in-
             Audiences grew comfortable watch-  And perhaps most importantly, they in-  creasingly appear in theatre scripts.
           ing stories from their living rooms.   troduce new viewers to theatre itself.   Playwrights explore the tension between
           Many discovered international films and   For someone who first watches a   digital life and physical presence, a

           16                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[greatest strength.

                                                                           Can the stage survive?
                                                                              So can live theatre survive the age of
                                                                           streaming?
                                                                              The honest answer is yes, but not by
                                                                           ignoring the digital world.
                                                                              Theatres that thrive today tend to em-
                                                                           brace change while preserving the es-
                                                                           sence of the art form. They use technol-
                                                                           ogy creatively, reach audiences online
                                                                           and experiment with new storytelling
                                                                           formats.
                                                                              But at the center of it all remains the
                                                                           same simple act: people gathering in a
                                                                           room to watch other people tell a story.
                                                                              Streaming may dominate global en-
                                                                           tertainment. It offers scale, accessibility
                                                                           and astonishing variety.

























            “                              The appeal of slowness          equally powerful.
                                                                              Theatre offers something quieter, but
                                             There’s another reason theatre con-

                                           tinues to matter.
                                                                              A shared moment that exists only
                                                                           once.
                                             It offers something increasingly rare:
            In a world of pause
                                             Streaming encourages constant con-
            buttons and                    slowness.                       A final thought
                                           sumption. One episode leads immedi-
                                                                              Perhaps the stage does not need to
            autoplay, theatre              ately to another. Stories blur together.   compete with the screen at all.
                                                                              They serve different emotional needs.
                                           Entertainment becomes background
                                                                              Streaming gives us convenience and
            remains one of the             noise.                          endless choice. Theatre gives us pres-
                                             Theatre interrupts that rhythm.
            few places where                 When people sit in a theatre, they   ence and connection. One fills our even-
                                           give their full attention to a single narra-  ings; the other reminds us why stories
            stories unfold only            tive. Phones are silenced. Distractions   matter in the first place.
                                           fade. The experience becomes deliberate   And sometimes, when the lights dim
            once, in real time.”           rather than passive.            and a voice speaks the first line of a
                                             For many younger audiences, this in-  play, the world outside seems to pause
                                           tensity feels surprisingly refreshing.   for a moment.
           theme audiences recognize instantly.   Students who attend live perform-  No buffering. No pause button.
             In a curious way, streaming culture   ances often describe the experience as   Just people, a stage and a story un-
           has become both competitor and inspira-  more “real” than watching content on-  folding in real time.
           tion.                           line. Not necessarily better, but different   In an era of infinite content, that
             It pushes theatre artists to rethink   in a way that feels meaningful.   fleeting magic may be theatre’s greatest
           how stories are told.             Perhaps that difference is theatre’s   advantage. ■

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION








































           Tech Tattoos                                                    The rise of bio-sensing tattoos

                                                                              One of the most promising devel-
                                                                           opments is the bio-sensing tattoo. These
           The future                                                      sense. Instead, they are made with spe-
                                                                           are not traditional tattoos in the aesthetic
                                                                           cial inks that react to changes in the
                                                                           body.
                                                                              Imagine a tattoo that changes colour
                                                                           when your blood sugar rises. Or one that
           under the skin                                                  subtly shifts shade when you're dehy-
                                                                           drated.
                                                                              Researchers at institutions like MIT
                                                                           and Harvard have experimented with
                                                                           biosensitive inks that can detect varia-
                                                                           tions in glucose, sodium and pH levels
           Still, it’s hard not to feel a sense of curiosity about         in the skin. Instead of pricking a finger
                                                                           to test blood sugar, a person could
           where this path leads. By Riya Verma                            simply glance at a small patch of tat-
                                                                           tooed skin.
                                                                              For people living with chronic con-
                  hat if your tattoo could do   tists, designers and engineers are now   ditions such as diabetes, the idea is
                  more than tell a story? What   experimenting with “tech tattoos”, a new   quietly revolutionary. Monitoring health
           Wif it could quietly monitor    generation of body art that may blur the   could become effortless, almost invisi-
           your health, unlock your phone, or even   line between decoration and device.   ble. The tattoo becomes a silent guard-
           change appearance through augmented   It sounds futuristic. Yet in labo-  ian under the skin.
           reality?                        ratories and design studios around the   Of course, the technology is still
             For centuries, tattoos have been   world, the idea is already taking shape.   evolving. Accuracy, safety and long-
           deeply personal. Symbols of identity, re-  And strangely enough, it feels less   term durability remain questions scien-
           bellion, memory or belonging. But   like science fiction and more like the   tists are working through. But the princi-
           something interesting is happening at the   natural evolution of wearable technol-  ple is compelling. Our bodies already
           intersection of art and technology. Scien-  ogy.                hold enormous information. Tech tattoos

           18                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[the cultural dimension. Tattoos have
                                                                           long carried personal meaning and so-
                                                                           cial history. Some people may worry
                                                                           that turning them into gadgets could di-
                                                                           lute that symbolism.
                                                                              But technology has always reshaped
                                                                           how we express ourselves. Clothing
                                                                           once carried purely practical value be-
                                                                           fore becoming fashion. Phones started
                                                                           as communication tools before evolving
                                                                           into lifestyle devices.
                                                                              Tattoos may be entering a similar
                                                                           transformation.
                                                                           A glimpse of the future
           may simply make that information vis-
           ible.

           Smart ink and the body as
           interface
             Another fascinating branch of inno-
           vation involves conductive or electronic
           tattoos. Unlike permanent ink, some of
           these designs are ultra-thin electronic
           circuits printed onto the skin, almost like
           temporary tattoos.
             These “electronic skin” systems can
           track heart rate, muscle movement or
           body temperature. Some prototypes can
           even transmit that data to smartphones.
             Athletes, for example, could monitor
           muscle fatigue during training. Patients
           recovering from surgery might wear
           such tattoos to track vital signs without
           bulky equipment. It’s a small shift, but a   dragon. A tattoo of a bird could appear   Perhaps the most interesting thing
           meaningful one. Medical monitoring be-  to flap its wings. A memorial tattoo   about tech tattoos is how quietly they
           comes lighter, more comfortable and   might reveal a short video or message   change our relationship with technology.
           less intrusive.                 when scanned.                      Wearable devices today still feel ex-
             The broader idea is that our skin may   It’s a curious blend of physical per-  ternal. We charge them, remove them,
           become an interface.            manence and digital fluidity. The ink   forget them on bedside tables.
             We already carry technology every-  stays the same, but the experience   Tech tattoos suggest something more
           where. Phones in our pockets, watches   evolves through software.   intimate. Technology that blends with
           on our wrists, earbuds in our ears. Tech   For younger audiences raised in a   the body rather than sitting on top of it.
           tattoos suggest a future where technol-  world of filters, avatars and virtual   Will everyone embrace that idea?
           ogy doesn’t sit on us but becomes part   spaces, this kind of hybrid art feels sur-  Probably not.
           of us.                          prisingly natural.                 Some people will always prefer tat-
             That thought excites some people. It   The body becomes both canvas and   toos that carry stories, memories or cul-
           unsettles others.               portal.                         tural roots rather than circuits and sen-
             Both reactions are understandable.                            sors. And that’s perfectly fine. Tradition
                                           Between expression and          and innovation often coexist in unex-
           Tattoos that come alive with    surveillance                    pected ways.
           augmented reality                 Still, the rise of tech tattoos raises   Still, it’s hard not to feel a sense of
             Then there is the playful side of tech   questions that go beyond aesthetics.   curiosity about where this path leads.
           tattoos. The kind that merges body art   If tattoos begin collecting health data,   The next time someone gets a tattoo,
           with augmented reality.         who owns that information? If electronic   it might not only express who they are.
             Some tattoo artists and digital de-  tattoos connect to smartphones or medi-  It might quietly monitor their heartbeat,
           signers are already creating tattoos that   cal systems, how secure are they? And   respond to their environment or come
           interact with smartphone apps. When   how comfortable are people with tech-  alive through a screen.
           viewed through a phone camera, the tat-  nology that sits directly on their skin,   For thousands of years, tattoos have
           too can trigger animation, music or a 3D   potentially tracking their bodies around   marked the human body as a canvas of
           visual effect on the screen.    the clock?                      meaning.
             A simple geometric pattern on the   Privacy experts have already begun   Now, they may also become a win-
           arm might transform into a moving   discussing these concerns. There’s also   dow into the future. ■

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH




































           Power and Inequality                                            Lohiya was not simply a socialist leader
                                                                           or a freedom fighter. He was a sharp
                                                                           critic of centralized power, a champion
                                                                           of linguistic and cultural diversity and
           Lohiya’s lens on                                                hierarchies. More than five decades after
                                                                           an early voice against entrenched caste
                                                                           his death, his name travels easily
                                                                           through Indian politics, but the sub-
                                                                           stance of his thinking often does not.
                                                                              To understand why Lohiya still
           modern India                                                    matters, one must look beyond cere-
                                                                           monial remembrance and examine how
                                                                           his ideas shaped regional politics, social
                                                                           justice movements and the uneasy rela-
                                                                           tionship between ideology and power in
           Looking at Indian politics through a Lohiyaite                  contemporary India.

           lens reveals patterns that might otherwise go                   The socialist who questioned
                                                                           power
           unnoticed. By Rajeev Khanna                                        Lohiya belonged to that generation of
                                                                           leaders who were shaped by the freedom
                                                                           struggle yet remained deeply dissatisfied
                  hat would Indian politics look   acy. Yet, if one listens closely, some-  with the direction independent India
                  like if ideas mattered more   thing feels missing. The debate around   took. Unlike many of his contempo-
           Wthan slogans? It’s a question   his ideas, the radical questions he raised   raries, he refused to settle comfortably
           that quietly hangs in the air whenever   about power, caste and inequality, rarely   into the dominant political framework of
           the name of Ram Manohar Lohiya is in-  makes it into mainstream political con-  the time.
           voked in political speeches today. His   versation.                His socialism was not imported
           portrait appears at party offices, anniver-  The birth anniversary of Ram Mano-  wholesale from Europe. It was rooted in
           saries are marked with solemn tributes   har Lohiya falls on March 23, a date that   Indian realities. Lohiya argued that class
           and leaders across the ideological spec-  marks the arrival of one of India’s most   struggle alone could not explain inequal-
           trum claim some connection to his leg-  restless and original political thinkers.   ity in India. Caste, language, gender and

           20                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             In Indian politics
                                                                             today, Lohiya’s
                                                                             name travels

                                                                             widely, but the

                                                                             courage to debate
                                                                             his ideas rarely
                                                                             follows.”



                                                                           that democracy must address social in-
                                                                           equality directly.
                                                                              In the decades following independ-
                                                                           ence, India’s political discourse largely
                                                                           revolved around development and na-
                                                                           tion building. Issues of caste discrim-
                                                                           ination and social exclusion were ac-
                                                                           knowledged but not always confronted
                                                                           with urgency.
                                                                              Lohiya took a different approach. He
                                                                           argued that political democracy without
                                                                           social equality would remain incom-
                                                                           plete. His advocacy for reservations for
           regional disparities were equally power-  Kumar built their political careers within   backward classes laid intellectual
           ful forces shaping society.     networks shaped by Lohiyaite thought.   groundwork for later policies aimed at
             He famously proposed what he called   For instance, the rise of backward   expanding representation in education
           the “Sapta Kranti” or Seven Rev-  caste politics in northern India during   and government jobs.
           olutions. These revolutions addressed   the late twentieth century cannot be un-  The Mandal movement of the 1990s,
           caste discrimination, gender inequality,   derstood without Lohiya’s influence. He   which dramatically reshaped Indian pol-
           economic injustice and colonial mental-  was among the earliest leaders to argue   itics, drew heavily from the ideological
           ities. For Lohiya, political freedom with-  that political power in India was dispro-  currents Lohiya helped create. Suddenly,
           out social transformation meant little.   portionately concentrated among upper   communities that had long been margin-
             At a time when the post-indepen-  castes. His famous slogan calling for   alized began to assert themselves politi-
           dence state was becoming increasingly   greater representation of backward com-  cally.
           centralized, Lohiya pushed for decen-  munities challenged entrenched hierar-  But the story does not end there. The
           tralized governance and stronger local   chies long before the Mandal Commis-  social justice agenda today faces new
           institutions. He believed democracy   sion era.                 challenges. Economic inequality has
           should function not only in parliament   Later political leaders transformed   widened. Urbanization has transformed
           but also in villages, towns and com-  these ideas into electoral strategies.   social structures. Identity politics some-
           munities.                       Parties such as the Samajwadi Party and   times overshadows the broader eco-
             Many of these ideas sound strikingly   Rashtriya Janata Dal mobilized back-  nomic questions that concerned Lohiya.
           contemporary today. Conversations   ward caste identities to build durable po-  Still, the central question he raised
           about federalism, social justice and   litical bases. Figures like Akhilesh   remains stubbornly relevant. Who gets
           grassroots governance echo concerns   Yadav still publicly invoke Lohiya as a   power in India and who does not?
           Lohiya raised decades ago.      guiding inspiration.
                                             Yet here lies an interesting paradox.   Why his name is invoked but ideas
           Influence on regional parties   While these parties celebrate Lohiya   rarely debated
             If Lohiya’s intellectual legacy some-  symbolically, the complexity of his ideas   Walk into any political rally in parts
           times feels muted in national debates,   often gets simplified into electoral arith-  of northern India and you may hear Lo-
           his political influence is far more visible   metic. His broader socialist critique of   hiya’s name spoken with reverence. Yet
           at the regional level.          inequality and capitalism rarely finds the   genuine engagement with his philoso-
             Several of India’s major regional   same enthusiasm.          phy is surprisingly rare.
           parties trace their ideological lineage to                         Why?
           the socialist movements inspired by Lo-  The social justice legacy   One reason is that Lohiya’s ideas
           hiya. Leaders such as Mulayam Singh   Lohiya’s most enduring contribution   were uncomfortable. He challenged the
           Yadav, Lalu Prasad Yadav and Nitish   to Indian politics may be his insistence   political establishment of his time, in-

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[“                                                              ganizing force in elections, policymak-


                                                                           ing and social movements. Lohiya
                                                                           would likely say this only proves his
            Lohiya warned that
                                                                              Even his critiques of economic in-
            democracy without                                              point.
                                                                           equality feel strikingly relevant. India
            social equality                                                has experienced impressive economic
                                                                           growth, yet disparities in wealth and
            would remain                                                   opportunity remain vast. Lohiya consis-
                                                                           tently warned that economic progress
            unfinished, a                                                  without social balance could deepen di-
                                                                           visions.
            question India still                                              In that sense, revisiting his ideas is
                                                                           not merely an exercise in historical re-
            struggles to answer.”                                          flection. It can also serve as a tool for
                                                                           understanding contemporary political
                                                                           dynamics.


























           cluding leaders he personally respected.   speeches, particularly when discussing   Remembering the restless thinker
           He criticized bureaucracy, centralized   social justice or criticizing the old Con-  There is something quietly ironic
           planning and even aspects of main-  gress establishment. The appeal of Lo-  about how Lohiya is remembered
           stream socialist politics.      hiya’s anti establishment stance cuts ac-  today. A man who spent his life chal-
             In today’s environment, where politi-  ross ideological lines.   lenging authority has been transformed
           cal messaging often favors simplicity,   But again, the conversation often   into a ceremonial figure invoked by au-
           such complex and sometimes contradic-  stops at symbolism.      thority.
           tory thinking does not easily translate                            Yet his legacy refuses to stay en-
           into slogans.                   A lens for investigating today’s   tirely confined to statues and anniver-
             Another reason lies in the transfor-  politics                sary speeches. It resurfaces in debates
           mation of political culture. Modern elec-  Looking at Indian politics through a   about caste representation, in regional
           toral politics tends to focus on immedi-  Lohiyaite lens reveals patterns that   political movements and in arguments
           ate gains, coalition arithmetic and media   might otherwise go unnoticed.   over the balance between state power
           narratives. Ideological debates require   Consider the continuing tension be-  and local democracy.
           patience, something fast moving politi-  tween centralized authority and regional   Perhaps the real tribute to Lohiya
           cal cycles rarely allow.        aspirations. Lohiya believed India’s di-  would not be another garlanded portrait
             There is also the awkward reality that   versity demanded a strong federal   or commemorative slogan. It would be
           many leaders invoking Lohiya operate   structure with meaningful autonomy for   a willingness to revisit his questions
           within political systems that he himself   states. Today, debates around fiscal fed-  honestly. Who holds power? Who re-
           might have criticized. Patronage net-  eralism, language policy and regional   mains excluded? And what kind of de-
           works, dynastic politics and centralized   identity echo those concerns.   mocracy does India truly want to
           party structures sit uneasily with his vi-  Or take the persistence of caste in   build?
           sion of decentralized democracy.   political life. Some observers once pre-  Those questions are uncomfortable.
             Even opponents occasionally invoke   dicted that economic development   They disrupt neat narratives. But then
           Lohiya strategically. Leaders such as   would gradually erase caste identities.   again, Lohiya himself was never par-
           Narendra Modi have referenced him in   Instead, caste remains a powerful or-  ticularly interested in comfort. ■

           22                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[wrapped in string or inserted into
                                                                           wooden holders, creating the earliest
           Before the Keyboard                                             versions of what we now recognize as a
                                                                           pencil.
                                                                              By the eighteenth and nineteenth   FEATURE
                                                                           centuries, pencil-making had become an
           There was                                                       industry. Among the companies that
                                                                           transformed it into a global craft was the
                                                                           German firm Faber-Castell, founded in
                                                                           1761. Over time, it developed tech-
                                                                           niques for shaping wood casings, stan-
                                                                           dardizing graphite mixtures and produc-
           graphite                                                        ing pencils on a scale never seen before.
                                                                              Another legendary German brand,
                                                                           Staedtler, established in the nineteenth
                                                                           century, refined the manufacturing pro-
                                                                           cess further. Both companies helped turn
                                                                           the pencil from a simple writing stick
           Because sometimes progress doesn’t begin with                   into a carefully engineered tool.
                                                                              It may seem like a small evolution.
           complexity. Sometimes it begins with a question, a              But that refinement mattered. Because
                                                                           when tools become reliable, ideas be-
           blank page and a pencil poised above it. By Ishita Desai        come easier to capture.






                  hat if the most powerful tool
                  behind modern civilization
           Wisn’t a supercomputer, but a
           simple stick of wood and graphite? It
           sounds almost absurd in an age of artifi-
           cial intelligence, quantum computing
           and digital design software. Yet for cen-
           turies, before engineers wrote code, be-
           fore architects opened CAD programs,
           before astronauts orbited Earth, some-
           one sat at a desk with a pencil and began
           sketching an idea.
             The pencil rarely appears in grand
           histories of innovation. It is too ordinary,
           too quiet. It doesn’t flash or beep or up-
           date itself overnight. And yet, from
           bridges and buildings to spacecraft and
           satellites, many of the world’s most
           transformative ideas were first born as
           faint graphite lines on paper.
             The modern world, in many ways,
           began with a pencil.

           A discovery that changed writing
             The story of the pencil begins in the
           mid-sixteenth century in the English vil-
           lage of Borrowdale, where an unusually
           pure deposit of graphite was discovered
           beneath the ground. At first, people did-
           n’t even know what the material was.
           They simply noticed it left dark marks
           on paper and wood.
             Shepherds used pieces of graphite to
           mark their sheep. Craftsmen used it to
           sketch designs. Soon the material was

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[“


                                                                             Long before algorithms

                                                                             and software shaped
                                                                             the modern world, a
                                                                             pencil quietly sketched

                                                                             the first outlines of
                                                                             humanity’s biggest

                                                                             ideas.”


           The first draft of every invention
             Look closely at the history of engi-
           neering and architecture and you’ll no-
           tice a quiet pattern.
             Before blueprints. Before simula-
           tions. Before computer modeling.
             There was always a sketch.
             Leonardo da Vinci filled notebooks
           with pencil-like drawings of machines
           centuries before modern engineering ex-
           isted. In the nineteenth century, engi-
           neers designing railways and bridges re-
           lied on graphite lines to test their ideas.
           Architects drafted entire cities using
           pencils and rulers.
             Even today, many designers still
           begin with hand sketches. Something
           about the tactile movement of graphite
           across paper encourages experimenta-
           tion. Mistakes are easy to erase. Ideas   open design software. The reason is sim-  sitioning to specialized pressurized pens
           evolve organically.             ple: drawing helps them see.    designed for spaceflight. Still, the fact
             Digital tools are powerful, of course.   And seeing, in architecture, is every-  that pencils were once trusted tools
           But they often come later in the process.   thing.              aboard spacecraft says something pro-
           The first spark usually arrives as a rough                      found.
           drawing, a scribble, a quick outline of   When NASA turned to pencils   Even at the frontier of space explora-
           possibility.                      Even space exploration owes a quiet   tion, humanity relied on graphite and
             In other words, the pencil is not just a   debt to the humble pencil.   wood.
           writing tool. It’s a thinking tool.   In the early days of the American
                                           space program, engineers at NASA   The analog tool behind digital
           Sketching the modern skyline    faced a surprisingly practical problem:   revolutions
             Walk through any major city and   how do astronauts write in space?   Ironically, many of the technologies
           you’ll see the legacy of pencil sketches   Regular pens didn’t work well in mi-  that define our digital world were first
           rising in steel and glass.      crogravity because ink relies partly on   imagined with pencils.
             Every skyscraper once began as a   gravity to flow. Early astronauts there-  Early computer engineers sketched
           simple drawing. Architects used pencils   fore carried pencils for note-taking,   circuit layouts by hand. Game designers
           to test proportions, angles and structural   checklists and calculations.   drafted characters and worlds on paper
           balance. Entire neighborhoods were   The solution seemed perfect. Pencils   before turning them into pixels. Film di-
           imagined this way, page by page.   wrote reliably in zero gravity, required   rectors storyboard scenes with pencil
             Frank Gehry, one of the world’s most   no pressurized ink and were easy to use.   drawings before cameras ever start rol-
           influential architects, famously begins   But the story didn’t end there.   ling.
           many projects with loose pencil   Engineers eventually realized that   Silicon Valley itself, the heart of the
           sketches. These rough drawings capture   wooden pencils posed a risk. Graphite   digital revolution, has a long tradition of
           movement and energy that rigid digital   dust and wood fragments could float in   whiteboards and sketchpads. Engineers
           tools sometimes struggle to replicate.   the spacecraft cabin, potentially interfer-  scribble diagrams and algorithms before
             Students in architecture schools   ing with delicate electronics or even   coding them into existence.
           around the world still spend hours prac-  being inhaled by astronauts.   It’s a reminder that innovation rarely
           ticing pencil sketching before they ever   By the mid-1960s, NASA began tran-  begins with a finished product. It begins

           24                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[notebooks.

                                                              And then      “
                                                            there’s the emo-
                                                            tional dimen-    Every spacecraft,
                                                            sion. A pencil
                                                            carries a certain   skyscraper and
                                                            intimacy. It feels   circuit board once
                                                            personal in a
                                                            way that screens   existed as a fragile
                                                            sometimes
                                                            don’t.           graphite line on a
                                                              A child learn-
                                                            ing to write their   sheet of paper.”
                                                            name.
                                                              An architect
                                                            sketching a    They sit quietly on desks and in pencil
                                                            dream building.   cases, rarely attracting attention.
                                                              A student       Yet the pencil has shaped education,
                                                            drafting the first   engineering, architecture and art in ways
                                                            lines of a poem.   that few technologies ever have. Entire
                                                              All of it be-  industries have relied on it. Generations
                                                            gins with graph-  of students have learned with it. Some
                                                            ite.           of humanity’s greatest ideas began as
                                                                           faint graphite lines that could easily
                                                                           have been erased.
                                                                              In a world obsessed with the newest
                                                                           gadget, the pencil remains stubbornly
                                                                           simple.
                                                                              Maybe that’s the point.
                                                                              Because sometimes progress doesn’t
                                                                           begin with complexity. Sometimes it be-
                                                                           gins with a question, a blank page and a
                                                                           pencil poised above it.
                                                                              And somewhere, right now, someone
                                                                           is sketching the next idea that will
                                                                           change the world. ■








           with an idea. And ideas are messy.   A tool that grows with us
             The pencil, with its erasable graphite   Another quiet virtue of the pencil is
           and forgiving simplicity, welcomes that   its adaptability. Unlike ink, graphite can
           messiness.                      be erased. Ideas can evolve. Lines can
                                           be redrawn.
           Why pencils still matter in the   That flexibility encourages creativity.
           digital age                       A pencil invites experimentation be-
             In classrooms across the world, chil-  cause it forgives mistakes. The smudge
           dren still learn to write with pencils be-  of graphite becomes part of the process
           fore they ever type on keyboards.   rather than a permanent flaw.
           There’s a reason for that.        Perhaps that’s why so many thinkers
             Writing by hand engages the brain   keep pencils nearby even in our digital
           differently. Studies have shown that stu-  age. They know that the earliest stages
           dents often retain information better   of creativity require freedom, not preci-
           when they take notes with a pencil   sion.
           rather than typing them.          And few tools offer that freedom
             Artists value pencils for their subtle   better than a pencil.
           shading and control. Designers use them
           to explore form and texture. Scientists   A small object with a vast legacy
           jot quick equations or diagrams in lab   It’s easy to overlook everyday tools.

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[IN FOCUS
































           The Lonely Ritual



           Whiskey                                                         feels poetic. Yet somehow whiskey,

                                                                           more than any other drink, has become
                                                                           its literary companion.
                                                                              The relationship between whiskey
                                                                           and solitude isn’t accidental. It has been
           and the art of                                                  masculinity and the quiet rituals people
                                                                           shaped by storytelling, cultural ideas of
                                                                           build when they need a moment alone
                                                                           with their thoughts.


           drinking alone                                                  Literature’s favourite companion
                                                                              Writers have long turned to whiskey
                                                                           when describing moments of introspec-
                                                                           tion. Think of the weary detective in
                                                                           crime fiction, the war veteran remem-
                                                                           bering things he’d rather forget, or the
                                                                           aging writer staring out of a rain-soaked
           Perhaps the reason whiskey and loneliness                       window.
                                                                              Whiskey works well in these scenes
           remain culturally linked is that both invite                    because it carries a certain emotional
                                                                           weight. Unlike champagne, which cele-
           contemplation. By Aditya Joshi                                  brates, or beer, which suggests casual
                                                                           sociability, whiskey feels slower, more
                                                                           deliberate.
                                                                              In literature, the drink often becomes
                  hy does a man sitting alone   pears reflective, almost dignified. The   a symbol rather than just a beverage. Er-
                  with a glass of whiskey look   room is dimly lit. The glass catches the   nest Hemingway’s characters drink it
           Wthoughtful rather than trou-   light. Somewhere between the first sip   while confronting loss. Raymond Chan-
           bled? It’s a curious cultural image. In   and the last, a private conversation   dler’s detectives pour it after long nights
           films, novels and even advertisements,   seems to unfold.       chasing uncomfortable truths. Even in
           the solitary whiskey drinker often ap-  But loneliness, in real life, rarely   contemporary novels, the solitary glass

           26                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[still signals something deeper. A pause.
           A reckoning.
             Readers recognize the ritual. A per-
           son pours a drink, sits down and lets
           their mind wander. It’s less about intoxi-
           cation and more about reflection. The
           act becomes almost meditative.
             Of course, literature also shapes how
           we see the world. After encountering the
           image repeatedly, the solitary whiskey
           drinker starts to look less lonely and
           more philosophical.
             But that’s storytelling at work.
           The bar as a modern confessional
             Step into almost any quiet bar late in
           the evening and you’ll notice something
           interesting. Conversations tend to be-
           come unusually honest.
             Strangers share fragments of their
           lives. Bartenders listen patiently, some-
           times offering advice, sometimes simply
           nodding. In a way, the bar functions as a
           modern confessional.
             Whiskey often plays a central role in
           this setting. Perhaps because it’s usually
           sipped slowly, it encourages conver-
           sation rather than quick consumption.
           One drink lasts long enough for some-
           one to gather the courage to say what’s
           really on their mind.           tions go?                          That said, solitude itself isn’t always
             Bartenders around the world will tell   Sometimes, they end up in quiet rit-  negative. Many people genuinely value
           you similar stories. The exhausted office   uals. A drink after work. A solitary mo-  moments of quiet reflection. A solitary
           worker talking about a failing relation-  ment on the balcony. A glass poured   drink at the end of a long week can feel
           ship. The traveler passing through with a   slowly while replaying the day’s events.   less like loneliness and more like a
           story no one back home would under-  Psychologists have often pointed out   pause in a noisy world.
           stand. The regular who sits quietly at the   that alcohol can function as a socially   The difference lies in intention. Are
           same corner stool every Friday night.   acceptable emotional outlet. It creates a   we escaping something or simply giving
             There’s something oddly comforting   temporary space where reflection feels   ourselves time to think?
           about these spaces. People may arrive   permissible. The drink becomes a prop,
           alone, but they rarely feel completely in-  almost an excuse to sit with feelings that   A glass, a moment, a story
           visible.                        might otherwise remain unspoken.   Perhaps the reason whiskey and lone-
             And sometimes, a quiet glass be-  That doesn’t mean whiskey causes   liness remain culturally linked is that
           comes the bridge between silence and   loneliness. More often, it simply accom-  both invite contemplation.
           confession.                     panies it.                         The drink slows us down. It asks to
                                                                           be sipped rather than rushed. And in that
           Masculinity, silence and the    The thin line between reflection   slow rhythm, thoughts surface that
           whiskey glass                   and isolation                   might otherwise stay buried beneath
             Whiskey’s connection with masculin-  Still, the romantic image has its   daily distractions.
           ity runs deep.                  limits.                            Sometimes those thoughts are heavy.
             For generations, popular culture has   What literature often portrays as   Sometimes they’re unexpectedly hope-
           portrayed the drink as rugged and   thoughtful solitude can sometimes drift   ful.
           strong. Western heroes, detectives, sol-  into genuine isolation. A single drink to   Either way, the image of the solitary
           diers and businessmen often reach for   unwind may gradually turn into a   whiskey drinker endures because it cap-
           whiskey rather than wine or cocktails.   nightly habit. Reflection can become ru-  tures a familiar human moment. A quiet
           The message is subtle but persistent.   mination.               room. A glass in hand. A mind wander-
           Whiskey is serious. Whiskey is mascu-  Writers themselves have acknowl-  ing through memories, questions and
           line.                           edged this tension. Many celebrated au-  half-formed answers.
             But this symbolism also intersects   thors who romanticized solitary drinking   Not every story needs an audience.
           with another cultural expectation. Men   also struggled with its consequences.   Some are meant for the space between a
           are often discouraged from expressing   Their work captured the atmosphere of   person and their thoughts.
           vulnerability openly.           those quiet moments but rarely the long   And occasionally, a small amber
             So where do those unspoken emo-  mornings that followed.      glass. ■

           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                               March 16-31, 2026










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Your birthday season begins with fresh confidence   Relationships come into focus, encouraging bal-
                     and renewed motivation. Initiatives started now   ance and cooperation. Constructive dialogue re-
                     gain attention. Avoid impatience with colleagues   solves lingering misunderstandings. Professional
                     or loved ones. Channel energy into clear goals and   collaborations move forward smoothly. Maintain
                     maintain balance between ambition and rest.     fairness while protecting your own priorities.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     A reflective period encourages you to slow down   Work routines become busier, requiring organi-
                     and reassess priorities. Quiet planning strengthens   zation and steady focus. Health and productivity
                     future stability. Financial caution proves wise.   improve with disciplined habits. Avoid unnec-
                     Emotional clarity emerges through solitude,     essary stress by delegating tasks when possible
                     helping you approach relationships.             and maintaining emotional composure.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Social connections become valuable sources of   Creativity and enthusiasm return strongly. Ro-
                     inspiration. Friends or colleagues may introduce   mantic interactions feel warm and spontaneous.
                     promising ideas. Collaboration brings success.   Personal interests bring renewed joy. Financial
                     Keep communication clear to avoid confusion     moderation ensures stability while you pursue
                     and maintain realistic expectations.            meaningful experiences and self-expression.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Professional matters demand attention and       Home and family matters require thoughtful at-
                     steady effort brings recognition. Responsibilities   tention. A practical approach resolves domestic
                     may increase, but confidence grows as you han-  concerns. Professional responsibilities continue
                     dle challenges calmly. At home, supportive con-  steadily, but emotional grounding helps maintain
                     versations strengthen emotional stability.      inner balance during busy days.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Optimism rises as new possibilities appear.     Communication plays a vital role in progress.
                     Learning, travel plans, or creative pursuits in-  Important discussions or negotiations move for-
                     spire you. Stay grounded while exploring oppor-  ward positively. Short trips or new learning op-
                     tunities. Financial discipline remains important   portunities broaden your perspective. Remain
                     and decisions ensure long-term security.        open to different viewpoints.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Shared responsibilities require patience and dis-  Financial awareness increases as you review re-
                     cussion. Financial or professional partnerships   sources and future plans. Practical choices
                     benefit from transparency. Avoid overthinking   strengthen long-term security. Confidence grows
                     small issues. Emotional honesty improves trust   when you trust your instincts while maintaining
                     and strengthens personal connections.           realistic expectations in relationships and work.


           28                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






                                           itary actions risk destabilising already
           A painful blow to Muslim        fragile international relations. The
           sentiments                      global community must encourage dia-  His exposure to global governance,
             The assassination of Iran’s Supreme   logue and peaceful resolution to prevent   negotiation and public administration
           Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei has   further escalation and protect maritime   could offer a fresh perspective in man-
           deeply shocked Muslims across the   stability.                  aging Delhi’s complex governance
           world. Khamenei, who served as Iran’s   Harendra Kumar, Delhi, India   structure. At the same time, expectations
           highest political and religious authority                       from the office of the Lieutenant Gov-
           for decades, was killed in a targeted                           ernor remain high, especially in main-
           strike in Tehran on 28 February 2026   Regulating social media for   taining coordination between the Centre
           amid escalating regional conflict.    children                  and the elected government. Citizens
             Regardless of political differences,   The proposal by the Karnataka gov-  hope that Sandhu’s experience will help
           the killing of such a prominent religious   ernment to ban social media for children   ensure stable governance and construc-
           figure has caused grief and anger among   under the age of 16 has triggered an im-  tive dialogue in the capital.
           many Muslims who view it as an attack   portant debate on digital safety. An-  Swati Sharma, Delhi, India
           on their faith and identity. Protests, con-  nounced during the state’s recent budget,
           dolence gatherings and vigils have been   the measure aims to reduce the harmful
           reported in several countries, reflecting   effects of excessive mobile phone and   A crisis of confidence in Bengal
           the emotional impact of this event on the   social media use among minors.    The controversy surrounding the
           global Muslim community. At a time   Undoubtedly, young users today face   Special Investigation Report (SIR) in
           when the world urgently needs peace   risks such as cyberbullying, online add-  West Bengal and the subsequent resig-
           and dialogue, acts of violence against re-  iction and exposure to harmful content.   nation of the state’s governor have
           ligious leaders only deepen divisions.   Limiting early access to social media   raised serious concerns about transpar-
           The international community must work   could help protect their mental health   ency and accountability in public life.
           towards restraint, justice and respect for   and encourage healthier habits.   The episode has once again highlighted
           religious sentiments.             However, a complete ban may also   the fragile relationship between consti-
           Nayab Ali, Meerut, UP, India    raise questions about implementation   tutional offices and political establish-
                                           and digital freedom. Instead of relying   ments.
                                           solely on restrictions, governments,   Such developments not only create
           A disturbing escalation in the   schools and parents must work together   administrative uncertainty but also erode
           Indian Ocean                    to promote responsible and balanced in-  public trust in democratic institutions.
             The sinking of the Iranian naval ves-  ternet use.            The office of a governor carries im-
           sel IRIS Dena off the coast of Sri Lanka   H.K.Muniyappa, Bengaluru, Karna-  mense responsibility and is expected to
           in a United States strike has raised se-  taka, India           function above political pressures. Any
           rious concerns about the growing ten-                           controversy linked to it naturally invites
           sions in global waters. The Iranian frig-                       public scrutiny and debate. Restoring
           ate was reportedly torpedoed by a US   A diplomat at the helm of Delhi   public confidence must remain the fore-
           submarine on 4 March 2026 in the In-  The appointment of former diplomat   most priority.
           dian Ocean while returning from an in-  Taranjit Singh Sandhu as the new Lieu-  Moushumi Bose, Kolkata, West Ben-
           ternational naval event hosted in India.    tenant Governor of Delhi, replacing V.   gal, India
             This tragic incident resulted in signif-  K. Saxena, marks a significant admin-
           icant loss of life and has intensified fears   istrative transition for the national cap-
           of a wider conflict spreading beyond the   ital. Sandhu brings with him decades of   Letters (limited to one hundred
           Middle East into the Indian Ocean re-  diplomatic experience, including his ten-  words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           gion.                           ure as India’s ambassador to the United   Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
             At a time when the world desperately   States, where he played a key role in
           needs diplomacy and restraint, such mil-  strengthening bilateral relations.


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           MARCH 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Sergey Lexin



                                                              Sometimes the most scenic roads
                                                                 in life are the detours you didn’t
                                                                    mean to take. - Angela N. Blount]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                          REVOIR Magazine
                                                                        .in
                                                                                           MARCH 01 2026

                                                                                           |
           32                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026
           32
                                                                   .revoir
                                                               www
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>