<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                       VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 08 I  APRIL 16 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: АЛЛА МОРОЗ





               8



                                                           17













                                                            11                                       15
















           4-Editorial: Why wishes still matter            26-Tea as a chemical experience
           5-Can technologyrewrite the past?               28-Horoscopes

           8-The human need to believe in pos-             29-Letters

           sibility                                        31-Frame of thought

           11-How sound shapes identity
           15-The voice that outlived generations

           17-Healing through release

           20-When stars fade from human life

           23-Technology rewiring human time









           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Imagining Tomorrow
     EDITORIAL  Why wishes still                                                    Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           matter                                                               Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                hat is it about a wish that feels so   Art & Culture Editor
                                                necessary, even when we know it    Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Wmay never come true? A child
                                        closes their eyes before blowing out can-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        dles. A patient whispers a silent hope before   Vishakha Sharma
                                        surgery. Someone staring at a late-night
                                        ceiling makes a quiet deal with the uni-
                                        verse. These moments aren’t logical. They   Social Media Editor
                                        aren’t always practical. Yet they persist ac-  Sushil Kumar
                                        ross cultures, ages and circumstances. It’s
                                        tempting to dismiss wishing as naive, but   Art & Graphics Director
                                        that misses something essential about being   Vipin Agarwal
                                        human.
                                           At its core, wishing is less about out-
           comes and more about orientation. It points us toward possibility. Psychologists often   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           talk about hope as a cognitive process, a way of setting goals and imagining path-
           ways. But wishing is softer than that. It lives in the space before strategy. It’s the   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           emotional rehearsal of a better future, a way of trying on a life that doesn’t yet exist.   Editor, United News of India, New
             And maybe that’s why it matters.
             In uncertain environments, the human brain doesn’t just seek facts. It seeks mean-  Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           ing. When we wish, we’re not ignoring reality. We’re negotiating with it. A student   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           from a small town who wishes for a different life isn’t deluded. They’re sketching a   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           direction. Even if the path is unclear, the wish gives it shape. Without that first fragile   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           idea, action rarely follows.                                    Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Shahid
             There’s also something quietly communal about wishing. Think of shared rituals,   A Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           from New Year resolutions to collective prayers during crises. These acts create a
           sense of connection, a reminder that we’re not alone in wanting things to improve.
           Even in solitude, a wish carries echoes of others who have hoped before us, people   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           who stood in similar uncertainty and still chose to imagine something better.
             Of course, wishes can mislead. When they replace effort, they become escape
           routes rather than beginnings. But most of the time, people understand this tension.   Phone +91 20 40199102
           They know wishing isn’t enough. Still, they do it. Not because they expect magic, but   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           because it keeps a certain door open inside them, a door that reality alone sometimes   Baner Road,
           tries to shut, especially during difficult, uncertain stretches of life.   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
             In a world that often demands certainty, wishing allows room for doubt and imagi-  Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           nation to coexist. It says, things aren’t fixed yet. There’s still a chance, however   Website www.revoir.in
           small, however distant. Perhaps that quiet insistence is what keeps people moving
           forward, even when evidence suggests otherwise.                          Legal Advisor
             I think we keep wishing not out of foolishness, but out of resilience. It’s a small   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           act, almost invisible. Yet without it, the idea of possibility itself might begin to fade,
           and with it, a quiet but vital part of what makes us human.
             And perhaps that’s enough. Not every wish needs fulfillment to matter. Some-
           times, the act itself sustains us, gently reminding us that even in uncertainty, we are   Copyright © 2026 REVOIR (eZine),
           still capable of imagining, hoping, and quietly believing in something more.   all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.


         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH



































           When Time Erases                                                works lost to accidental fires. History is

                                                                           filled with absences.
                                                                              And that’s where the urgency begins.
           Can technology                                                  Preservation is no longer just about
                                                                           maintaining what exists. It’s about cap-
                                                                           turing what might soon disappear.

           rewrite the past?                                               Enter the digital archivists
                                                                              In recent years, a quiet revolution has
                                                                           been unfolding. Teams of researchers,
                                                                           historians and technologists are using
                                                                           tools that sound almost futuristic. Laser
           What’s interesting is how this technology is reshaping          scanners, photogrammetry, drones, im-
                                                                           mersive modeling. Together, they are
           our relationship with history itself. By Aarav Sharma           building precise digital replicas of her-
                                                                           itage sites.
                                                                              3D scanning, for instance, can cap-
                                                                           ture a structure down to the smallest
                  hat happens to memory when   The fragility of memory     crack. Millions of data points create a
                  the stone crumbles, the paint   Walk through any ancient site and   detailed model that can be explored,
           Wfades and the stories lose     you can almost feel the weight of what’s   measured, even restored virtually. It’s
           their keepers? It’s a question that lingers   missing. A chipped sculpture. A wall   not just a photograph. It’s a living
           quietly in the background of every   that once carried color but now holds   record.
           ruined monument, every weathered ma-  only dust. Even the grandest heritage   Consider the reconstruction of an-
           nuscript, every fading mural tucked into   sites are, in a way, incomplete. They are   cient ruins damaged by conflict. Using
           an old city lane. Time, as it turns out, is   fragments of something that used to be   archived images and 3D modeling, ex-
           both a creator and a relentless eraser.   whole.                perts have recreated lost structures with
           For centuries, we’ve accepted this slow   Natural disasters, wars, pollution,   astonishing accuracy. It’s not the origi-
           erosion as inevitable. But now, technol-  neglect. The reasons for decay are many   nal, of course. But it’s something more
           ogy is stepping in with an ambitious   and they rarely ask for permission.   than memory. It’s a form of continuity.
           promise: maybe loss isn’t final anymore.   Think of cities that have vanished under   There’s something quietly hopeful
           Or at least, not entirely.      water, temples reduced to rubble, or art-  about that.

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             A digital replica can

                                                                             preserve the shape of

                                                                             history, but the soul

                                                                             still lingers in what

                                                                             time has touched.”


           When reality meets virtual space
             Virtual reality has taken this idea
           even further. It doesn’t just preserve. It
           reimagines experience.
             Put on a VR headset and you might
           find yourself walking through a temple
           that no longer exists, hearing ambient
           sounds that evoke its past, seeing tex-
           tures and colors restored to their original
           vibrancy. It’s immersive, almost unset-
           tling at times.
             You’re not just observing history.
           You’re inside it.
             Museums and cultural institutions are
           beginning to embrace this shift. Digital
           exhibits allow people across the world
           to access places they may never physi-
           cally visit. A student in one country can   Probably not.       Stories beyond structures
           explore a distant monument without   But perhaps that’s the wrong ques-  Heritage isn’t just about buildings or
           boarding a plane. A researcher can study   tion. Maybe digital heritage isn’t meant   objects. It’s also about intangible cul-
           intricate details without risking damage   to replace. Maybe it’s meant to comple-  ture. Languages, rituals, music, oral his-
           to the original artifact.       ment.                           tories. These are even more fragile,
             Access, in this sense, becomes demo-                          often disappearing quietly without doc-
           cratic.                         Preservation versus experience   umentation.
             But there’s a subtle tension here. Be-  There’s a growing recognition that   Technology is beginning to address
           cause while digital access expands   preservation operates on two levels. One   this too. Audio archives, digital story-
           reach, it also raises a question that’s   is physical. The other is experiential.   telling platforms, interactive maps. They
           hard to ignore.                   Physical preservation focuses on pro-  capture voices, not just visuals.
                                           tecting the original object or site. It’s   Imagine listening to a folk song
           Can a copy ever be enough?      about conservation, restoration, careful   recorded in its original setting, or ex-
             A digital replica can be perfect in   maintenance. This work is slow, expen-  ploring a digital archive of dialects that
           form. Every curve, every color, every di-  sive and often constrained by environ-  are no longer spoken. These are not
           mension captured with precision. Yet   mental and political realities.   grand monuments, but they carry just as
           something feels different.        Digital preservation, on the other   much cultural significance.
             Maybe it’s the absence of at-  hand, is about capturing and sharing. It   In some ways, digital preservation
           mosphere. The temperature of the air.   ensures that even if the original is lost,   gives these intangible elements a new
           The echo of footsteps. The unpredict-  its form and story remain accessible.   kind of permanence.
           ability of light shifting across a surface.   The two approaches don’t compete.
           These are things technology still strug-  They coexist.         The ethical layer
           gles to replicate fully.          In fact, digital tools are increasingly   Of course, this shift isn’t without
             Standing before an ancient structure,   supporting physical conservation. De-  complications.
           you’re aware of its age in a way that’s   tailed scans can help experts monitor   Who owns a digital replica of a her-
           almost physical. You sense the passage   structural changes over time, predict   itage site? Who decides how it’s used,
           of time, not just intellectually but emo-  damage and plan interventions more ef-  displayed, or monetized? These ques-
           tionally. A digital version, no matter how   fectively. It’s a partnership between tra-  tions are becoming increasingly relevant
           accurate, doesn’t quite carry that same   dition and innovation.   as technology advances.
           weight.                           And sometimes, it’s the only viable   There’s also the risk of oversimplifi-
             So, can it replace the real thing?   option.                  cation. A digital model might capture

           6                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Technology may

                                                                             not replace the

                                                                             past, but it refuses

                                                                             to let it disappear

                                                                             completely.”



                                                                              And yet, the memory that stayed with
                                                                           me was not the digital version. It was
                                                                           the quiet stillness of the original, the
                                                                           sense of standing in a place shaped by
                                                                           time.
                                                                              The digital model helped me under-
                                                                           stand. The real place helped me feel.
                                                                              Perhaps that’s the balance we’re
                                                                           searching for.

                                                                           Holding on, letting go
                                                                              So, can technology preserve what
                                                                           time destroys?
                                                                              In a way, yes. It can capture, doc-
                                                                           ument and recreate with remarkable ac-
                                                                           curacy. It can extend access, deepen un-
                                                                           derstanding and safeguard against total
                                                                           loss.
                                                                              But preservation is not just about sur-
                                                                           vival. It’s about meaning.
                                                                              And meaning often lives in the im-
           physical details, but it can’t always con-  But it also raises a subtle concern.   perfect, the incomplete, the physical
           vey cultural context or historical com-  When history becomes editable, does it   presence of something that has endured.
           plexity. Without careful interpretation, it   lose some of its authority? Or does it be-  Digital heritage doesn’t replace that.
           might even distort understanding.   come more open to interpretation?   It stands beside it.
             And then there’s the issue of access.   There’s no easy answer.   A companion, not a substitute.
           While digital tools promise inclusivity,                           And maybe that’s enough. ■
           they also depend on infrastructure. Not   Between loss and continuity
           everyone has equal access to high-speed   At its core, digital heritage sits in a
           internet or advanced devices. So the dig-  space between loss and continuity. It ac-
           ital divide quietly persists.   knowledges that physical decay is inev-
             Preservation, in that sense, remains   itable, but it refuses to let disappearance
           uneven.                         be absolute.
                                             There’s something profoundly human
           A changing relationship with the   in that impulse. A desire to hold on, to
           past                            remember, to pass something forward.
             What’s interesting is how this tech-  Technology, for all its precision, is
           nology is reshaping our relationship   ultimately serving that emotional need.
           with history itself.              And maybe that’s why it resonates.
             We’re no longer passive observers.
           We interact, explore, sometimes even   A personal reflection
           alter digital representations. History be-  I remember visiting an old structure
           comes something we can navigate rather   once, its walls worn and its details fad-
           than simply read about.         ing. There was a small plaque nearby
             This interactivity can deepen engage-  explaining its history, but much of it felt
           ment, especially for younger audiences.   incomplete. Later, I came across a digi-
           It makes heritage feel less distant, more   tal reconstruction of the same site. It
           immediate.                      was vivid, detailed, almost alive.

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[COVER STORY






































           Why We Wish


                                                                           Across cultures, languages and genera-
           The human                                                       instinctive.
                                                                           tions, the act repeats itself. It’s almost
                                                                              Psychologists often describe wishing
                                                                           as a form of mental simulation. We
                                                                           imagine a better outcome, a different
                                                                           possibility, a version of life that feels
           need to believe                                                 more aligned with who we want to be.
                                                                           But that explanation, while useful, feels
                                                                           incomplete. Because wishing isn’t just
                                                                           about imagining. It’s about feeling.
                                                                              Think about the last time you wished
           in possibility                                                  for something. Maybe it wasn’t grand.
                                                                           Maybe it was as simple as hoping a dif-
                                                                           ficult conversation would go well. There
                                                                           was probably a flicker of tension in your
                                                                           chest. A mix of doubt and belief. That
           It’s not always easy. Some days, wishing feels pointless.       emotional blend is where wishing lives.
                                                                              And strangely, it’s not irrational.
           Other days, it feels essential. By Naina Kapoor
                                                                           Wishing as a survival tool
                                                                              It might sound surprising, but wish-
                   child closes their eyes before   amine it. Yet beneath its simplicity lies   ing has roots in survival. Early humans
                 blowing out birthday candles. A   something deeply human, something   didn’t just react to their environment.
           Acommuter stares out of a train   tied not just to desire, but to survival it-  They anticipated it. They imagined out-
           window, quietly hoping for a different   self.                  comes, weighed possibilities and hoped
           life. A patient in a hospital bed imagines                      for favorable ones. That ability to men-
           tomorrow being kinder than today.   The quiet habit we all share   tally project into the future helped them
           Wishing shows up in small, almost in-  Wishing isn’t something we’re taught   prepare, adapt and endure.
           visible moments. It slips into ordinary   formally. No one sits us down and ex-  In modern terms, wishing is closely
           life so easily that we rarely stop to ex-  plains how to wish. And still, we do it.   tied to hope. And hope, research sug-

           8                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Wishing is not
                                                                             escape; it is the

                                                                             mind’s quiet way

                                                                             of rehearsing
                                                                             hope.”



                                                                              There’s also a vulnerability in wish-
                                                                           ing. To wish is to admit that something
                                                                           is missing. That there’s a gap between
                                                                           where we are and where we’d like to be.
                                                                           And that can feel uncomfortable.
                                                                              Maybe that’s why some people stop
                                                                           wishing altogether, or at least pretend to.
                                                                           They call it being realistic. Practical.
                                                                           Grounded. But beneath that, there’s
                                                                           often a quiet reluctance to hope and risk
                                                                           disappointment.
                                                                           Cultural rituals and collective
                                                                           belief
                                                                              Across the world, wishing isn’t just a
                                                                           private act. It’s embedded in rituals.
                                                                           People toss coins into fountains, tie
                                                                           threads on sacred trees, whisper hopes
           gests, plays a significant role in resil-  Still, it’s worth asking ourselves:   into the wind. These practices might
           ience. People who can imagine a better   when does wishing help and when does   differ in form, but they share a common
           future are more likely to work toward it.   it hold us back?    thread.
           They’re also better equipped to handle   There are times when wishing be-  They turn wishing into something
           setbacks.                       comes a substitute for change. When we   communal.
             This doesn’t mean every wish leads   stay in the comfort of imagined possibil-  There’s a certain comfort in knowing
           to action. Of course not. Some wishes   ities rather than facing uncomfortable   that others are wishing too. That hope
           remain just that. But even then, they   realities. It’s easier to wish for a better   isn’t an isolated experience. It’s shared,
           serve a purpose. They create a psycho-  job than to update a résumé. Easier to   even if silently.
           logical buffer against despair. They re-  hope for stronger relationships than to   These rituals also give shape to
           mind us that the present moment, ho-  have difficult conversations.   something abstract. They make wishing
           wever difficult, isn’t the only version of   But then again, even those wishes are   tangible. You perform an action, ho-
           reality available to us.        telling us something. They’re pointing   wever small and attach your hope to it.
             It’s a quiet kind of resistance.   toward what matters.       It doesn’t guarantee anything, of course.
                                                                           But it creates a sense of participation in
           The line between wishing and    The emotional weight of small   your own future.
           doing                           wishes                             And sometimes, that’s enough.
             There’s often a subtle tension here.   Not all wishes are dramatic. In fact,
           We’re told, sometimes quite firmly, that   most aren’t.         The psychology of possibility
           wishing isn’t enough. That action is   A student wishes for clarity before an   At its core, wishing is about possibil-
           what matters. And that’s true, to an ex-  exam. A young professional hopes their   ity. It’s about holding space for some-
           tent. Dreams without effort can become   effort will finally be noticed. An artist   thing that doesn’t yet exist. That might
           illusions.                      wonders if their work will ever reach   sound simple, but psychologically, it’s
             But dismissing wishing entirely   someone. These are quiet wishes, almost   quite powerful.
           misses the point.               private. They don’t demand attention,   Humans are meaning-making crea-
             Wishing is often the first step. Before   but they carry weight.   tures. We’re constantly trying to make
           any plan is made, before any decision is   What’s interesting is how often these   sense of our experiences, to connect
           taken, there’s a moment of imagining. A   small wishes shape our decisions. They   past, present and future into a coherent
           brief, fragile thought that something else   influence the risks we take, the chances   story. Wishing plays a role in that narra-
           could exist. Without that, action has no   we give ourselves, the patience we hold   tive. It allows us to extend the story for-
           direction.                      onto.                           ward.

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“



            Every wish carries


            a small, stubborn

            belief that life can

            still shift.”


             There’s also a cognitive aspect here.
           When we wish for something, our atten-
           tion subtly shifts. We start noticing op-
           portunities, patterns, connections that
           align with that wish. Not because the
           world has changed, but because our per-
           ception has.                    The quiet persistence of hope   values? Our fears? Our unmet needs?
             It’s a bit like tuning a radio. The sig-  Even in difficult circumstances,   There’s also room for balance. To
           nals were always there. We just weren’t   people continue to wish. This persist-  wish, but also to act. To hope, but also to
           listening.                      ence is, in many ways, remarkable.   adapt. To imagine possibilities, while
                                             Think about individuals facing uncer-  staying grounded in reality.
           When wishes don’t come true     tainty, illness or loss. They often hold   It’s not always easy. Some days,
             Of course, not every wish is fulfilled.   onto small, specific hopes. Not grand   wishing feels pointless. Other days, it
           In fact, many aren’t.           transformations, but simple things. A   feels essential.
             This is where wishing becomes com-  good day. A moment of relief. A conver-
           plicated. Repeated disappointment can   sation that brings comfort.   A personal kind of ending
           lead to cynicism. People begin to see   These wishes might seem modest,   If you think about it, wishing is one
           wishing as pointless, even naive. They   but they carry immense emotional sig-  of the few things we carry from child-
           replace it with guarded expectations or,   nificance. They provide structure to   hood into adulthood without completely
           in some cases, complete detachment.   time. They create something to look for-  letting go. The form changes, the stakes
             But here’s the thing. The value of   ward to, even if it’s just a few hours   become higher, the innocence fades a lit-
           wishing doesn’t lie solely in outcomes.   ahead.                tle. But the instinct remains.
             Sometimes, a wish doesn’t come   And in doing so, they make the pres-  And maybe that’s something worth
           true, but it still changes you. It might   ent more bearable.   holding onto.
           push you to try something you otherwise                            Because to wish is to believe, even
           wouldn’t have. It might reveal what you   Living with our wishes   briefly, that things can be different. That
           care about more clearly than anything   So what do we do with our wishes?   life isn’t fixed. That there’s still room
           else could. It might even lead you some-  Maybe the answer isn’t to control   for change, however small.
           where unexpected, somewhere better   them too tightly. Or to dismiss them as   It doesn’t solve everything. It doesn’t
           than what you initially imagined.   unrealistic. Perhaps it’s about learning to   guarantee anything. But it keeps a door
             That doesn’t erase the disappoint-  listen to them more carefully.   open.
           ment. But it adds context to it.   What are they telling us about our   And sometimes, that’s all we need. ■

           10                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[INSIGHT



































                                                        The power of voice


             f you close your eyes and listen, who
             am I? It’s a strange question, but try         How sound
           Ianswering it. Before you picture a
           face or imagine a personality, you’re al-
           ready forming impressions from sound
           alone. A voice reaches you before any-
           thing else does. It carries age, mood,
           confidence, hesitation, sometimes even   shapes identity
           prejudice. And often, without realizing
           it, we respond to it faster than we do to
           facts.
             Think about the last time you heard   A voice carries fragments. Memory, culture, emotion,
           someone speak on the phone for the first
           time. You probably guessed something    intention. It shifts with context. By Pooja Mehta
           about them. Friendly or distant. Edu-
           cated or not. Local or foreign. Maybe
           you were right. Maybe you weren’t. But   raphy, upbringing and belonging rolled   Should I sound like myself, or should I
           the judgment came quickly, almost in-  into sound. A person speaking English in   sound like what’s expected? It’s not al-
           stinctively.                    Mumbai sounds different from someone   ways a conscious choice. Over time,
             Voice is not just sound. It is identity   in London, Nairobi, or Sydney. Even   people adapt. Their voice shifts. Words
           in motion.                      within a single city, voices shift across   change. Intonation smooths out.
                                           neighbourhoods and social circles.   But somewhere in that adjustment, a
           The sound of who we are           And yet, accents are often treated as   question lingers. When we change how
             We like to believe identity is rooted   something to be corrected, softened, or   we sound, are we also reshaping who we
           in visible markers. Our name, our face,   even hidden. That says a lot about how   are?
           our clothes, our work. But voice quietly   deeply voice is tied to identity and how
           does something more subtle. It tells a   easily identity becomes something to ne-  Between tone and emotion
           story without showing anything.   gotiate.                         Beyond accent, there’s tone. The way
             An accent, for instance, is not merely   For many people, especially in global   we say something often matters more
           a way of pronouncing words. It’s geog-  workplaces, there’s a quiet tension.   than what we say.

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[“



            A voice doesn’t just
            carry words, it
            carries history,

            emotion and the

            quiet weight of who
            we are.”



             A simple “hello” can be warm, cold,
           distracted, or nervous. The words re-
           main the same, but the meaning doesn’t.
           That’s because voice carries emotional
           texture. It reveals what we’re feeling,
           sometimes even when we try to hide it.
             Psychologists often point out that hu-
           mans are wired to pick up vocal cues
           quickly. Long before written language
           became central to communication, voice
           was the primary medium. Survival de-
           pended on it. A raised voice could signal
           danger. A calm one could reassure.
             That instinct hasn’t disappeared. It’s
           still there, shaping how we respond to
           people.
             This is why leaders are often remem-
           bered for how they speak, not just what
           they say. A confident, steady voice can
           inspire trust. A hesitant one can create
           doubt, even if the message is sound.
           Teachers, broadcasters, customer service
           professionals, even podcasters, all rely
           on this subtle interplay between tone   phone interviews or voice-based inter-  Bias, hidden in plain sound
           and perception.                 actions. A recruiter might unconsciously   We often talk about visual bias. But
             And then there’s emotion. It slips   favour a candidate whose voice sounds   auditory bias is just as powerful and per-
           into voice whether we invite it or not.   confident or familiar. A customer might   haps more subtle.
           Stress tightens it. Joy lifts it. Fatigue   trust a service agent more if their tone   A strong regional accent might lead
           dulls it. You can hear someone smile.   feels calm and clear.   someone to assume a lack of education.
           You can also hear when they’re holding   The tricky part is that these judg-  A non-native speaker might be per-
           something back.                 ments are rarely deliberate. They operate   ceived as less competent, even when
             In a way, voice is one of the few   below awareness. Which makes them   their ideas are sharp and well-informed.
           things we carry that refuses to stay neu-  harder to challenge.   On the other hand, a “neutral” or
           tral.                             Consider how certain voices are la-  globally familiar accent often receives
                                           belled. “Authoritative.” “Soft.” “Ag-  unearned credibility.
           First impressions, formed in    gressive.” “Pleasant.” These labels carry   This is not about right or wrong. It’s
           seconds                         weight. They influence opportunities, re-  about conditioning.
             There’s a curious phenomenon in   lationships and perceptions of compe-  From media to education systems,
           communication studies. People often   tence.                    certain voices are repeatedly positioned
           form judgments about someone within   For instance, studies have shown that   as standard. Others are marked as differ-
           seconds of hearing their voice. Not mi-  deeper voices are often associated with   ent. Over time, these patterns shape our
           nutes. Seconds.                 authority, especially in men. Meanwhile,   preferences and prejudices.
             Without visual cues, the brain fills in   women’s voices are sometimes judged   In workplaces, this can influence hir-
           the blanks. It estimates age, gender, so-  more harshly, expected to balance   ing decisions. In classrooms, it can af-
           cial status, even personality traits. It’s   warmth with assertiveness, a narrow   fect how students are perceived. In ev-
           not always accurate, but it feels convinc-  space that’s not always easy to navigate.   eryday conversations, it can determine
           ing.                              So, voice becomes more than expres-  who gets listened to and who gets inter-
             This is particularly noticeable in   sion. It becomes a site of expectation.   rupted.

           12                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Before we see a face,
                                                                             we’ve already
                                                                             decided something

                                                                             about the voice

                                                                             behind it.”


                                                                           ourselves and think, “Do I really sound
                                                                           like that?” It’s unsettling, almost like
                                                                           meeting a version of yourself you didn’t
                                                                           know existed.
                                                                              But over time, that awareness can
                                                                           turn into something else. Acceptance.
                                                                           Even ownership.
                                                                              Voice is not fixed. It evolves with ex-
                                                                           perience. People become more confident
                                                                           speakers. They learn to articulate better.
                                                                           They adapt to different contexts. But
                                                                           ideally, without losing what makes their
                                                                           voice distinct.
                                                                              For some, this journey is deeply per-
                                                                           sonal. It might involve reclaiming an ac-
                                                                           cent they once tried to hide. Or learning
                                                                           to speak up after years of staying quiet.
                                                                           Or simply becoming comfortable with
                                                                           how they sound.
                                                                              There’s a quiet power in that. Not the
                                                                           kind that dominates a room, but the kind
                                                                           that feels grounded and real.
                                                                              Because ultimately, voice is not
                                                                           about perfection. It’s about presence.

             And yet, awareness is growing.   often strips away. You hear hesitation.   A closing thought
           There’s a slow but steady shift toward   You sense enthusiasm. You catch the   If you go back to that opening ques-
           valuing diversity in voice. Podcasts, dig-  rhythm of thought.   tion, “If you close your eyes and listen,
           ital platforms and independent media   At the same time, technology is also   who am I?”, the answer is never just one
           have opened space for a wider range of   reshaping voice itself. Voice assistants,   thing.
           sounds. Voices that once felt marginal   synthetic speech and AI-generated   A voice carries fragments. Memory,
           are now being heard more widely.   voices are becoming more common.   culture, emotion, intention. It shifts with
             Still, the journey is uneven. Bias   They’re designed to sound human, but   context, but it rarely disappears. Even in
           doesn’t disappear easily. It just becomes   something still feels slightly off.   silence, we hold onto it.
           quieter, like a background noise we stop   Maybe it’s the lack of imperfection.   Maybe that’s why certain voices stay
           noticing.                       Real voices stumble, pause, breathe.   with us long after the words are for-
                                           They carry irregularities that make them   gotten. A teacher’s encouragement. A
           Voice in a digital world        believable.                     parent’s reassurance. A friend’s laughter.
             Interestingly, as communication be-  There’s also a deeper question here.   They linger, not because of what was
           comes more digital, voice is finding new   If voices can be replicated or generated,   said, but how it sounded.
           relevance.                      what happens to authenticity? When a   In a world that often prioritizes what
             Text dominates much of our daily in-  voice is no longer tied to a person, does   we see, it’s easy to overlook what we
           teraction. Messages, emails, comments.   it still carry identity in the same way?   hear. But voice, in its own quiet way,
           They’re efficient, but they lack tone.   We don’t have clear answers yet. But   keeps shaping how we connect, how we
           This often leads to misunderstandings. A   the conversation has begun.   judge and how we understand each
           sentence meant casually might come ac-                          other.
           ross as rude. A joke might fall flat.   Finding and owning your voice   And perhaps, if we listen a little more
             Voice notes, video calls and audio   At some point, most of us become   carefully, we might start to hear not just
           platforms have started to fill that gap.   aware of our own voice in a new way.   others, but ourselves, a bit more clearly
           They bring back the nuance that text   Maybe it’s when we hear a recording of   too. ■

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[TRIBUTE


































           Asha Bhosle’s timeless sound



           The voice                                                       A voice that refused to stand still
                                                                              Asha Bhosle’s journey was never
                                                                           about staying relevant. It was about
                                                                           staying curious. That distinction matters.
                                                                              She began in an era dominated by
           that outlived                                                   classical influences and traditional play-
                                                                           back singing. Yet, she never allowed
                                                                           herself to be boxed in. From early ro-
                                                                           mantic duets to cabaret numbers that
                                                                           carried a certain boldness for their time,
           generations                                                     her voice adapted not by force, but by
                                                                           instinct. You can hear it in the playful
                                                                           lilt of “Piya Tu Ab To Aaja” and the soft
                                                                           melancholy of “Dil Cheez Kya Hai.”
           It’s easy to reduce a career like hers to numbers.              Same voice, entirely different emotional
                                                                           worlds.
                                                                              There was something almost chame-
           Thousands of songs, multiple languages, decades of              leon-like about her singing. Not imita-
           work. By Riya Verma                                             tion, but transformation. She didn’t just
                                                                           sing songs, she inhabited them.
                  hat does it mean for a voice   sense of loss felt unusually personal,   Crossing genres, crossing time
                  to outlive time? For millions,   even for those who had never seen her   What makes her longevity remark-
           Wthe answer has long been       perform live. Perhaps that’s because her   able is not just the number of years she
           Asha Bhosle. Not just a singer, but a   voice had been a quiet companion ac-  sang, but the number of musical worlds
           presence that seemed to shift effort-  ross generations. It played in homes, in   she entered.
           lessly with every passing decade, every   taxis, on old cassette decks, and now   The 1960s and 70s saw her experi-
           changing taste, every new rhythm that   through streaming playlists. It grew   ment with jazz-inspired compositions
           arrived at India’s musical doorstep.   with people. In some ways, it never   and Western instrumentation. By the 80s
             On her death April 12, 2026, the   aged at all.               and 90s, she was equally at ease with

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[ghazals and more introspective   listeners stumble upon her songs and
           melodies. Then came the unexpected   wonder, almost surprised, “When was
           turn. Collaborations with younger com-  this recorded?”         ience behind that journey.
           posers in the 2000s introduced her to a   That question itself is a testament to   She faced personal and professional
           new generation that perhaps first heard   her timelessness.     challenges, navigated a fiercely compet-
           her not as a legend, but simply as a fresh                      itive industry, and still managed to
           voice.                          A bridge between generations    evolve. There’s a certain grit in that
             It’s rare, almost unheard of, for an   Ask someone in their seventies about   story, one that perhaps shaped the emo-
           artist to remain relevant across such   Asha Bhosle, and you’ll hear stories of   tional depth in her singing.
           sweeping shifts. Most voices belong to a   radio evenings and vinyl records. Ask   You can hear lived experience in her
           time. Hers seemed to travel through   someone in their twenties, and you’ll   voice. Not as a performance, but as
           time.                           likely hear about rediscovering her   something felt.
                                           through playlists or film retrospectives.
           Reinvention without losing        Very few artists manage to become a   A lingering echo
           identity                        shared cultural memory. She did.   Even now, after her passing, it feels
             There’s often a fear among artists   Her voice didn’t belong to one gener-  strange to talk about her in the past
           that change might dilute authenticity.   ation’s nostalgia. It became a thread   tense. Play one of her songs, and she’s
           Asha Bhosle proved the opposite.   connecting different eras of listeners.   there again. Immediate, alive, almost
             Even as music technology evolved,   Parents passed it down without even re-  present in the room.
           from orchestras to digital production,   alizing it. Children picked it up without   Maybe that’s what it means for a
           her voice retained its unmistakable tex-  feeling it was old.   voice to outlive generations. It doesn’t
           ture. Slightly husky, expressive, capable   And maybe that’s the quiet magic.   fade into archives or memory. It con-
           of teasing lightness or carrying deep   Her music never demanded reverence. It   tinues to speak, to surprise, to comfort.
           emotion. It was never about technical   invited listening.         In the end, Asha Bhosle didn’t just
           perfection alone. It was about personal-                        adapt to changing times. She became
           ity.                            The human behind the legend     part of how those times are remembered.
             She could sound mischievous in one   It’s easy to reduce a career like hers   And long after headlines move on, her
           song and deeply reflective in the next.   to numbers. Thousands of songs, multi-  voice will remain. Not as an echo of the
           That emotional agility kept her work   ple languages, decades of work. But   past, but as something that still feels,
           from feeling dated. Even today, younger   what often gets overlooked is the resil-  quite remarkably, like now. ■

           16                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE








































           The art of letting go


           Healing                                                         inclined toward attachment. We assign
                                                                           meaning to experiences, people and out-
                                                                           comes. These meanings become part of
                                                                           our identity. So when something ends,
                                                                           whether it’s a relationship, a career path
                                                                           or even a long-held belief, it doesn’t feel
           through release                                                 like we’re just losing something exter-
                                                                           nal. It feels like we’re losing a part of
                                                                           ourselves.
                                                                              There’s also fear. Not just of loss, but
                                                                           of uncertainty. Holding on, even to
           What if the hardest thing to release isn’t the past, but the    something painful, can feel safer than
                                                                           stepping into the unknown. It’s a strange
           version of ourselves still holding onto it? By Anaya Gupta      comfort, but a real one. People stay in
                                                                           jobs that drain them, relationships that
                                                                           hurt them, or patterns that limit them,
                here’s a quiet kind of exhaustion   rarely framed as strength. It feels like   simply because they know what to ex-
                that doesn’t show up on medical   surrender. Like failure. Like losing   pect.
           Treports. It lingers in late-night   something we fought hard to keep. And   And then there’s the illusion of con-
           thoughts, in the way conversations re-  yet, if you look closely at how healing   trol. We convince ourselves that if we
           play long after they’re over, in the heav-  actually unfolds, it almost always begins   just try a little harder, think a little
           iness we carry for reasons we can’t al-  there, not with resistance, but with ac-  longer, replay things enough times, we
           ways explain. We call it stress, burnout,   ceptance.           might somehow change the outcome.
           maybe even heartbreak. But often, it’s                          We won’t. But the mind doesn’t easily
           something simpler and far more diffi-  Why we hold on           give up that hope.
           cult: the inability to let go.    Letting go sounds easy in theory. In
             We’re taught to hold on. To relation-  practice, it’s anything but.   The quiet cost of resistance
           ships, ambitions, identities, expecta-  Part of the reason lies in how our   What we don’t often talk about is the
           tions. Letting go, on the other hand, is   minds are wired. Psychologically, we’re   cost of holding on.

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Letting go in everyday life
                                                                              Letting go isn’t always about dra-
                                                                           matic endings. Often, it’s about subtle
                                                                           shifts.
                                                                              A young professional realizes that the
                                                                           career they once dreamed of no longer
                                                                           fulfills them. They’ve invested years
                                                                           into it. Walking away feels like wasting
                                                                           that time. But staying feels worse. Let-
                                                                           ting go, in this case, isn’t about quitting
                                                                           impulsively. It’s about acknowledging
                                                                           the mismatch and allowing space for
             Emotionally, it can manifest as anx-  Acceptance is simply acknowledg-  something new to emerge.
           iety, resentment or a lingering sense of   ing reality as it is, not as we wish it to   Or take relationships. Not all of them
           being stuck. Physically, it can show up   be. It’s saying, “This happened,” or   end abruptly. Some fade. Some change
           as fatigue, tension, even sleep distur-  “This is no longer working,” without   shape. Letting go might mean releasing
           bances. Over time, resistance becomes   immediately trying to fix, deny or es-  expectations, accepting that a person
           a kind of internal friction. It drains   cape it.               can’t meet certain needs, or simply al-
           energy without moving us forward.   That’s where healing begins.   lowing distance without bitterness.
             Think about someone who can’t let   Philosophically, many traditions   Even on a smaller scale, we face op-
           go of a past mistake. They replay it   have pointed to this idea. Not as pas-  portunities to let go every day. A harsh
           endlessly, dissecting every detail, imag-  sive resignation, but as an active rec-  comment. A delayed plan. A version of
           ining alternative outcomes. The event   ognition of truth. When we stop argu-  the day that didn’t unfold as expected.
           itself may have lasted minutes. The   ing with reality, we free up mental and   Holding on to these moments adds
           mental loop can last years. Or consider   emotional energy that was previously   weight. Releasing them, even partially,
           someone holding onto a relationship   spent on resistance.      creates lightness.
           that has already ended in every mean-  Psychologists often describe this as   It’s not about becoming indifferent.
           ingful way, except on paper. The at-  a shift from avoidance to awareness.   It’s about becoming less entangled.
           tachment keeps them from fully engag-  Instead of pushing discomfort away, we
           ing with the present.           allow ourselves to experience it. It’s   The role of identity
             In both cases, the past continues to   uncomfortable, yes. Sometimes deeply   One of the most overlooked aspects
           occupy space that the present desper-  so. But it’s also temporary. Emotions,   of letting go is identity.
           ately needs.                    when acknowledged, tend to move.   We often define ourselves by our
                                           When suppressed, they tend to linger.   roles and experiences. “I’m the one who
           Acceptance isn’t giving up        Acceptance, then, isn’t the end of   always succeeds.” “I’m the one who
             There’s a common misunderstanding   effort. It’s the beginning of a different   stays.” “I’m the one who fixes things.”
           that acceptance means approval. It   kind of effort, one that’s aligned with   These narratives can be empowering,
           doesn’t.                        reality rather than in conflict with it.   but they can also trap us.

           18                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[The paradox of release
                                                                              Here’s  the  strange  thing  about  let-
                                                                           ting  go:  it  often  gives  us  back  more
                                                                           than  it  takes  away.
                                                                              When  we  release  control,  we  often
                                                                           gain  clarity.  When  we  let  go  of  rigid
                                                                           expectations,  we  become  more  open
                                                                           to  possibility.  When  we  stop  clinging
                                                                           to  the  past,  we  become  more  present.
                                                                              It’s  not  immediate.  And  it’s  rarely
                                                                           complete.  Letting  go  tends  to  happen
                                                                           in  layers.  You  might  think  you’ve
                                                                           moved  on,  only  to  find  remnants  of
                                                                           attachment  resurfacing  later.  That’s
                                                                           normal.  It  doesn’t  mean  you’ve
                                                                           failed.  It  means  you’re  human.
                                                                              Healing  isn’t  linear.  It  circles
                                                                           back,  pauses,  moves  forward  again.
                                                          1. Notice what
                                                          you’re holding onto   A  quieter  kind  of  strength
                                                            This sounds ob-   We  tend  to  admire  visible
                                                          vious, but it’s often   strength.  The  kind  that  pushes
                                                          overlooked. What   through,  that  endures,  that  refuses  to
                                                          thoughts keep re-  break.  But  there’s  another  kind  of
                                                          turning? What situ-  strength,  quieter  and  less  celebrated.
                                                          ations feel unre-  The  strength  to  release.
                                                          solved? Awareness   It  shows  up  in  small  decisions.  In
                                                          is the first step.   choosing  not  to  respond  to  something
                                                                           that  once  would  have  triggered  you.
                                                          2. Name the      In  accepting  an  apology  you  may
                                                          emotion          never  receive.  In  allowing  yourself  to
                                                            Is it anger, sad-  outgrow  something  without  guilt.
                                                          ness, regret, fear?   It  doesn’t  make  headlines.  But  it
                                                          Naming emotions   changes  lives,  slowly,  from  the  inside
                                                          can reduce their in-  out.
                                                          tensity. It brings
                                                          clarity to what might   Closing  reflection
                                                          otherwise feel like a   Letting  go  isn’t  a  single  moment.
                                                          vague heaviness.   It’s  a  series  of  choices.  Some  con-
                                                                           scious,  some  almost  instinctive.  And
                                                          3. Allow the feeling   it’s  rarely  perfect.
                                                          without rushing to   There  are  days  when  you’ll  feel
                                                          fix it           lighter,  as  if  something  has  finally
                                                            This is where   shifted.  And  there  are  days  when  the
                                                          many people strug-  weight  returns,  unexpectedly.  That’s
             When a situation challenges that iden-  gle. The instinct is to solve, distract or   part  of  the  process.
           tity, letting go can feel like losing our-  suppress. Instead, try sitting with the feel-  Maybe  the  goal  isn’t  to  master
           selves. But in reality, it’s often an oppor-  ing, even briefly. It won’t last forever,   letting  go  completely.  Maybe  it’s  to
           tunity to expand.               even if it feels like it might.   become  a  little  more  willing,  a  little
             Consider someone who’s always been                            more  open  to  the  idea  that  not  ev-
           seen as strong, the one others rely on. Let-  4. Question the story   erything  needs  to  be  held  onto.
           ting go, for them, might mean admitting   What are you telling yourself about   Because  sometimes,  the  healing
           vulnerability. Asking for help. Redefin-  the situation? Is it entirely accurate? Are   we’re  searching  for  isn’t  found  in
           ing strength not as constant resilience, but   there other perspectives? This doesn’t   fixing  what’s  broken  or  reclaiming
           as the ability to adapt.        mean invalidating your experience, but it   what’s  lost.  It’s  found  in  the  simple,
             It’s uncomfortable. It disrupts the   does mean loosening the grip of a single   difficult  act  of  release.
           story. But it also makes room for a more   narrative.              And  in  that  release,  something
           nuanced, flexible sense of self.                                quieter  begins  to  grow.  Not  immedi-
                                           5. Choose what to carry forward   ately  visible,  not  dramatic,  but  steady.
           How to begin releasing            Letting go doesn’t mean forgetting. It   A  sense  of  space.
             There’s no single method for letting   means deciding what’s worth keeping.   A  sense  of  ease.  A  sense,  per-
           go. It’s less a technique and more a prac-  Lessons, perhaps. Growth. But not the   haps,  of  finally  being  able  to  breathe
           tice. Still, there are a few ways to begin.   weight.           again. ■

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY  The disappearing night sky                             less. It doesn’t poison rivers or choke
                                                                              Light pollution sounds almost harm-

                                                                           the air. It doesn’t leave visible scars on
                                                                           the land. But it spreads quietly, relent-
           When stars fade
                                                                           lessly, and often without resistance.
                                                                              Streetlights, billboards, glass towers,
                                                                           floodlit monuments, LED screens. Indi-

                                                                           sirable. Together, they create a dome of
           from human life                                                 vidually, they seem necessary, even de-
                                                                           artificial brightness that washes out the
                                                                           faint glow of distant stars.
                                                                              There are different forms of this pol-
                                                                           lution. Skyglow, the most visible, is the
                                                                           diffuse brightness over cities that turns
           There are efforts underway. Communities advocating              night into a dull orange or white haze.
                                                                           Glare from poorly designed lighting
           for responsible lighting. Scientists tracking changes in        strains the eyes and reduces visibility.
                                                                           Light trespass spills into homes and hab-
           sky brightness. By Rohan Kapoor                                 itats where it doesn’t belong.




                  hen was the last time you
                  looked up and saw a sky full
           Wof stars, not just a handful
           struggling through a hazy glow? For
           many people today, that question lands
           somewhere between nostalgia and con-
           fusion. They’ve seen stars, of course. A
           few bright ones, maybe a planet or two.
           But the vast river of light our ancestors
           called home, the Milky Way, has quietly
           slipped out of everyday human experi-
           ence. Not vanished from the universe,
           but from our lives.
             This isn’t about astronomy alone. It’s
           about what happens when something an-
           cient and shared fades without us fully
           noticing.
             Farmers read seasons in the stars.
           Sailors navigated oceans by them. Sto-
           rytellers wove constellations into myths
           that explained life, death and everything
           in between. Even those who never stud-
           ied the heavens still lived under them,
           night after night, absorbing a quiet sense
           of scale.
             The sky was a shared language. It
           didn’t matter where you were born. You
           could step outside, look up and feel con-
           nected to something vast and enduring.
           Today, that experience is
           becoming rare.
             Studies suggest that a significant por-
           tion of the global population, especially
           in urban areas, can no longer see the
           Milky Way with the naked eye. In some
           regions, children grow up without ever
           witnessing a truly dark sky. Not once.
             It’s not that the stars have dimmed.
           It’s that we’ve brightened everything
           else.

           20                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[and protected reserves, the stars still
                                                                           shine in their full intensity. There are
                                                                           designated dark sky parks and regions
                                                                           where artificial lighting is carefully
                                                                           managed. In these places, the Milky
                                                                           Way stretches across the sky like a lumi-
                                                                           nous river, just as it did centuries ago.
                                                                              But access to such places isn’t equal.
                                                                           For many urban residents, especially in
                                                                           densely populated regions, reaching a
                                                                           truly dark sky requires travel, time and
                                                                           resources.
                                                                              This creates a subtle divide. The ex-
                                                                           perience of a natural night sky becomes
                                                                           something you have to seek out, rather
                                                                           than something you simply live with.
                                                                              And when something becomes occa-
                                                                           sional, it risks becoming optional.
             And then there’s the cumulative ef-
           fect. As cities expand and technologies
           become cheaper, illumination increases.
           More light feels like progress. Brighter
           streets feel safer. But the unintended
           consequence is a sky that slowly dis-
           appears.
             What’s striking is how normalized
           this has become. Many people don’t re-
           alize anything is missing. If you’ve
           never seen a sky dense with stars, you
           don’t know what you’re not seeing.
           What we lose beyond the stars
             The loss of the night sky isn’t just
           aesthetic. It’s cultural, psychological and
           even scientific.
                                             Without the stars, we lose a subtle   Can cities and stars coexist?
           A fading cultural inheritance   but powerful emotional anchor. That   It’s tempting to frame this as an
             Across civilizations, the stars have   quiet moment of looking up and realiz-  either-or situation. Either we have mod-
           shaped identity. Indigenous communities   ing how vast everything is. That feeling   ern, well-lit cities, or we preserve the
           mapped stories across constellations,   doesn’t come easily from a glowing sky-  night sky. But that’s not entirely true.
           embedding knowledge about land, sea-  line.                        The issue isn’t light itself. It’s how
           sons and survival. Ancient texts from                           we use it.
           Greece, India, China and the Arab world   A barrier to curiosity and science   Better-designed lighting can signifi-
           are filled with celestial references that   Astronomy often begins with simple   cantly reduce pollution without compro-
           guided philosophy and daily life.   observation. A child notices a bright ob-  mising safety or functionality. Shielded
             As the stars fade from view, so does   ject, asks a question, follows curiosity.   fixtures direct light downward instead of
           a part of that heritage. Traditions that   But if the sky itself is obscured, that first   scattering it into the sky. Warmer color
           once relied on direct observation risk   spark becomes less likely.   temperatures reduce the harsh blue light
           becoming abstract, disconnected from   While professional astronomy has   that contributes heavily to skyglow.
           lived experience.               moved to remote observatories and ad-  Timers and motion sensors ensure light
             It’s like inheriting a language you can   vanced instruments, public engagement   is used only when needed.
           read but never hear spoken.     still matters. Amateur astronomers, stu-  Some cities have begun to experi-
                                           dents and casual observers form the base   ment with these approaches. Not out of
           A quieter sense of wonder       of scientific curiosity.        nostalgia, but practicality. Reducing un-
             There’s something about a dark sky   When the sky disappears, so does an   necessary lighting saves energy, lowers
           that recalibrates the mind. It makes ev-  accessible entry point into science.   costs and improves quality of life.
           eryday concerns feel smaller, not in a                             There’s also a growing awareness
           dismissive way, but in a grounding one.   The uneven geography of   that darkness has value. Not as absence,
             Urban life rarely offers that perspec-  darkness              but as a resource. Something to be pro-
           tive. We’re surrounded by constant stim-  The irony is that the night sky hasn’t   tected, like clean air or quiet spaces.
           ulation, noise, light, urgency. The night   disappeared everywhere. It’s just be-  Still, change is slow. Lighting is
           no longer signals rest or reflection. It’s   come unevenly distributed.   deeply embedded in how we design and
           just an extension of day.         In remote deserts, high mountains   experience urban environments. Shifting

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[that mindset requires not just policy, but
           public understanding.
           Relearning how to look up
             Perhaps the most overlooked aspect
           of this issue is behavioral.
             Even in places where a few stars are
           visible, many people rarely look up.
           Our attention is directed downward, to-
           ward screens, streets, immediate sur-
           roundings. The sky becomes peripheral.
             Reconnecting with the night sky
           doesn’t always require a remote expedi-
           tion. Sometimes it begins with small
           acts. Turning off unnecessary lights.
           Stepping outside for a few minutes. Let-
           ting your eyes adjust to the dark.
             At first, you might see only a hand-
           ful of stars. Then a few more. Grad-
           ually, patterns emerge. A sense of depth
           returns.
             It’s a quiet process. Easy to dismiss,
           but surprisingly meaningful.

           A personal reflection on vanishing
           light
             There’s a particular kind of memory
           that surfaces when people talk about the
           night sky. A childhood trip to a village.
           A power outage that revealed an unex-
           pected sky. A moment during travel
           when the stars felt overwhelming in
           their number.
             These memories tend to carry a cer-
           tain softness. Not dramatic, not life-
           changing in an obvious way. Just
           quietly significant.
             What’s striking is how often they’re
           framed in the past tense.
             It’s not that such experiences are
           gone forever. But they’re becoming less
           common, less accessible, less woven
           into everyday life.
             And that raises a simple question.
           What happens when future generations
           don’t have those memories at all?

           Holding on to what we can still
           see
             The disappearing night sky isn’t an
           irreversible loss. Not yet.
             There are efforts underway. Com-
           munities advocating for responsible
           lighting. Scientists tracking changes in
           sky brightness. Educators bringing as-
           tronomy into classrooms in new ways.
           Travelers seeking out dark sky destina-
           tions and sharing their experiences.   Because the sky hasn’t really gone   you’ll step outside, look up and catch a
             But beyond organized efforts, there’s   anywhere. It’s still there, above the   glimpse of what’s been fading. Not a
           also a quieter responsibility. To notice.   haze, waiting.      full sky, perhaps. Just a few more stars
           To care. To recognize that something as   The real question is whether we’ll   than usual.
           seemingly distant as the stars is still   make space for it again.   Sometimes, that’s enough to remind
           part of our shared environment.   And maybe, on some clear night,   us what we’ve been missing. ■

           22                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[DEEP DIVE































           Blue Light Nation


                                                                           three. Somewhere along the way, human
                                                                           time stopped being tied to the sun and
           Technology                                                      started orbiting around devices. And per-
                                                                           haps the most curious part is this: we
                                                                           don’t always feel in control of it.

                                                                           The science behind the glow
           rewiring                                                        fact, it’s everywhere. Sunlight contains a
                                                                              Blue light isn’t inherently bad. In
                                                                           significant amount of it and during the
                                                                           day, it helps us stay alert, focused and
                                                                           awake. It tells our brain that it’s time to
                                                                           be active.
           human time                                                      light appears at night, it confuses the
                                                                              But here’s the catch. When that same
                                                                           body.
                                                                              Our internal clock, often called the
                                                                           circadian rhythm, relies heavily on light
                                                                           cues. As evening approaches, the brain
           When was the last time your day truly ended                     releases melatonin, a hormone that sig-
                                                                           nals sleep. Exposure to blue light from
           because the sun went down, not because your                     phones, laptops and televisions sup-
                                                                           presses that release. The body delays its
           battery did? By Aditya Joshi                                    own shutdown process, even if the mind
                                                                           feels tired.
                                                                              So you lie in bed, exhausted but
                here was a time when evenings   night and leisure stretches past what   strangely alert, eyes adjusting to dark-
                had a natural rhythm. The light   used to be considered “late.”   ness that arrived too late.
           Tsoftened, conversations slowed   We rarely notice when it happened.   It’s not just about sleep duration. It’s
           and the body, almost instinctively, began   There was no announcement, no turning   about sleep quality. Studies have shown
           to prepare for rest. Today, that rhythm   point. Just a gradual shift, one evening   that late-night screen exposure reduces
           feels… negotiable. The glow of screens   at a time. A quick scroll before bed   deep sleep phases, the kind that truly re-
           has replaced twilight. Notifications   turned into an hour. A late email became   stores the body. The result is subtle but
           punctuate silence. Work seeps into mid-  routine. A streaming episode rolled into   persistent. You wake up feeling like

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             We haven’t just
                                                                             extended the day,

                                                                             we’ve quietly

                                                                             erased the night.”



                                                                           the natural cycle of activity and rest be-
                                                                           comes fragmented.
                                                                           The erosion of natural rhythms
                                                                              Human beings evolved with predict-
                                                                           able cycles. Daylight signaled activity.
                                                                           Darkness signaled rest. Meals, move-
                                                                           ment and social interaction followed
                                                                           fairly stable patterns.
                                                                              Now, those cues are diluted.
                                                                              You can eat at midnight, work at
                                                                           dawn, watch movies at 3 am and attend
                                                                           meetings across continents before break-
                                                                           fast. Flexibility has its advantages, no
                                                                           doubt. It allows for creativity, accessibil-
                                                                           ity and new opportunities.
                                                                              But there’s a cost.
                                                                              When routines become irregular, the
                                                                           body struggles to maintain balance. Hor-
                                                                           mones fluctuate. Sleep becomes incon-
                                                                           sistent. Energy levels rise and fall unpre-
                                                                           dictably. Over time, this can contribute
                                                                           to stress, fatigue and even long-term
                                                                           health issues like metabolic disorders or
           you’ve slept, but not quite rested.   Work, time zones and the always-  mood disturbances.
                                           on culture                         It’s not dramatic. It’s gradual. A slow
           Dopamine loops and digital habits   For many professionals, especially in   drift away from what the body expects.
             If blue light disrupts the body, dopa-  urban environments, the boundaries be-
           mine hooks the mind.            tween work and rest have blurred almost   Real lives, real consequences
             Every notification, like, message, or   entirely. Global teams mean emails ar-  Talk to anyone juggling a demanding
           update carries a small reward. It’s unpre-  rive at odd hours. Remote work, while   job and a digital life and you’ll hear fa-
           dictable, which makes it powerful. You   flexible, often extends the workday   miliar stories.
           don’t know when something interesting   rather than compressing it.   A young professional in Mumbai de-
           will appear, so you keep checking. Just   A message at 10 pm no longer feels   scribes checking emails at 2 am “just to
           one more scroll. Just one more refresh.   unusual. In fact, it can feel expected.   stay ahead,” only to wake up groggy and
             This cycle isn’t accidental. Platforms   There’s a quiet pressure to respond,   irritable. A college student admits to
           are designed to keep attention engaged.   to stay visible, to remain available. Even   scrolling through short videos until sun-
           Infinite scrolling, autoplay, algorithmic   if no one explicitly demands it, the cul-  rise, promising each night will be differ-
           feeds, they all encourage continuation.   ture often implies it. And with devices   ent. A parent notices their child strug-
           Stopping requires effort. Continuing   always within reach, disconnecting re-  gling to fall asleep, tablet still glowing
           feels effortless.               quires conscious effort, sometimes even   under the blanket.
             Over time, this creates a feedback   guilt.                      These aren’t extreme cases. They’re
           loop. The brain begins to associate   Students face a similar pattern. As-  common.
           screens with stimulation and reward.   signments, online classes, group chats,   And often, they come with a quiet
           Quiet moments, once filled with reflec-  digital resources, everything exists on   awareness that something isn’t quite
           tion or rest, now feel incomplete without   the same device that hosts entertain-  right. People know they’re tired. They
           input. Boredom becomes something to   ment. Switching off isn’t just about clos-  know they should sleep earlier. But
           avoid rather than a space to inhabit.   ing a book anymore. It’s about resisting   knowing doesn’t always translate into
             And so, even when we intend to   an entire ecosystem.         doing.
           sleep, we linger. The body waits. The   The result is a kind of temporal drift.   Because the system around them
           mind resists.                   Days stretch longer, nights start later and   keeps pulling them back in.

           24                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Is technology the villain?      ules. Others need strict routines. What

             It’s tempting to frame this as a sim-  matters is alignment, between what your   “
           ple story. Screens are bad. The past was   body needs and what your habits allow.   Our bodies still
           better. But that’s not entirely fair, or ac-  And that alignment requires atten-
           curate.                         tion, something our current environment   follow ancient
             Technology has brought undeniable   doesn’t always encourage.
           benefits. It connects people across dis-                          rhythms, even as our
           tances, provides access to information,   Closing reflections
           enables flexible work and offers enter-  We live in a world that never really   screens demand
           tainment that can genuinely enrich life.   sleeps. Lights stay on. Screens stay ac-
           For many, it’s not optional. It’s essential.   tive. Conversations continue long after   modern ones.”
             The issue isn’t technology itself. It’s   midnight. It’s exciting, in a way. Full of
           how seamlessly it has integrated into   possibility.
           every hour of our day.
             There’s no clear boundary anymore.
           No obvious stopping point. The tools we
           use for productivity are the same ones
           we use for relaxation. The line between
           necessity and habit becomes blurred.
             And so, the challenge isn’t to reject
           technology. It’s to renegotiate our rela-
           tionship with it.
           Small shifts, meaningful changes
             Reclaiming time doesn’t require
           drastic measures. In fact, small, consis-
           tent changes often make the biggest dif-
           ference.
             Some people start by setting a “digi-
           tal sunset,” a time after which screens
           are avoided or minimized. Others switch
           devices to night mode, reducing blue
           light exposure in the evening. Simple
           habits like reading a physical book be-
           fore bed or dimming lights can signal
           the body that it’s time to wind down.
             Even something as basic as charging
           your phone outside the bedroom can
           create a buffer between intention and
           impulse.
             Workplaces, too, are beginning to
           recognize the importance of boundaries.
           Encouraging asynchronous communica-
           tion, respecting offline hours and pro-
           moting realistic expectations can help
           reshape the culture.
             For students and younger users,
           awareness is key. Understanding how
           these systems work can make it easier to   But it also asks something of us.To
           resist them, or at least use them more   choose, occasionally, to step back. To let
           consciously.                    the night be night again. To remember
             It’s not about perfection. It’s about   what it feels like to be guided not by no-
           direction.                      tifications, but by a quieter, older
                                           rhythm.
           A different kind of awareness     Maybe it starts with a simple deci-
             Perhaps the most important shift is   sion. Turning off the screen a little ear-
           internal. To notice how you feel after a   lier. Sitting in the dim light.
           night of late scrolling. To recognize the   Letting the day end without extend-
           difference between rest and distraction.   ing it artificially.
           To ask, gently, whether the way you’re   It sounds small. Almost insignificant.
           spending your time is actually serving   But sometimes, reclaiming time be-
           you. There’s no universal answer. Some   gins with something as simple as allow-
           people thrive in unconventional sched-  ing it to pass. ■

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION






































           Not just a drink


           Tea as a                                                        The chemistry in your cup


                                                                              At the heart of tea’s effect are two
                                                                           key compounds: caffeine and L-thea-
                                                                           nine. On their own, they’re hardly
                                                                           unique. Caffeine is the world’s most
           chemical                                                        coffee, chocolate and energy drinks. L-
                                                                           widely consumed stimulant, found in
                                                                           theanine, an amino acid, is less famous
                                                                           but abundant in tea leaves, especially in
                                                                           green varieties.
                                                                              What makes tea different is how
           experience                                                      these two interact.
                                                                              Caffeine, as we know, blocks adeno-
                                                                           sine receptors in the brain. That’s the
                                                                           chemical responsible for making you
                                                                           feel sleepy. When it’s blocked, alertness
                                                                           rises. Heart rate may tick up slightly,
           What if the calm you feel after a cup of tea isn’t just         thoughts sharpen and for a while, you
           comfort, but chemistry quietly at work? By Ishita Desai         feel switched on. But caffeine alone can
                                                                           also bring jitters, that slightly anxious
                                                                           edge many coffee drinkers know too
                                                                           well.
             t usually begins without much   that explains why tea doesn’t quite be-  L-theanine works in a quieter way. It
             thought. A kettle hums, leaves unfurl   have like coffee and why its effects feel   crosses the blood-brain barrier and pro-
           Iin hot water and a familiar aroma   gentler, more sustained, almost… con-  motes the production of alpha brain
           fills the room. For many of us, tea is   siderate.              waves, which are associated with a re-
           routine, almost background noise to the   Tea isn’t just hydration or habit. It’s a   laxed but alert state. It also influences
           day. Yet beneath that simple act lies a   subtle negotiation between molecules   neurotransmitters like dopamine and se-
           surprisingly intricate chemical story, one   and mind.          rotonin, nudging the brain toward a

           26                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Beyond stimulation
                                                                              It’s tempting to think of beverages
                                                                           only in terms of energy. How quickly
                                                                           they wake us up, how long they keep
                                                                           us going. But tea suggests a different
                                                                           framework. One where the goal isn’t
                                                                           just stimulation, but balance.
                                                                              In a world that often feels overstim-
           sense of calm focus.            rushed. It’s not just cultural coincidence.   ulated already, that balance matters.
             Separately, they do different things.   There’s a biochemical logic behind it.   The gentle interplay of caffeine and L-
           Together, they create something distinct.                       theanine offers a kind of middle
                                           A personal rhythm               ground. Not too much, not too little.
           Focus without the rush            Of course, chemistry doesn’t operate   Just enough to stay present.
             This is where tea earns its reputation.   in a vacuum. The way tea affects you   You notice it in small ways.
           The combination of caffeine and L-thea-  depends on context. Time of day, your   Reading feels easier. Conversations
           nine doesn’t cancel each other out. In-  sensitivity to caffeine, even how the tea   flow without effort. Even silence be-
           stead, they seem to smooth each other’s   is brewed can shift the experience.   comes more comfortable.
           rough edges. The caffeine provides   A strong black tea in the morning   It’s not dramatic. It doesn’t an-
           alertness, while L-theanine tempers   might feel brisk, almost energizing in a   nounce itself. But it lingers.
           overstimulation, leading to a steadier,   traditional sense. A lighter green tea in
           more balanced mental state.     the afternoon can feel softer, more med-  A final sip
             Some researchers describe this as   itative. Matcha, with its higher concen-  So the next time you make a cup of
           “calm alertness.” It’s not the sharp spike   tration of both caffeine and L-theanine,   tea, it might be worth pausing for a
           of energy you might get from an es-  often produces a deeper, longer-lasting   second. Not just to enjoy the taste, but
           presso shot, followed by an equally   focus.                    to consider what’s happening beneath
           sharp drop. Tea’s effect is more gradual,   And then there’s the ritual itself. The   the surface.
           more sustained. You’re awake, but not   pause it demands. The warmth of the   Two molecules, working together in
           restless. Focused, but not tense.   cup in your hands. These sensory details   a way that feels almost intentional,
             Think of it less like a sprint and more   matter, even if they’re not strictly chem-  shaping your thoughts, your mood,
           like a long, even walk.         ical. They shape how the body receives   your pace.
             This might explain why tea has long   and interprets the experience.   It’s a quiet kind of chemistry. Easy
           been associated with reflective practices.   Sometimes it’s hard to separate the   to overlook. But once you notice it,
           Monks, scholars, writers, people who   science from the setting. Maybe that’s   it’s hard to see tea as just a drink
           need to think clearly without feeling   the point.              again. ■

           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                April 16-30, 2026










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Energy remains high, but patience is essential.   Shared responsibilities require careful handling.
                     Focus on completing pending tasks before starting   Financial planning is important now. Emotional
                     new ones. Relationships improve through         depth strengthens relationships when communi-
                     listening. Financial discipline helps maintain   cation remains honest. Avoid unnecessary risks
                     stability and prevents unnecessary stress.      and focus on long-term stability.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Your season begins, bringing renewed confidence.   Partnerships take center stage. Cooperation
                     Personal goals gain clarity and momentum.       brings progress in both personal and professional
                     Financial opportunities may arise. Relationships   life. Avoid controlling tendencies. Financial
                     feel stable, though clear communication ensures   matters remain balanced, while emotional under-
                     harmony and avoids misunderstandings.           standing improves connections.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     A reflective phase encourages you to slow down   Work routines demand attention and discipline.
                     and reassess priorities. Avoid overcommitting.   Health improves with structured habits. Avoid
                     Work progresses quietly. Emotional balance im-  procrastination. Financial stability grows slowly,
                     proves through rest, helping you prepare for up-  while relationships benefit from practical sup-
                     coming opportunities and social engagement.     port and consistent communication.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Social connections bring support and new oppor-  Creativity and personal interests bring satisfac-
                     tunities. Teamwork benefits career growth. Emo-  tion. Romantic energy improves. Professional
                     tional stability improves with open conver-     life remains steady. Financial matters stay bal-
                     sations. Financial matters remain steady with   anced when you avoid unnecessary spending and
                     careful planning.                               focus on long-term goals.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Career responsibilities increase, demanding     Home and family matters require attention.
                     focus and discipline. Recognition follows con-  Emotional balance improves through meaningful
                     sistent effort. Avoid ego clashes at work. Rela-  conversations. Work remains steady. Financial
                     tionships improve through understanding, while   planning supports stability, while patience helps
                     financial stability remains steady.             resolve domestic concerns effectively.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     New ideas and learning opportunities inspire    Communication improves, bringing clarity in
                     growth. Travel or planning may attract attention.   personal and professional matters. Short trips or
                     Stay practical while exploring options. Relation-  discussions prove useful. Financial decisions
                     ships benefit from patience and finances remain   should remain practical. Emotional confidence
                     stable with thoughtful decisions.               grows with clear expression.


           28                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | APRIL 16 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






                                           coercive action. Law enforcement
           Sting video triggers political storm   agencies must act with restraint and im-
             The recent viral sting video allegedly   partiality to ensure that the spirit of de-  tion without explanation may create an
           involving Humayun Kabir, in which   mocracy is not undermined. At the same   impression of opacity and weaken pub-
           claims of arranging ₹1000 crore for a   time, political leaders should exercise   lic confidence in democratic institutions.
           Babri Masjid-related initiative in Mur-  responsibility in their public statements.   Citizens expect clarity, especially in
           shidabad have surfaced, is deeply con-  This episode serves as a reminder that   matters involving high offices and con-
           cerning. Adding to this, there are allega-  both authority and accountability must   stitutional accountability.
           tions that such narratives are being used   go hand in hand to preserve democratic   Providing reasons for such decisions
           to deviate minority voters from the All   values and constitutional safeguards.   is essential to maintain credibility and
           India Trinamool Congress led by Ma-  Naresh Kumar Singh, Delhi, India   ensure that due process is visibly fol-
           mata Banerjee ahead of the upcoming                             lowed. Greater openness in parliamen-
           Bengal state elections.                                         tary functioning will strengthen demo-
             Such developments, whether verified   Resignation puts judiciary under   cratic values and reinforce public trust
           or not, have the potential to inflame   lens                    in the system.
           communal sentiments and disturb social   The resignation of Justice Yashwant   Ravindra Sharma, Delhi India
           harmony in a sensitive region. In the age   Varma has sparked serious discussion on
           of rapid digital dissemination, misinfor-  transparency and accountability within
           mation can easily mislead the public and   the judiciary. While stepping down may   Court order highlights need for
           deepen divisions. Therefore, it is imper-  be seen as a responsible move in the   fiscal responsibility
           ative that authorities conduct a prompt   given circumstances, it also raises larger   The recent directive of the Bombay
           and impartial investigation to ascertain   questions about the processes that gov-  High Court regarding the possible dis-
           the truth. Political stakeholders must   ern judicial conduct and oversight.   continuation of the Ladki Behan scheme
           also act responsibly, avoiding statements   The judiciary is a pillar of democ-  if adequate funds are not available for
           or strategies that could polarize voters.   racy, and public trust in its integrity is   pensions has brought fiscal priorities
           Upholding communal harmony and   paramount. Any development involving   into sharp focus.
           democratic integrity must remain the   a judge inevitably impacts the percep-  Welfare schemes are vital for social
           foremost priority.              tion of fairness and independence of the   support, but their sustainability must be
           K. Laxma Reddy, Hyderabad, Telan-  institution. Therefore, it is essential that   ensured through sound financial plan-
           gana, India                     such matters are addressed with com-  ning.
                                           plete transparency and due process.   Governments must strike a balance
                                           Arvind Sharma, New Delhi, India   between introducing populist initiatives
           Interim bail raises questions on                                and fulfilling essential obligations like
           arrest and expression                                           pensions, which directly impact vulner-
             The recent grant of interim bail to   Silence over impeachment   able sections. The court’s observation
           Pawan Khera by the Telangana High   decision                    underscores the importance of respon-
           Court has once again brought the issue   The reported rejection of the im-  sible governance and prudent allocation
           of freedom of expression and the   peachment motion against Gyanesh   of public resources.
           manner of arrests into public debate.   Kumar Gupta (Chief Election Commis-  Seema Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           While the judiciary’s timely intervention   sioner)by the Lok Sabha Speaker and   India
           has upheld personal liberty, the circum-  the Rajya Sabha Chairman, without as-
           stances leading to his detention raise   signing any reasons, raises serious con-
           concerns about the possible misuse of   cerns about transparency and accounta-  Letters (limited to one hundred
           legal provisions to curb political dissent.   bility in parliamentary procedures.   words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
             In a democratic framework, it is es-  Impeachment is a significant consti-  Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           sential that criticism, even if sharp, is   tutional mechanism meant to uphold in-
           addressed through dialogue rather than   stitutional integrity. Denying such a mo-


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           APRIL 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                               29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Dźmitryj

        Live in the sunshine, swim the sea,

        drink the wild air. - Ralph Waldo Emerson]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                          REVOIR Magazine
                                                                        .in
                                                                                           MARCH 01 2026

                                                                                           |
           32                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MARCH 16 2026
           32
                                                                   .revoir
                                                               www
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>