<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                       VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 10  I  JUNE 16 2024       ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             20



                                                            25













                                                             5                                        9















           4-Editorial: Global tranquility                 23- The forgotten role of courtesans

           5-Narendra Modi's hat trick                     25- A vibrant fusion of East and West

           9- The journey of yoga                          29-Horoscopes

           12- Yoga’s rising star Shraddha                 30-Letters
           Gawande

           15- Ensuring safe food for all

           18- A champion of food safety
           20- Heeramandi: Review













           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Global Tranquility
     EDITORIAL  Celebrating the Timeless                                           Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           Wisdom of Yoga                                                         Art & Culture Editor

                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                              n June 21st, the world unites to   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                              celebrate International Yoga Day, a
                                        Oglobal acknowledgment of an                Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        ancient practice that transcends time and
                                        borders. Recognized by the United Nations   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        since 2014, this day highlights yoga's       Sushil Kumar
                                        profound impact on physical, mental, and
                                        spiritual well-being.                     Social Media Editor
                                           Yoga, originating over 5,000 years ago   Vishakha Sharma
                                        in India, is more than just exercise; it is a
                                        holistic discipline integrating mind, body,   Art & Graphics Director
                                        and spirit. The term 'yoga' comes from the   Vipin Agarwal
                                        Sanskrit word 'yuj,' meaning to unite,
                                        symbolizing the connection between
           individual and universal consciousness. Through asanas (postures), pranayama
           (breathing techniques), and dhyana (meditation), yoga fosters balance, reduces stress,   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           and promotes inner tranquility.
             International Yoga Day brings people from all walks of life together in pursuit of   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           well-being. Celebrations range from large public gatherings to small, intimate   Editor, United News of India, New
           sessions, held in diverse locations from city parks to natural landscapes. This   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           inclusivity underscores yoga's ability to unite people globally.   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
             Yoga's versatility and adaptability are evident in its integration into healthcare,   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           education, and corporate environments. Medical research supports yoga's   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           effectiveness in managing chronic conditions such as hypertension, diabetes, and   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           cardiovascular diseases, as well as alleviating mental health issues like anxiety and
           depression. Schools incorporate yoga to enhance physical health and cognitive   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           abilities, while corporations offer yoga as part of wellness programs to reduce stress   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           and boost productivity.
             The digital age has amplified yoga's reach. Online platforms, mobile apps, and   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           virtual classes have made yoga accessible worldwide, breaking down geographical
           and temporal barriers. This digital expansion, especially significant during the   Phone +91 20 40199102
           COVID-19 pandemic, allowed people to practice yoga safely at home, maintaining   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           their well-being during challenging times.                                Baner Road,
             However, as yoga gains popularity, preserving its authenticity is crucial. While   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           commercialization has mainstreamed yoga, it is essential to maintain its core   Email revoir@post.com
           principles and holistic approach. Yoga is not merely a physical workout but a path to   Website www.revoir.in
           mental clarity and spiritual growth. Practitioners and instructors must honor this
           tradition, promoting a comprehensive understanding of yoga's true essence.
             On this International Yoga Day, as we join millions around the world in   Legal Advisor
           celebrating this ancient practice, let us also honor the individuals like Shraddha   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           Gawande whose dedication continues to inspire and uplift. Her journey reminds us
           that yoga is not just about physical fitness but about cultivating a balanced,   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           harmonious life. As we embrace the transformative power of yoga, we move closer to   all rights reserved. This publication
           a world marked by peace, wellness, and unity.                    may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[GOVERNANCE















































           The 2024 Parliamentary Elections


           Narendra Modi's







           hat trick








           By Siddharth Mehta

             n an unprecedented political   nata Dal (United) (JDU) and N. Chan-  Key factors behind Modi's
             achievement, Narendra Modi has se-  drababu Naidu of the Telugu Desam   electoral victory
           Icured a third consecutive term as the   Party (TDP) adds a new dimension to   Economic reforms and devel-
           Prime Minister of India, marking a his-  Modi’s leadership. This article examines   opment: Modi's administration has con-
           toric hat trick in the 2024 Parliamentary   the key factors behind Modi's victory,   sistently pushed for economic reforms
           elections. The formation of a new coali-  the dynamics of the new coalition gov-  aimed at improving infrastructure,
           tion government with the support of key   ernment, and the implications for India's   boosting manufacturing, and enhancing
           regional leaders Nitish Kumar of the Ja-  future.               the ease of doing business. Policies such

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[as the Goods and Services Tax (GST),
                                                                           the Make in India initiative, and various
         Oath of Office and Secrecy administered to PM Modi
                                                                           digital economy measures have bol-
                                                                           stered his reputation as a pro-devel-
                                                                           opment leader.
                                                                              Social welfare programs: The gov-
                                                                           ernment's social welfare schemes have
                                                                           had a profound impact on the electorate.
                                                                           Programs like Pradhan Mantri Awas Yo-
                                                                           jana (housing for all), Swachh Bharat
                                                                           Abhiyan (Clean India Mission), and
                                                                           Ayushman Bharat (health insurance)
                                                                           have reached millions, particularly in ru-
                                                                           ral areas.
                                                                              National security and foreign pol-
                                                                           icy: Modi's tenure has been marked by a
                                                                           strong stance on national security and a
                                                                           proactive foreign policy. His govern-
                                                                           ment’s response to cross-border tensions
                                                                           and efforts to strengthen India's position
                                                                           in global diplomacy have resonated with
                                                                           voters.
                                                                              Effective communication and pop-
                                                                           ulism: Modi's ability to connect with the
                                                                           masses through effective communica-
                                                                           tion strategies, particularly his use of so-
                                                                           cial media, has been a key factor. His
                                                                           emphasis on nationalism and cultural
                                                                           identity has further solidified his appeal.

                                                                           Formation of the new coalition
                                                                           government
                                                                              The 2024 elections also saw the BJP
                                                                           forming a coalition government with the
                                                                           support of Nitish Kumar's JDU and N.
                                                                           Chandrababu Naidu's TDP. This alliance
                                                                           was instrumental in securing the major-
                                                                           ity needed to govern, bringing together
                                                                           diverse political ideologies and regional
                                                                           interests.

                                                                           Key ministerial portfolios and their
                                                                           implications
                                                                              Home Ministry: Amit Shah retains
                                                                           his position as the Home Minister, re-
         After taking the oath, PM Modi greeted everyone present
                                                                           flecting a continued focus on internal se-
                                                                           curity, counter-terrorism, and law and
                                                                           order. Shah's experience and past ac-
                                                                           tions, such as the abrogation of Article
                                                                           370, suggest a steadfast approach to na-
                                                                           tional security.
                                                                              Finance Ministry and Corporate
                                                                           Affairs: Nirmala Sitharaman continues
                                                                           to lead the Finance Ministry. Her role
                                                                           will be critical in steering the economy
                                                                           towards recovery, particularly post-pan-
                                                                           demic, and implementing further re-
                                                                           forms to attract foreign investment and
                                                                           boost economic growth.
                                                                              External Affairs: Dr. Subrah-
                                                                           manyam Jaishankar, with his extensive
                                                                           diplomatic experience, remains the Ex-
                                                                           ternal Affairs Minister. His priorities

           6                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[N. Chandrababu Naidu (TDP)                                                                        PM taking charge of the office in South Block












                                           icy and focusing on modernizing the
                                           armed forces and enhancing indigenous
                                           defense production.
                                             Education Ministry: Dharmendra
                                           Pradhan, tasked with implementing the
                                           National Education Policy (NEP) 2020,
                                           aims to transform India's educational
                                           landscape to make it more inclusive and
                                           skill-oriented.
                                             Health Ministry: Jagat Prakash
                                           Nadda, tasked with focusing on expand-                          PM interacting with PMO staff at South Block
                                           ing healthcare infrastructure and imple-
         Nitish Kumar (JDU)                menting the Ayushman Bharat scheme to
                                           improve healthcare access across the
                                           country.
                                             Women and Child Development:
                                           Smt. Annpurna Devi tasked with empha-
                                           sizing programs to improve nutrition,
           will include strengthening India’s global   education, and empowerment of women   Role of Coalition Partners
           partnerships, navigating complex inter-  and children.             Nitish Kumar (JDU): As a seasoned
           national relations, and enhancing India’s   Commerce and Industry: Piyush   politician and Chief Minister of Bihar,
           role in multilateral organizations.   Goyal retains his position, aiming to   Nitish Kumar brings a wealth of
             Defence Ministry: Rajnath Singh   boost exports, drive industrial growth,   experience and regional influence to the
           continues to oversee the Defence Mini-  and secure favorable trade deals for   coalition. His focus on social justice,
           stry, ensuring continuity in defense pol-  India.               education, and development aligns with
                                                                           the broader objectives of the coalition
                                                                           government. Kumar's role in the
         The President, the Vice President, PM and other dignitaries
                                                                           government is expected to bridge regional
                                                                           aspirations with national policies.
                                                                              N. Chandrababu Naidu (TDP):
                                                                           The TDP's support is crucial for the co-
                                                                           alition, particularly in the southern
                                                                           states. Naidu's experience in infrastruc-
                                                                           ture development and technology will be
                                                                           instrumental in driving the government's
                                                                           vision for a digitally empowered and in-
                                                                           frastructurally robust India.

                                                                           Analysis of the coalition
                                                                           government's priorities
                                                                              Economic revival and growth: The
                                                                           coalition government is expected to pri-
                                                                           oritize economic stability and growth,
                                                                           focusing on post-pandemic recovery,

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[maintaining a disciplined stance on key
                                                                           issues.
                                                                                Challenge: The BJP had to ensure
                                                                           Public Expectations and Promises
         All members of Council of Ministers                               made during the election campaign, in-
                                                                           that it could deliver on the promises

                                                                           cluding economic reforms, social wel-
                                                                           fare schemes, and national security.
                                                                              Addressed: The government quickly
                                                                           began implementing its agenda, focus-
                                                                           ing on economic growth, job creation,
                                                                           and addressing social issues to meet
                                                                           public expectations.

           boosting manufacturing, and attracting   Addressed: The party turned to its   Maintaining National Unity
           foreign direct investment (FDI).   allies within the National Democratic   Challenge: With a diverse coalition,
             National security and internal sta-  Alliance (NDA) to form a coalition   maintaining national unity and address-
           bility: With Amit Shah retaining the   government. The support from the   ing regional disparities were crucial to
           Home Ministry, the government will   NDA bloc, which included various re-  ensure that the government's policies
           likely maintain a firm stance on na-  gional parties, provided the necessary   were accepted across different states.
           tional security and internal law and   numbers to cross the majority thres-  Addressed: The government took
           order, ensuring robust measures against   hold.                 measures to ensure equitable distribu-
           terrorism and insurgency.                                       tion of resources and development proj-
             Healthcare and education:     Negotiating with Regional Allies   ects across the country, paying particu-
           Strengthening healthcare infrastructure   Challenge: The BJP needed to ne-  lar attention to regions that historically
           and implementing the National Educa-  gotiate terms with regional parties to   felt neglected.
           tion Policy (NEP) will be key priorities.   ensure their support in government for-
           The government aims to enhance   mation. These negotiations often in-  Handling Media and Public
           healthcare accessibility and make edu-  volved concessions such as cabinet   Perception
           cation more inclusive and skill-oriented.   berths, policy agreements, and devel-  Challenge: Managing media rela-
             Social welfare and development:   opment funds for their respective states.   tions and public perception was critical,
           Ministries focused on social welfare   Addressed: The BJP engaged in   as any missteps could be exploited by
           will drive initiatives to improve living   diplomatic and political negotiations,   the opposition.
           standards and empower marginalized   ensuring that the regional allies were   Addressed: The government main-
           communities. Enhancing rural infras-  given significant roles in the govern-  tained a proactive communication
           tructure and supporting farmers will be   ment and promises were made for state-  strategy, engaging with media and pub-
           important areas of focus.       specific development programs.   lic platforms to highlight its achieve-
             Technological advancement and                                 ments and policies.
           innovation: Continued investment in   Managing Internal Party      The process of government forma-
           digital infrastructure, promoting innova-  Dynamics             tion, while challenging, was ultimately
           tion, and leveraging technology for   Challenge: Within the BJP, there   successful due to strategic political ma-
           governance and development will re-  were internal dynamics to manage, in-  neuvering, effective negotiation, and the
           main a priority under the coalition gov-  cluding the distribution of ministerial   commitment to fulfill the promises
           ernment.                        positions and responsibilities among   made to the electorate.
                                           party members.                     Narendra Modi’s third consecutive
           Challenges for BJP post-2024      Addressed: The party leadership   term as Prime Minister, achieved
           election                        carefully balanced the distribution of   through a strategic coalition with Nitish
             The formation of the government   key portfolios to ensure that various   Kumar’s JDU and N. Chandrababu
           following the 2024 Indian Parliamen-  factions within the party were satisfied,   Naidu’s TDP, marks a significant chap-
           tary elections presented a set of chal-  maintaining internal harmony and unity.   ter in India's political landscape. The
           lenges for Narendra Modi's Bharatiya                            new government formation, featuring a
           Janata Party (BJP) and its allies, prima-  Addressing Opposition's Critiques   blend of experienced leaders and fresh
           rily due to the party not securing an   Challenge: The opposition alliance,   faces, reflects a strategic approach to
           outright majority. The main challenges   led by the Indian National Congress   governance. The allocation of ministe-
           and how they were addressed can be   Party, had won 235 seats, and the BJP   rial portfolios indicates a clear focus on
           summarized as follows:          had to deal with strong opposition in   economic revival, national security,
                                           Parliament.                     healthcare, education, and social wel-
           Lack of Absolute Majority         Addressed: The government fo-  fare. As Modi embarks on this historic
             Challenge: The BJP won only 240   cused on maintaining a strong legis-  third term, the coalition government’s
           seats, falling short of the 272 seats re-  lative agenda and managed to keep the   policies and initiatives will play a cru-
           quired to form a government independ-  opposition's impact on governance min-  cial role in shaping India’s future tra-
           ently.                          imal by aligning with NDA allies and   jectory. ■

           8                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[GLOBAL CELEBRATION
















































           The journey of yoga




           From ancient roots to







           modern practice






           By Vipin Agarwal


             nternational Yoga Day, celebrated on   India, yoga has transcended geographi-  on September 27, 2014. He highlighted
             June 21st each year, has become a   cal and cultural boundaries, becoming a   yoga as an invaluable gift of India's an-
           Iglobal phenomenon, symbolizing the   unifying practice for people worldwide.   cient tradition, emphasizing its benefits
           universal appeal and benefits of yoga.                          in fostering peace and harmony among
           Initiated by the United Nations General   Origins and significance   individuals and communities. The pro-
           Assembly in 2014, this day emphasizes   The inception of International Yoga   posal received overwhelming support,
           the holistic nature of yoga, which not   Day can be attributed to the efforts of   and on December 11, 2014, the UNGA
           only involves physical exercise but also   Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi,   declared June 21st as International Yoga
           fosters mental and spiritual well-being.   who proposed the idea during his speech   Day.
           With its origins deeply rooted in ancient   at the United Nations General Assembly   June 21st was chosen as it is the

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[longest day of the year in the Northern
           Hemisphere, known as the summer sol-
           stice, and holds significant cultural and
           spiritual importance in many parts of the
           world. This date marks the transition to
           Dakshinayana, which, according to
           yogic lore, is the time when there is nat-
           ural support for those pursuing spiritual
           practices.

           The essence of yoga
             Yoga is a holistic discipline that en-
           compasses physical postures (asanas),
           breathing techniques (pranayama), med-                                                          Yoga enthusiasts at New York Square
           itation (dhyana), and ethical principles
           (yamas and niyamas). The term 'yoga' is
           derived from the Sanskrit word 'yuj,'
           which means to unite or integrate. It rep-
           resents the union of body, mind, and
           spirit, promoting balance and harmony.
             The benefits of yoga are manifold.   In India, the birthplace of yoga, the   In the healthcare sector, yoga is in-
           Physically, it enhances flexibility,   celebrations are particularly grand.   creasingly recognized as a
           strength, and balance. Mentally, it re-  Iconic landmarks such as the Red Fort in   complementary therapy for various con-
           duces stress, anxiety, and depression.   Delhi and the ghats of Varanasi serve as   ditions. Studies have shown that yoga
           Spiritually, it fosters a sense of inner   picturesque backdrops for massive yoga   can help manage chronic diseases such
           peace and connection with the broader   sessions. The day is marked by the par-  as hypertension, diabetes, and cardio-
           universe. The practice of yoga encour-  ticipation of government officials, yoga   vascular ailments. It is also effective in
           ages mindfulness and self-awareness,   gurus, and citizens from all walks of   alleviating symptoms of mental health
           leading to a more conscious and fulfill-  life, reflecting the inclusive and univer-  disorders, including anxiety, depression,
           ing life.                       sal nature of yoga.             and post-traumatic stress disorder
                                                                           (PTSD). Many hospitals and clinics now
           Celebrations around the world   Yoga's global impact            offer yoga therapy as part of their holis-
             International Yoga Day is celebrated   The global celebration of Inter-  tic treatment programs.
           with great enthusiasm across the globe.   national Yoga Day underscores the
           From the bustling streets of New York to   widespread acceptance and practice of   Education
           the serene landscapes of New Zealand,   yoga. In recent years, yoga has become   In the educational domain, yoga is
           millions of people come together to   an integral part of lifestyle and wellness   introduced to students to enhance their
           practice yoga, often in large public gath-  routines worldwide. It is incorporated   physical health and cognitive abilities.
           erings. These events typically include   into various sectors, including health-  Schools and universities across the
           mass yoga sessions, workshops, semi-  care, education, and corporate environ-  globe have incorporated yoga into their
           nars, and cultural performances, show-  ments, due to its proven benefits.   curricula, helping students improve their
           casing the diverse ways in which yoga                           concentration, memory, and emotional
           can be practiced and appreciated.   Healthcare                  regulation. Yoga in schools also pro-
                                                                           motes a sense of discipline and reduces
                                                                           behavioral issues, contributing to a more
                                                                           conducive learning environment.

                                                                           Corporate Wellness
         M Narendra Modi at India Gate, New Delhi, 2015                    stress work environment, yoga offers
                                                                              Corporations have also embraced
                                                                           yoga as a part of their employee well-
                                                                           ness programs. In a fast-paced and high-

                                                                           employees a way to de-stress and re-
                                                                           juvenate. Regular yoga sessions in the
                                                                           workplace improve productivity, reduce
                                                                           absenteeism, and enhance overall job
                                                                           satisfaction. Many companies now pro-
                                                                           vide on-site yoga classes and encourage
                                                                           their employees to incorporate yoga into
                                                                           their daily routines.

                                                                           The Role of technology
                                                                              The advent of technology has played

           10                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[manding form of yoga that focuses on a
                                                                           specific sequence of postures synchro-
                                                                           nized with the breath. Ashtanga Yoga
                                                                           has a significant following worldwide
                                                                           and has influenced various modern yoga
                                                                           styles.

         Female yoga enthusiasts                                           endary yogi Krishnamacharya, empha-
                                                                           T.K.V. Desikachar
                                                                              T.K.V. Desikachar, the son of the leg-

                                                                           sized the therapeutic aspects of yoga.
                                                                           His approach, known as Viniyoga, tai-
                                                                           lors yoga practices to individual needs
                                                                           and conditions, making yoga accessible
                                                                           to people of all ages and health con-
           a significant role in popularizing yoga   Sutra states: "Yogashchitta Vrittini-  ditions.
           globally. Online platforms, mobile appli-  rodha," which means that mental dis-
           cations, and social media have made   orders are alleviated by stabilizing the   Challenges and the way forward
           yoga accessible to millions of people,   mind, leading to wisdom and prudence.   Despite its widespread popularity,
           regardless of their location. Virtual yoga   For the holistic development of indi-  yoga faces several challenges. Commer-
           classes and tutorials have surged in pop-  viduals, encompassing physical, mental,   cialization and the proliferation of su-
           ularity, especially during the COVID-19   and spiritual aspects, Patanjali pro-  perficial forms of yoga have diluted its
           pandemic, when social distancing meas-  pounded "Ashtanga Yoga," which con-  essence. In some cases, yoga is viewed
           ures restricted in-person gatherings.   sists of Yama, Niyama, Asana, Pranay-  merely as a fitness trend, overlooking its
             Prominent yoga instructors and in-  ama, Pratyahara, Dharana, Dhyana, and   profound philosophical and spiritual di-
           fluencers use platforms like YouTube,   Samadhi.                mensions.
           Instagram, and Zoom to reach a broad                               To preserve the authenticity of yoga,
           audience, offering classes ranging from   Swami Vivekananda     it is essential to promote its comprehen-
           beginner to advanced levels. These digi-  Swami Vivekananda is often credited   sive understanding. Yoga practitioners
           tal resources provide flexibility and con-  with introducing yoga to the Western   and instructors should emphasize the
           venience, allowing individuals to prac-  world. His historic speech at the Parlia-  importance of integrating the physical,
           tice yoga at their own pace and comfort.   ment of the World's Religions in Chi-  mental, and spiritual aspects of yoga.
                                           cago in 1893 garnered immense atten-  Education and awareness programs can
           Prominent yoga gurus and their   tion and laid the foundation for the   help dispel misconceptions and high-
           contributions                   spread of yoga and Vedanta philosophy   light the true essence of yoga.
             Several yoga gurus have been instru-  in the West.               Additionally, there is a need for in-
           mental in popularizing yoga worldwide.                          clusivity and accessibility in yoga. Ef-
           Their teachings and contributions have   B.K.S. Iyengar         forts should be made to make yoga af-
           transcended cultural barriers, making   B.K.S. Iyengar, the founder of Iyen-  fordable and available to marginalized
           yoga a global phenomenon.       gar Yoga, is renowned for his precise   and underserved communities. Initia-
                                           and alignment-based approach to yoga.   tives such as free community yoga
           Maharishi Patanjali             His book, "Light on Yoga," is consid-  classes and outreach programs can help
             Yoga philosophy is one of the six   ered a seminal text in the field and has   bridge this gap.
           components of Vedic philosophy. The   inspired millions to take up the practice.   International Yoga Day is more than
           fundamental tenets of Yoga philosophy                           just a celebration; it is a reminder of the
           are systematically compiled and refined   Pattabhi Jois         timeless wisdom and universal appeal of
           in the "Yoga Sutra" authored by Mahar-  Pattabhi Jois popularized Ashtanga   yoga. As millions of people come to-
           ishi Patanjali. The first sutra of the Yoga   Yoga, a dynamic and physically de-  gether to practice yoga, they contribute
                                                                           to a global movement towards health,
                                                                           harmony, and inner peace. Yoga, with its
                                                                           profound benefits and holistic approach,
         Yoga session near the Eiffel Tower, Paris                         yoga and promoting its practice, we can
                                                                           has the potential to transform lives and
                                                                           societies.
                                                                              By embracing the true essence of

                                                                           foster a world that values well-being,
                                                                           mindfulness, and compassion. Inter-
                                                                           national Yoga Day serves as a testament
                                                                           to the enduring power of yoga and its
                                                                           relevance in the contemporary world, in-
                                                                           spiring individuals and communities to

                                                                           monious lives. ■

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             lead healthier, happier, and more har-  11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Transforming lives worldwide
     LIFESTYLE  Yoga’s rising star











           Shraddha Gawande








           By Dr. Uzma Naaz


             n a world where the hustle and bus-
             tle of everyday life often take a toll
           Ion our well-being, Shraddha Ga-
           wande stands as a beacon of health and
           tranquility. Born in Nagpur, Maharash-
           tra, Shraddha's journey from a computer
           application graduate to a renowned yoga
           expert is a testament to the transfor-
           mative power of passion and dedication.
           In this exclusive interview, Shraddha
           opens up about her life, her motivations,
           and her aspirations, providing a glimpse
           into the heart and soul of a woman ded-
           icated to spreading the benefits of yoga
           across the globe.

           Early life and education
             Shraddha Gawande was born to Sri
           Ruprao ji Gawande, a businessman
           turned farmer, and Mrs. Vanita Ruprao
           Gawande, a devoted housewife. Grow-
           ing up in Nagpur, Shraddha shared her
           childhood with her only brother, Yogesh
           Ruprao Gawande, who now works as a
           PDI Manager at an automobile com-
           pany. Her academic journey began at
           Government Polytechnic College, Nag-
           pur, where she completed her 11th and
           12th grades while simultaneously taking
           up a teaching job.
             Her passion for education led her to
           pursue a Bachelor of Computer Applica-
           tion (BCA) from Dr. Ambedkar College,
           Nagpur, graduating in 2009. Despite her
           technical background, Shraddha's life                                                           Shraddha Gawande: A celebrated yoga instructor
           took a significant turn when she enrolled
           in a certificate course in Yoga, Acupres-
           sure Therapy, and Pregnancy Yoga, sow-
           ing the seeds for her future career.

           The turning point
             After completing her BCA, Shraddha

           12                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[began her professional career as a Man-
           ual Tester at Abyss Enterprises Private
           Limited in Nagpur. It was here that she
           met her future husband, Sandesh
           Dhamne, an IT professional in the same
           company. The couple tied the knot in
           2013. However, Shraddha's journey was-
           n't without challenges. She faced health
           issues related to low hemoglobin levels
           and mental stress, which led her to ex-                                                         Utilizing Zoom to connect with a larger group of students
           plore yoga as a means of coping.
             In 2014, after relocating to Pune and
           leaving her job, Shraddha felt a profound
           sense of emptiness. The birth of her son,
           Arav, became a catalyst for change.
           "When I made myself healthy through
           yoga, I thought, why not do something
           for others facing similar health issues?"
           she reflects. This realization marked the
           beginning of her journey as a yoga in-  main motivator who wanted me to stand   sonal transformation; it was about mak-
           structor.                       on my own feet," she shares. Her hus-  ing a difference in others' lives. "Many
                                           band, Sandesh, and her father-in-law, Sri   people contacted me who were strug-
           The motivation behind the mission   Jairam Tanbaji Dhamne, also played piv-  gling physically, mentally, and internally
             Shraddha attributes her success to the   otal roles in encouraging her to pursue   with their health issues. So, I delved
           unwavering support of her family. "My   this career.            deeper into the practice of yoga,"
           father, Sri Ruprao ji Gawande, was the   Her journey wasn't just about per-  Shraddha explains.

                                                                           Overcoming challenges and
                                                                           expanding horizons
                                                                              Initially, Shraddha started conducting
                                                                           online yoga classes via WhatsApp video
                                                                           calls, but this approach had its limita-
         Side stretching improves body flexibility                         them correctly," she recalls. The lack of
                                                                           tions. "It was challenging to explain pos-
                                                                           tures on a small screen and ensure the
                                                                           person on the other end was performing

                                                                           awareness about online sessions at the
                                                                           time also posed a challenge, as most
                                                                           people preferred physical classes.
                                                                              To overcome these hurdles, Shraddha
                                                                           transitioned to using larger screens, uti-
                                                                           lizing platforms like Zoom to connect
                                                                           with a larger group of students from var-
                                                                           ious corners of the world. Her commit-
                                                                           ment to her students and her personalized
                                                                           attention during classes earned her a
                                                                           growing number of followers, purely
                                                                           through word-of-mouth.

                                                                           Inspiring success stories
                                                                              Shraddha's dedication has led to re-
                                                                           markable success stories. She recalls one
                                                                           of her most challenging cases: a 27-year-
                                                                           old student named Resham from Nasik,
                                                                           whose right hand and leg were paralyzed.
                                                                           "It was a challenge for me as I had never
                                                                           dealt with such a case before. But I de-
         Performing Malasana                                               Through dedicated yoga sessions, Reshm
                                                                           cided to accept it," Shraddha says.
                                                                           experienced significant recovery, re-
                                                                           gained movement in her limbs, and even
                                                                           saw her postponed marriage finalized.


                                                                                                       13
           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                Another poignant story involves a 60-]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[year-old cancer patient from Mumbai,
           Mrs. Sandhya Waghmare. Having under-
           gone surgery and 31 chemotherapy ses-
           sions, Mrs. Sandhya faced significant
           health challenges and weight gain. "It
           was my first experience handling a
           cancer patient, but I didn't lose my con-
           fidence," Shraddha recalls. With yoga,
           Mrs. Sandhya experienced remarkable                                                             Halasana: The shape of an Indian Plough (farming tool)
           improvements in her health and now
           leads a healthy life.

           A global reach
             Shraddha's impact extends beyond
           India, with students from the USA, UK,
           Russia, Singapore, Australia, the Nether-
           lands, and Dubai attending her online
           yoga classes. She conducts six sessions
           in the morning and two in the evening,   from her students, as she meticulously
           balancing personal and group sessions.   monitors and corrects their postures, en-
           Despite her busy schedule, she manages   suring a safe and effective practice.
           to find time for herself and her family,
           demonstrating impeccable time manage-  Future aspirations and advice
           ment skills.                      Looking ahead, Shraddha has ambi-
                                           tious plans for her yoga career. "My aspi-
           Inspirations and methodology    ration is to create introductory videos for
             Shraddha draws inspiration from re-  students who cannot attend regular ses-
           nowned yoga guru Swami Ramdev,   sions. It is my life's wish to be known as a
           known for his precise demonstration and   famous yoga guru worldwide," she
           explanation of yoga steps. She also   shares. She also plans to expand her ses-
           credits Mrs. Kalpana Kshirsagar, her   sions, converting personal sessions into
           guru, for her foundational yoga educa-  group ones to benefit more people.
           tion.                             To those considering a career in yoga,
             Each of Shraddha's sessionas begins   Shraddha offers valuable advice: "Yoga
           with Guru Prathana and includes a vari-  performance and yoga training are en-                  Performing Sarvangasana
           ety of yoga practices such as Surya Na-  tirely different. A small mistake can have
           maskar, Cardio Yoga, Power Yoga, Cir-  serious consequences. Always be care-
           cuit Training, Facial Yoga, Meditation,   ful, and if you are not confident, don't in-
           and Pranayama. To keep the sessions en-  struct others without expert guidance."
           joyable, she incorporates Hula Hoop,                            Shraddha credits her time management
           Bhangra, and Yoga with Dance once a   Balancing personal and    skills for her ability to juggle various re-
           week, along with chanting mantras like   professional life      sponsibilities. "I am very punctual and
           Omkar and Gayatri Mantra.         Maintaining a balance between per-  strict with my schedule. My husband and
             Her keen observation skills have   sonal life and professional commitments   child are very satisfied with me, whether
           earned her the nickname "Eagle Eye"   is crucial in a demanding field like yoga.   it's about their food, washing, or ironing
                                                                           their clothes. Even if I have to travel, my
                                                                           online yoga sessions continue uninter-
                                                                           rupted," she explains.

                                                                           Final thoughts
                                                                              As our interview concludes, Shraddha
                                                                           leaves readers with a powerful message:
                                                                           "If you want to bring discipline into your
                                                                           life, do yoga. Yoga is essential for flex-
                                                                           ibility in the body and makes your per-
                                                                           sonality more attractive."
         Shraddha's radiant family                                         manual tester to a celebrated yoga in-
                                                                              Shraddha Dhamne's journey from a
                                                                           structor is a story of resilience, passion,
                                                                           and a relentless drive to help others. Her
                                                                           dedication to yoga not only transformed
                                                                           her own life but continues to inspire and
                                                                           heal countless others around the world. ■

           14                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL










































           World Food Safety Day



           Ensuring










           safe food for all









           By Riya Verma

               ood safety is a critical component   spire action towards preventing, detect-  farm to table. Unsafe food containing
               of public health, encompassing   ing, and managing foodborne risks, thus   harmful bacteria, viruses, parasites, or
           Fthe proper handling, preparation,   contributing to food security, human   chemical substances causes more than
           and storage of food to prevent food-  health, economic prosperity, agriculture,   200 diseases, ranging from diarrhea to
           borne illnesses and contamination. Rec-  market access, tourism, and sustainable   cancers. According to the World Health
           ognizing its importance, the United Na-  development.           Organization (WHO), an estimated 600
           tions designated June 7th as World Food                         million – almost 1 in 10 people in the
           Safety Day (WFSD). This annual obser-  The importance of food safety   world – fall ill after eating contaminated
           vance aims to draw attention to and in-  Food safety impacts everyone, from   food, and 420,000 die every year, result-

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[ing in the loss of 33 million healthy life
           years (DALYs). Children under 5 years
           of age carry 40% of the foodborne dis-
           ease burden, with 125,000 deaths every
           year.
             The economic consequences of un-
           safe food are significant. Unsafe food
           hampers socio-economic development
           by straining healthcare systems and
           harming national economies, tourism,
           and trade. In low- and middle-income
           countries, it is estimated that foodborne
           diseases cost $110 billion in lost produc-
           tivity and medical expenses annually.

           History and significance of world
           food safety day                                                                                 Food markets and grocery stores
             World Food Safety Day was estab-
           lished in 2018 by the United Nations
           General Assembly in collaboration with
           the Food and Agriculture Organization
           (FAO) and the World Health Organiza-
           tion (WHO). The day provides an oppor-  Healthy Tomorrow" highlighted the role   Governments: Establish and enforce
           tunity to strengthen efforts to ensure that   of safe food in ensuring a healthy future   food safety regulations, conduct food
           the food we eat is safe. It aims to inspire   and sustainable food systems.   safety monitoring and risk assessments,
           actions at all levels to prevent, detect,   2022 Theme: "Safer Food, Better   and educate the public about food safety
           and manage foodborne risks, thus con-  Health" underlined the connection be-  practices.
           tributing to food security, human health,   tween food safety and overall health.   Food industry: Adopt food safety
           economic prosperity, and sustainable de-  2023 Theme: “Food Standards Save   management systems, comply with reg-
           velopment.                      Lives” food standards help us to ensure   ulations, and ensure that food products
                                           what we eat is safe.            are safe through every stage of produc-
           Themes and campaigns              2024 Theme: “Food safety: prepare   tion, processing, and distribution.
             Each year, World Food Safety Day   for the unexpected” the critical impor-  Consumers: Play a vital role by
           adopts a specific theme to highlight dif-  tance of being proactive in safeguarding   practicing good hygiene, properly stor-
           ferent aspects of food safety. The themes   our food supply from potential hazards.   ing and cooking food, and being aware
           are designed to raise awareness and   These themes serve as a focal point   of food safety information and guide-
           drive collective action towards reducing   for organizing events and activities that   lines.
           foodborne risks. For instance:   engage the public, industry, and policy-  International organizations: WHO
             2020 Theme: "Food Safety, Every-  makers.                     and FAO provide international leader-
           one’s Business" emphasized that food                            ship, set global standards, and support
           safety is a shared responsibility among   Key players in food safety   countries in improving their food safety
           governments, producers, and consumers.   Ensuring food safety requires coordi-  systems.
             2021 Theme: "Safe Food Now for a   nated efforts from multiple stakeholders:
                                                                           Best practices for ensuring food
                                                                           safety
                                                                              To maintain and improve food safety,
                                                                           various practices can be adopted:
                                                                              Good Agricultural Practices
                                                                           (GAP): Ensuring that the methods used
                                                                           in farming are safe and sustainable. This
                                                                           includes the safe use of pesticides and
                                                                           fertilizers, proper animal husbandry, and
         Food inspector examining products                                 ufacturers can follow to ensure their
                                                                           efficient water use.
                                                                              Good Manufacturing Practices
                                                                           (GMP): These are guidelines that man-

                                                                           products are consistently produced and
                                                                           controlled according to quality stan-
                                                                           dards. They cover all aspects of produc-
                                                                           tion, from raw materials to finished pro-
                                                                           ducts.
                                                                              Hazard Analysis and Critical Con-
                                                                           trol Points (HACCP): A systematic

           16                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Challenges in food safety
                                                                              Despite advancements in food safety,
                                                                           several challenges persist:
                                                                              Globalization: The global nature of
                                                                           food trade increases the complexity of
                                                                           ensuring food safety, as food products
                                                                           often cross multiple borders before
                                                                           reaching the consumer.
                                                                              Emerging pathogens: New food-
                                                                           borne pathogens continue to emerge, ne-
                                                                           cessitating constant vigilance and up-
                                                                           dated safety practices.
                                                                              Climate change: Climate change can
                                                                           affect food safety by influencing the
                                                                           prevalence and distribution of
                                                                           pathogens, contaminants, and myco-
                                                                           toxins in food.
                                                                              Resource limitations: Many low-
                                                                           and middle-income countries lack the
                                                                           resources needed to effectively monitor
         Meat Thermometer                                                  and enforce food safety regulations.
                                                                              Consumer behavior: Changes in
                                                                           consumer preferences and behaviors,
                                                                           such as the demand for raw or mini-
                                                                           mally processed foods, can increase


           preventive approach to food safety that   ensures they stay informed about the la-  food safety risks.
           identifies physical, chemical, and bio-  test food safety practices and standards.   The future of food safety
           logical hazards in production processes   Consumer awareness: Educating con-  Looking ahead, ensuring food safety
           that can cause the finished product to be   sumers on how to safely handle and pre-  will require a combination of traditional
           unsafe and designs measurements to re-  pare food can significantly reduce the   practices and innovative solutions. Ad-
           duce these risks to a safe level.   incidence of foodborne illnesses. This   vances in technology, such as block-
             Food safety training and educa-  includes proper cooking techniques,   chain for traceability, rapid diagnostic
           tion: Continuous education for those in-  avoiding cross-contamination, and un-  tests, and predictive analytics, offer new
           volved in food production and handling   derstanding food labels.   ways to enhance food safety. Ad-
                                                                           ditionally, there is a growing recognition
                                                                           of the importance of a One Health ap-
                                                                           proach, which considers the intercon-
                                                                           nectedness of human, animal, and envi-
                                                                           ronmental health.
                                                                              Moreover, international collaboration
                                                                           will be crucial. Global food safety initia-
                                                                           tives, such as the Codex Alimentarius,
                                                                           which provides international food stan-
                                                                           dards, guidelines, and codes of practice,
                                                                           will play an essential role in harmoniz-
                                                                           ing food safety measures worldwide.
                                                                              World Food Safety Day is more than
                                                                           just an annual observance; it is a call to
                                                                           action to prioritize and improve food
                                                                           safety globally.
         Lab technicians testing food samples                              holders, and the best practices to miti-
                                                                              By understanding the significance of
                                                                           food safety, the roles of different stake-

                                                                           gate risks, we can work towards a world
                                                                           where foodborne illnesses are mini-
                                                                           mized, and everyone has access to safe,
                                                                           nutritious food. As we celebrate this day,
                                                                           let us remember that food safety is in-
                                                                           deed everyone’s business, and our col-

                                                                           communities worldwide. ■

                                                                                                       17
           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             lective efforts can lead to healthier, safer]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[A champion of food safety

     NATIONAL  An Interview with Dr. Umesh Kumar








           By Arjun Patel


                 octor. Umesh Kumar boasts an
                 impressive academic back-
           Dground in microbiology and
           food safety. With an M.Sc in Applied
           Microbiology, an M. Phil, a PhD in Mi-
           crobiology, and a Post Graduate Di-
           ploma in Food Safety and Quality Man-
           agement from Indira Gandhi National
           Open University, Dr. Umesh is also an
           Internal Auditor for FSMS: 22000, BRC
           (British Retail Consortium), and
           ISO/IEC: 17025: 2017. This extensive
           education has paved the way for a robust
           career in food safety.                                                                          Dr. Umesh Kumar, Food Analyst, Government of U.P.

           Tenure at the FDA
             Since 2012, Dr. Umesh has been
           serving as a Food Analyst, specifically
           as the Notified Food Analyst for Uttar
           Pradesh. This role involves analyzing
           food samples to ensure compliance with
           the Food Safety and Standards Act of
           2006 and related regulations.
                                           national research papers and authored 17   aimed at enhancing food safety, includ-
           Motivation for a career in food   books on various topics related to food   ing:
           safety                          safety and microbiology. Notable pub-  Detection systems for foodborne
             Dr. Umesh’s journey into food safety   lications include:     pathogens like Salmonella using func-
           was driven by a desire to provide safe   "Immunogenicity of Candidate   tional gold nanoparticles.
           and nutritious food, particularly for eco-  Chimeric DNA Vaccine Against Tuber-  Techniques for studying air pollu-
           nomically weaker sections of society.   culosis and Leishmaniasis" in the Jour-  tants emitted from vehicles.
           "Growing up in a middle-class family   nal of Vaccine.             Surface Plasmon resonance for IgG
           and witnessing the prevalence of food   "Bisorption of Heavy Metals Oxides   detection using nanosensors.
           adulteration in poorer communities mo-  by Resistant Microorganisms in Liquid
           tivated me to pursue a career in this   Culture – ICPMS Techniques."   Role and responsibilities at the
           field," he explains. Ensuring the avail-  "Nutritional Aspects of Ready-to-Eat   FDA
           ability of safe food for all has been a   and Homemade Food Products."   As the Commissioner of Food Safety
           fundamental driving force.                                      for Uttar Pradesh, Dr. Umesh plays a
                                           Significant research contributions   pivotal role in analyzing food samples
           Key accomplishments and           Dr. Umesh’s  research on environ-  and ensuring their compliance with reg-
           experience                      mental microbiology, specifically the   ulatory standards. This includes prepar-
             With over 18 years of experience in   isolation and identification of heavy   ing Standard Operating Procedures
           medical and clinical microbiology, Dr.   metal-resistant microorganisms from the   (SOPs) for various tests, conducting re-
           Umesh has specialized in manufacturing   roots of Eichhornia crassipes, has signif-  peat and blind tests, and participating in
           rapid testing kits, DNA fingerprinting,   icant implications for bioremediation.   proficiency testing with global food la-
           and testing food samples under stringent   This work demonstrates how these mi-  boratories.
           safety standards. His expertise extends   croorganisms can degrade and disinte-
           to areas such as Westron Blotting,   grate heavy metals, offering potential   Challenges and successes
           DNA/RNA isolation, and recombinant   solutions for polluted industrial sites.   Dr. Umesh believes that internal
           DNA technology.                                                 motivation and a strong knowledge base
           Publications and research       Innovations and patents         can help overcome any challenges in the
             Dr. Umesh has published five inter-  Dr. Umesh holds several patents   field of food safety. His work has been

           18                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[instrumental in maintaining high
                                                                           standards and achieving laboratory
                                                                           accreditation through third-party
                                                                           assessments.
         Dr. Umesh working in the lab with an assistant                    focusing on providing highly sensitive

                                                                           Current food safety trends
                                                                              The Indian government is currently

                                                                           instruments for testing pesticide residues,
                                                                           contaminants, and toxins. Automation in
                                                                           food processing and risk-based analysis
                                                                           are also emerging trends aimed at
                                                                           improving food safety.

                                                                           Staying updated
                                                                              To keep abreast of the latest
                                                                           developments, Dr. Umesh emphasizes the
                                                                           importance of automation in food
                                                                           processing, healthier food options, and a
                                                                           transparent supply chain. He advocates for
                                                                           stricter regulations to control food safety
                                                                           and protect public health, stressing the
                                                                           need for proactive, risk-based
                                                                           preventative controls.

                                                                           Future outlook
                                                                              Dr. Umesh envisions a future where
                                                                           food safety remains a cornerstone of the
                                                                           agri-food system. Key areas requiring
         A food thermometer is an important instrument                     plastic recycling, and food fraud. He sees
                                                                           attention include the impact of climate
                                                                           change, changing consumer preferences,
                                                                           new food sources, urban agriculture,
                                                                           technological innovations and scientific
                                                                           advances as crucial in addressing these
                                                                           challenges.

                                                                           Advice for consumers and industry
                                                                           professionals
                                                                              Drawing from 16 years of experience,
                                                                           Dr. Umesh advises consumers to be
                                                                           vigilant about food labeling, including
                                                                           checking for ingredient lists, batch
                                                                           numbers, and packaging dates. For
                                                                           industry professionals, he emphasizes the
                                                                           importance of using residue-free raw
                                                                           materials, adhering to regulatory
                                                                           guidelines, and maintaining robust recall
                                                                           systems.

                                                                           Final thoughts
                                                                              "Safe food is a fundamental right," Dr
                                                                           Umesh asserts. On World Food Safety
                                                                           Day, he urges everyone to work towards
         Graphic of the food supply chain                                  ensuring global food security. "Protecting
                                                                           eliminating foodborne illnesses and
                                                                           our health starts with safe food," he
                                                                           concludes, emphasizing that food safety is
                                                                           crucial for public health, economic
                                                                           stability, and overall societal well-being.
                                                                           Ensuring safe food not only prevents
                                                                           diseases but also supports sustainable



           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             development and fosters trust. ■   19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[FILM REVIEW































           Heeramandi




           A rich tapestry of love,







           betrayal, and historical






           intrigue







           By Naina Kapoor

                 eeramandi, the latest Netflix                             Visual splendor and cinematic
                 series directed by the renowned                           grandeur
           HSanjay Leela Bhansali, offers an                                  Bhansali's mastery in creating visually
           opulent dive into the lives of courtesans                       spectacular worlds is on full display in
           in the Heera Mandi district of Lahore                           "Heeramandi." The series is marked by its
           during pre-independence India. Bhan-                            meticulous attention to detail, from the
           sali, known for his grandiose and                               sumptuous costumes to the elaborate set
           visually stunning films, does not stray                         designs. Subrata Chakraborty and Amit
           from his trademark style, presenting a                          Ray's production design transforms the
           series that is as much a feast for the eyes                     screen into a vibrant tableau that captures
           as it is a narrative exploration of com-                        the essence of the era, while Rimple and
           plex characters and historical context.                         Harpreet Narula’s costumes add layers of
                                                 Sanjay Leela Bhansali
           20                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[authenticity and beauty to the characters.
                                                                           The cinematography by Sudeep
                                                                           Chatterjee, Mahesh Limaye, Huentsang
                                                                           Mohapatra, and Ragul Herian Dharuman
                                                                           complements this visual feast, offering a
                                                                           classy and elegant lens through which the
                                                                           story unfolds.
                                                                              The musical score, composed by
                                                                           Bhansali himself, is both soulful and
                                                                           evocative, although some critics note
                                                                           that it may not have lasting appeal.
         Main characters in the film                                       soom Dil Hai Mera" stand out, while
                                                                           Tracks like "Tilasmi Bahein" and "Ma-
                                                                           others, such as "Azadi" and "Najariya Ki
                                                                           Maari," fail to leave a strong impression.
                                                                           The choreography by Kruti Mahesh is
                                                                           another highlight, showcasing well-re-
                                                                           searched and impressive dance
                                                                           sequences that enhance the narrative.

                                                                           Compelling performances
         Heeramandi's set design draws from Mughal architecture
                                                                              The cast of "Heeramandi" delivers
                                                                           performances that are both powerful and
                                                                           nuanced. Manisha Koirala, playing Ma-
                                                                           likajaan, the matriarch of the courtesans,
                                                                           commands the screen with a perform-
                                                                           ance that is poised and elegant. Her por-
                                                                           trayal brings depth to a character who is
                                                                           both authoritative and compassionate,
                                                                           struggling to maintain her dominance in
                                                                           a rapidly changing world.
                                                                              Sonakshi Sinha's portrayal of Faree-
                                                                           dan, marked by anger and resilience, is
                                                                           particularly noteworthy. Her one-take
                                                                           performance in "Tilasmi Bahein" is a
                                                                           testament to her acting prowess, earning
                                                                           widespread acclaim. Aditi Rao Hydari,
                                                                           though somewhat overshadowed, de-
                                                                           livers a strong performance, while Shar-














         Mujra practice on the set of Heeramandi

















           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[min Segal, despite some criticism re-
           garding her emotional range, shows
           promise and commitment to her role.
             Richa Chadda as Lajjo and Sanjeeda
           Sheikh as Waheeda offer compelling
           supporting performances. Chadda's por-
           trayal of a heartbroken and addicted
           courtesan is emotionally charged, while
           Sheikh's portrayal of the unhinged and                                                          Taha Shah Badussha in Heeramandi
           traumatized Waheeda adds a layer of un-
           predictability to the series. Other notable
           performances include Taha Shah, whose
           character arc is both revealing and im-
           pactful, and the return of Fardeen Khan,
           whose presence, although limited, adds
           to the series' nostalgic appeal.   The series attempts to balance the   argue that the series is overly indulgent
                                           personal dramas of its characters with   and slow, with a tendency to prioritize
           Narrative depth and historical   the larger historical context, often high-  style over substance. The plot, at times,
           context                         lighting the intersection of personal and   feels disjointed, and the storytelling can
             "Heeramandi" is not just a visual   political struggles. The looming threat of   be convoluted, making it difficult for
           spectacle; it delves deeply into the per-  revolution and the fight for independ-  viewers to stay engaged through all eight
           sonal and political turmoil of its char-  ence provide a rich backdrop for the   episodes.
           acters. Set against the backdrop of In-  characters' stories, adding layers of com-  Critics also note that while the series
           dia's struggle for independence, the   plexity and urgency to their personal di-  excels in its visual and musical ele-
           series weaves together themes of love,   lemmas.                ments, it occasionally falters in deliver-
           betrayal, and sacrifice. Malikajaan's rule                      ing a cohesive and compelling narrative.
           over the courtesans and their interactions   Critiques and reception   The extensive focus on aesthetics some-
           with patrons and revolutionaries reflect   Despite its many strengths, "Heera-  times overshadows the plot, leading to
           the broader societal and political ten-  mandi" has faced criticism for its pacing   moments where the story feels second-
           sions of the time.              and narrative structure. Some reviewers   ary to the spectacle. This has led to
                                                                           mixed reviews, with some viewers ap-
                                                                           preciating the series' artistic ambition
                                                                           while others find it lacking in narrative
                                                                           drive.
         Mallikajaan's ornate private chamber                              that showcases the grandeur of his film-
                                                                              In conclusion, "Heeramandi" stands
                                                                           as a testament to Sanjay Leela Bhansali's
                                                                           vision and artistic prowess. It is a series

                                                                           making style, with stunning visuals, in-
                                                                           tricate costumes, and a rich musical
                                                                           score. The performances, particularly by
                                                                           Manisha Koirala and Sonakshi Sinha,
                                                                           are compelling and add depth to the
                                                                           characters' intricate lives.
                                                                              However, the series is not without its
                                                                           flaws. Its slow pacing and occasionally
                                                                           disjointed narrative may test the patience
         Director talks about Alamzeb's role to Sharmin Segal
                                                                           of some viewers. Yet, for those willing
                                                                           to immerse themselves in Bhansali's me-
                                                                           ticulously crafted world, "Heeramandi"
                                                                           offers a rich and rewarding experience.
                                                                           It is a series that not only explores the
                                                                           lives of its characters but also reflects
                                                                           the broader historical and cultural
                                                                           changes of the time.
                                                                              Ultimately, "Heeramandi" is a bold
                                                                           and ambitious work that underscores
                                                                           Bhansali's position as one of India's
                                                                           foremost filmmakers. It is a series that,
                                                                           despite its imperfections, leaves a lasting
                                                                           impression and contributes significantly
                                                                           to the landscape of Indian television dra-
                                                                           mas. ■

           22                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[PRESERVING THE LEGACY                                                                                 CULTURAL HISTORY




           The forgotten role of







           courtesans







            By Anaya Gupta



                                                                           light on a hidden aspect of courtesan
                                                                           culture—many were accomplished
                                                                           poets, their verses adorning the pages of
                                                                           history alongside renowned literary fig-
                                                                           ures. "It is a testament to their intellect
                                                                           and creativity," Dr. Mairaj muses, "that
         Dr. Mairaj Uddin Ahmad, former Irrigation Minister                Cultural epicenters and Urdu
                                                                           their poetry transcended societal norms
                                                                           and found its way into the hearts of
                                                                           scholars and commoners alike."


                                                                           pedagogues
                                                                              Beyond the glittering lights of cities
                                                                           like Lucknow and Hyderabad, Dr. Mai-
                                                                           raj elucidates the lesser-known but
                                                                           equally significant contributions of cour-
                                                                           tesans in towns like Rampur, Sambhal,
                                                                           and Amroha. Here, these women served
                                                                           not only as purveyors of art but also as
                                                                           educators, imparting the richness of
                                                                           Urdu language and etiquette to eager
                                                                           learners. "In the havelis of Rampur," Dr.
             n the vibrant tapestry of Indian cul-  of Nawabs, landlords, and talukdars en-  Mairaj says, "courtesans held court,
             ture and history, there exist threads   trusting their children's education to   teaching the nuances of language and
           Ioften overlooked, stories whispered   these learned women, who imparted not   tradition to the aristocracy. Their in-
           in the corners of forgotten alleys. Dr.   only poetry and manners but also wis-  fluence was profound, shaping the cul-
           Mairajuddin Ahmed, the former irriga-  dom garnered from centuries of refined   tural landscape for generations to
           tion minister of Uttar Pradesh, is a cus-  culture. "The courtesans were the custo-  come."
           todian of one such narrative, shedding   dians of refinement," Dr. Mairaj reflects.
           light on the legacy of courtesans in a re-  "Their influence extended far beyond   The evolution of entertainment
           cent discussion on Sanjay Leela Bhan-  the confines of their chambers, shaping   As society evolved, so too did its
           sali's film, Hiramandi. In this exclusive   the very fabric of society."   forms of entertainment. Dr. Mairaj rem-
           interview, Dr. Mairaj takes us on a jour-                       inisces about a time when Mujra per-
           ney through time, revealing the intricate   Literary luminaries in brothels   formances were the pinnacle of social
           role courtesans, or Tawaifs, played in   Delving deeper into his family his-  gatherings, gracing wedding festivities
           shaping society, etiquette, and artistry.   tory, Dr. Mairaj unveils a treasure trove   and noble soirées with their grace and
                                           of literary brilliance. He reveals that his   allure. Yet, with the passage of time, the
           The educational hubs of etiquette   great-grandfather, Hakeem Fasihuddin   melodies of Mujra faded into the back-
             Dr. Mairaj paints a vivid picture of a   Ranj Meerathi, a disciple of the legen-  ground, making way for modern forms
           bygone era where courtesans were not   dary Mirza Ghalib, chronicled the lives   of music and dance. "The decline of
           merely entertainers but esteemed edu-  of courtesans in his seminal work,   Mujra marked the end of an era," Dr.
           cators of etiquette. He shares anecdotes   Bahristan e Naaz. This revelation sheds   Mairaj reflects somberly. "Yet, it also

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Mairaj reminisces, "one that has stayed
                                                                           with me throughout my life."
                                                                              Dr. Mairajuddin Ahmed also re-
                                                                           members how, during his childhood,
                                                                           many courtesans from Meerut would
                                                                           visit his father, Padma Shri Hakim Sai-
                                                                           fuddin Ahmed, for medical treatment.
         Artistic depiction of courtesan culture                           rive in the most famous royal carriage of
                                                                           His father was the honorary physician to
                                                                           the then President of India, Fakhruddin
                                                                           Ali Ahmed. "The courtesans would ar-

                                                                           the time, the ‘Baggi,’" he recalls. "They
                                                                           were covered in such a way that not even
                                                                           a single finger of their hand could be
                                                                           seen, preserving their modesty and mys-
                                                                           tique."

                                                                           The legacy lives on
                                                                              Though the era of courtesans may
                                           paved the way for new expressions of   have faded into memory, Dr. Mairaj be-
                                           artistry, ensuring that the spirit of crea-  lieves their legacy endures. Through his
                                           tivity continued to thrive."    words, he paints a picture of a time when
                                                                           art, culture, and tradition intertwined, en-
                                           A glimpse into the past         riching society in ways both profound
                                             In a poignant recollection, Dr. Mairaj   and enduring. As we bid farewell to this
                                           shares a childhood memory that encapsu-  enlightening conversation, let us re-
                                           lates the grace and dignity of courtesan   member that the echoes of the past rever-
                                           culture. Sent by his father to deliver med-  berate still, waiting to be heard and cher-
                                           icine to a renowned courtesan, he was   ished once more. "The legacy of the
         Mujra performance                 with warmth and generosity. This en-  books," Dr. Mairajuddin Ahmed con-
                                                                           courtesans is not confined to history
                                           greeted not with judgment or disdain, but
                                                                           cludes. "It lives on in the poetry, the
                                           counter, he reflects, was a testament to
                                                                           music, and the traditions they left be-
                                           the inherent decency and humanity that
                                                                           hind—a timeless reminder of the beauty
                                           transcended societal divides. "It was a
                                                                           and complexity of our shared heritage." ■
                                           lesson in humility and empathy," Dr.



















         Glamorous depiction of a courtesan















           24                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[TRAVEL



































           Hong Kong



           A vibrant fusion of









           East and West








           By Navormi Vats


                 ong Kong, a bustling metropo-  suring you capture the essence of this   chargeable smart card, is highly rec-
                 lis, is a unique blend of Chinese   fascinating city.     ommended for ease of travel on public
           Hheritage and British colonial in-                              transport, including buses, trams, and
           fluence. This dynamic city is not just a   Arrival and getting around   the MTR (Mass Transit Railway).
           financial hub but also a vibrant travel   Hong Kong International Airport is
           destination that offers a rich tapestry of   one of the busiest and best-connected   Accommodation
           experiences, from towering skyscrapers   airports in the world. Upon arrival, you   Hong Kong offers a wide range of
           and bustling markets to serene temples   can take the Airport Express train, which   accommodation options to suit all budg-
           and verdant parks. Here’s a comprehen-  swiftly connects you to the city center in   ets. For luxury seekers, the iconic Pen-
           sive guide to exploring Hong Kong, en-  just 24 minutes. The Octopus Card, a re-  insula Hotel and the Ritz-Carlton offer

           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[opulent stays with breathtaking views of
           Victoria Harbour. Mid-range options in-
           clude the centrally located Ovolo Hotels
           and the boutique Hotel ICON. Budget
           travelers can find comfortable hostels
           and guesthouses in areas like Mong Kok
           and Tsim Sha Tsui.

           Day 1: Exploring Hong Kong Island
           Victoria peak
             Start your journey at Victoria Peak,
           the highest point on Hong Kong Island.
           The Peak Tram, a funicular railway,                                                             Lan Kwai Fong at night
           takes you up the steep slope to the sum-
           mit. The Sky Terrace 428 offers a pano-
           ramic view of the city’s skyline, Victoria
           Harbour, and the lush hills of the New
           Territories. For nature enthusiasts, the   Road), a trendy neighborhood brimming
           Peak Circle Walk provides a scenic trail   with international cuisine, chic cafes,   Lan Kwai Fong and Duddell street
           with equally stunning views.    and art galleries.                 As evening approaches, explore Lan
                                                                           Kwai Fong, Hong Kong’s premier night-
           Central and SoHo                Man Mo temple                   life district. This area is famous for its
             Descend to Central, the heart of   After lunch, take a short walk to Man   vibrant bars, clubs, and restaurants. Just
           Hong Kong’s business district. Here, the   Mo Temple, one of Hong Kong’s oldest   nearby, the historic Duddell Street steps
           juxtaposition of colonial buildings and   temples, dedicated to the gods of litera-  and gas lamps provide a picturesque set-
           modern skyscrapers is striking. Visit the   ture and war. The intricate incense coils   ting reminiscent of old Hong Kong.
           historic St. John’s Cathedral and the   hanging from the ceiling create an other-
           manicured Hong Kong Park. For lunch,   worldly atmosphere, offering a peaceful   Day 2: Kowloon and beyond
           head to SoHo (South of Hollywood   retreat from the city’s hustle and bustle.   Tsim Sha Tsui Promenade and Star
                                                                           ferry
                                                                              Begin your second day in Tsim Sha
                                                                           Tsui, Kowloon. The Tsim Sha Tsui
                                                                           Promenade offers stunning views of the
                                                                           Hong Kong Island skyline, especially
                                                                           during the Symphony of Lights show
                                                                           each evening. Don’t miss the Avenue of
                                                                           Stars, Hong Kong’s version of the Hol-
         Ngong Ping 360 Cable Car                                          Chan.
                                                                           lywood Walk of Fame, honoring local
                                                                           celebrities like Bruce Lee and Jackie
                                                                              A short walk away, the Star Ferry
                                                                           provides a scenic and inexpensive ride
                                                                           across Victoria Harbour, offering one of
                                                                           the best ways to take in the city’s im-
                                                                           pressive skyline.

                                                                           Nathan road and Mong Kok
                                                                              Stroll along Nathan Road, known as
                                                                           the "Golden Mile," filled with shops,
                                                                           restaurants, and markets. Continue to
                                                                           Mong Kok, one of the most densely
                                                                           populated places in the world, where
                                                                           you’ll find bustling markets such as the
                                                                           Ladies’ Market, known for fashion bar-
                                                                           gains, and the Flower Market, a fragrant
                                                                           oasis of colorful blooms.

                                                                           Temple street night market
                                                                              As night falls, head to Temple Street
         Victoria Peak                                                     tling market is a feast for the senses,
                                                                           Night Market in Yau Ma Tei. This bus-
                                                                           with vendors selling everything from
                                                                           clothing and accessories to gadgets and

           26                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[street food. Be sure to try local deli-
                                                                           cacies like stinky tofu and egg waffles.

                                                                           Day 3: Cultural and natural
                                                                           highlights
                                                                           Lantau Island
                                                                              Dedicate your third day to exploring
                                                                           Lantau Island, home to some of Hong
         Kam Shan Country Park                                             Ngong Ping 360 cable car from Tung
                                                                           Kong’s most iconic sights. Take the
                                                                           Chung to Ngong Ping Village. The 25-
                                                                           minute ride offers breathtaking views of
                                                                           the South China Sea and lush moun-
                                                                           tains.

                                                                           Tian Tan Buddha and Po Lin
                                                                           monastery
                                                                              Once at Ngong Ping, visit the Tian
                                                                           Tan Buddha, a massive bronze statue
                                                                           standing at 34 meters tall. Climb the 268
                                                                           steps to the base for a closer look and to
                                                                           enjoy panoramic views. Nearby, the Po
                                                                           Lin Monastery, with its exquisite archi-
                                                                           tecture and peaceful gardens, is a spiri-
                                                                           tual haven.
         Duddell Street Steps                                              Tai O fishing village

                                                                              A short bus ride from Ngong Ping
                                                                           takes you to Tai O Fishing Village.
                                                                           Known as the "Venice of Hong Kong,"
                                                                           Tai O offers a glimpse into Hong Kong’s
                                                                           past with its traditional stilt houses and
                                                                           bustling seafood markets. Enjoy a boat
                                                                           ride through the village’s waterways and
                                                                           sample fresh seafood.

                                                                           Culinary delights
                                                                              Hong Kong is a food lover’s para-
                                                                           dise, boasting a diverse culinary scene.
                                                                           Don’t miss trying dim sum at renowned
                                                                           establishments like Tim Ho Wan and
                                                                           Luk Yu Tea House. Other must-try
                                                                           dishes include wonton noodles, roast
                                                                           goose, and pineapple buns.
         Peak Tram                                                         Jumbo Kingdom, a massive floating res-
                                                                              For a unique dining experience, visit
                                                                           taurant in Aberdeen. Enjoy fresh sea-
                                                                           food while taking in the elaborate Chi-
                                                                           nese-style decor.

                                                                           Shopping extravaganza
                                                                              Hong Kong is a shopper’s haven, of-
                                                                           fering everything from luxury brands to
                                                                           quirky street markets. In addition to the
                                                                           markets mentioned earlier, visit Cause-
                                                                           way Bay for high-end shopping at Times
                                                                           Square and Hysan Place. For unique
         Tai O Fishing Village                                             dependent labels in Sheung Wan and the
                                                                           finds, explore the boutique shops and in-
                                                                           Cat Street Market.

                                                                           Day trips and excursions


                                                                                                       27
           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                If you have more time, consider day]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[trips to the New Territories, where you
                                                                           can explore the serene Kam Shan Coun-
                                                                           try Park, also known as Monkey Hill, or
                                                                           the historic Ping Shan Heritage Trail,
                                                                           which showcases traditional Chinese ar-
                                                                           chitecture and culture.
                                                                              The Outlying Islands, such as
                                                                           Cheung Chau and Lamma Island, offer a
                                                                           more relaxed pace. These islands are
                                                                           perfect for hiking, cycling, and enjoying
                                                                           fresh seafood by the sea.

                                                                           Practical tips
                                                                              Language: While Cantonese is the
                                                                           primary language, English is widely
                                                                           spoken, especially in tourist areas.
         Man Mo Temple                                                     (HKD) is the local currency. Credit
                                                                              Currency: The Hong Kong Dollar
                                                                           cards are widely accepted, but it’s al-
                                                                           ways good to have some cash on hand.
                                                                              Climate: Hong Kong has a subtropi-
                                                                           cal climate. The best time to visit is dur-
                                                                           ing the cooler months from October to
                                                                           December. Summers can be hot and
                                                                           humid, with occasional typhoons.
                                                                              Safety: Hong Kong is generally safe
                                                                           for tourists, with low crime rates. Ho-
                                                                           wever, always stay aware of your sur-
                                                                           roundings and keep an eye on your be-
                                                                           longings.
                                                                              Hong Kong is a city of contrasts,
                                                                           where futuristic skyscrapers stand
                                                                           alongside traditional temples, and bus-
         Dim Sum at Tim Ho Wan                                             delights, and vibrant atmosphere make it
                                                                           tling markets coexist with tranquil
                                                                           parks. Its rich cultural heritage, culinary
                                                                           a must-visit destination. Whether you’re
                                                                           exploring its urban jungle or venturing
                                                                           into its natural landscapes, Hong Kong
                                                                           promises an unforgettable travel experi-
                                                                           ence. ■

















         Hong Kong skyline at sunset












           28                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[HOROSCOPES                                     June 16-30, 2024
                                                                                                                ASTROLOGY







           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     During this bi-weekly period, Aries, with       This period brings a renewed focus on relation-
                     summer's fire igniting your soul, Be bold, take   ships for Libra. Harmony-seeking Libra, balance
                     charge and reach your goal. Adventure awaits,   your scales, Relationships thrive, and love un-
                     embrace the thrill, Success and passion, your   veils. Diplomacy and fairness guide your way,
                     destiny fulfill.                                Find joy in partnerships, day by day.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     The spotlight is on relationships and partnerships   During this bi-weekly period, Scorpio, dive deep
                     for Taurus. Nurture your connections with loved   into your passions and motivations. Focus on
                     ones and strengthen the bonds of trust. Collaborate   personal transformation and growth. Let go of
                     with others to achieve mutually beneficial      what no longer serves you and embrace positive
                     outcomes.                                       change.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     This period highlights communication and self-  For Sagittarius, this is a time of adventure and
                     expression for Gemini. Express your thoughts    expansion. Embrace new experiences, whether
                     and ideas with clarity and confidence. Embrace   through travel, education, or stepping out of
                     new ways of thinking and be open to learning    your comfort zone. Broaden your horizons and
                     from others.                                    seek out opportunities for personal growth.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     During this bi-weekly period, Cancer, focus on   This bi-weekly period brings a focus on stability
                     bringing balance and harmony to your personal   and practicality for Capricorn. Set clear goals
                     and professional life. Take time for self-care and   and establish a solid foundation for your en-
                     nurture your emotional well-being. Trust your   deavors. Discipline and hard work will lead to
                     intuition to guide you.                         long-term success.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     This bi-weekly period brings oodles of creativity   During this period, Aquarius, allow your unique
                     and self-confidence for Leo. Your passion and   perspective to shine. Embrace your individuality
                     charisma will attract opportunities and admirers.   and share your ideas with others. Connect with
                     Use your creative talents to manifest your      like-minded individuals and engage in meaning-
                     dreams and pursue new ventures.                 ful conversations that inspire change.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     For Virgo, this is a time for introspection and   This is a time for introspection and spiritual
                     self-reflection. Take a step back, review your   growth. Connect with your inner self through
                     goals, and assess your progress. Make necessary   meditation, creative pursuits, or spending time in
                     adjustments and focus on personal growth. Trust   nature. Trust your intuition and let it guide you
                     in your abilities and dedicate time to self-care.   towards the path of enlightenment.





           JUNE 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Heartfelt Thanks for Mother's Day
                                           Strength
           Editorial
                                             I feel compelled to acknowledge the
                I wanted to express my heartfelt
                                           immense influence of maternal love.
           gratitude for the beautiful editorial on   Honoring Maternal Love and   Advocating for Workers' Rights
                                                                              International Labour Day on May 1st
           Mother's Day. It brought immense joy to   Mothers epitomize strength, sacrifice, and   is a vital reminder of the on-going struggle
           my heart. In today's materialistic world,   unwavering support. Their love is a   for workers' rights. Rooted in the historic
           we often overlook the value of mothers   beacon of hope, guiding us through life's   fight for fair labor practices, this day
           and parents. It's only when they're gone   challenges. Let's take this opportunity to   celebrates the contributions of workers
           that we realize their importance. Their   honor and celebrate these extraordinary   globally and highlights current challenges
           absence leaves a void, and we're left   women who shape our lives with their   like unsafe conditions and income
           longing for someone to care for us. Your   boundless love and devotion.   inequality, especially in the wake of
           editorial poignantly captured this   Kishori Lal, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh,   COVID-19. We must renew our
           sentiment. Thank you for reminding us of   India                commitment to advocating for dignified
           the priceless gift of maternal love. Happy                      working conditions and fair wages.
           mother's day to all the readers.                                Together, we can build a future where
           Shahid A Siddiqui IRS (Retd.), Camp:   Recognizing Workers:     every worker is respected and valued.
           Hamdard Education Society,      International Labour Day        Rohit Verma, Secunderabad,
           Talimabad, New Delhi, India       I want to highlight the significance of   Hyderabad, India
                                           International Labour Day in honoring
                                           the tireless contributions of workers
           Honoring Mothers' Unwavering    worldwide. This day, rooted in the his-  Exploring Off-Grid Living
           Love                            torical struggles for fair labor practices,   I am writing to express my interest in
             I am filled with deep gratitude for the   serves as a reminder of the ongoing fight   the topic of off-grid living, which is
           extraordinary women who shape our   for workers' rights and dignified work-  increasingly relevant in today's world. As
           lives with their boundless love and sac-  ing conditions.       more individuals seek sustainable and
           rifice. A mother's love is an unparalleled   Today, workers continue to face chal-  self-sufficient lifestyles, the appeal of
           force, offering unwavering support and   lenges such as income inequality, unsafe   living off the grid grows. This lifestyle not
           comfort through life's many challenges.   workplaces, and job insecurity, exacer-  only reduces one's environmental
           It is a love that nurtures, heals, and em-  bated by the COVID-19 pandemic. Ho-  footprint but also promotes resilience and
           powers us, remaining a constant beacon   wever, Labour Day also presents an op-  independence.
           of hope and strength.           portunity to reflect on the progress made
             Let us honor and celebrate the silent   and to recommit to advocating for jus-  Off-grid living involves generating
           heroes who have given us so much of   tice and equality.        your own power, sourcing water, and
           themselves. Let us cherish their mem-  We must celebrate the spirit of sol-  often growing your own food. It offers a
           ories, acknowledge their sacrifices, and   idarity and resilience that defines the   unique sense of freedom from the con-
           express our heartfelt gratitude for their   labor movement and work towards a fu-  straints of traditional utility services and
           enduring love. To all mothers, thank you   ture where every worker is respected   fosters a closer connection to nature. It
           for your unyielding devotion and for   and valued.              also requires significant planning to sus-
           being the guiding light in our lives.   Ram Kumar Sharma, Bhopal, Mad-  tainable practices.
           Ramesh Sehgal, Delhi, India     hya Pradesh, India              Nirmal Deshpande, Nagpur, Maha-
                                                                           rashtra, India

            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JUNE 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>