<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[28




                                                                                                   5











                                                                                                   8












                                                                                                 12










              18
                                                                                                 15





           IN THIS ISSUE                                                                        2024



                     VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 5, JANUARY 01 2024
                                                                                                 24
          4. Editorial: Securing truth in a digi-  18. The untold story of Shastri's last
          tal era                          hours in Tashkent
          5. Are we ready for the next wave?   22. Anil Shastri unravels his father's
          8. Decoding the surge of social anx-  legacy
          iety in Indian young minds       24. Resolutions with a purpose
          12. How smart devices are rewriting   26. Shah Rukh Khan's magnetic
          the entertainment script         odyssey through immigrant hilarity
          15. 2024 elections engage half of   28. A Journey into the Heart of the                26

          the World's population!          Himalayas



           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Deepfakes and Democracy
     EDITORIAL  Securing truth in a                                                 Editor-in-Chief




                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           digital era                                                            Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n 2024, elections in 70 countries, engag-
                                           ing nearly half the world's population,   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                        Iare set against the backdrop of a historic   Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        integration of generative AI tools like
                                        ChatGPT and Midjourney into the electoral   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        landscape. This convergence demands a        Sushil Kumar
                                        closer look at the transformative impact of
                                        AI on elections, the rising threat of misin-  Social Media Editor
                                        formation, and evolving global responses to   Vishakha Sharma
                                        safeguard democratic processes.
                                           Generative AI tools, including ChatGPT   Art & Graphics Director
                                        and Midjourney, are reshaping the infor-
                                        mation landscape surrounding the 2024        Vipin Agarwal
                                        elections in the UK, the US, India, and bey-
           ond. The integration of these tools into politics necessitates an understanding of their
           implications on political discourse and public opinion.           EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             With over two billion participants in the upcoming elections, the surge in AI-
           driven misinformation poses a significant challenge. Deepfakes, hyper-realistic vi-  D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           deos manipulating public figures, have the potential to sway opinions and disrupt the   Editor, United News of India, New
           democratic process. Immediate attention is required to counter this threat and pre-  Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           serve the authenticity of digital content.                        Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
             Governments worldwide recognize the severity of AI-driven misinformation and   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           are actively pursuing regulatory measures. The US and the European Union propose   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           watermarking and regulatory deals, while the UK exercises caution about overregula-
           tion. Fact-checkers and dedicated task forces play a pivotal role in countering misin-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           formation, emphasizing the need for international collaboration.   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
             Tech giants like Meta face scrutiny due to past failures in combating fake news.   Jamali (Architect)
           Pressured by governments and the public, these companies must take proactive meas-
           ures. Robust guardrails and ethical considerations are imperative as we navigate the   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           complex intersection of technology and democracy, learning from past mistakes to
           forge a more responsible future.                                     Phone +91 20 40199102
             Individuals must play an active role in safeguarding against AI-generated content.   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           Internet security experts stress the importance of vigilance, urging individuals to ver-  Baner Road,
           ify online content. Diversifying news sources and being conscious of confirmation   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           bias are essential tools in navigating the complex information landscape.   Email revoir@post.com
             As India prepares for its 2024 elections, the convergence of generative AI, bots,
           and social media presents both challenges and opportunities. Establishing a compre-  Website www.revoir.in
           hensive ethical framework for generative AI is essential to ensure accountability,
           transparency, and responsible technology use.                            Legal Advisor
             In 2024, as politics and generative AI converge, a nuanced and collaborative ap-  Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           proach is crucial. While technology offers transformative potential, guarding against
           manipulation and misinformation is paramount. Governments, tech companies, and   Copyright © 2023 REVOIR (eZine),
           individuals must work globally to navigate these uncharted waters successfully, shap-  all rights reserved. This publication
           ing the future of democracy in an era dominated by artificial intelligence. Decisions   may not be reproduced in any form
                            made today will echo through history, determining the path   without permission.
                            forward for democratic ideals in the age of AI.




           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[GLOBAL HEALTH


















































           Covid-19 JN.1 variant alert:

           Are we ready for the








           next wave?







             n the ever-evolving landscape of the   spike protein compared to its predeces-  weeks ago.
             COVID-19 pandemic, new variants   sor, the BA.2.86 variant. The spike pro-  Transmissibility:
           Icontinue to emerge, each with its   tein is crucial for the virus to enter   One of the key concerns associated
           unique characteristics and implications.   human cells, making any changes in this   with the JN.1 variant is its increased
           One such variant that has recently   region significant in terms of transmis-  transmissibility. The rapid rise in its
           gained attention is JN.1, classified as a   sibility and immune evasion. Detected   prevalence within a short span has
           "variant of interest" by the World Health   in the United States since September   raised alarms among health authorities.
           Organization (WHO).             2023, JN.1 has rapidly become more   Currently accounting for a significant
           Origins and Characteristics:    prevalent, accounting for approximately   proportion of COVID-19 cases in the
             JN.1 is an offshoot of the Omicron   44% of COVID-19 cases in the country,   U.S., JN.1's transmission dynamics are
           variant, featuring a single change in the   a notable increase from 8% just four   under close scrutiny. Efforts are under-

           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[way to understand how efficiently it
           spreads compared to other variants and
           whether it possesses unique characteris-
           tics that contribute to its rapid dissemi-
                                                                                                           A healthcare professional in full protective gear
           nation.
           Severity:
             As of the latest information, there is
           no evidence suggesting that JN.1 poses
           an increased risk to public health or
           causes more severe cases of COVID-19.












                                           While its transmissibility is a cause for   to enhance protection against the JN.1
                                           concern, it is crucial to differentiate be-  variant, similar to their efficacy against
                                           tween transmission rates and disease   other variants. The adaptability of vac-
                                           severity. Continuous monitoring and re-  cine development to address emerging
                                           search are essential to determine   variants is a testament to ongoing efforts
                                           whether JN.1 exhibits any changes in   to stay ahead of the virus. Continued re-
                                           disease severity compared to other vari-
                                                                           search and surveillance will be nec-
         A specimen for analysis           Vaccine Effectiveness:          ments needed in vaccination strategies.
                                                                           essary to assess any potential adjust-
                                           ants.
                                             The effectiveness of existing
                                                                           Symptoms:
                                                                              At present, it remains unclear
                                           COVID-19 vaccines against JN.1 is a
                                                                           whether JN.1 manifests different symp-
                                           critical aspect in managing its spread.
                                                                           toms compared to other variants. The
                                           According to current understanding, up-
                                                                           rapid growth of JN.1 has sparked con-
                                           dated COVID-19 vaccines are expected















         A young woman getting COVID-19 vaccinations




















           6                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[The molecular structures of JN.1








                                                                                                           COVID-19 vaccines







                                                                           succumbed to the new variant, high-
                                                                           lighting the potential consequences of its
                                                                           spread. Additionally, three deaths were
                                                                           reported in Kerala, the first state to con-
                                                                           firm the presence of the JN.1 sub-variant
                                                                           in India.
                                                                              As the world grapples with the ongo-
         Performing PCR tests                                              ants adds complexity to the situation.
                                                                           ing challenges posed by the COVID-19
                                                                           pandemic, the emergence of new vari-
                                                                           The JN.1 variant, with its increased
                                                                           transmissibility, raises concerns about

                                                                           current evidence suggests that it does
           cerns about its potential impact on pub-  Beyond the borders of the United   the trajectory of the pandemic. However,
                                                                           not lead to more severe cases of
           lic health. However, health officials em-  States, the JN.1 variant has made its   COVID-19, and updated vaccines are
           phasize that, as of now, there is no indi-  presence known across India. Recent la-  expected to provide protection.
           cation of increased severity associated   boratory reports confirm the spread of   Continuous monitoring, robust re-
           with JN.1. Ongoing studies aim to char-  this new variant, with 21 cases identified   search, and international collaboration
           acterize the clinical presentation of   in the country. The Indian SARS-CoV-2   are paramount in addressing the threat
           JN.1-infected individuals and identify   Genomics Consortium (INSACOG) has   posed by variants like JN.1. The global
           any distinctive features in symptoms.   reported 18 cases of the JN.1 sub-variant   community's collective efforts in vacci-
           Global Spread and Impact:       in Goa and one case each in Kerala and   nation, surveillance, and public health
                                           Maharashtra.                    measures remain crucial in navigating
                                             Tragically, reports have surfaced of   the evolving landscape of the pandemic
                                           fatalities associated with the JN.1 vari-  and mitigating its impact on societies
                                           ant. A man in Bengaluru, Karnataka,   worldwide.








         Sanitizing hands for cleanliness                                                                  Vigilant symptom monitoring













           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[EDUCATION AND PARENTING
















































           Breaking the chains
           Decoding the surge of social




           anxiety in Indian young minds





           This article delves deeper into the multifaceted factors contributing to the rise of social
           anxiety in Indian children and provides an extensive exploration of coping strategies for
           both parents and children.


             n recent years, the prevalence of so-                         ments, plays a pivotal role in the rise of
             cial anxiety among children in India                          social anxiety among children. The
           Ihas witnessed a concerning surge.                              fierce competition and the societal em-
           The modern landscape, marked by rapid                           phasis on grades create an environment
           technological advancements and evolv-                           where children fear judgment and per-
           ing social dynamics, poses unique chal-                         formance anxiety, impacting their ability
           lenges for the younger generation.                              to navigate social interactions.
           Factors Contributing to the Rise of                                Technology and Social Media: While
           Social Anxiety in Indian Children:                              technology has revolutionized com-
             Academic Pressure: The intense aca-                           munication, it has also given rise to new
           demic pressure in India, where success                          challenges, especially for the younger
           is often equated with academic achieve-                         generation. Social media platforms ex-

           8                                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[pose children to constant comparison,   Cultural Expectations: Indian society  A parent comforting a child to provide emotional support
                                           cyberbullying, and the pressure to con-  places a significant emphasis on con-
                                           form to unrealistic standards. The fear of   formity and adherence to societal norms.
                                           being judged or bullied online can mani-  Children may develop social anxiety as
                                           fest into real-world social anxiety, hin-  they fear deviating from these expecta-
                                           dering healthy social development.   tions, especially in environments where
                                             Changing Family Dynamics: Shifts   they feel their actions or appearance
                                           in family structures, with an increase in   might not align with cultural norms.
                                           nuclear families and hectic schedules,   ciety that sometimes values stoicism
                                                                              Lack of Emotional Support: In a so-
         A child under stress              Limited social interactions within the   over emotional expression, children may
                                           contribute to social anxiety in children.
                                                                           find it challenging to seek emotional
                                           family unit may result in children feel-
                                                                           support. The stigma surrounding mental
                                           ing unprepared or anxious when faced
                                                                           health issues and the lack of open com-
                                           with social situations outside their im-
                                                                           munication contribute to the devel-
                                           mediate circle.













                                                                                                           Overburden can disturb the child













           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                       9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[A student exhibiting signs of stress during exams











         A sad-looking child






                                                                           opment of social anxiety.
                                                                           Coping Strategies for Children:
         Focusing solely on education may disturb the child                Simple exercises such as deep breathing,
                                                                              Mindfulness and Relaxation Tech-
                                                                           niques: Teaching children mindfulness
                                                                           and relaxation techniques provides them
                                                                           with practical tools to manage anxiety.

                                                                           meditation, or progressive muscle relax-
                                                                           ation can be incorporated into their daily
                                                                           routine to foster emotional resilience.
                                                                           Encouraging Open Communication:
                                                                           Parents and guardians play a crucial role
                                                                           in creating an environment where chil-
                                                                           dren feel comfortable expressing their
                                                                           feelings. Encouraging open communica-
                                                                           tion not only helps identify the root
                                                                           causes of anxiety but also facilitates a
                                                                           supportive relationship between parents
                                                                           and children.
                                                                              Gradual Exposure: Gradual exposure
                                                                           to social situations is an effective
         Balancing academics and extracurriculars is beneficial
                                                                           strategy for building resilience. Starting
                                                                           with small, controlled social interactions
                                                                           and gradually increasing the complexity
                                                                           of social situations can help desensitize
                                                                           children to anxiety triggers and boost
                                                                           their confidence.
                                                                              Social Skills Training: Equipping
                                                                           children with essential social skills is
                                                                           paramount. Social skills training can in-
                                                                           clude role-playing, communication exer-
                                                                           cises, and activities that promote team-
                                                                           work and cooperation, enabling children
                                                                           to navigate various social situations with
                                                                           confidence.
                                                                              Setting Realistic Expectations: Man-
                                                                           aging academic and extracurricular ex-
                                                                           pectations is crucial for mitigating social

           10                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[fostering a sense of security and ac-
         Children engaged in teamwork exercises and role-playing
                                                                           ceptance, which serves as a crucial
                                                                           foundation for managing social anx-
                                                                           iety.
                                                                              Seeking Professional Help: If social
                                                                           anxiety significantly impacts a child's
                                                                           daily life, seeking professional help
                                                                           from a mental health expert is essen-
                                                                           tial. Therapists can provide targeted in-
                                                                           terventions and coping strategies tai-
                                                                           lored to the child's specific needs,
                                                                           facilitating a more comprehensive and
                                                                           effective approach to treatment.
                                                                              Limiting Screen Time: Parents
                                                                           should monitor and limit their chil-
                                                                           dren's screen time, especially on social
                                                                           media platforms. Setting age-appropri-
                                                                           ate restrictions and discussing respon-
                                                                           sible online behavior can mitigate the
                                                                           negative impact of technology on chil-
                                                                           dren's mental health.
                                                                              Promoting Healthy Social Connec-
                                                                           tions: Encouraging children to engage
                                                                           in positive social interactions outside
                                                                           of academic settings is crucial. Activ-
                                                                           ities such as team sports, arts and
                                                                           crafts clubs, or community service can
                                                                           help build self-esteem and social skills,
                                                                           providing a well-rounded approach to
         Children involved in group activities                             contributing to the surge in social anx-
                                                                           social development.
                                                                              Understanding the myriad factors

                                                                           iety among Indian children is essential
                                                                           for devising effective coping strategies.
                                                                           By implementing these comprehensive
                                                                           coping strategies, parents and children
                                                                           can work collaboratively to build resil-
                                                                           ience, foster healthy social connec-
                                                                           tions, and create an environment that
                                                                           promotes emotional well-being. It is
           anxiety. Parents should encourage their   structive approach.   imperative for society to recognize the
           children to strive for personal growth   Fostering a Supportive Home Envi-  importance of mental health in chil-
           rather than perfection, emphasizing that   ronment: Creating a nurturing and sup-  dren and collectively take steps to al-
           failures are opportunities to learn and   portive home environment is vital for   leviate the pressures contributing to
           not reasons for shame.          children's mental health. Parents   the rise of social anxiety, ensuring a
           Coping Strategies for Parents:   should be attuned to their children's   brighter and more mentally resilient
             Education and Awareness: Parents   emotional needs, actively engaging in   future for the younger generation.
           should actively educate themselves
           about social anxiety, including its symp-
           toms and impact on children. Under-
           standing the condition enables parents to
           provide informed support and guidance,
           fostering a more empathetic and con-





         Meditation or Yoga                                                                                Physical activity







           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[MEDIA AND ENTERTAINMENT





































           The mobile takeover



           How smart devices are rewriting



           the entertainment script





           In this article, we will delve into the reasons behind this shift, the impact on DTH services, and
           the evolving dynamics of the Indian home entertainment industry.


                he landscape of home entertain-                            tion of smart televisions has further al-
                ment in India has undergone a                              tered the way people consume content.
           Tsignificant transformation in re-                              Smart TVs come equipped with internet
           cent years, primarily due to the in-                            connectivity and the capability to run
           creased use of mobiles and smart televi-                        applications, essentially turning them
           sions for viewing movies and                                    into large-screen gateways to the digital
           entertainment programs. This shift has                          world. This has resulted in a decline in
           had a remarkable impact on the usage of                         the demand for traditional DTH serv-
           traditional Direct-to-Home (DTH) serv-                          ices, which were once the primary
           ices such as Tata Play, Airtel and Dish                         means of accessing television content.
           TV. As more and more individuals, espe-  phones and smart televisions. With the   The Dominance of OTT Platforms
           cially the youth, turn to mobile devices   advent of affordable smartphones and   The emergence and rapid growth of
           and smart TVs, Over-The-Top (OTT)   high-speed internet connectivity, indi-  OTT platforms have played a pivotal
           platforms like Hotstar, Netflix, Amazon   viduals now have the convenience of ac-  role in reshaping the home entertain-
           Prime, Sony Liv, and Zee5 have become   cessing a plethora of entertainment op-  ment landscape. Platforms like Hotstar,
           the go-to sources for entertainment.    tions at their fingertips. The portability   Netflix, Amazon Prime, Sony Liv, and
           The Rise of Mobiles and Smart Televi-  and personalization offered by mobile   Zee5 offer a diverse range of content, in-
           sions                           devices have made them the preferred   cluding movies, TV shows, original
             One of the primary factors contrib-  choice for a significant portion of the   series, and documentaries. The on-de-
           uting to the decline in the use of DTH   population.            mand nature of these platforms allows
           services is the pervasive use of mobile   Simultaneously, the widespread adop-  users to watch content at their conven-

           12                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Leading OTT services








           ience, eliminating the need to adhere to   their primary source of entertainment.   approach of OTT platforms.
           scheduled programming.          The seamless integration of social   Evolving Content Consumption
             OTT platforms cater to a wide au-  media, gaming, and video streaming   Habits
           dience by providing content across var-  apps on smartphones has made them in-  The shift from DTH to OTT plat-
           ious genres and languages. This diver-  dispensable companions for young indi-  forms is not merely a technological
           sity appeals to the preferences of both   viduals. The convenience of watching   change but also a reflection of evolving
           the youth, who are often on mobile de-  movies, TV shows, and short videos on   content consumption habits. The tradi-
           vices, and older individuals, who can   the go has led to a decline in the time   tional model of linear programming,
           enjoy programs on smart TVs. The con-  spent on traditional television viewing.   where viewers had to adhere to fixed
           venience of streaming content on multi-  OTT platforms have capitalized on   schedules, is being replaced by a more
           ple devices, along with the ability to   this trend by optimizing their content for   flexible and personalized approach.
           create personalized watchlists, has   mobile consumption. Short-form   OTT platforms allow users to choose
           further solidified the popularity of OTT   content, exclusive mobile-friendly   what they want to watch, when they
           platforms.                      series, and interactive features have   want to watch it, and on the device of
           Youth Preference for Mobile Enter-  been introduced to cater to the prefer-  their choice.
           tainment                        ences of the younger audience. As a re-  Binge-watching, the practice of
             The youth demographic, in particu-  sult, traditional DTH services are facing   watching multiple episodes of a TV
           lar, has embraced mobile devices as   stiff competition from the mobile-centric   series in one sitting, has become a prev-















         Tablets and mobile devices                                                                        Youth captivated by their mobile devices











           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Challenges Faced by DTH Services
         A modern living room with a sleek smart television                lenges include:
                                                                              As the dominance of OTT platforms
                                                                           continues to grow, DTH services face
                                                                           numerous challenges in retaining their
                                                                           market share. Some of the key chal-
                                                                              Limited On-Demand Options: DTH
                                                                           services traditionally operate on a linear
                                                                           programming model, offering limited
                                                                           on-demand options. This lack of flex-
                                                                           ibility contrasts sharply with the on-de-
                                                                           mand nature of OTT platforms.
                                                                              Internet Connectivity: While urban
                                                                           areas enjoy robust internet connectivity,
                                                                           rural regions may still face challenges in
                                                                           accessing high-speed internet. DTH
                                                                           services, with their satellite-based trans-
                                                                           mission, have an edge in providing reli-
                                                                           able services in areas with limited inter-
                                                                           net infrastructure.
                                                                              Cost Considerations: Some users
                                                                           may find the subscription costs of OTT
                                                                           platforms more affordable than tradi-
                                                                           tional DTH services, especially consid-
         Youth with Mobile Devices                                         technology used by DTH services may
                                                                           ering the wide range of content available
                                                                           on streaming platforms.
                                                                              Technological Obsolescence: The
                                                                           be considered outdated compared to the
                                                                           interactive and dynamic features offered
                                                                           by smart TVs and OTT platforms.
                                                                              Competition from Smart TVs: The
                                                                           increasing affordability and popularity
           alent trend facilitated by OTT platforms.   exclusivity encourages users to sub-  of smart TVs provide users with a single
           This binge culture has further dimin-  scribe to these platforms, further reduc-  device that can access both traditional
           ished the appeal of DTH services, which   ing the dependence on DTH services.   DTH channels and OTT platforms, con-
           often lack the on-demand flexibility pro-  Original content has proven to be a   tributing to a decline in the demand for
           vided by streaming platforms.   game-changer, attracting subscribers and   standalone DTH services.
           Original Content and Exclusivity   retaining their loyalty. The diverse gen-  The transformation of home enter-
             One of the key drivers of OTT plat-  res and innovative storytelling found in   tainment in India from traditional DTH
           form popularity is the creation of origi-  original series have elevated the status   services to OTT platforms is a multi-
           nal and exclusive content. Platforms like   of OTT platforms as trendsetters in the   faceted phenomenon driven by techno-
           Netflix and Amazon Prime invest   entertainment industry. In contrast, DTH   logical advancements, changing con-
           heavily in producing high-quality origi-  services often struggle to compete in   sumer preferences, and the allure of
           nal series and movies that are not avail-  terms of offering unique and compelling   on-demand content. While DTH serv-
           able through traditional channels. This   content.              ices continue to cater to a segment of the
                                                                           population, the undeniable momentum
                                                                           of OTT platforms suggests a paradigm
                                                                           shift in the way individuals consume en-
                                                                           tertainment.
                                                                              The challenge for DTH services lies
                                                                           in adapting to the evolving landscape by
         Rise of mobile-centric entertainment                              ploring partnerships with OTT plat-
                                                                           incorporating on-demand features, en-
                                                                           hancing the diversity of content, and ex-

                                                                           forms.
                                                                              As technology continues to advance
                                                                           and consumer expectations evolve, the
                                                                           home entertainment industry in India
                                                                           will likely witness further innovations,
                                                                           ultimately shaping the future of how in-
                                                                           dividuals experience and enjoy content
                                                                           in the comfort of their homes.

           14                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[TECHNOLOGY








































           POWER TO THE PEOPLE






           2024 elections engage half





           of the World's population!





                he year 2024 is not only                                     and the evolving global responses
                poised to witness pivotal elec-                              aimed at securing the integrity of
           Ttions in major nations such as                                   democratic processes.
           the UK, the US, and India. Around                                 The Rise of Generative AI and
           70 countries with a total of more                                 Elections
           than 3.7 billion inhabitants, or al-                                 The advent of generative AI
           most half of the global population,                               tools, notably ChatGPT and Mid-
           plan to hold presidential or legis-                               journey, has ushered in a new era in
           lative elections in the year 2024. But                            technology, transforming the way in-
           is also marked by the historic con-                               formation is created, disseminated,
           vergence with mainstream generative                               and consumed. As these tools be-
           AI tools. In this extended explora-                               come integral to our digital land-
           tion, we will delve deeper into the                               scape, the 2024 elections in the UK,
           transformative effects of generative                              the US, and India are destined to un-
           AI on the electoral landscape, the                                fold against the backdrop of un-
           growing threats of misinformation,                                precedented technological influence.

           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[2024 elections engage half of the world's population
                                                                           myr Zelenskyy have fallen prey to these
                                                                           manipulative techniques. Even Labour
                                                                           leader Sir Keir Starmer's voice has been
                                                                           cloned, raising questions about the au-
                                                                           thenticity of digital content.
                                                                           Global Responses and Regulatory Ini-
                                                                           tiatives
                                                                              Recognizing the severity of the threat
                                                                           posed by AI-driven misinformation,
                                                                           governments worldwide are grappling
                                                                           with regulatory measures to safeguard
                                                                           the integrity of their democratic pro-
                                                                           cesses. While the US, under President
                                                                           Biden, has proposed watermarking AI-
                                                                           generated content, the European Union
                                                                           has reached a regulatory deal set to take
                                                                           effect in 2025. However, the UK gov-
             The Impact of AI-Driven Misinfor-  countries participating in the upcoming   ernment remains cautious about over-
           mation: The emergence of generative AI   elections, the potential for misinfor-  regulation, fearing it may stifle innova-
           tools has not only empowered individ-  mation to sway public opinion is higher   tion.
           uals and industries but has also unveiled   than ever.             In the face of these challenges, fact-
           a Pandora's box of challenges. One of   Deepfakes, characterized by hyper-real-  checkers are playing a crucial role in ad-
           the foremost concerns is the escalating   istic videos, pose a particularly potent   vocating for increased public awareness.
           influence of AI-driven misinformation,   threat. High-profile figures such as US   Governments, including India, are mobi-
           especially in the political sphere. With   President Joe Biden, former President   lizing resources through Defending De-
           more than two billion people from 50   Donald Trump, and Ukraine's Volody-  mocracy Taskforces and dedicated teams
                                                                           to rapidly respond to potential threats.
                                                                           The Online Safety Act in the UK and
                                                                           similar initiatives globally are designed
                                                                           to hold social media platforms account-
                                                                           able for swiftly removing illegal misin-
                                                                           formation, including AI-generated
                                                                           content.
                                                                              The Elections Act, with its stringent
                                                                           requirements for political advertising,
                                                                           aims to ensure transparency and ac-
                                                                           countability in the electoral process. Ho-
                                                                           wever, the efficacy of these measures re-
                                                                           mains contingent on a cohesive
                                                                           international approach, as highlighted by
                                                                           cybersecurity experts who caution
         Voting process                                                    lations in the face of global threats.
                                                                           against the limitations of national regu-





                                                                                                           Deepfake Dilemma











         Social Media Scrutiny                                                                             Digital social media platforms









           16                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Tech and Politics Merge









                                           The Meta Paradigm: Learning from                                The decision will determine the future
                                           Past Failures
                                             The role of tech giants like Meta
                                           (formerly Facebook) comes under scru-
                                           tiny, particularly in light of past failures
                                           to combat fake news during significant   The Indian Perspective: Chal-
                                           elections such as the 2016 US election
         U.S. President Joe Biden          ments and the public are increasingly   lenges and Opportunities
                                           and the Brexit referendum. Govern-

                                           pressuring these companies to take
                                                                              As India prepares for its 2024 general
                                                                           elections, the confluence of generative
                                           proactive measures in curbing the spread
                                                                           AI, bots, and social media presents both
                                           of AI-driven misinformation. The need
                                                                           challenges and opportunities. Political
                                           for robust guardrails and ethical consid-
                                           erations is paramount as we navigate the
                                                                           mative potential of technology, adapting
                                           intricate intersection of technology and   parties are grappling with the transfor-
                                           democracy.                      their campaign strategies to reach a wider
                                           Protecting Oneself from AI Fakes   audience and influence voter sentiment
                                             Individuals, too, play a crucial role in   positively.
                                           safeguarding themselves against the ris-  However, the dark side of technology
                                           ing tide of AI-generated content. Inter-  looms large, with the spread of fake news
                                           net security experts stress the impor-  and disinformation threatening the demo-
                                           tance of vigilance, urging individuals to
                                                                           cratic process. In response, the Indian
         Indian PM Narendra Modi           Diversifying news sources and being   sive ethical framework for generative AI.
                                                                           government must establish a comprehen-
                                           verify the content they encounter online.
                                                                           This framework should not only address
                                           conscious of confirmation bias are es-
                                           sential in navigating the complex land-
                                                                           the challenges but also ensure accounta-
                                                                           bility, transparency, and the responsible
                                           scape of information, especially when
                                                                           use of technology to uphold the demo-
                                           confronted with the challenges of detect-
                                                                           cratic ideals that underpin the electoral
                                           ing deepfakes.
                                                                           process.
                                                                              As we stand on the precipice of a land-
                                                                           mark year of elections in 2024, the intri-
                                                                           cate dance between politics and gener-
                                                                           ative AI demands a nuanced and
                                                                           collaborative approach. The transfor-
                                                                           mative power of technology should be
                                                                           harnessed for the greater good, while si-
                                                                           multaneously guarding against its poten-
                                                                           tial for manipulation and misinformation.
         Cybersecurity Vigilance                                           viduals must work in unison on a global
                                                                           Governments, tech companies, and indi-
                                                                           scale to navigate these uncharted waters
                                                                           successfully. The decisions made today
                                                                           will reverberate through the annals of his-
                                                                           tory, shaping the future of democracy in


                                                                                                       17
           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                          an era dominated by artificial intelligence.]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY







                                                                                                           A somber moment when the mortal remains reached India
























           Behind closed doors




           The untold story of








           Shastri's last hours








           in Tashkent







                 n the 58th death anniversary of                           stan, remains shrouded in mystery, giv-
                 Lal Bahadur Shastri, it is both a                         ing rise to numerous speculations and
           Osomber occasion to remember                                    conspiracy theories.
           the stalwart who led India through cru-                         Lal Bahadur Shastri's Legacy:
           cial times and an opportunity to delve                             Lal Bahadur Shastri, born on October
           into the lingering mystery surrounding                          2, 1904, in Mughalsarai, Uttar Pradesh,
           his untimely death. Lal Bahadur Shastri                         played a crucial role in shaping India's
           served as the second Prime Minister of                          destiny during a critical period. He rose
           India from 1964 to 1966, left an indeli-                        through the political ranks, earning the
           ble mark on the nation with his leader-                         title of "Man of Peace" for his calm de-
           ship during a challenging period. Yet,                          meanor and strong leadership qualities.
           his death in 1966, in Tashkent, Uzbeki-                         Shastri became the Prime Minister of
                                                  Lal Bahadur Shastri
           18                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[India after the sudden demise of Jawa-
                                                                           harlal Nehru in 1964.
                                                                              Under Shastri's leadership, India
                                                                           faced significant challenges, including
                                                                           the Indo-Pak War of 1965. Shastri's fa-
         Lal Bahadur Shastri being sworn in as Prime Minister
                                                                           mous slogan "Jai Jawan Jai Kisan" (Hail
                                                                           the Soldier, Hail the Farmer) captured
                                                                           the essence of the nation's spirit during
                                                                           those turbulent times. His commitment
                                                                           to social justice, economic development,
                                                                           and national unity endeared him to the
                                                                           masses.
                                                                           The Tashkent Accord:
                                                                              As the leader of a newly independent
                                                                           and diverse nation, Lal Bahadur Shastri
                                                                           faced the daunting task of ensuring
                                                                           peace and stability in the region. The
                                                                           Indo-Pak War of 1965 had escalated ten-
                                                                           sions, and international intervention was
                                                                           needed to broker a ceasefire. This led to
                                                                           the Tashkent Agreement, a peace accord
                                                                           signed between India and Pakistan on
                                                                           January 10, 1966, with Soviet Premier
                                                                           Alexei Kosygin mediating the discus-
                                                                           sions.
                                                                              Shastri and Pakistani President Ayub
         Prime Minister Shastri interacting with security officials
                                                                           Khan agreed to withdraw their forces to
                                                                           the pre-war positions, and the Tashkent
                                                                           Accord was hailed as a diplomatic tri-
                                                                           umph. However, the celebrations were
                                                                           short-lived as the news of Shastri's sud-
                                                                           den demise the next day shocked the na-
                                                                           tion and sparked numerous conspiracy
                                                                           theories.
                                                                           The Mysterious Circumstances of
                                                                           Shastri's Death:
                                                                              Lal Bahadur Shastri's death in Tash-
                                                                           kent remains shrouded in mystery, with
                                                                           conflicting accounts and unanswered
                                                                           questions surrounding the circum-
                                                                           stances. According to official reports,
                                                                           Shastri died of a heart attack in his
                                                                           sleep. However, the lack of a post-mor-
                                                                           tem examination and the hasty embal-



























           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      19  Prime Minister Shastri delivering a speech in Parliament]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Lal Bahadur Shastri alongside his wife, Mrs. Lalita Shastri








                                                                                                           Plowing the land with oxen













           ming of his body fueled suspicions and
           fueled conspiracy theories.
             One of the primary concerns raised
           by skeptics was the absence of a detailed
           investigation into the cause of Shastri's
           death. Given the high-stakes political
           scenario and the strategic importance of
           the Tashkent talks, many believed that a
           thorough examination of the circum-
           stances surrounding the leader's demise
           was imperative. The Indian govern-                                                              Interacting with a farmer
           ment's decision not to conduct an au-
           topsy only deepened the mystery.
           Conspiracy Theories:
             Over the years, several conspiracy
           theories have emerged, suggesting foul
           play in Shastri's death. Some speculate
           that he was poisoned, either by external
           forces or elements within the Indian es-
           tablishment who opposed the terms of
           the Tashkent Accord. Others believe that
           Shastri's death was a result of natural
           causes but was concealed to prevent any
           potential unrest or political fallout.
             The lack of transparency and the
           swift repatriation of Shastri's body to
           India further fueled suspicions. Critics                                                        A photograph from the Tashkent Files
           argue that a thorough investigation
           would have helped dispel doubts and put
           an end to the various conspiracy theories
           that continue to circulate even today.
           Calls for a Reinvestigation:
             In the decades following Lal Bahadur
           Shastri's death, there have been persist-  evidence and the passage of time have   the welfare of the nation. Shastri's con-
           ent calls for a reinvestigation into the   made it challenging to unravel the mys-  tributions to India's progress and his role
           circumstances surrounding his demise.   tery, leaving many questions unan-  in fostering diplomatic relations with
           Various individuals, including some of   swered and allowing speculation to per-  other nations continue to be celebrated.
           Shastri's family members and political   sist.                     The Tashkent Accord, despite the
           figures, have sought to reopen the case   Legacy and Impact:    controversies surrounding Shastri's
           and bring closure to the lingering   Regardless of the uncertainties sur-  death, is acknowledged as a significant
           doubts.                         rounding his death, Lal Bahadur Shas-  diplomatic achievement that averted
             However, despite the demands for   tri's legacy remains intact. He is remem-  prolonged conflict between India and
           transparency, no official reinvestigation   bered as a leader who embodied   Pakistan. The accord paved the way for
           has taken place. The lack of conclusive   simplicity, integrity, and dedication to   a return to normalcy and laid the foun-

           20                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[The events in Tashkent marked a critical
                                                                           juncture in India's history, shaping the
                                                                           nation's trajectory and influencing its re-
                                                                           lationships with neighboring countries.
                                                                              A thorough and transparent investiga-
                                                                           tion into Shastri's death would not only
                                                                           address the concerns of the public but
                                                                           also contribute to a more accurate his-
         A newspaper clipping                                              crucial for a nation's understanding of its
                                                                           torical record. Historical accuracy is
                                                                           past, allowing future generations to
                                                                           learn from the successes and challenges
                                                                           faced by their predecessors.
                                                                           The Role of the Indian Government:
                                                                              The responsibility of addressing the
                                                                           mysteries surrounding Lal Bahadur
                                                                           Shastri's death falls on the shoulders of
                                                                           the Indian government. As custodians of
                                                                           the nation's history and keepers of pub-
                                                                           lic trust, the government has the au-
                                                                           thority and duty to initiate a comprehen-
                                                                           sive investigation into the circumstances
                                                                           leading to Shastri's death.
         A file photo from Tashkent Files                                  sential in this regard. While it is ac-
                                                                              The government's commitment to
                                                                           transparency and accountability is es-

                                                                           knowledged that the passage of time
                                                                           may pose challenges in collecting fresh
                                                                           evidence, advancements in forensic
                                                                           science and investigative techniques
                                                                           could provide valuable insights into the
                                                                           events that unfolded in Tashkent in
                                                                           1966.
           dation for future dialogue between the   renewed attention, with the rise of digi-  International Perspectives:
           two neighboring nations.        tal media and increased public aware-  The Tashkent Accord, which aimed
           Continued Speculations and Public   ness. Social media platforms have be-  at fostering peace in the region, had in-
           Concern:                        come forums for discussions, debates,   ternational implications. Therefore, it is
             Despite the passage of more than five   and calls for transparency regarding the   not only a matter of national importance
           decades, the mystery surrounding Lal   events in Tashkent. The younger genera-  but also one with international signifi-
           Bahadur Shastri's death has not faded   tion, with access to vast information and   cance. The circumstances surrounding
           from public consciousness. The lack of   the ability to voice opinions through so-  Shastri's death could have ramifications
           closure and unanswered questions have   cial media, has played a significant role   for India's relations with other nations,
           led to continued speculations and con-  in keeping the issue alive and urging au-  particularly those involved in the Tash-
           cerns among the Indian public. Various   thorities to reexamine the case.   kent talks.
           individuals and groups have questioned   The Importance of Historical Truth:   Engaging with the international com-
           the official narrative, demanding a thor-  The lingering doubts surrounding Lal   munity and seeking cooperation in in-
           ough investigation into the circum-  Bahadur Shastri's death go beyond per-  vestigating the matter could contribute
           stances that led to Shastri's untimely de-  sonal curiosity or conspiracy theories.   to a more comprehensive understanding
           mise.                           At its core, the issue represents the quest   of the events. Collaborating with the
             In recent years, the issue has gained   for historical truth and accountability.   governments of Uzbekistan and Russia.










                                                                                                           Funeral ceremony







           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[FOOTPRINTS OF HUMILITY
                                                                                                                 SPECIAL STORY










































                                                                                                           Anil Shastri






           Anil Shastri unravels






           his father's legacy








             n the intricate tapestry of Indian   and intimate glimpse into the private   Shastri's unique approach to parenting.
             history, few figures stand as tall as   moments that shaped a nation's destiny.   Anil, a young boy in the eighth grade,
           ILal Bahadur Shastri, a man of hum-                             was once summoned by his father after
           ble origins who rose to become the   Lessons in Humility:       dinner. Lal Bahadur Shastri, noticing a
           Prime Minister of India. For Anil Shas-  The interview commences with Anil   lapse in the traditional gesture of re-
           tri, the son of this iconic leader, the leg-  Shastri painting a vivid picture of a cul-  spect, responded not with scolding but
           acy of his father is not merely a histori-  tural tradition within the Shastri house-  with an unexpected humility. He
           cal narrative but a deeply personal and   hold—a practice of touching the feet of   touched his son's feet with respect,
           poignant journey. In an exclusive inter-  elders as a mark of respect, especially   demonstrating the proper way to greet
           view, Anil Shastri shares profound in-  during special occasions and festivals.   elders. Anil, initially defiant, was
           sights into the life, values, and myste-  However, a seemingly routine incident   moved by his father's non-egotistic ap-
           rious death of his father, offering a rare   stands out, illustrating Lal Bahadur   proach. It was a lesson in humility that

           22                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[left an indelible mark, one that words
           alone might have failed to convey.

           Driving Lessons and Ethical
           Choices:
             The interview takes an intriguing
           turn into the realm of teenage adven-
           tures when Anil, at the age of 15, ac-
           quired a driving license against legal
           requirements. Lal Bahadur Shastri's
           commitment to ethical conduct be-
           comes apparent in this narrative. Rather
           than expressing anger at Anil's prema-
           ture driving escapades, Shastriji, as
           Anil affectionately refers to his father,
           felt hurt and upset. The Prime Min-  layer of poignancy to the interview,   dive into the life of Lal Bahadur Shas-
           ister's moral compass guided him to   leaving room for the unresolved mys-  tri, a figure whose principles continue
           rectify the situation promptly, empha-  teries that surround his father's death.   to inspire generations. This section
           sizing the importance of abiding by the                         serves as a poignant call to future
           law, even within the confines of the   Aftermath and Challenges:   leaders to embrace the values that de-
           Prime Minister's residence. Anil's rev-  Anil Shastri reflects on the challeng-  fined Shastriji's leadership.
           elation not only sheds light on the ad-  ing period that followed his father's
           venturous spirit of a teenager but also   death. At the young age of 16, he,   Legacy Beyond Words:
           underscores the ethical foundations laid   along with his brothers, faced the harsh   In a reflective moment, Anil Shastri
           by his father.                  reality of their loss. There was no post-  emphasizes that Lal Bahadur Shastri
                                           mortem conducted, leaving the cause of   did not leave behind material wealth
           Man Management and Leadership   Shastriji's death shrouded in mystery.   but cherished goodwill from the people
           Insights:                       However, the family found solace in the   of India. The legacy is not measured in
             Anil Shastri fondly remembers his   shelter provided by the government,   monetary terms but in the enduring re-
           father as a remarkable man manager.   and with the unwavering support of   spect and affection that the late Prime
           Despite lacking formal education, Lal   their mother, they managed to stand on   Minister continues to command. This
           Bahadur Shastri embodied modern   their own feet. This section of the inter-  section invites readers to contemplate
           management concepts, earning love and   view underscores the resilience of the   the intangible but profound impact of
           respect from those around him. Anil   Shastri family in the face of adversity.   Shastriji's legacy on the collective con-
           emphasizes Shastriji's focus on self-reli-                      sciousness of the nation.
           ance in defense and agriculture, a con-  Declassification Efforts and
           viction that found expression in the his-  Legacy:              Encouragement to Explore
           toric slogan, "Jai Jawan Jai Kisan." The   The quest for truth continued as Anil   Shastriji's Life:
           interview provides a deeper understand-  Shastri shared insights into the attempts   Anil Shastri concludes the interview
           ing of Shastriji's leadership style, char-  to declassify documents related to Lal   by encouraging individuals to read ex-
           acterized by a profound understanding   Bahadur Shastri's death. An RTI inquiry   tensively about Lal Bahadur Shastri's
           of people and a commitment to India's   to the Prime Minister's Office yielded a   life. In this digital age, where infor-
           self-sufficiency.               response citing potential damage to dip-  mation is readily accessible, he invites
                                           lomatic relations with a friendly nation.   readers to explore the depths of Shas-
           Tashkent and Unanswered         The veil of secrecy shrouding Tashkent   triji's experiences, leadership, and the
           Questions:                      remained intact, leaving the Shastri   nuances of his personality. This final
             As the interview delves into the fate-  family and the nation with unanswered   touch serves as an invitation to a deeper
           ful events surrounding Lal Bahadur   questions. Despite the challenges, Anil   understanding of a leader whose life
           Shastri's death, Anil Shastri admits to   Shastri wishes for his father to be re-  was a beacon of inspiration.
           being in the dark. The circumstances of   membered as 'The Man of the Masses,'   In this intimate and expansive inter-
           the Tashkent deliberations remain con-  a leader who left behind goodwill   view, Anil Shastri opens a window into
           fidential, and the family had no access   rather than material wealth. This seg-  the life of a father, a leader, and a man
           to any documents. The last communica-  ment of the interview delves into the   who left an indelible mark on the tapes-
           tion Shastriji had with his family on the   complexities of dealing with official   try of India's history. Lal Bahadur Shas-
           night of January 10, 1966, seemed re-  documentation and the ongoing quest   tri's legacy, though clouded by the mys-
           assuring. However, the subsequent de-  for transparency.        teries of Tashkent, stands as a testament
           velopments in Tashkent—20 kilometers                            to the enduring impact of humility,
           away from his stay—revealed a stark   Advice for Future Leaders:   ethics, and unwavering commitment to
           lack of medical facilities, raising ques-  As the interview draws to a close,   the welfare of the people. Anil's narra-
           tions about the mysterious circum-  Anil Shastri imparts valuable advice for   tive enriches the understanding of a
           stances surrounding his demise. Anil's   aspiring leaders—honesty, simplicity,   leader whose influence transcends time
           candid acknowledgment of not knowing   hard work, dedication, and commitment   and continues to resonate in the hearts
           what transpired in Tashkent adds a   to the nation. He encourages a deep   of a grateful nation.

           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[PERSONAL DEVELOPMENT                                                      2024











































           Resolutions with a purpose


           Designing a life you love








                 s the calendar turns its pages,                           goals that align with one's values and as-
                 ushering in a new year, it brings                         pirations, fostering a sense of purpose
           Awith it a renewed sense of hope                                and direction in life.
           and a chance for self-reflection. The tra-                         Reflection and Self-Awareness: The
           dition of making New Year resolutions                           process of setting resolutions encour-
           has been a longstanding practice across                         ages individuals to reflect on their past
           cultures, symbolizing a commitment to                           experiences, successes, and challenges.
           personal growth, positive change, and                           This self-awareness is crucial for identi-
           the pursuit of happiness. In this article,                      fying patterns, understanding one's
           we will delve into the significance of                          strengths and weaknesses, and determin-
           New Year resolutions, explore common                            ing areas that warrant improvement.
           pitfalls, and provide practical tips for                           Positive Psychology: The act of set-
           setting and achieving realistic goals in   provement. The beginning of a new year   ting resolutions is inherently positive, as
           the coming year.                serves as a natural marker, prompting in-  it signifies a belief in the possibility of
           The Tradition of New Year Res-  dividuals to reflect on their lives, ac-  change and the pursuit of a better future.
           olutions:                       knowledge areas that need attention, and   Positive psychology emphasizes the im-
           The tradition of making resolutions as   commit to making positive changes.   portance of cultivating a positive mind-
           the new year dawns dates back cen-  Significance of New Year Resolutions:   set, and New Year resolutions provide a
           turies, with its roots embedded in var-  Personal Growth and Development:   tangible way to channel optimism into
           ious cultures and religious practices.   New Year resolutions are a manifesta-  actionable steps.
           While the specific customs and rituals   tion of the innate human drive for per-  Common Pitfalls in Resolution Set-
           may differ, the underlying theme re-  sonal growth and self-improvement. It is   ting:
           mains consistent – the desire for self-im-  an opportunity to set intentions and   While the intention behind setting

           24                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[requires time, effort, and persistence.
                                                                              Practical Tips for Successful Res-
                                                                           olutions:
                                                                              Set Realistic and Attainable Goals:
                                                                           Instead of aiming for drastic transfor-
                                                                           mations, set small, achievable goals that
                                                                           contribute to larger objectives. This ap-
         Supportive community gathering                                    increasing the likelihood of success.
                                                                           proach allows for incremental progress,
                                                                              Be Specific and Measurable: Clearly
                                                                           define your resolutions with specific,
                                                                           measurable criteria. For instance, re-
                                                                           place a vague goal like "exercise more"
                                                                           with a specific target, such as "exercise
                                                                           for 30 minutes three times a week." This

                                                                           progress.
           New Year resolutions is positive, many   out clear objectives and action plans, it   provides clarity and a basis for tracking
                                                                              Create a Plan of Action: Develop a
           individuals find it challenging to follow   becomes challenging to measure pro-  detailed plan outlining the steps required
           through with their commitments. Some   gress and stay motivated.   to achieve your resolutions. Break down
           common pitfalls include:          Failure to Plan: A lack of strategic   larger goals into smaller tasks, making
             Unrealistic Expectations: Setting   planning is a significant obstacle to res-  them more manageable and less over-
           overly ambitious goals without consid-  olution success. Without a well-defined   whelming. A well-thought-out plan en-
           ering the practicality of achieving them   roadmap and actionable steps, individ-  hances accountability and direction.
           can lead to frustration and disappoint-  uals may feel overwhelmed and unsure   Focus on the Process, Not Just the
           ment. Unrealistic expectations may un-  of where to begin, increasing the likeli-  Outcome: While the end goal is essen-
           dermine motivation and make it difficult   hood of abandoning their resolutions.   tial, placing emphasis on the journey
           to sustain efforts over time.     Impatience and Instant Gratification:   and the daily habits that contribute to
             Lack of Specificity: Vague or general   In our fast-paced society, the desire for   success is equally crucial. Celebrate
           resolutions, such as "get in shape" or   immediate results can lead to impatience   small victories along the way, reinforc-
           "save money," lack the specificity   and a tendency to abandon resolutions   ing positive behaviors and maintaining
           needed for effective goal-setting. With-  prematurely. Sustainable change often   motivation.
                                                                              Build a Support System: Share your
                                                                           resolutions with friends, family, or a
                                                                           support group. Having a network of in-
                                                                           dividuals who can offer encouragement,
         Resolutions for a happier life                                    cantly impact your ability to stay com-
                                                                           guidance, and accountability can signifi-
                                                                           mitted to your goals.
                                                                              Embrace Flexibility and Learn from
                                                                           Setbacks: Recognize that setbacks are a
                                                                           natural part of any transformative jour-
                                                                           ney. Instead of viewing them as failures,
                                                                           see them as opportunities to learn and
                                                                           adjust your approach. Flexibility and
                                                                           adaptability are key to long-term suc-
                                                                           cess.
                                                                              As we stand on the threshold of a
                                                                           new year, the tradition of making res-
                                                                           olutions remains a powerful vehicle for
                                                                           personal growth and positive change. By
         A triumphant smile after reaching a goal                          individuals can embark on a journey of
                                                                           understanding the significance of res-
                                                                           olutions, recognizing common pitfalls,
                                                                           and adopting practical tips for success,

                                                                           self-improvement with confidence and
                                                                           purpose. The key lies not only in setting
                                                                           inspiring goals but also in cultivating the
                                                                           resilience and determination needed to
                                                                           see them through. May the coming year
                                                                           be a canvas upon which you paint the

                                                                           dreams. Happy New Year!

           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                          masterpiece of your aspirations and   25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[FILM REVIEW














                                                                                                           Shah Rukh Khan in the trailer for 'Dunki'

















           Dunki




           Shah Rukh Khan's magnetic



           odyssey through immigrant hilarity





                 unki arrives as a cinematic                               headed for London. Yet, amidst the up-
                 spectacle, setting the stage for                          roarious situations, it doesn't forget the
           DBollywood's titan Shah Rukh                                    bittersweet ties they leave behind, tug-
           Khan to collaborate with the storytell-                         ging at heartstrings and inviting the
           ing virtuoso Rajkumar Hirani. This                              audience to reflect on their own con-
           union promised not just a film but an                           nections and aspirations.
           experience—a melange of emotions,                                  Shah Rukh Khan, a luminary in his
           humor, and social commentary that                               own right, dons the persona of Dunki
           could leave an enduring mark on the                             with his trademark charm and mag-
           audience. As the curtains drew open                             netic screen presence. His portrayal
           and the narrative unfolded, it became                           adds layers of depth to a character
           evident that "Dunki" is not merely a                            brimming with optimism and resil-
           movie; it's a canvas painting the aspi-                         ience, crafting a protagonist that not
           rations, struggles, and resilience of in-                       only entertains but also connects on a
           dividuals navigating the labyrinth of                           profound emotional level. Taapsee
           immigration and dreams.                                         Pannu, in a role that complements
             At the core of "Dunki" lies a story                           Khan's Dunki, paints a vivid and emo-
           that resonates with many—a tale of or-                          tionally resonant canvas, enriching the
           dinary individuals from Punjab grap-                            storyline with her stellar performance.
           pling with the desire for a better life                            The supporting ensemble, including
           abroad. The film tactfully encapsulates                         the seasoned Boman Irani, the rising
           their journey, a rollercoaster of laugh-                        star Vicky Kaushal, contributes signifi-
           ter and peril as they find themselves in                        cantly to the film's vibrancy. Their per-
           the maze of illegal immigration,                                formances breathe life into the narra-
                                                    Rajkumar Hirani
           26                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[A still from ‘Dunki’







           tive, making it an ensemble act that   ations portrayed in the film provide   soulful Punjabi tracks and lively tunes,
           enriches every frame and dialogue, en-  ample material for witty exchanges and   seamlessly intertwines with the narra-
           hancing the movie's overall impact.   slapstick humor, creating an immersive   tive, amplifying the emotions depicted
             Hirani's mastery in infusing humor   experience for the viewers.   on screen.
           that strikes a chord with the audience   Visually, "Dunki" is a feast for the   However, as the narrative pro-
           remains a highlight of "Dunki." The   eyes. The cinematography beautifully   gresses, "Dunki" encounters stumbling
           first half of the movie is a delightful   captures the vibrant landscapes of Pun-  blocks that slightly tarnish its bril-
           rollercoaster ride filled with moments   jab and the bustling streets of London,   liance. The film, despite its entertain-
           that provoke genuine laughter. The cul-  immersing the audience in these con-  ing nature, leaves some aspects feeling
           tural idiosyncrasies and immigrant situ-  trasting worlds. The music, with its   wanting. The emotional resolution,
                                                                           while touching, feels rushed, leaving
                                                                           behind an unfinished sentimentality.
                                                                           Hirani's attempt at social commentary,
                                                                           while commendable, lacks the nuanced
         An advertisement poster of movie ‘Dunki’                          loses its momentum, occasionally
                                                                           exploration that audiences have come
                                                                           to expect from his acclaimed works.
                                                                           Moreover, the pacing in the latter half
                                                                           meandering and diluting the impact of
                                                                           the movie's more poignant moments.
                                                                              Yet, "Dunki" manages to shine
                                                                           through its flaws, emerging as a de-
                                                                           lightful entertainer that blends the
                                                                           charisma of Shah Rukh Khan, the sto-
                                                                           rytelling finesse of Rajkumar Hirani,
                                                                           and a heartfelt immigrant story. It's a
                                                                           reminder that dreams, no matter how
                                                                           distant, possess the power to propel in-
                                                                           dividuals forward.
                                                                              In conclusion, "Dunki" beckons au-
                                                                           diences to embark on a journey—a
                                                                           journey not just on screen but within
                                                                           oneself. It's a tale of aspirations, resil-
                                                                           ience, and the unyielding spirit of indi-
                                                                           viduals striving for a better tomorrow.
                                                                           Watching this film isn't just about en-
                                                                           tertainment; it's about introspection,
                                                                           empathy, and embracing the roller-
                                                                           coaster of emotions that accompany
                                                                           every human pursuit. Despite its minor
         Movie Poster                                                      testament to the power of storytelling
                                                                           imperfections, "Dunki" stands tall as a
                                                                           and the unwavering spirit that fuels
                                                                           our dreams.

           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[TRAVEL
































                                                                                                 Annapurna Base Camp



           Exploring the Enchanting Charms of Nepal


           A Journey into the Heart






           of the Himalayas







                 estled between the towering   Geography and Climate:      mountains offer a cooler, alpine environ-
                 peaks of the Himalayas, Nepal   One of the most striking features of   ment. Visitors can choose the best time
           Nis a land of mystique and      Nepal is its diverse topography. From   to visit based on their interests, whether
           wonder, a haven for travelers seeking a   the lowland Terai region in the south to   it's trekking in the mountains or explor-
           unique blend of natural beauty, cultural   the towering peaks of the Himalayas in   ing the cultural gems in the valleys.
           richness, and spiritual enlightenment.   the north, the country spans a range of   Cultural Heritage:
           This small, landlocked country is bor-  altitudes and ecosystems. Eight of the   Nepal is a living museum of ancient
           dered by India to the south, China to the   world's fourteen highest peaks, includ-  traditions and cultural heritage. The
           north, and is renowned for its diverse   ing Mount Everest, reside in Nepal,   Kathmandu Valley, in particular, is a
           landscapes, ancient temples, and warm   drawing trekkers and mountaineers from   treasure trove of UNESCO World Her-
           hospitality. As we embark on a virtual   around the globe.      itage Sites, showcasing exquisite archi-
           journey through this enchanting nation,   The climate varies significantly ac-  tecture, intricate woodwork, and cen-
           we'll uncover the treasures that make   ross the country due to its diverse topog-  turies-old temples. Durbar Square in
           Nepal a must-visit destination for any   raphy. The Terai experiences a tropical   Kathmandu, Bhaktapur, and Patan are
           avid traveler.                  climate, while the higher altitudes of the   rich in history, offering a glimpse into

           28                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[the country's royal past.
                                                                              The sacred pilgrimage site of Lum-
                                                                           bini, located in the Rupandehi District,
                                                                           is another UNESCO-listed site and the
                                                                           birthplace of Siddhartha Gautama, who
                                                                           later became known as Buddha. Pil-
                                                                           grims and tourists alike visit Lumbini to
                                                                           explore the Maya Devi Temple and
                                                                           other monastic ruins, immersing them-
         Experiencing paragliding in Pokhara                               Adventure in the Himalayas:
                                                                           selves in the serene ambiance of this
                                                                           spiritual haven.

                                                                              For adventure enthusiasts, Nepal is
                                                                           synonymous with trekking and moun-
                                                                           taineering. The Annapurna and Everest
                                                                           regions are home to some of the world's
                                                                           most iconic trekking trails, offering a
                                                                           breathtaking panorama of snow-capped
                                                                           peaks, lush valleys, and picturesque vil-
                                                                           lages. The Annapurna Circuit and Ever-
                                                                           est Base Camp treks are bucket-list ex-
                                                                           periences, providing an opportunity to
                                                                           witness the unique culture of the Sherpa
                                                                           people and the warm hospitality of
                                                                           mountain communities.
                                                                              For those seeking the ultimate chal-
                                                                           lenge, summiting one of Nepal's majes-
                                                                           tic peaks is a life-changing endeavor.
                                                                           The climb to the top of Mount Everest,
                                                                           the world's highest peak, is an epic jour-
                                                                           ney that tests the limits of physical and
                                                                           mental endurance. Other notable peaks
                                                                           for mountaineering enthusiasts include
                                                                           Lhotse, Makalu, and Manaslu, each pre-
         Himalayas Tibetan Flags                                           wards.
                                                                           senting its own set of challenges and re-
                                                                           Wildlife and Nature Reserves:
                                                                              In addition to its towering mountains
                                                                           and cultural gems, Nepal is also home to
                                                                           a diverse array of flora and fauna. The
                                                                           Chitwan National Park, a UNESCO
                                                                           World Heritage Site, is a prime destina-
                                                                           tion for wildlife enthusiasts. This park,
                                                                           situated in the Terai region, is a habitat
                                                                           for the endangered one-horned rhinoc-
                                                                           eros, Bengal tigers, elephants, and a
                                                                           myriad of bird species. Visitors can em-
                                                                           bark on jungle safaris, canoe rides, and
                                                                           nature walks to witness the incredible
                                                                           biodiversity that thrives in this protected
                                                                           area.
                                                                              Another gem for nature lovers is the
                                                                           Sagarmatha National Park, home to the
                                                                           iconic Mount Everest. The park boasts a
                                                                           unique alpine ecosystem with rare
                                                                           species like the elusive snow leopard
                                                                           and the red panda. The vibrant rhodo-
         Himalayan Mountain                                                add to the allure of this natural wonder.
                                                                           dendron forests and pristine glacial lakes
                                                                           Culinary Delights:
                                                                              Nepali cuisine is a delightful blend of
                                                                           flavors, influenced by Indian, Tibetan,


           JANUARY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                          and Tibetan-Burmese culinary tradi-  29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[outdoor activities.
                                                                           Responsible Tourism and Community
                                                                           Engagement:
                                                                              Nepal's charm lies not only in its nat-
                                                                           ural beauty but also in the warmth of its
                                                                           people. Engaging with local com-
                                                                           munities and practicing responsible tour-
                                                                           ism can greatly enhance the travel ex-
                                                                           perience. Many tour operators and
         Maya Devi Temple, Lumbinu                                         able tourism practices, supporting local
                                                                           organizations in Nepal focus on sustain-
                                                                           economies and preserving the environ-
                                                                           ment.
                                                                              Visitors have the opportunity to par-
                                                                           ticipate in community-based homestays,
                                                                           allowing them to experience the daily
                                                                           lives of Nepali families and contributing
                                                                           directly to the local economy. Ad-
           tions. Dal Bhat, a traditional meal of   insight into the cultural and religious   ditionally, volunteering opportunities are
           lentil soup, rice, and a variety of side   fabric of Nepal, allowing visitors to par-  available for those interested in making
           dishes, is a staple in every household.   take in the joyous atmosphere that per-  a positive impact, whether through edu-
           Momos, steamed or fried dumplings   vades the streets.          cation, healthcare, or environmental
           filled with meat or vegetables, are a   Hidden Gems and Off-the-Beaten-  conservation projects.
           popular street food enjoyed by locals   Path Adventures:           Nepal is a captivating destination that
           and visitors alike.               While the popular trekking routes   offers a multifaceted experience to trav-
             Tea lovers will appreciate the rich   and cultural landmarks are well-known,   elers. Whether you're an adventure
           taste of Nepali tea, especially the re-  Nepal also hides numerous hidden gems   seeker, a culture enthusiast, or someone
           nowned Himalayan tea varieties. Enjoy-  for those willing to venture off the   simply seeking tranquility amidst
           ing a cup of tea while overlooking the   beaten path. The Langtang Valley, often   breathtaking landscapes, Nepal has
           breathtaking mountain scenery is a quin-  referred to as the "Valley of Glaciers,"   something to offer.
           tessential experience in Nepal.   offers a less crowded trekking experi-  The warmth of its people, the rich-
           Cultural Festivals:             ence with breathtaking landscapes and   ness of its culture, and the awe-inspiring
             Nepal is a land of festivals, and vis-  encounters with the Tamang and Sherpa   beauty of its natural wonders make
           itors have the opportunity to witness vi-  communities.         Nepal a destination that lingers in the
           brant celebrations throughout the year.   The medieval town of Bandipur,   hearts and minds of those fortunate
           Dashain, the biggest Hindu festival, is a   perched on a hilltop, provides a nostal-  enough to explore its charms.
           time for family reunions and the receiv-  gic journey back in time. With its pre-  Embark on a journey to Nepal, where
           ing of tika (a mixture of yogurt, rice,   served cultural heritage and panoramic   the Himalayas meet spirituality, and
           and vermillion) and jamara (barley   views of the Himalayas, Bandipur is a   every corner reveals a new facet of this
           sprouts). Tihar, the festival of lights, is   peaceful retreat away from the hustle   extraordinary land. From the soaring
           another colorful celebration that honors   and bustle of more touristy destinations.   peaks of the world's highest mountains
           various animals, including crows, dogs,   For a tranquil lakeside experience,   to the vibrant festivals that color the
           and cows.                       Pokhara and its serene Phewa Lake offer   streets, Nepal invites you to discover a
             During the Indra Jatra festival in   a perfect setting for relaxation. Sur-  tapestry of experiences that will leave an
           Kathmandu, a massive chariot proces-  rounded by the Annapurna Range and   indelible mark on your travel memories.
           sion takes place, featuring the living   the Machapuchare Peak, Pokhara is a   So, pack your bags, embrace the spirit of
           goddess Kumari and traditional Newar   gateway to the Annapurna region and a   adventure, and let Nepal weave its
           dances. These festivals provide a unique   hub for paragliding, boating, and other   magic on your soul.










         Festivals and daily life                                                                          Boudhanath Stupa in the Kathmandu Valley









           30                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | JANUARY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>