<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 02 I  JANUARY 16 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: ARINA KRASNIKOVA





              11



                                                             5













                                                            8                                        26
















           4-Editorial: How mentorship moved               24-The future of writing by hand
           online                                          26-The beat that changed Bollywood

           5-The Vanishing Snow                            29-Horoscopes

           8-The digitalization of worship                 30-Letters

           11-Mentors on social media                      31-Frame of thought
           15-How cultures celebrate life before

           death

           18-How senses trigger memory

           21-Compliments as emotional first aid









           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Screens as Teachers
     EDITORIAL  How mentorship                                                      Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           moved online                                                         Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                ho do you turn to when you’re     Art & Culture Editor
                                                stuck at 2 a.m, scrolling through   Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Wdoubts instead of messages? For
                                        a growing number of young people, the an-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        swer isn’t a teacher, a boss, or even a par-  Vishakha Sharma
                                        ent. It’s a stranger on a screen. A creator. A
                                        podcaster. Someone they’ve never met, yet   Social Media Editor
                                        somehow trust.
                                           For Gen Z, mentorship has quietly         Sushil Kumar
                                        slipped out of offices and classrooms and
                                        into comment sections, livestreams and   Art & Graphics Director
                                        short videos. It doesn’t arrive with a formal   Vipin Agarwal
                                        introduction. It appears while waiting for
                                        sleep, between classes, or during a long
           commute. Advice about careers, mental health, money, creativity, or simply how to   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           survive early adulthood now comes packaged in reels, threads and casual mono-
           logues recorded in bedrooms.                                      D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
             This shift didn’t happen overnight. Traditional mentorship has always depended   Editor, United News of India, New
           on access. The right school, the right workplace, the right network. Social media
           flattens that hierarchy. A 19-year-old in a small town can listen to a designer explain   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           rejection, a doctor talk about burnout, or a first-generation entrepreneur describe fai-  Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           lure without filters. It feels personal, even when it’s public.   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             There’s something comforting about that. These digital mentors often speak in un-  Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           finished sentences, admit they don’t have all the answers and share mistakes in real   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           time. That honesty resonates. It feels closer to a conversation than a lecture. And for a   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           generation raised amid uncertainty, economic pressure and constant comparison, re-  Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           assurance matters as much as instruction.
             But this new mentorship comes with its own contradictions. Algorithms reward   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           confidence, not always credibility. Advice goes viral faster than nuance. A 30-second
           clip can’t replace lived guidance or context. And sometimes, what looks like mentor-  Phone +91 20 40199102
           ship is really performance, monetized vulnerability dressed up as wisdom.
             Gen Z seems aware of this tension. Many don’t follow just one voice, but dozens.   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           They compare, cross-check, scroll skeptically. They know influencers can be wrong.   Baner Road,
           Yet they keep listening. Not because these creators are perfect, but because they’re   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           present. Available when traditional mentors are distant, busy, or simply absent.   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             For educators and institutions, this isn’t a threat. It’s a signal. Young people aren’t   Website www.revoir.in
           rejecting mentorship. They’re reshaping it. They want guidance that feels human, ac-
           cessible and honest about uncertainty. They value tone as much as expertise.   Legal Advisor
             Perhaps the real question isn’t whether social media creators should be mentors.   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           It’s why so many young people feel they have to look there in the first place. What
           gaps are being filled and which ones still remain?
             Mentorship today may not always come with a handshake or a formal title. Some-
           times it arrives through a glowing screen, whispered advice from someone far away,   Copyright © 2026 REVOIR (eZine),
           saying, “You’re not alone. I’ve been there.” And for now, that seems to be enough to   all rights reserved. This publication
           keep scrolling.                                                  may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.

         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[DEEP DIVE

































           The Vanishing Snow                                              nostalgia. When winter stops showing
                                                                           up the way it used to, the consequences
                                                                           ripple far beyond colder climates and
                                                                           mountain resorts. They reach rivers,
           What happens                                                    farms, cities and dinner tables.

                                                                           When snow was more than
                                                                           scenery
                                                                              Snow has never been just decoration.
           when winter stops                                               In many parts of the world, it functioned
                                                                           like a savings account for water. Winter
                                                                           snowpack stored moisture, releasing it
                                                                           slowly during warmer months. Rivers
           showing up?                                                     depended on it. Agriculture planned
                                                                           around it. Entire ecosystems evolved
                                                                           with it as a constant.
                                                                              Communities also built their lives
                                                                           around predictable winters. Festivals,
           The vanishing snow isn’t just a symptom of climate              livelihoods, school calendars and even
                                                                           architecture reflected an understanding
           change. It’s a signal. A gentle but persistent reminder         of cold, snow-heavy seasons. Winter had
           that systems we assumed were permanent are, in fact,            weight, purpose and presence.
                                                                              Now, that presence feels thinner.
           fragile.  By Riya Verma                                         Less reliable. Sometimes missing alto-
                                                                           gether.
                  hen did winter stop feeling   stead with dust, drizzle and confused   What’s really changing in winter
                  like winter? That question   flowers blooming far too early.   Climate change doesn’t simply mean
           Wsneaks up on many of us          Snow, for centuries, has been one of   warmer summers. It reshapes winters in
           quietly. It arrives when an old photo-  nature’s most dependable rhythms. It   complex ways. In many traditional snow
           graph pops up on your phone, children   fell, it melted, it returned. It shaped cal-  zones, temperatures now hover just
           bundled in sweaters and breath visible in   endars, cultures, economies and child-  above freezing. That small difference
           the air, snow piled on rooftops that now   hood memories. Today, that rhythm is   matters. Snow turns into rain. Snowfalls
           stay bare. Or when a hill town that once   faltering.           arrive later, melt sooner, or don’t come
           promised icy mornings greets you in-  This isn’t just about postcards and   at all.

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Water pays the

                                                                                      price

                                                                                Snow acts like nature’s slow-
                                                                              release reservoir. It gathers in
                                                                              winter, waits patiently and melts
                                                                              gradually to feed rivers, lakes and
                                                                              groundwater. When snowfall de-
                                                                              clines or melts too quickly, this
                                                                              delicate timing breaks down.
                                                                              Water arrives all at once, causing
                                                                              floods, or not at all when farms
                                                                              and cities need it most. In regions
                                                                              dependent on mountain snow, in-
                                                                              cluding large parts of India, this
                                                                              disruption threatens drinking
             Globally, scientists have observed   farming and electricity. When snowfall   water, agriculture and hydro-
           declining snow cover and shrinking   declines or becomes erratic, river flows   power. What looks like a warmer
           snow seasons across mountain ranges.   change. Some flood unpredictably.   winter often hides a deeper risk.
           The effect is subtle at first. A week less   Others run low when they’re needed   Less snow today can quietly be-
           of snow here. A thinner layer there. But   most.                   come a water crisis tomorrow,
           over time, the losses stack up.   Hill communities have noticed the   long after winter has passed and
             A winter without snow isn’t just   shifts firsthand. Winters are shorter.   attention has shifted elsewhere.
           milder. It’s unstable. Freeze-thaw cycles   Snow arrives late or falls as rain. Tradi-
           increase, damaging soil, roads and   tional farming calendars are harder to
           crops. Pests that once died off in cold
           weather survive and spread. Water sys-
           tems lose their natural timing.
             Winter doesn’t vanish overnight. It
           fades.
           The Indian story, closer than we
           think
             In India, snow is often viewed as dis-
           tant, something that belongs to postcards
           from hill stations or adventure trips. But
           its role is deeply practical.
             The Himalayan region acts as a water
           tower for much of the subcontinent.
           Snow and glaciers feed major rivers that
           millions depend on for drinking water,
            “                              follow. Apple growers, for example,   when snow-fed rivers behave differ-



            When snow disappears, it

                                           what their crops need.
                                                                           tions and food price fluctuations trace
            isn’t just winter that fades.   struggle when chilling hours drop below   ently. Water shortages, power disrup-
                                             Tourism too feels the strain. Places   their roots back to altered winters.
            Rivers lose their rhythm,      once guaranteed a snowy winter now   Urban areas also lose a natural cooling
                                           rely on artificial snow or rebrand them-  buffer. Snow reflects sunlight. Without
            mountains lose memory          selves entirely. For local economies built   it, land absorbs more heat, reinforcing
                                           around winter visitors, uncertainty has   warming trends.
            and people lose a season       become the new normal.             Even cultural life changes. Winter
                                                                           sports decline. Seasonal rituals fade.
                                           Beyond mountains: why cities    Children grow up without experiencing
            they once trusted without      should care                     snow as something familiar, only as an
                                             It’s tempting to think vanishing snow   exception or spectacle.
            question.”                     is a mountain problem. It isn’t.   What disappears isn’t just ice. It’s
                                             Cities downstream feel the impact   continuity.

           6                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Growing up


                                                                               without winter


                                                                                For older generations, winter
                                                                              meant routines, clothes pulled
                                                                              from trunks, early sunsets and
                                                                              sometimes snow underfoot. For
                                                                              many young people today, winter
                                                                              feels increasingly uncertain. In
                                                                              some places, it barely feels differ-
                                                                              ent from autumn. This shift
                                                                              shapes how children understand
                                                                              seasons, climate and even mem-
            “                                                                 ory. Experiences once shared ac-
                                                                              ross generations become stories

                                                                              rather than lived moments. The
                                                                              loss isn’t dramatic, but it’s deeply
            A snowless winter doesn’t
                                                                              cultural. When snow becomes
                                                                              rare, winter loses its identity. And
            arrive as a crisis. It arrives                                    when seasons lose meaning, our
                                                                              connection to nature grows
            quietly, week by week,                                            thinner, making environmental
                                                                              change easier to ignore and har-
            until absence becomes the                                         der to protect against.
            new normal.”
                                                                              For many, the memory of snow is
                                                                           tied to family, childhood, or a sense of
           Wildlife caught off guard                                       place. When winter stops showing up,
             Animals and plants are calibrated to                          something intimate shifts. It feels like
           seasonal cues. Snow cover signals when                          losing a familiar voice in the back-
           to hibernate, migrate, or bloom. When                           ground of life.
           those cues shift, survival becomes un-                             That emotional connection isn’t triv-
           certain.                                                        ial. It’s often what motivates care, con-
             Some species wake too early, only to                          cern and action more effectively than
           face sudden cold snaps. Others lose                             charts or forecasts.
           camouflage when snow arrives late or
           not at all. Predators and prey fall out of   water management, restoring wetlands   Standing at a quieter crossroads
           sync. Forests face stress as insects thrive   and rethinking agriculture to adapt to   We are living through a transition
           in warmer winters.              changing winters.               that future generations will either accept
             Nature can adapt, but not always at   Cities are learning to plan for vari-  as normal or look back on with dis-
           the speed change demands.       ability rather than predictability. Com-  belief. They may ask what winter once
                                           munities in mountain regions are diver-  felt like. Or why we didn’t protect it
           A quiet crisis, easy to overlook   sifying livelihoods. On a global level,   when the warning signs were already
             Snow loss doesn’t always arrive with   conversations about emission reductions   there.
           dramatic headlines. There’s no single   and climate resilience are no longer   The vanishing snow isn’t just a
           storm to blame, no obvious disaster on   fringe.                symptom of climate change. It’s a sig-
           day one. That makes it easy to ignore.   Hope, though, doesn’t lie in quick   nal. A gentle but persistent reminder that
             But the long-term effects are cumu-  fixes. Artificial snow can’t replace natu-  systems we assumed were permanent
           lative. Less snow today means less   ral systems. Short-term adaptation can’t   are, in fact, fragile.
           water tomorrow. Less stability next year.   fully compensate for long-term warm-  Maybe the question isn’t whether
           Less resilience over decades.   ing.                            winter will disappear completely. It’s
             This quietness is part of the danger.   What helps most is acknowledging   whether we’ll notice its absence in time
           By the time absence becomes obvious,   that winter matters.     to change course.
           recovery is far harder.                                            And the next time the season arrives
                                           Why snow is worth remembering   quietly, without the crunch underfoot or
           Are there any reasons for hope?   Snow teaches patience. It slows life   the hush that only snowfall brings, per-
             It’s not all bleak. Awareness is grow-  down. It asks people to adapt, prepare   haps we’ll pause. Not just to miss it, but
           ing. Climate science is clearer than ever.   and cooperate. Losing it alters not only   to understand what its silence is trying
           Some regions are investing in better   landscapes but behavior.   to tell us. ■

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION








































           Sacred Algorithms




           The digitalization                                              Faith in the age of code
                                                                              Religion has always used technology.
                                                                           The printing press spread scriptures.
                                                                           Loudspeakers amplified sermons. Radio
                                                                           carried prayers across borders. What’s
           of worship                                                      algorithms and artificial intelligence
                                                                           different now is intimacy. Smartphones,
                                                                           don’t just broadcast belief. They person-
                                                                           alize it.
                                                                              Today’s digital worship is respon-
           Digital worship leaves trails. Prayer habits, donation          sive. Apps remember prayer times, sug-
                                                                           gest readings based on mood and gently
           histories, emotional reflections. This data is valuable,        nudge users when routines slip. Some
                                                                           platforms analyze engagement patterns
           not just spiritually but commercially. By Naina Kapoor          and recommend spiritual content the
                                                                           way streaming services suggest movies.
                                                                           It can feel unsettling, even intrusive. Yet
                  hat does prayer look like   screen. A calm voice guides the chant.   for many, it also feels surprisingly sup-
                  when it fits into a notification   Somewhere else, a church livestream   portive.
           Wreminder? For millions of      buffers briefly before settling into a   A young software engineer in Benga-
           people today, devotion begins not with   hymn. Across the world, a Muslim pro-  luru once described it simply. “I forget
           bells or incense, but with a glowing   fessional checks a digital compass to   things. My app doesn’t. It keeps me
           screen and a gentle vibration in the   align with Mecca before salah. Faith, it   honest.”
           pocket.                         seems, has learned to load, refresh and   That sentence captures the moment
             Early morning in an Indian city. A   adapt.                   we’re in.
           temple bell echoes faintly outside, but   This isn’t a loss of the sacred. It’s a
           inside an apartment, someone opens a   transformation of how the sacred   Prayer apps and pocket shrines
           prayer app. A mantra scrolls across the   travels.                 Prayer apps are no longer basic

           8                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[India’s quiet



                  digital devotion

                In India, the digital turn in
             worship hasn’t arrived with noise
             or disruption. It’s come quietly,
             folded into daily routines. Temple
             livestreams play during morning
             chores. Devotional playlists re-
             place radio bhajans. Apps remind
             users of fasts, prayer times and
             festival rituals with gentle nudges
             rather than commands. For many
             urban believers, especially the
             young, this isn’t about replacing
             temples or traditions. It’s about
             continuity in crowded lives.
             Technology becomes a bridge be-
             tween inherited faith and modern
             schedules. The sacred, once
             bound by place, now moves
             freely through screens, head-
             phones and notifications, adapt-
             ing without asking permission.


           timers or text repositories. They guide
           breathing, offer reflections and create
           virtual sacred spaces that fit between
           meetings and metro rides. For people
           who feel disconnected from traditional
           institutions, these apps often become
           entry points rather than replacements.
             In India, the scale is remarkable.   Some people felt relief. Others felt
           Hindu devotional platforms stream live   grief.

           aartis from major temples. Devotees in   A ritual, after all, is not just words.   “
           small towns watch rituals from distant   It’s bodies sharing space, sounds over-
           shrines they may never visit. Digital do-  lapping, silences stretching together.   Faith hasn’t disappeared
           nation systems allow offerings without   Virtual rituals recreate structure but
           queues or crowds. During festivals, vir-  struggle with atmosphere. You can mute   into screens. It has simply
           tual darshan sometimes attracts more   yourself, step away, multitask. Sacred
           viewers than the physical sanctum can   time competes with everyday noise.   learned how to travel
           hold.                             Yet many faith leaders noticed some-
             For the Indian diaspora, this matters   thing unexpected. Attendance rose.   through them.”
           deeply. Distance dissolves when a famil-  People who had never entered physical
           iar chant plays through earbuds in a for-  spaces logged in. Elderly devotees
           eign city. Homesickness softens. Be-  joined without travel. Those anxious   and offer moral reflections. Some users
           longing returns, briefly, through   about judgment felt safer behind   treat them as study tools. Others treat
           bandwidth.                      screens.                        them as companions during moments of
             Still, there’s a quiet tension here.   Presence, it turns out, is not only   doubt. A few admit they talk to them the
           When devotion becomes convenient,   physical. It’s also emotional and inten-  way they’d talk to a spiritual mentor.
           does it also become disposable?   tional. Technology can’t guarantee it,   This raises uncomfortable questions.
                                           but neither can tradition.      Can an algorithm understand faith? Or is
           Virtual rituals and the question of                             it merely reflecting patterns back to us?
           presence                        When AI becomes a spiritual guide   AI doesn’t believe. It doesn’t doubt.
             The pandemic accelerated what tech-  Artificial intelligence adds another   It doesn’t feel awe. But it does listen pa-
           nology had already begun. Weddings   layer and this is where debates grow   tiently, respond instantly and never
           were blessed over video calls. Funerals   sharper.              judge. For people navigating loneliness
           were attended via screens. Communal   AI-powered chatbots now answer   or spiritual confusion, that combination
           rituals went digital almost overnight.   theological questions, explain scriptures   can feel powerful.

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Algorithms can guide

                                                                             attention, but devotion still

                                                                             begins where intention

                                                                             lives.”










                                           flections. This data is valuable, not just
                                           spiritually but commercially.
              When AI listens                Who owns it? Who protects it?

                                             Faith-based platforms increasingly

            without judgment               face ethical scrutiny. If an algorithm
                                           learns when someone is most vulner-

                                           able, should it intervene spiritually or
                AI-powered spiritual tools   market something? The line between
             don’t claim belief, yet many users   care and exploitation can blur quickly.
             turn to them in moments of      There’s also the danger of echo
             doubt. They ask questions they   chambers. Personalized spirituality
             hesitate to voice elsewhere. What   might reinforce beliefs without chal-
             does forgiveness really mean? Is   lenge. Faith traditions grow through dia-
             doubt a failure? The responses   logue, doubt and discomfort. Algorithms
             are calm, structured, endlessly   prefer comfort.
             patient. That’s part of their ap-  These concerns aren’t reasons to re-
             peal. Unlike humans, algorithms   ject technology. They’re reasons to ap-
             don’t interrupt or moralize. But   proach it with humility and safeguards.
             this raises a deeper concern.                                 sibility. Continuity. New voices entering
             Comfort can’t replace wisdom.   Young believers, new languages   ancient conversations.
             Faith traditions grow through   Urban youth often occupy a hybrid   Sacredness has never depended on
             struggle, disagreement and lived   spiritual space. They may distrust insti-  form alone. It lives in intention, atten-
             experience. AI can assist reflec-  tutions but still crave meaning. They   tion and the willingness to pause in a
             tion, but it can’t walk the inner   meditate with apps, attend festivals oc-  restless world.
             path for anyone. Used thought-  casionally and discuss belief on social   Technology doesn’t erase that pause.
             fully, it’s a mirror. Used blindly,   media.                  Sometimes, it creates it.
             it risks becoming an authority it   For them, digital spirituality feels
             was never meant to be.        natural. It speaks their language. Visual.   A quiet ending
                                           Interactive. Flexible.             Late at night, a woman finishes her
                                             Many aren’t abandoning faith.   prayer using an app. The screen fades to
             The risk lies in authority. When an-  They’re remixing it.    black. The room is silent again. No noti-
           swers come quickly and confidently,   This shift unsettles older generations,   fications follow. For a moment, it’s just
           users may forget that AI doesn’t possess   but it also keeps traditions alive in   her and her thoughts.
           wisdom. It simulates it. Religious tradi-  evolving forms. Faith that refuses to   The algorithm did its part. The rest is
           tions are built on centuries of interpreta-  adapt risks becoming a museum artifact.   human.
           tion, disagreement and lived experience.   Faith that adapts thoughtfully remains   Perhaps that’s the balance we’re still
           Flattening that into neat responses risks   lived and breathing.   learning. Let technology open doors, but
           oversimplification.                                             not replace the act of walking through
             Still, dismissing AI outright misses   What gets lost, what remains   them. Let AI assist, not decide. Let faith
           the point. Many believers already use it   Something is lost when rituals lose   remain imperfect, searching and deeply
           critically, as a tool, not a teacher.   physicality. The smell of incense. The   personal.
                                           shared glance during a hymn. The awk-  Because in the end, no matter how
           Sacred data and ethical fault lines   ward silence that deepens into rever-  advanced the code becomes, the sacred
             Digital worship leaves trails. Prayer   ence.                 still begins where the screen ends and
           habits, donation histories, emotional re-  But something is gained too. Acces-  reflection begins. ■

           10                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT




































                                           Mentors on social media
                  ho do you turn to when
                  you’re stuck? For many
           Wyoung people today, the an-
           swer isn’t a teacher, a boss, or even a                           Gen Z’s
           family elder. It’s a stranger on a screen.
           Someone they’ve never met, but whose
           voice feels familiar. Someone who posts
           short videos from a bedroom, a campus
           lawn, or the front seat of a car, speaking
           with a confidence that feels earned, or at   unconventional
           least honest.
             This isn’t mentorship in the old
           sense. There’s no formal introduction,
           no long-term obligation, no office hours.
           And yet, for Gen Z, it’s real enough to                            guides
           matter.

           The quiet shift in where guidance
           comes from                      In a world where certainty is rare and paths are less linear
             Traditional mentorship used to de-
           pend on proximity. You found guidance   than they once were, Gen Z is finding its guides wherever
           at school, at work, in your neighbour-
           hood, or within your family. But those   it can. On screens. In comments. By Anaya Gupta
           structures haven’t disappeared so much
           as they’ve become uneven. Not every-
           one has access to a supportive work-  navigated layoffs, study tips from stu-  calm intimacy once reserved for one-on-
           place, a patient teacher, or a senior who   dents who cracked competitive exams   one conversations. Instagram offers bite-
           understands today’s anxieties.   and mental health reflections from   sized motivation, daily routines and be-
             Digital spaces stepped into that gap   people still figuring things out them-  hind-the-scenes honesty that feels
           quietly. Scroll through TikTok for a few   selves. On YouTube, long-form creators   reassuringly imperfect.
           minutes and you’ll find career advice   break down personal finance, relation-  None of these creators may call
           from twenty-somethings who’ve just   ships, burnout and self-worth with a   themselves mentors. But for millions of

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Why digital

                                                                             mentors feel so


                                                                                  personal


                                                                                Social media advice often
                                                                              feels personal, even when it’s not
                                                                              meant to be. A face filling the
                                                                              screen, direct eye contact and a
                                                                              conversational tone create a sense
                                                                              of closeness that traditional men-
                                                                              torship rarely offers so quickly.
                                                                              For Gen Z, who grew up com-
                                                                              municating through screens, this
                                                                              format feels natural, not distant.
                                                                              Late at night, when doubts creep
                                                                              in, a familiar voice can feel
                                                                              grounding. The advice may be
                                                                              generic, but the timing makes it
                                                                              powerful. It’s not about replacing
                                                                              real relationships. It’s about fill-
                                                                              ing emotional gaps when real-
                                                                              time guidance isn’t available.
                                                                              That perceived intimacy explains
                                                                              why digital mentors resonate so
                                                                              deeply, especially during mo-
                                                                              ments of uncertainty.


                                                                           rate their guidance. Instead of relying on
                                                                           one mentor, they piece together insights
                                                                           from many voices. One creator helps
            “                              in spotting forced sincerity. Polished   with productivity. Another with emo-
                                             Gen Z grew up online. They’re fluent
                                                                           tional boundaries. A third with navigat-

                                                                           ing early careers. It’s a mosaic approach
                                           perfection doesn’t persuade them the
                                           way it once might have. What resonates
                                                                           to mentorship, shaped by algorithms and
            Gen Z doesn’t look for
                                           is relatability. A creator who failed an
                                           exam before figuring out a study   personal choice.
                                                                              Of course, this freedom comes with
            perfect mentors. They look     method. A freelancer who talks openly   responsibility. Not all advice is sound.
                                           about inconsistent income. A young pro-  Not all mentors are qualified. Gen Z
            for people who admit           fessional explaining how they asked for   seems aware of that risk, even if they
                                           a raise and got rejected before trying   don’t always avoid it.
            they’re still figuring things   again.
                                             It feels less like being instructed and   When advice feels personal, even
            out.                           more like being accompanied.    if it isn’t
                                                                              There’s an emotional layer here that’s
                                           Mentorship without hierarchy    hard to ignore. Watching someone speak
           followers, that’s exactly what they are.   One of the most striking differences   directly into a camera creates an illusion
                                           is the absence of hierarchy. Traditional   of intimacy. The advice feels tailored,
           Why Gen Z listens differently   mentors often occupy positions of   even when it’s meant for millions. Late
             Part of the appeal is tone. Social   power. They evaluate you, promote you,   at night, with headphones on, a creator’s
           media mentors don’t talk down. They   or grade you. That dynamic can make   words can feel like a private conver-
           don’t arrive with decades of authority or   honesty difficult.   sation.
           rigid formulas. They speak from experi-  Online mentors don’t hold that   For young people navigating loneli-
           ence, often recent and messy. They   power. You can listen, disagree, scroll   ness, anxiety, or uncertainty, that matters
           admit mistakes. They say things like,   past, or unfollow without consequence.   deeply.
           “I’m still learning,” or “This worked for   The relationship is voluntary, fluid and   A college student scrolling through
           me, it might not for you.”      surprisingly empowering.        videos after a rough day may find com-
             That vulnerability matters.     This also allows young people to cu-  fort in someone saying, “You’re not be-

           12                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             In a noisy digital world,

                                                                             guidance doesn’t always

                                                                             come from authority.

                                                                             Sometimes it comes from

                                                                             relatability.

                                                                           or success often reflects the creator’s so-
                                                                           cial and economic context. Gen Z users
                                                                           are increasingly aware of this. They dis-
                                                                           cuss privilege, location and opportunity
                                                                           with a sophistication that surprises older
                                                                           generations.
                                           supporting it. Some creators uninten-  They don’t just consume content.
                                           tionally position themselves as au-  They question it. Comment sections be-
                                           thorities on everything, from mental   come debates. Duets and response vi-
                                           health to money, without the training   deos offer counterpoints. Mentorship be-
                                           such topics demand.             comes a conversation, not a monologue.
                                             Gen Z isn’t blind to these issues.
                                           Many openly discuss “taking advice   So, what does mentorship mean
                                           with a pinch of salt” or cross-checking   now?
                                           information. But awareness doesn’t al-  Maybe it’s time to loosen the defini-
                                           ways translate into restraint.   tion.
                                                                              Mentorship no longer has to be ex-
                                           Educators and mentors are paying   clusive, formal, or long-term. It can be
                                           attention                       brief. Fragmented. Unexpected. It can
                                             Interestingly, teachers, counsellors   come from someone you’ll never meet,
                                           and youth mentors aren’t entirely resist-  at a moment you didn’t plan for, in a for-
                                           ant to this shift. Many are adapting.   mat that didn’t exist a decade ago.
                                             Some educators now recommend     That doesn’t make it shallow. It
                                           specific creators as supplementary re-  makes it different.
                                           sources. Career counsellors acknowl-  For Gen Z, guidance isn’t about find-
                                           edge that students often arrive with   ing one perfect mentor. It’s about gath-
                                           ideas shaped by online voices. Instead of   ering perspectives, testing ideas and
           hind. You’re just early in your journey.”   dismissing them, they unpack them to-  building a sense of direction in a noisy
           It’s a simple line. But at the right mo-  gether. What’s useful here? What’s mis-  world.
           ment, it can steady someone’s breathing,   sing? What might not apply to your
           shift their perspective, or keep them   context?                A quiet reflection to end on
           from spiralling.                  In this way, digital mentorship and   There’s something hopeful in this
             Is that mentorship? Maybe not in a   traditional guidance don’t have to com-  shift. Amid all the criticism of social
           formal sense. But emotionally, it plays a   pete. They can complement each other.   media, it’s easy to forget that young
           similar role.                     The best outcomes seem to happen   people are using these platforms not just
                                           when young people have both. The im-  to perform, but to learn. To ask ques-
           The limits no one should ignore   mediacy and relatability of online men-  tions. To feel less alone.
             Still, social media mentorship has its   tors, paired with the depth and accounta-  A stranger’s video won’t replace a
           cracks.                         bility of real-world relationships.   caring teacher or a trusted elder. It
             Algorithms reward engagement, not                             shouldn’t. But it might spark a thought,
           accuracy. Extreme opinions travel faster   A global conversation, shaped   offer reassurance, or help someone take
           than nuanced ones. Advice that sounds   locally                 a small step forward.
           confident can drown out quieter, more   One reason social media mentorship   And sometimes, that’s enough.
           responsible perspectives. There’s also   resonates internationally is its acces-  In a world where certainty is rare and
           the risk of oversimplification. Life does-  sibility. A teenager in a small town can   paths are less linear than they once
           n’t always fit into a 60-second video.   learn from someone across the world.   were, Gen Z is finding its guides
             And then there’s dependency. When   Cultural boundaries blur, but they don’t   wherever it can. On screens. In com-
           guidance becomes a constant scroll, it   disappear.             ments. In shared stories. Not perfect
           can replace critical thinking instead of   Advice about careers, relationships,   mentors, but human ones. ■

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Before the final goodbye                                        be seen, honoured and emotionally held
                                                                           before death arrives, not as denial of mor-
                                                                           tality, but as an acceptance of it.
                                                                              There’s something profoundly human   PERSPECTIVE
           How cultures                                                    isn’t just about the past. It’s also about the
                                                                           in that choice. It recognises that memory
                                                                           present moment, about saying, “You mat-
                                                                           tered to me and you still do.”

           celebrate life                                                  When joy meets impermanence
                                                                              Some societies weave celebration and
                                                                           impermanence together so tightly that the
                                                                           line between the two almost disappears.
                                                                           Life is treated as precious because it’s
                                                                           fragile, not despite it.
                                                                              In parts of Latin America, for in-
           before death                                                    stance, families often gather while elders
                                                                           are still alive to share stories, jokes and
                                                                           even playful mockery about the past.
                                                                           These gatherings aren’t sombre rehear-
                                                                           sals for death. They’re warm, loud, some-
                                                                           times chaotic. People speak openly about
           Cultures that celebrate life before death                       ageing, loss and the future, but they do it
                                                                           with laughter, food and music close by.
                                                                              The emotional tone matters. By nor-
           don’t eliminate regret. But they reduce                         malising conversations about mortality,
           its weight. By Pooja Mehta                                      fear loses some of its grip. Death isn’t in-
                                                                           vited early, but it’s acknowledged hon-
                                                                           estly.


                  hat if we didn’t wait for a eu-
                  logy to say what matters?
           WWhat if gratitude, honour and
           affection were spoken aloud while people
           could still hear them, laugh at them,
           maybe even argue with them?
             Across the world, many cultures have
           quietly answered that question. Long be-
           fore wellness hashtags and mindfulness
           apps, societies found ways to celebrate
           people not after they’re gone, but while
           they’re still living, breathing, arguing,
           loving and changing. These traditions
           aren’t always loud or festive. Some are
           subtle, some deeply emotional, others
           joyful to the point of being noisy. But
           they all share a simple idea. Life deserves
           acknowledgement before the final good-
           bye.

           The urge to honour the living
             In many modern societies, celebration
           is oddly postponed. We wait for mile-
           stones, anniversaries, retirement parties.
           Or worse, we wait until someone dies to
           speak about their impact. Funerals be-
           come the space where love finally gets
           articulated.
             Anthropologists often point out that
           this delay isn’t universal. In several cul-
           tures, rituals exist precisely to avoid that
           silence. These practices allow people to

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Living

                                                                               honours, not



                                                                                  farewells

                                                                                In many cultures, appreciation
                                                                              isn’t postponed until someone is
                                                                              gone. Elders are celebrated with
                                                                              words, rituals and attention while
                                                                              they are still very much part of
                                                                              daily life. From milestone birth-
                                                                              days to communal storytelling,
                                                                              these moments allow people to
           rial days. It’s practiced daily through  “                         aloud. There’s laughter, some-
                                                                              hear their own impact spoken
           Rituals of gratitude in everyday life
             In East Asian cultures influenced by
                                                                              times discomfort and often tears.

                                                                              But there’s also relief. These liv-
           Confucian thought, respect for elders
                                                                              ing honours don’t erase grief.
           isn’t limited to old age homes or memo-
                                                                              ilies and communities that love
           gestures, language and shared respon-  What if we didn’t wait for a   They soften it. They remind fam-
           sibility.                         eulogy to say what               doesn’t need a formal ending to
             Special birthdays, particularly those                            be expressed. Saying thank you
           marking advanced age, are often cele-  matters, but said it while   early doesn’t diminish memory. It
           brated with elaborate family gatherings.                           deepens it, anchoring it in shared
           These aren’t just parties. They’re ac-  people could still hear us?”  moments rather than quiet regret.
           knowledgements of survival, endurance
           and accumulated wisdom. Elders are in-
           vited to speak, advise and sometimes
           scold. Their presence is central, not
           symbolic.
             What’s striking is how these rituals
           frame ageing not as decline but as con-
           tribution. Living longer isn’t just about
           years added. It’s about meaning deep-
           ened.
           India’s quiet celebrations of being
           alive
             In India, the celebration of life before
           death often hides in plain sight. It’s not
           always labelled as such, but it’s deeply
           embedded in social and spiritual prac-
           tices.
             Consider the tradition of marking
           significant birthdays like the 60th or
           80th year with ceremonies that resemble
           weddings. These events aren’t about de-  Even farewell rituals for those choos-  because pain is acknowledged.
           nial of ageing. They’re about gratitude.   ing a life of renunciation are telling.   In parts of Africa, communal story-
           The individual is thanked for their role   When someone leaves worldly life for   telling plays this role. Elders share
           in the family, their struggles, their per-  spiritual pursuits, communities often   stories of hardship, survival and mis-
           sistence. Children touch their feet. Eld-  celebrate it while the person is alive, ac-  takes. Younger members respond not
           ers bless the younger generation. The   knowledging the courage of that transi-  with pity but with recognition. These
           message is clear. You are still needed.   tion rather than mourning it later.   sessions often end in music or dance,
             There’s also a cultural emphasis on                           not because sorrow has vanished, but
           doing good deeds while alive. Feeding   Celebrations without denial   because it’s been shared.
           others, donating quietly, mentoring   One common misconception is that   There’s an understanding that joy and
           younger people. These acts are seen as   celebrating life before death somehow   sadness aren’t opposites. They’re com-
           ways of preparing one’s legacy in real   ignores grief or suffering. In reality,   panions. One makes the other intelligi-
           time, not posthumously.         many of these traditions exist precisely   ble.

           16                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[“



            Across cultures,

            celebrating life before

            death isn’t about
            denying loss. It’s

            about refusing

            silence.”





                                                                                     India’s


                                                                                  unspoken ritual

                                                                                 of gratitude

                                                                                In India, celebrating life be-
                                                                              fore death is often woven quietly
                                                                              into tradition. Ceremonial birth-
                                                                              days, community meals, acts of
                                                                              charity and intergenerational
                                                                              gatherings all serve this purpose
                                                                              without naming it directly. Elders
                                                                              are honoured not only through
                                                                              rituals but through everyday ges-
                                                                              tures. Touching feet, shared
                                                                              meals, listening without interrup-
                                                                              tion. These acts affirm presence,
                                                                              not legacy. They say, “You matter
                                                                              now.” In a culture deeply aware
                                                                              of impermanence, such practices
                                                                              offer balance. They acknowledge
                                                                              ageing and loss while insisting on
           Modern reinterpretations and    Why these traditions matter today   dignity, connection and rel-
           personal rituals                  In a world obsessed with productivity   evance. Celebration here isn’t
             In recent years, some of these ideas   and future planning, it’s easy to forget   loud. It’s lived.
           have found new expressions, especially   that life isn’t only about what comes
           in urban and globalised settings. People   next. It’s also about what’s already here.
           host “living wakes” where friends gather   Celebrating life before death shifts   pliment withheld because it felt awk-
           to share what someone has meant to   attention back to presence. It asks us to   ward.
           them, not because death is imminent,   notice people while they’re still imper-  Cultures that celebrate life before
           but because honesty feels overdue.   fect, still capable of surprising us, still   death don’t eliminate regret. But they re-
             Others write letters to loved ones,   capable of disappointment and forgive-  duce its weight. They create more
           give away possessions with intention, or   ness.                spaces where love is expressed clumsily,
           create memory projects that document   For ageing societies, these rituals   honestly and in time.
           everyday moments. These practices   also challenge the fear-driven narratives   Perhaps the real lesson isn’t about
           might not belong to any ancient tradi-  around old age. They remind us that   adopting specific rituals from elsewhere.
           tion, but they echo the same instinct.   value doesn’t expire. It evolves.   It’s about a shift in habit. About choos-
           Say it now. Celebrate now.                                      ing to celebrate people now, in ordinary
             Psychologists note that such practices   A personal reflection   moments, without waiting for a reason
           often reduce anxiety, both for those   Most of us can recall a moment when   dramatic enough to justify it.
           being honoured and those doing the   we wished we’d said more to someone   After all, life doesn’t need a closing
           honouring. There’s relief in not leaving   who’s no longer around. A thank you   ceremony to be meaningful. Sometimes,
           things unsaid.                  left unsent. An apology delayed. A com-  it just needs to be noticed. ■

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[INSIGHT


































           Smell of a Summer Day



           How senses                                                      We picture photo albums in the brain,


                                                                           neatly labeled and filed. But sensory
                                                                           memory doesn’t work that way. It does-
                                                                           n’t ask permission. It barges in.
           trigger memory                                                  sight or sound, which pass through sev-
                                                                              Smell is particularly unruly. Unlike
                                                                           eral layers of processing, smell takes a
                                                                           more direct route to the brain areas
                                                                           linked with emotion and long-term
           For writers and artists, sensory memory is a kind of            memory. That’s why a familiar fragrance
                                                                           can feel like a sudden emotional wave
           quiet treasure. Describing a smell or texture often             rather than a thought you chose to recall.
                                                                              It’s not dramatic. It’s almost quiet.
           evokes stronger responses than explaining emotions              And that’s what makes it powerful.
                                                                              You’re walking down a street, dis-
           directly. By Aarav Sharma                                       tracted, thinking about tomorrow. Some-
                                                                           one passes by wearing a perfume you
                                                                           haven’t encountered in decades. Sud-
                 ave you ever caught a scent in   ens its grip. The mind slips quietly back-  denly, you’re eight years old again, sit-
                 the air and suddenly found   ward and before logic has a chance to   ting in the back seat of a car, half-asleep
           Hyourself somewhere else en-    intervene, memory arrives, fully formed   on a summer evening, your mother’s
           tirely?                         and emotional.                  scarf brushing your cheek. You didn’t
             Not just remembering it, but standing   This is the strange, intimate power of   try to remember that moment. It came to
           there again. A different year. A different   our senses. Especially smell.   you.
           version of you.
             It might be the smell of dust after   When memory doesn’t knock, it   The brain’s shortcut between
           rain, warm asphalt, cut grass, or ripe   enters                 scent and emotion
           mangoes. For a split second, time loos-  Memory is often imagined as orderly.   Neuroscientists often describe smell

           18                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Why smell feels

               so emotional


                Smell is the only sense that
             takes a direct neurological route
             to the brain’s emotional and
             memory centers. That shortcut
             explains why scents often trigger
             intense, sudden recollections,
             sometimes without context. Un-
             like visual memories, which are
             usually reconstructed con-
             sciously, smell-based memories
             arrive whole, carrying emotion
             first and meaning later. This is
             why a fragrance can feel comfort-
             ing or unsettling without a clear
             reason. Summer scents linger
             longer because heat amplifies air-
             borne molecules and keeps win-
             dows open, blending indoor and
             outdoor worlds. Over time, the
             brain fuses these smells with feel-
             ings of safety, freedom, or long-
             ing. The result isn’t just recall.
             It’s emotional time travel.


           as the most emotionally loaded sense.
           The olfactory system connects closely
           with the amygdala and hippocampus, re-
           gions involved in emotion and memory
           formation. This wiring explains why   or tone can recreate an entire at-
           smell-based memories tend to be vivid,   mosphere. Not just a scene, but a feel-

           emotional and stubbornly persistent.   ing. The slow pace of afternoons. The   “
             You might forget names, dates, even   laziness of long evenings. The sense that
           faces. But certain smells refuse to fade.   time wasn’t rushing you.   A familiar smell doesn’t
             There’s also something less dis-  Sound-based memories are often so-  just remind us of the past.
           cussed. Smell memories aren’t always   cial. Laughter drifting from another
           accurate. They’re emotional reconstruc-  room. A radio playing while someone   It quietly returns us to a
           tions, shaped by time, context and   cooks. Footsteps on a staircase late at
           mood. But accuracy isn’t the point. Im-  night. These aren’t dramatic moments,   version of ourselves we
           pact is.                        but they’re emotionally dense. The brain
             And summer, with its heat and open-  remembers them because they meant   didn’t know we were still
           ness, seems to imprint these sensory ex-  safety, connection, familiarity.
           periences more deeply. Windows stay                               carrying.”
           open. Life spills outdoors. The brain   Touch, texture and the body’s
           records more without us noticing.   memory                      physical responses. That’s why certain
                                             Texture is the most underestimated   textures can provoke emotional reac-
           Sound as a time machine         sense when it comes to memory. Yet the   tions without clear explanations.
             Smell may be the fastest trigger, but   body remembers even when the mind   A breeze on your arm might make
           sound isn’t far behind.         doesn’t.                        you feel inexplicably calm. A particular
             Think of the low hum of ceiling fans,   The stickiness of humidity on skin.   fabric might feel comforting or unset-
           the clink of ice in a glass, cicadas buz-  The roughness of concrete under bare   tling. These responses are rarely intel-
           zing at dusk, or the distant call of a   feet. The cool shock of water on a hot   lectual. They’re physical echoes of ear-
           street vendor. These sounds don’t de-  afternoon. These sensations lodge them-  lier experiences.
           mand attention. They sit in the back-  selves in the nervous system.   In summer especially, the body is
           ground, quietly embedding themselves   Psychologists sometimes talk about   more exposed. More aware. Less insu-
           into memory.                    embodied memory. The idea that mem-  lated. Sensory information travels freely
             Years later, hearing a similar rhythm   ory isn’t stored only in the brain but in   and memory quietly follows.

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[The body


                  remembers what

             the mind forgets


                Not all memory lives in words
             or images. The body stores ex-
             periences through texture, tem-
             perature and movement. Psychol-
             ogists call this embodied
             memory. The coolness of tiled
             floors on bare feet, the stickiness
             of humid air, or the weight of
             damp clothes after swimming can
             resurface decades later through
             physical sensations alone. These
             memories often bypass conscious   they’re also deeply human.
             thought, appearing as comfort,   Grief researchers note that sensory

             unease, or calm without explana-  triggers often appear long after con-  “
             tion. Summer, with its exposure   scious mourning has eased. You think   Memory isn’t always
             and loosened routines, creates   you’re fine. Then a smell hits and sud-
             strong bodily imprints. When   denly your throat tightens.      stored in stories.
             similar sensations return, the   It doesn’t mean you’re moving back-
             nervous system responds first.   ward. It means memory is layered. Emo-  Sometimes it lives in the
             The mind follows later, if at all.   tional processing doesn’t follow time-  sound of a fan, the feel of
             Some memories don’t need      lines.
             names to be real.               Sometimes, these moments are gifts.   heat on skin, or a scent we
                                           Other times, they sting. Both responses
                                           are valid.                        can’t quite name.”
           Why ordinary moments last the
           longest                         Can we create better memories on   larly. A described scent activates regions
             It’s tempting to think memory is built   purpose?             linked to personal memory, pulling
           from milestones. Big events. Firsts and   This question comes up often. If   readers into their own experiences.
           lasts. But sensory memory tells a differ-  senses are so powerful, can we design   This is why sensory detail feels inti-
           ent story.                      experiences that last?          mate. It bypasses explanation and goes
             What stays with us are often the mo-  To some extent, yes. Mindfulness   straight to feeling.
           ments that felt unimportant at the time.   practices often emphasize sensory   It’s also why these details must be
             A hallway that smelled of soap. A   awareness for this reason. Paying atten-  handled carefully. Overuse dulls their ef-
           kitchen filled with steam. A notebook   tion to how something smells, sounds,   fect. Precision matters more than quan-
           page warmed by sunlight. These weren’t   or feels increases the likelihood it will   tity.
           events. They were environments. And   be remembered.
           environments shape us quietly, re-  But there’s a catch. You can’t force   A personal return
           peatedly.                       meaning. Trying too hard often does the   I still remember the smell of a particu-
             The brain doesn’t just record what   opposite.                lar summer afternoon. No special event
           matters socially or logically. It records   The most enduring memories are   attached. Just light, dust, something
           what’s repeated and emotionally col-  created when attention is present but re-  sweet in the air. I don’t know why that
           ored. Summer days, with their slower   laxed. When you’re there, not doc-  moment stayed when so many others dis-
           rhythms, provide that repetition. The   umenting. Feeling, not curating.   appeared.
           same smells. The same sounds. The   Children understand this instinc-  Maybe because I wasn’t trying to re-
           same textures. Day after day.   tively. Adults have to relearn it.   member it.
             That’s how they sink in.                                         Sometimes memory chooses for us.
                                           Writers, artists and the sensory   And when it does, it often speaks through
           Memory, loss and gentle longing   shortcut                      the senses. Quietly. Honestly. Without
             Not all sensory memories feel good.   For writers and artists, sensory mem-  asking whether we’re ready.
           Some ache. Some bring a soft sadness   ory is a kind of quiet treasure. Describing   Perhaps that’s the real lesson of sen-
           that’s hard to name.            a smell or texture often evokes stronger   sory memory. Life doesn’t wait for sig-
             A scent can remind you of someone   responses than explaining emotions di-  nificance. It leaves traces anyway. If
           who’s gone. A sound can bring back a   rectly.                  you’re lucky, one day, you’ll catch a fa-
           version of life that no longer exists.   Readers might not share the same   miliar scent in the air and smile without
           These moments can feel intrusive, but   memories, but their brains respond simi-  knowing why. And that will be enough. ■

           20                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Healing words                                                         ou don’t know how much I        SPECIAL FEATURE
                                                                                 needed to hear that. Most of us
                                                                           Yhave said it at least once. Some-
           Compliments                                                     times quietly. Sometimes with a small,
                                                                           embarrassed smile. Often after a single,
                                                                           unexpected sentence landed exactly
                                                                           where it hurt.
                                                                              We don’t usually think of compli-
           as emotional                                                    most decorative. Something extra, nice
                                                                           ments as powerful. They sound soft, al-
                                                                           to have, but not essential. Yet in mo-
                                                                           ments of emotional strain, a well-timed,
                                                                           sincere compliment can work like first
                                                                           aid. Not a cure. Not a solution. But a
           first aid                                                       pause in the pain. A reminder that some-
                                                                           one sees you and that you’re not invisi-
                                                                           ble.
                                                                           More than politeness
                                                                              Compliments often get confused with
           Words won’t fix everything. They won’t erase                    manners. We teach children to say “nice
                                                                           shirt” the same way we teach them to
           trauma or injustice. But in moments of strain,                  say “please.” But emotional compli-
                                                                           ments are different. They aren’t about
           they can offer first aid. A pause. A reminder of                politeness or social lubrication. They’re
                                                                           about recognition.
           worth. By Rajeev Khanna                                         “Good job” and “I noticed how patiently
                                                                              Think about the difference between














































           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[“



            A sincere

            compliment doesn’t
            fix your life. It fixes

            the moment. And
            sometimes, that’s

            enough.”







                                                                                  The anatomy of

                                                                                  a healing

                                                                                compliment


                                                                                A compliment that actually
                                                                              helps has three quiet ingredients.
                                                                              First, it’s specific. “You handled
                                                                              that conversation with patience”
                                                                              lands better than “You’re great.”
                                                                              Second, it’s effort-focused. It no-
                                                                              tices trying, not just winning.
                                                                              Third, it’s sincere, without
                                                                              strategy or expectation attached.
                                                                              Healing compliments don’t rush
           you handled that meeting.” One slides   remain unpaid. Grief doesn’t disappear.   to fix emotions or demand a re-
           off the surface. The other sinks in. It   Anxiety still hums in the background.   sponse. They simply acknowl-
           tells someone that their effort mattered,   But something shifts. The person receiv-  edge reality with kindness. When
           that their way of being in the world was   ing the compliment stands a little   people feel seen without being
           seen and valued.                straighter. Breath comes easier. For a   evaluated, their nervous system
             Psychologists have long pointed out   moment, the inner critic loses its micro-  softens. That’s when words stop
           that humans are wired for social feed-  phone.                     feeling decorative and start feel-
           back. Praise activates the same reward   What makes these words healing is   ing supportive. Not every compli-
           pathways as physical comfort or food. In   their specificity and sincerity. They are-  ment needs to be memorable. It
           simpler terms, kind words can calm the   n’t loud declarations. They’re small ac-  just needs to be honest.
           nervous system. They lower stress,   knowledgments that say, “I see you try-
           soften self-doubt and in some cases, in-  ing.”
           terrupt spirals of negative thinking.                           They validate effort, not perfection.
           That’s not magic. That’s biology mixed   Compliments and mental well-  For people with anxiety, compli-
           with emotion.                   being                           ments can counter relentless self-ques-
                                             In conversations about mental health,   tioning. When someone says, “You han-
           The quiet moments when words    we often focus on therapy, medication,   dled that better than you think,” it offers
           matter most                     routines, boundaries. All important. But   an alternative narrative. It doesn’t dis-
             Compliments don’t usually arrive   everyday emotional care also matters   miss fear, but it reframes competence.
           during life’s highlight reels. They show   and compliments are part of that ecosys-  Of course, compliments alone aren’t
           up in the in-between moments.   tem.                            treatment. They don’t replace profes-
             A teacher tells a struggling student,   For someone dealing with depres-  sional help. But they can soften the ter-
           “You ask thoughtful questions.”   sion, positive self-talk can feel impos-  rain, making it easier for someone to
             A colleague says, “You bring clarity   sible. External affirmation becomes a   keep going.
           when things get messy.”         bridge. Not forced positivity, but
             A parent whispers to an exhausted   grounded recognition. “You showed up   The workplace effect
           child, “I’m proud of how hard you try.”   today.” “You were kind, even when you   In professional settings, compliments
             None of these erase problems. Bills   were tired.” These aren’t empty phrases.   are often rationed, as if praise might di-

           22                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Compliments

                  become everyday

                      care

                Compliments don’t need
             grand moments. They work best
             when they slip into ordinary life.
             A parent noticing patience at bed-
             time. A manager acknowledging
             clarity during chaos. A friend ap-
             preciating emotional honesty.
             Over time, these small rec-
             ognitions shape how people see
             themselves. They become inter-
             nal reference points during stress.
             Think of compliments as emo-
             tional maintenance rather than
             emotional rescue. Given regu-
             larly, they reduce wear and tear.
             Given sincerely, they build trust.
             The habit isn’t about being posi-
             tive all the time. It’s about paying   Especially when they focus on character   both sides. Offering genuine praise
             attention, then saying out loud   and effort rather than talent alone. Say-  means paying attention. It means risking
             what you might otherwise keep to   ing “You’re smart” feels good. Saying   sincerity in a culture that sometimes
             yourself.                     “You didn’t give up when it got hard”   prefers irony.
                                           builds resilience.                 But compliments don’t require
                                             Educators and caregivers often un-  eloquence. They require presence.
           lute standards. Yet research consistently   derestimate how deeply their words   “I liked how you listened.”
           shows that recognition improves morale,   land. A single sentence can become a   “That took courage.”
           engagement and resilience.      lifelong anchor, or a lifelong wound.   “You made today easier.”
             The key is how compliments are de-  Compliments, when thoughtful, help tilt   Simple sentences. Honest observa-
           livered. Vague praise can feel perfor-  that balance toward healing.   tions. That’s it.
           mative. Strategic praise can feel ma-                              And sometimes, the most important
           nipulative. But genuine         When compliments go wrong       compliment is the one we learn to give
           acknowledgment of effort, growth, or   Not all compliments help. Some miss   ourselves. Not the loud affirmations
           judgment builds trust.          the mark entirely.              pasted on mirrors, but quiet truths. “I did
             A manager who says, “I appreciated   Backhanded praise.       my best today.” “I handled more than I
           how you handled client feedback   Comparison-based compliments.   thought I could.”
           calmly,” isn’t just being nice. They’re   Comments that focus only on appear-
           reinforcing values. They’re also offering   ance or productivity.   A small habit with lasting impact
           emotional safety, which allows people to   “You look tired but still pretty.”   Imagine if compliments were treated
           take risks without fear of humiliation.   “You’re better than most people at   like emotional hygiene. Not rare re-
             In leadership circles, there’s growing   this.”               wards, but regular care. Something we
           awareness that kindness isn’t weakness.   “You’re amazing when you don’t   practiced intentionally, without over-
           It’s infrastructure. Compliments are part   overthink.”         thinking.
           of that structure, quietly supporting per-  These don’t soothe. They confuse.   The world wouldn’t suddenly be-
           formance and mental well-being at the   They can reinforce insecurity rather than   come gentle. But it might become more
           same time.                      ease it.                        breathable. Words won’t fix everything.
                                             Healing compliments respect the   They won’t erase trauma or injustice.
           Parenting, teaching and shaping   whole person. They don’t come with   But in moments of strain, they can offer
           inner voices                    conditions or hidden instructions. They   first aid. A pause. A reminder of worth. I
             Many of us still hear the voices that   aren’t about control. They’re about ac-  still remember a sentence someone once
           shaped us early. A teacher who once   knowledgment.             said to me, years ago, after a difficult as-
           said, “You’re good at explaining things.”                       signment. It wasn’t dramatic. Just, “You
           A parent who noticed persistence rather   Learning to give what we also   have a way of making complex things
           than results. Those words don’t fade.   need                    understandable.” I didn’t frame it or post
           They become internal companions.   Many people who struggle to accept   about it. I carried it. Still do. That’s the
             Compliments given to children and   compliments are also the ones who give   quiet power of healing words. They
           young adults have a long shelf life.   them sparingly. There’s vulnerability on   don’t shout. They stay. ■

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[ANALYSIS

































           The Last Signature


                                                                           legal documents, school notebooks, all
           The future of                                                   bore the intimate stamp of the writer’s
                                                                           hand.
                                                                              Ask an older generation about their
                                                                           first signature and many will smile. It
                                                                           was practiced, perfected, sometimes re-
           writing by hand                                                 Signing your name felt like crossing a
                                                                           hearsed in the margins of notebooks.
                                                                           threshold into adulthood. You were offi-
                                                                           cially someone.
                                                                              Today, that ritual is fading quietly,
                                                                           without protest.
           One day, signing your name by hand may feel unusual.
                                                                           Click here to agree
           Almost ceremonial. You might pause, smile and think                Digital signatures are efficient. Bio-
                                                                           metrics are secure. Fingerprints, facial
           about how rarely you do this anymore. The pen might             recognition and iris scans don’t forget,
                                                                           smudge or change with mood or age. In
           feel heavier. By Rohan Kapoor                                   offices and courtrooms across the world,
                                                                           they save time and reduce fraud. Few
                                                                           would argue against their convenience.
                                                                              Yet something subtle is lost in the ex-
                  hen was the last time you   once a quiet declaration of self, is begin-  change.
                  signed your name slowly, de-  ning to feel like a relic.    A handwritten signature takes time. It
           Wliberately, aware of the curve                                 asks for attention, however brief. It’s
           of every letter? For many of us, the an-  A gesture that meant something   physical, slightly risky, occasionally im-
           swer is unsettlingly vague. A hurried   For centuries, handwriting carried   perfect. Digital authorization, by con-
           scrawl on a delivery slip. A rushed sig-  weight far beyond words. A signature   trast, is frictionless. A checkbox replaces
           nature at a bank counter. Or perhaps   wasn’t just proof of identity. It was char-  intention. Consent becomes procedural.
           nothing at all. Increasingly, our consent   acter on paper. The firmness of a line   Does that matter? In practical terms,
           is given with a click, a tap, a thumb   suggested confidence. The flourish   maybe not. But emotionally, culturally,
           pressed against glass. The signature,   hinted at pride, even vanity. Love letters,   it does.

           24                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[“




                                                                             A handwritten

                                                                             signature asks us

                                                                             to slow down. To be

                                                                             present. To mean

                                                                             what we approve.”


            “



            When consent

            becomes a click,

            what happens to

            intention?”



           The brain remembers the hand
             Neuroscience has long suggested that
           writing by hand engages the brain differ-
           ently from typing. When we write, mul-
           tiple regions activate at once, those   amnesia.                drafts. Or why people treasure notes
           linked to memory, motor skills and com-  What happens when future genera-  scribbled by loved ones long after text
           prehension. Students who take hand-  tions encounter handwritten archives,   messages are deleted.
           written notes often retain information   diaries, marginal notes in books? Will   Handwriting carries presence. You
           better. The act itself slows thinking in a   they feel connected, or simply ex-  can see the pressure, the pause, the tre-
           useful way.                     cluded?                         mor. A signature written by someone
             Signatures, though brief, are part of                         who’s nervous looks different from one
           that embodied cognition. They’re per-  Adaptation, not extinction   written in confidence. That honesty is
           sonal symbols, rehearsed and remem-  It’s tempting to frame this as a battle   hard to replicate digitally.
           bered. Removing them entirely isn’t just   between old and new. Pen versus screen.   Perhaps that’s why the last signature
           a change in habit. It alters how we inter-  Ink versus algorithm. But history rarely   won’t disappear entirely. It will retreat
           act with language, identity and commit-  works that way. Technologies don’t   to the margins, then resurface where
           ment.                           usually erase what came before. They   meaning matters more than speed.
             And no biometric scan, however pre-  reposition it.
           cise, captures hesitation. Or intention.   The signature may no longer be cen-  A final thought
                                           tral to daily transactions, but that doesn’t   One day, signing your name by hand
           The fading script of identity   mean it’s meaningless. It might become   may feel unusual. Almost ceremonial.
             There’s another quiet consequence.   ceremonial. Symbolic. Reserved for mo-  You might pause, smile and think about
           Handwriting is deeply individual. Two   ments that demand reflection rather than   how rarely you do this anymore. The
           people may type the same sentence in   speed. Wills. Letters. Personal agree-  pen might feel heavier. The moment,
           identical fonts, but no two handwritten   ments. Creative work.   strangely intimate.
           signatures are truly alike. As writing by   In a world of instant validation,   And maybe that’s okay.
           hand recedes, a layer of human variation   handwriting could regain value precisely   The future of writing by hand isn’t
           disappears with it.             because it’s slower.            about resisting technology. It’s about re-
             Already, many young adults struggle                           membering that not everything mean-
           to read cursive. Some schools have   Why some still hold on     ingful needs to be optimized. Some
           stopped teaching it altogether, favoring   There’s a reason many professionals   things deserve time. A pause. A line
           keyboards over pens. Efficiency wins.   still keep fountain pens on their desks.   drawn slowly, by a human hand, saying
           Time is saved. But the cost is cultural   Or why authors insist on handwritten   quietly: I was here. ■

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[PROFILE



























           The rhythm king O. P. Nayyar



           The beat that




           changed Bollywood



                                                                           heavily on violins and sweeping ar-
           O. P. Nayyar didn’t invent rhythm in Bollywood, but he          rangements, Nayyar foregrounded
                                                                           rhythm instruments. The dholak wasn’t
           gave it a new authority. He made it central. He made it         shy. The bongos didn’t whisper. The
                                                                           claps snapped. His songs felt as if they
           stylish. He made it impossible to ignore. By Ishita Desai       were walking briskly, not strolling.
                                                                              Think of “Mera Naam Chin Chin
                                                                           Chu” from Howrah Bridge. It doesn’t
                                                                           unfold politely. It struts. Or “Yeh Hai
                  hat makes a song unforgetta-  slightly rebellious.       Bombay Meri Jaan”, where the city it-
                  ble? Is it the melody you hum   Born on January 16, 1926, a date his   self seems to pulse in time. These were-
           Wdays later, or the rhythm that   admirers quietly mark every year, Nay-  n’t just songs. They were soundscapes of
           quietly taps your foot without asking   yar didn’t just compose songs. He   urban confidence.
           permission? In Hindi cinema, melodies   changed the way Bollywood moved to
           have often taken the spotlight. But once   music.               Rhythm as personality
           in a while, someone comes along who                                What set Nayyar apart was not just
           makes rhythm the hero. Someone who   A sound that arrived fully formed   technical skill, but attitude. His rhythms
           proves that a song doesn’t have to flow,   Many composers evolve gradually,   had character. They could be cheeky, ro-
           it can swing, skip, tease, even argue a   polishing their style film by film. Nay-  mantic, street-smart, or teasing, some-
           little. That someone was O. P. Nayyar.   yar didn’t seem interested in that jour-  times all at once. He understood that
             Listen closely to his songs and you’ll   ney. When he arrived, his sound was al-  rhythm could tell a story even before a
           notice something almost mischievous.   ready sharp, confident and   word was sung.
           The beat doesn’t just support the tune. It   unmistakable. Punjabi folk rhythms,   In films like C.I.D. and Kashmir Ki
           challenges it. It flirts with it. It dares the   Latin percussion, jazzy brass sections   Kali, the beats added layers to the narra-
           singer to keep up. Long before playlists,   and crisp beats came together in a way   tive. Suspense became sharper. Ro-
           remixes, or electronic loops, Nayyar   Hindi cinema hadn’t quite heard before.   mance felt lighter, more flirtatious.
           made rhythm feel modern, playful and   At a time when orchestras leaned   Dance numbers didn’t feel ornamental;

           26                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Why his rhythm


                                                                                 felt different

                                                                                O. P. Nayyar’s signature lay in
                                                                              his fearless use of percussion.
                                                                              Punjabi folk beats, dholak pat-
                                                                              terns, bongos and Western drum
                                                                              kits often took center stage, while
                                                                              strings played a supporting role.
                                                                              He borrowed from jazz and Latin
                                                                              music without copying them,
                                                                              adapting global influences into
                                                                              something distinctly Indian. His
                                                                              arrangements were crisp, unclut-
                                                                              tered and driven by tempo. Si-
                                                                              lence mattered too. Pauses be-
                                                                              tween beats created tension and
                                                                              charm. This approach gave his
                                                                              songs a conversational quality, as
                                                                              if the music itself was speaking.
                                                                              It’s why many of his composi-
                                                                              tions still feel fresh in an age of
                                                                              digital excess.


                                                                              Later, Asha Bhosle became the voice
                                                                           most closely associated with Nayyar’s
                                                                           style. He challenged her. Pushed her.
                                                                           Asked her to sing against the beat,
                                                                           around it, sometimes slightly ahead of it.
                                                                           The result was magic. Songs like “Aaiye
                                                                           Meherbaan” or “Yeh Hai Reshmi Zulfon
                                                                           Ka Andhera” shimmer with control and
                                                                           spontaneity.
                                                                              Interestingly, Nayyar famously chose
                                                                           not to work with Lata Mangeshkar, be-
                                                                           lieving her voice didn’t suit his rhythmic
                                                                           sensibility. It was a controversial deci-
                                                                           sion, but it also revealed his uncompro-
                                                                           mising artistic instinct. He knew exactly
                                                                           what he wanted.
            “                              their screen presence. Audiences trusted   A difficult man with clear
                                           him because his tunes stayed fresh long

                                                                           principles
                                           after the theatre lights came on.
                                                                              By most accounts, Nayyar wasn’t
            His rhythm walked
                                           The voices that danced to his beat
                                             A rhythm-centric composer needs   easy to work with. He was stubborn,
                                                                           proud and deeply protective of his
            ahead of the                   singers who can ride the wave without   music. He didn’t bend easily to pro-
                                           getting drowned. Nayyar found them. Or   ducers or trends. When disagreements
            melody and dared               perhaps, he shaped them.        arose, he walked away, sometimes at
                                             His collaborations with Geeta Dutt
                                                                           great personal cost.
                                           remain among the most electrifying in   This rigidity, admirable to some and
            it to follow.”                 Hindi cinema. Her voice had bite,   frustrating to others, partly explains why
                                           warmth and fearless expression. To-  his output slowed earlier than expected.
                                           gether, they created songs that still   As musical tastes shifted toward lush ar-
           they felt essential.            sound alive, not archived. There was   rangements and later electronic sounds,
             Directors trusted him because his   chemistry there, both musical and per-  Nayyar refused to dilute his core style.
           music carried scenes forward. Actors   sonal, though it eventually ended in   He didn’t chase relevance. He waited for
           trusted him because his songs enhanced   painful silence.       it to come to him.

           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[“




            In a melody-driven

            industry, Nayyar

            made the beat the

            star. Decades later,

            his songs still

            sound like they’re

            moving forward.”


             And when it didn’t, he accepted ob-
           scurity with surprising calm.   Nayyar often describe his music as   thority. He made it central. He made it
                                           “surprisingly modern.” The beats feel   stylish. He made it impossible to ig-
           Silence after the storm         clean. The arrangements feel unclut-  nore.
             One of the most striking chapters of   tered. The energy feels honest. In an era   There’s a quiet lesson in his story.
           Nayyar’s life is how abruptly the music   of layered production and digital per-  Trends come and go. Technology
           stopped. After dominating the charts   fection, his songs breathe.   evolves. But clarity of vision lasts. Nay-
           through the 1950s and 1960s, he grad-  Music students study his work to un-  yar knew who he was, musically and
           ually faded from the industry. Not be-  derstand how rhythm can lead, not fol-  personally. He didn’t smooth out his
           cause his talent dimmed, but because   low. Cultural historians point to his   edges and he didn’t apologize for his
           the ecosystem around him changed.   compositions as markers of a changing   beat.
             For years, he lived away from the   urban India, confident, curious and   Maybe that’s why, decades later,
           limelight, largely forgotten by an indus-  slightly defiant.    when one of his songs comes on, some-
           try that rarely looks back. Yet, even in   And for older listeners, his songs are   thing still stirs. A foot taps. A smile
           silence, his songs continued to play. On   time machines. They recall evenings,   forms. The rhythm takes over. And for
           radios. At weddings. In memory.   black-and-white screens and the thrill of   a moment, Bollywood moves the way
             There’s something deeply poetic   hearing something new.      O. P. Nayyar taught it to. ■
           about that. The man stepped away, but
           the rhythm didn’t.              The rhythm that never really
                                           ended
           Why his music still matters       O. P. Nayyar didn’t invent rhythm in  The man behind

             Today, younger listeners discovering   Bollywood, but he gave it a new au-
                                                                                    the beat

                                                                                Nayyar’s personal life was as
                                                                              sharply defined as his music. He
                                                                              was known to be stubborn, proud
                                                                              and unwilling to compromise,
                                                                              even when it cost him work. He
                                                                              chose singers carefully, avoided
                                                                              trends he didn’t believe in and
                                                                              walked away from collaborations
                                                                              when principles clashed. This ri-
                                                                              gidity shortened his active years
                                                                              in cinema, but it also protected
                                                                              his artistic identity. He didn’t
                                                                              fade into mediocrity. He stopped
                                                                              on his own terms. In an industry
                                                                              built on adaptation, Nayyar stood
                                                                              out by refusing to bend. His si-
                                                                              lence, in many ways, was as in-
                                                                              tentional as his sound.


           28                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                 January 16-31, 2026







           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Momentum builds in professional matters. Your   Libra, creativity and romance reawaken. You’re
                     leadership is noticed, but collaboration will take   reminded that joy is not a distraction, it’s nour-
                     you further than force. In personal life, patience   ishment but avoid carelessness. Express yourself
                     brings understanding. Avoid rushing decisions;   freely without hesitation. Emotional openness
                     timing is on your side.                         deepens connections.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Long-term goals feel clearer now. Career        Scorpio, home and emotional security take prior-
                     ambitions gain structure and support may come   ity. Family matters or personal foundations need
                     from an unexpected source. Emotionally, stability   attention, be careful. Career remains steady, but
                     comforts you. Trust consistency, it’s working in   inner peace becomes your true focus, be atten-
                     your favor.                                     tive.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Gemini, a desire for expansion returns. Travel   Sagittarius, communication flows smoothly.
                     plans, studies, or fresh perspectives energize   Writing, teaching, or negotiations progress well.
                     you. Conversations spark inspiration. Relation-  Short journeys or reconnections bring insight.
                     ships benefit when curiosity replaces assump-   Speak honestly, but listen just as carefully don’t
                     tions.                                          lose alertness.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Cancer, emotional depth intensifies, pushing you   Capricorn, financial clarity improves as the
                     toward honest reflection. Shared responsibilities   month ends. Practical planning strengthens con-
                     or finances may need review, be careful. Let go   fidence. Emotionally, you feel grounded. Let go
                     of old fears, growth lies on the other side of vul-  of the need to control everything, trust what
                     nerability.                                     you’ve built.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, partnerships demand balance. Whether per-  Aquarius, your season begins, bringing fresh
                     sonal or professional, cooperation becomes es-  energy and self-awareness. New ideas take shape
                     sential. A meaningful conversation reshapes ex-  and others respond positively to your vision.
                     pectations. Choose understanding over pride.    Lead with authenticity rather than rebellion.
                     Enjoy the time with passion.                    Alertness will be beneficial.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, work routines and health habits require   Pisces, a quiet, introspective phase helps you
                     refinement. Small adjustments now bring lasting   reset emotionally. Rest, reflection and solitude
                     benefits. Stay organized but avoid self-criticism,   prepare you for renewed action. Trust that still-
                     don’t lose alertness. Progress doesn’t need per-  ness now will bring clarity soon. Strengthening
                     fection.                                        resolve and allowing quiet confidence to grow.


           JANUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Allegations, raids and democratic
                                           online and faster grievance redressal
           trust
                                           mechanisms.
             The recent raid involving Indian
                                                                           exploit gig workers who lack social se-
                                           Kavita Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           Political Action Committee (I-PAC) in   should encourage stricter self-regulation   lines normalise dangerous driving and
           Kolkata, and Mamata Banerjee’s   India                          curity and bargaining power. Conven-
           allegation that the Enforcement                                 ience should not come at the cost of
           Directorate acted as part of a conspiracy to                    human safety. As India builds its digital
           seize her party’s documents, raises serious   A grim failure of compassion   economy, ethical responsibility must
           concerns for India’s democratic   The shocking killing of nearly 500   guide innovation. Delivery platforms
           framework. With the matter now reaching   stray dogs in villages across Telangana   should prioritise fair timelines, worker
           the Supreme Court of India, institutional   within a single week is a disturbing re-  welfare, and road safety over aggressive
           credibility is firmly under the spotlight.   flection of how fear and neglect can turn   marketing claims. True progress lies not
                                           into cruelty. While concerns about   in speed alone, but in sustainability and
             While investigative agencies must be   safety, rabies, and attacks cannot be dis-  compassion.
           free to perform their duties, political   missed, mass killings are neither hu-  Dolly Anand, Delhi, India
           neutrality and procedural fairness are   mane nor legal solutions. They expose
           equally vital. Allegations of misuse of   serious gaps in animal welfare govern-
           central agencies, if left unaddressed, risk   ance, public awareness, and local ad-  A voice that will echo forever
           eroding public confidence. It is impera-  ministration.            The news of the untimely death of
           tive that the judiciary ensures transpar-  India has clear animal protection   Prashant Tamang has cast a shadow of
           ency, protects constitutional rights, and   laws and proven methods such as steril-  grief across the nation. For millions, he
           upholds the rule of law—free from po-  isation, vaccination, and community dog   was not just a reality show winner but a
           litical vendetta or perception thereof.   management. Ignoring these measures   symbol of hope—an ordinary man
           Naveen Kumar, Delhi, India      and resorting to violence only deepens   whose sincerity and soulful voice
                                           social insensitivity and lawlessness.   touched hearts far beyond the stage. His
                                           Local bodies must be held accountable   journey from humble beginnings to na-
           Protecting digital dignity      for failing to implement scientific and   tional recognition inspired countless
             The recent order of the Delhi High   ethical solutions. Civil society, veteri-  young dreamers who believed talent
           Court directing the removal of unwanted   narians, and governments must work to-  could still triumph over circumstance.
           and misleading images of YouTuber   gether to prevent such tragedies from re-  Prashant’s music carried emotion,
           Bhuvan Bam is a timely reaffirmation of   curring. How a society treats its most   humility, and an unmistakable warmth
           the right to privacy in the digital age.   vulnerable beings says much about its   that made him deeply relatable. His
           Coming after similar relief granted to   moral health.          passing is a reminder of how fragile life
           public figures like Salman Khan and   Suresh C. Sharma, Delhi, India   is, even for those who seem eternally
           Aishwarya Rai Bachchan, the ruling                              alive through their art. As admirers
           highlights that fame does not dilute per-                       mourn his loss, his songs will continue
           sonal dignity.                  Speed vs safety on our streets   to resonate, reminding us that true artists
             In an era where images are morphed,   The Indian government’s push to   never really leave us.
           recycled, and circulated endlessly for   companies like Blinkit and Swiggy to   Ravina Kumari, Dehradun, Uttarak-
           clicks, reputational harm can be swift   remove the 10-minute delivery deadline   hand, India
           and irreversible. The court’s intervention   is a welcome and necessary step. Hyper-
           sends a strong message to platforms and   fast delivery promises may excite con-
           content creators about accountability   sumers, but they quietly transfer pres-  Letters (limited to one hundred
           and ethical boundaries. More impor-  sure onto delivery riders, often forcing   words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           tantly, it reassures citizens that the law   them to risk lives on crowded roads.   Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           can still protect individual identity   In cities already grappling with traf-
           against digital misuse. Such judgments   fic congestion and accidents, such dead-


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Kübra Bayraktar





     The lake and the trees were silent witnesses
     to passing time. - Haruki Murakami]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>