<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                       VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 11  I  JULY 01 2024       ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             21



                                                            11













                                                             5                                       15
















           4-Editorial: Investing in our collective        21-Chocolate's universal appeal
           future                                          24-The bicycle's journey and impact

           5-Global initiatives and the path               29-Horoscopes

           forward                                         30-Letters

           9-The Talwar's unique population
           crusade

           11-A beacon of hope and opportunity

           15-The hidden threats to global health

           18-Art and science of transformation









           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[World Population
     EDITORIAL  Investing in                                                        Editor-in-Chief




                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           our collective future                                                  Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                              n July 11th each year, we mark    Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                              World Population Day, a moment to
                                        Oreflect on the profound implications       Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        of global population trends and to reaffirm
                                        our commitment to sustainable            Digital Strategy Editor
                                        development. As the world's population       Sushil Kumar
                                        surpasses 8 billion, this day serves as a
                                        crucial reminder of the challenges and    Social Media Editor
                                        opportunities that come with our growing   Vishakha Sharma
                                        numbers.
                                           Population growth affects every facet of   Art & Graphics Director
                                        human existence, from food security and      Vipin Agarwal
                                        healthcare to environmental sustainability
                                        and economic development. It is a dynamic
           force that demands proactive, innovative solutions. The theme of this year's World
           Population Day, "Empowering People, Developing Nations," underscores the   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           transformative power of education, gender equality, and accessible healthcare in
           shaping a brighter future for all.                                D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
             Education lies at the heart of sustainable development. When individuals   Editor, United News of India, New
           especially women and girls are empowered through education, they gain the   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           knowledge and skills to make informed decisions about their health, family size, and   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           economic opportunities. Education not only enhances individual well-being but also   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           strengthens communities and economies, paving the way for inclusive growth.   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
             Gender equality is another essential pillar of population management. By ensuring   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           women's rights and opportunities, we can break the cycle of poverty, reduce fertility   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           rates, and improve maternal and child health outcomes. When women have access to
           reproductive health services and can participate fully in society, entire communities   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           thrive.
             Healthcare accessibility is fundamental to achieving population stability. Access   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           to family planning services, maternal and child healthcare, and disease prevention
           programs are essential for promoting healthy societies.              Phone +91 20 40199102
             Environmental sustainability cannot be overlooked in our efforts to manage   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           population growth. As we strive to meet the needs of a growing population, we must   Baner Road,
           adopt sustainable practices that conserve natural resources, protect biodiversity, and   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           mitigate climate change.                                              Email revoir@post.com
             The campaign led by Dinesh Talwar and his wife Disha cannot be forgotten. They   Website www.revoir.in
           have been running it for the last 30 years, walking backwards through the streets of
           over 300 cities.
             On this World Population Day, let us recommit ourselves to fostering a world   Legal Advisor
           where every individual has the opportunity to thrive. By investing in education,   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           promoting gender equality, expanding access to healthcare, and embracing
           sustainable development practices, we can shape a future that is equitable, resilient,   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           and prosperous for generations to come. Together, let's build a world where the   all rights reserved. This publication
           potential of every person is realized, and where our collective actions pave the way   may not be reproduced in any form
           for a sustainable future.                                              without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY











































           World Population Day



           Global initiatives and







           the path forward








           By Naina Kapoor


                  orld Population Day, ob-  rise, it becomes increasingly important   world’s population reached an estimated
                  served annually on July 11,   to reflect on the challenges and opportu-  five billion people. This milestone
           Wserves as a crucial reminder   nities that come with this growth and to   prompted the United Nations to estab-
           of the urgent need to address global pop-  explore strategies for ensuring a sustain-  lish a day dedicated to raising awareness
           ulation issues. This day, established by   able and equitable future.   about population issues and their impli-
           the United Nations in 1989, emphasizes                          cations for development and the envi-
           the significance of population trends and   The history and significance   ronment. World Population Day aims to
           their profound impact on sustainable de-  The idea for World Population Day   highlight the importance of family plan-
           velopment, health, and the environment.   originated from the Day of Five Billion,   ning, gender equality, poverty, maternal
           As the global population continues to   observed on July 11, 1987, when the   health, and human rights.

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Family planning and reproductive
         High-rise buildings towering over a bustling urban landscape
                                                                           health are central to managing pop-
                                                                           ulation growth and improving the qual-
                                                                           ity of life for individuals and com-
                                                                           munities. Access to contraception,
                                                                           education, and healthcare empowers in-
                                                                           dividuals to make informed choices
                                                                           about their reproductive health and
                                                                           family size. Family planning helps re-
                                                                           duce unintended pregnancies, lower ma-
                                                                           ternal and child mortality rates, and im-
                                                                           prove economic outcomes for families.

                                                                           Barriers to family planning
                                                                              Despite the importance of family
                                                                           planning, many barriers still exist. Cul-
                                                                           tural, religious, and social factors can
                                                                           limit access to contraception and repro-
                                                                           ductive health services. In some regions,
                                                                           there is a lack of availability of modern
                                           resources. Achieving sustainable devel-  contraceptives, inadequate healthcare in-
           Current global population trends   opment requires addressing the complex   frastructure, and insufficient education
             As of 2024, the world’s population is   interplay between population growth,   about reproductive health. Addressing
           estimated to be around 8 billion people.   economic development, and environ-  these barriers is essential for achieving
           This rapid growth presents several chal-  mental sustainability.   global population goals.
           lenges, including the strain on natural
           resources, increased demand for food   Urbanization and population   Success stories in family planning
           and water, and the need for adequate   density                     There have been significant suc-
           healthcare and education. The pop-  Urbanization is a significant trend as-  cesses in family planning initiatives
           ulation growth rate has been slowing in   sociated with population growth. More   worldwide. Countries like Bangladesh,
           recent years, particularly in developed   than half of the world’s population now   Iran, and Thailand have implemented ef-
           countries, but many developing nations   lives in urban areas, a proportion ex-  fective family planning programs that
           continue to experience high birth rates   pected to increase in the coming dec-  have led to substantial reductions in fer-
           and rapid population increases.   ades. While urbanization can drive eco-  tility rates and improvements in mater-
                                           nomic growth and development, it also   nal and child health. These success
           Population growth and           poses challenges such as overcrowding,   stories demonstrate the potential for pos-
           sustainable development         inadequate infrastructure, and increased   itive change when comprehensive and
             Sustainable development is intrinsi-  pollution. Managing urban growth sus-  culturally sensitive family planning pro-
           cally linked to population dynamics. A   tainably is crucial for ensuring healthy   grams are implemented.
           rapidly growing population can exacer-  and livable cities.
           bate environmental degradation, in-                             Gender equality and women’s
           crease greenhouse gas emissions, and   The role of family planning and   empowerment
           lead to the overexploitation of natural   reproductive health      Gender equality and women’s em-
                                                                           powerment are critical components of
                                                                           addressing population issues. Empower-
                                                                           ing women through education, economic
                                                                           opportunities, and reproductive rights
                                                                           leads to smaller family sizes and im-
                                                                           proved health and well-being for women
                                                                           and children. When women have access
                                                                           to education and economic resources,
                                                                           they are more likely to make informed
                                                                           choices about their reproductive health
                                                                           and contribute to the development of
                                                                           their communities.

                                                                           Education and economic
         Crowded cityscapes                                                tive tools for empowering women and
                                                                           opportunities
                                                                              Education is one of the most effec-
                                                                           reducing fertility rates. Educated women
                                                                           are more likely to delay marriage and
                                                                           childbirth, have fewer children, and in-

           6                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[style changes associated with population
                                                                           growth can increase the prevalence of
                                                                           non-communicable diseases such as dia-
                                                                           betes, heart disease, and cancer.
                                                                           Strengthening healthcare systems and
                                                                           promoting healthy lifestyles are essen-
                                                                           tial for addressing these health chal-
                                                                           lenges.

                                                                           Environmental sustainability and
                                                                           population growth
                                                                              The relationship between population
                                                                           growth and environmental sustainability
                                                                           is complex. A growing population in-
         Deforestation crisis                                              creases the demand for natural re-
                                                                           sources, leading to deforestation, loss of
                                                                           biodiversity, and increased greenhouse
                                                                           gas emissions. Sustainable development
                                                                           requires balancing the needs of a grow-
                                                                           protect the environment and mitigate cli-
           vest more in the health and education of   quate access to medical services and re-  ing population with the imperative to
           their children. Economic opportunities   sources. Ensuring that healthcare sys-  mate change.
           for women, including access to jobs and   tems can meet the needs of growing
           financial resources, also play a crucial   populations is essential for improving   Food Security and agriculture
           role in enabling women to make choices   health outcomes and achieving global   Food security is a critical issue linked
           about their reproductive health and   health goals.             to population growth. Ensuring that a
           family size.                                                    growing population has access to suffi-
                                           Maternal and child health       cient, safe, and nutritious food requires
           Addressing gender-based           Maternal and child health are particu-  sustainable agricultural practices and ef-
           violence                        larly affected by population growth.   ficient food distribution systems. Inno-
             Gender-based violence is a signifi-  High fertility rates and closely spaced   vations in agriculture, such as improved
           cant barrier to women’s empowerment   pregnancies can increase the risk of ma-  crop varieties and sustainable farming
           and reproductive health. Violence and   ternal and child mortality. Access to   techniques, are essential for meeting the
           discrimination against women can limit   quality maternal and child healthcare,   food needs of a growing global pop-
           their access to education, healthcare, and   including prenatal and postnatal care,   ulation.
           economic opportunities. Addressing   immunizations, and nutrition, is crucial
           gender-based violence and promoting   for improving health outcomes and re-
           gender equality are essential for creating   ducing mortality rates.
           an environment where women can make
           informed choices about their lives and   Addressing communicable and
           families.                       non-communicable diseases
                                             Population growth can also influence
           The impact of population growth   the spread of communicable diseases
           on health                       and the burden of non-communicable
             Population growth has a profound   diseases. Overcrowding, poor sanitation,
           impact on health systems and outcomes.   and limited access to healthcare can fa-
           Rapid population growth can strain   cilitate the spread of infectious diseases.
           healthcare systems, leading to inade-  At the same time, urbanization and life-





















           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Water resources and sanitation
             Access to clean water and adequate
           sanitation is another significant challenge
           associated with population growth. A
           growing population increases the demand
           for water, leading to overextraction of
           water resources and contamination of
           water supplies. Ensuring access to clean
           water and sanitation requires investments                                                       Healthcare professionals offering family planning
           in infrastructure, efficient water
           management, and policies that promote
           water conservation and pollution
           prevention.

           Climate change and resource
           management
             Climate change exacerbates the chal-  vulnerable populations.   complex challenges associated with
           lenges of population growth and envi-                           population growth.
           ronmental sustainability. Rising tem-  The Role of policy and
           peratures, changing precipitation   international cooperation   National population policies
           patterns, and extreme weather events   Effective policy and international co-  Many countries have developed na-
           can impact agriculture, water resources,   operation are essential for addressing   tional population policies to address
           and human health. Addressing climate   population issues and promoting sus-  their specific population challenges.
           change requires coordinated global ef-  tainable development. Governments, in-  These policies often include measures to
           forts to reduce greenhouse gas emis-  ternational organizations, and civil soci-  promote family planning, improve
           sions, promote renewable energy, and   ety must work together to develop and   healthcare, and support gender equality.
           implement adaptive measures to protect   implement policies that address the   Successful population policies require
                                                                           political commitment, adequate funding,
                                                                           and collaboration with stakeholders at
                                                                           all levels.
         Green spaces in the urban environment                             for addressing population issues that

                                                                           International cooperation and
                                                                           global initiatives
                                                                              International cooperation is crucial

                                                                           transcend national borders. Global ini-
                                                                           tiatives, such as the Sustainable Devel-
                                                                           opment Goals (SDGs), provide a frame-
                                                                           work for addressing population and
                                                                           development challenges. The SDGs in-
                                                                           clude targets related to health, gender
                                                                           equality, and environmental sustainabil-
                                                                           ity, all of which are essential for manag-
                                                                           ing population growth and promoting
                                                                           sustainable development.
                                                                              World Population Day serves as a re-
                                                                           minder of the importance of addressing
                                                                           population issues for a sustainable and
         Students actively participating in a classroom                    equality, health, and environmental sus-
                                                                           equitable future. As the global pop-
                                                                           ulation continues to grow, it is essential
                                                                           to focus on family planning, gender

                                                                           tainability. By empowering individuals,
                                                                           particularly women, through education,
                                                                           economic opportunities, and reproduc-
                                                                           tive rights, and by promoting sustainable
                                                                           development practices, we can create a
                                                                           future where all people have the oppor-
                                                                           tunity to thrive. Effective policies and
                                                                           international cooperation are key to
                                                                           achieving these goals and ensuring a
                                                                           better world for future generations. ■

           8                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Backwards for a Better Future




           The Talwar's unique                                                                                   PERSPECTIVE






           population crusade







           By Staff Writer


             n the bustling city of Meerut, a
             unique and determined couple, Di-
           Inesh and Disha Talwar, have been
           making headlines with their unconven-
           tional approach to raising awareness
           about a critical issue: population control.
           Since 1994, they have been walking
           backwards through the streets of over
           300 cities, garnering attention and
           sparking conversations about the press-
           ing need for population management in
           India. Their journey, filled with chal-
           lenges, hopes, and unwavering ded-
           ication, is a testament to their commit-
           ment to a cause they hold dear.

           The genesis of a movement
             "It was 1994 when a procession was
           taken out in the municipal corporation,"
           Dinesh recalls. "The officials said that
           the population of your city is so much
           and the sanitation workers are not doing
           enough. Another official said that the
           population of India is so much that no
           one is ready to speak. This struck me,
           and I thought that I should work on the
           issue on which no one is working, and I
           started this campaign."
             Just four days after their marriage in
           1997, Disha Talwar joined her husband
           in this mission. Despite the challenges
           of raising a family, she remained ac-
           tively involved, even when their chil-
           dren, Simran and Yash, were young. To-                                                          Dinesh Talwar and his wife Disha advocating for population control
           gether, they adopted the symbolic act of
           walking backwards to represent the need
           for the government to take straightfor-
           ward actions regarding population con-
           trol.

           The campaign trail
             "We walk backwards so that the gov-
           ernment does straight work. The govern-
           ment spends billions of rupees on all the

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[problems but does not spend anything
           on population control," Dinesh explains.
           "We try to make people understand
           straight talk by walking backwards."
             Their unique method initially drew
           laughter and mockery from onlookers,
           but over time, it has garnered respect
           and support. "Experience says that ear-
           lier, 20 years ago, people used to laugh
           at us, and today they respect our work.
           At many places, we become a laughing
           stock, and some people even encourage                                                           People observing the Talwar couple's campaign
           us," Disha adds.
             Despite their efforts, the Talwars
           have faced significant obstacles in gain-
           ing the attention of the government. "We
           wrote more than one lakh letters to the
           previous governments. The government
           never showed seriousness on this issue,
           but our writing is still going on," says
           Dinesh.                         memorandums to the Prime Minister on
                                           that day. Despite their relentless efforts,
           The need for serious action     they have yet to secure a meeting with
             "Whether it is the government or the   any Prime Minister. "In the last 31 years,
           leader of any political party, they always   we have asked for time to meet all the
           avoid this biggest social evil because   Prime Ministers of the country, but till
           political parties see it through the lens of   date no Prime Minister has given us
           religion," Dinesh laments. "We say that   time to meet. We hope from the current
           these are the problems of the country   Prime Minister that he will give us time
           and not of religion."           to meet," Disha shares.                                         Dinesh Talwar, the crusader
             The Talwars firmly believe that adop-
           ting aspects of China's population policy   A call to action
           could be beneficial for India. "China's   "This movement is not ours. People
           policy can be proved to be effective in   should stand with our movement, and
           India because if a two-child law is made   every person of the country, irrespective   ing financial constraints. "We closed our
           in India, then the population of the   of his religion, should raise his voice   business to run this movement. Despite
           country will be controlled in the next   that now a law for population control   the lack of money, we continued this
           few years," Dinesh asserts.     should be made in the country," Dinesh   movement and whatever we earned, we
                                           urges. "If the damages caused by pop-  invested in this movement because the
           Future plans and continued hope   ulation are mentioned in the syllabus,   solution to all the problems of the coun-
             On World Population Day, the Tal-  then the coming generation should take   try is population control," Dinesh re-
           wars plan to take out a journey from   it seriously."           flects.
           Delhi to Varanasi, Modi ji's parliamen-  Over the past 28 years, the Talwars   As they continue their journey, Di-
           tary constituency, and will send 365   have faced numerous challenges, includ-  nesh and Disha Talwar remain hopeful
                                                                           that their message will reach those in
                                                                           power. "Through Revoir magazine, I
                                                                           want to give only this message: just 70
                                                                           kilometers away from the Prime Minis-
                                                                           ter, we husband-wife and our children
                                                                           are working for a national mission, and
                                                                           our message is not reaching him. This
                                                                           happens only in India that for 31 years,
                                                                           we have been continuously asking for
                                                                           time to meet the Prime Minister, but till
                                                                           date, no Prime Minister has given us
                                                                           time. Revoir magazine can be helpful in
                                                                           getting our message to the Prime Minis-
                                                                           ter," Dinesh concludes.
         Dinesh and Disha                                                  verance but a call to action for every cit-
                                                                              Their story is not just one of perse-
                                                                           izen to recognize and address the issue
                                                                           of population control, ensuring a sus-
                                                                           tainable future for the nation. ■

           10                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT





































           WORLD YOUTH SKILLS DAY



           A beacon of hope and






           opportunity








           By Siddharth Mehta

                                                                           Assembly in 2014, recognizing the critical
             n a rapidly evolving world where   youth with the essential skills to meet   role of skills development in enhancing
             technology and innovation shape our   the demands of the job market, foster   the employability and productivity of
           Idaily lives, the youth stand at the   entrepreneurship, and drive socio-eco-  young people. The decision to dedicate a
           forefront of change, embodying hope,   nomic progress. As we delve into the   day to youth skills was driven by the
           energy, and boundless potential. Amidst   significance of World Youth Skills Day,   growing awareness of the global youth
           this dynamic backdrop, World Youth   we unravel the myriad ways in which   unemployment crisis. According to the
           Skills Day emerges as a beacon of hope   skill development serves as a catalyst   International Labour Organization (ILO),
           and opportunity, dedicated to empower-  for individual growth and societal ad-  young people are three times more likely
           ing young individuals with the skills   vancement.              to be unemployed than adults, and even
           necessary to navigate and thrive in an                          those who are employed often face
           ever-changing global landscape. Cele-  The genesis              precarious working conditions. By
           brated annually on July 15, this day un-  World Youth Skills Day was   highlighting the importance of equipping
           derscores the importance of equipping   established by the United Nations General

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[youth with relevant skills, World Youth
           Skills Day aims to bridge the gap between
           education and employment, fostering a
           more inclusive and equitable future.

           The importance of skill
           development
             Bridging the education-employ-                                                                Young people engaging in online courses
           ment gap: One of the primary objec-
           tives of World Youth Skills Day is to ad-
           dress the disconnect between the
           education system and the job market.
           Traditional education systems often em-
           phasize theoretical knowledge over
           practical skills, leaving many graduates
           unprepared for the demands of the
           workforce. By promoting vocational
           training and technical education, World
           Youth Skills Day advocates for a more
           holistic approach to learning that inte-
           grates academic knowledge with hands-
           on experience. This not only enhances
           the employability of young people but
           also ensures that they possess the critical                                                     Students exploring new prospects
           thinking, problem-solving, and technical
           skills required in various industries.

           Fostering entrepreneurship and
           innovation
             In addition to enhancing employabil-  business development workshops are in-  nomic disparities, empowering margin-
           ity, skill development plays a crucial   strumental in nurturing the entrepreneu-  alized and disadvantaged youth to break
           role in fostering entrepreneurship and   rial potential of young individuals, en-  the cycle of poverty and achieve upward
           innovation among youth. With the right   abling them to transform their ideas into   mobility. By ensuring that all young
           skills, young people can identify oppor-  impactful ventures.   people, regardless of their background,
           tunities, create innovative solutions, and                      have access to skill development pro-
           start their own businesses. This entrepre-  Promoting social inclusion and   grams, we can create a more inclusive
           neurial spirit not only contributes to eco-  equality           society where everyone has the chance
           nomic growth but also generates em-  World Youth Skills Day also empha-  to succeed and contribute to their com-
           ployment opportunities for others,   sizes the role of skill development in   munities.
           creating a ripple effect that benefits en-  promoting social inclusion and equality.
           tire communities. Initiatives like startup   Access to quality education and training   Global initiatives and success
           incubators, mentorship programs, and   opportunities can help bridge socio-eco-  stories
                                                                              United Nations initiatives: The
                                                                           United Nations, in collaboration with
                                                                           various international organizations, gov-
                                                                           ernments, and private sector partners,
                                                                           has launched several initiatives to pro-
         Exploring initiatives launched to promote youth skills
                                                                           mote youth skills development globally.
                                                                           The Global Initiative on Decent Jobs for
                                                                           Youth, for instance, aims to scale up ac-
                                                                           tion and impact in youth employment
                                                                           through multi-stakeholder partnerships.
                                                                           This initiative focuses on areas such as
                                                                           digital skills, green jobs, youth entrepre-
                                                                           neurship, and quality apprenticeships,
                                                                           aligning with the broader goals of the
                                                                           2030 Agenda for Sustainable Devel-
                                                                           opment.

                                                                           Skills for a resilient youth
                                                                              The COVID-19 pandemic has under-
                                                                           scored the importance of resilience and
                                                                           adaptability in the face of unprecedented

           12                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[aged skill development to transform
                                                                           their lives and communities. From tech-
                                                                           savvy entrepreneurs in Silicon Valley to
                                                                           skilled artisans in rural Africa, these
                                                                           stories exemplify the transformative
                                                                           power of skills. For instance, in India,
                                                                           the Skill India Mission has trained mil-
                                                                           lions of youth in various trades, empow-
                                                                           ering them to secure gainful employ-
                                                                           ment and contribute to the country's
                                                                           economic growth. Similarly, in Kenya,
                                                                           the Ajira Digital Program has provided
                                                                           thousands of young people with digital
         Craftsman at work                                                 work opportunities and build sustainable
                                                                           skills, enabling them to access online
                                                                           livelihoods.

                                                                           The role of stakeholders
                                                                              Governments play a pivotal role in
                                           challenges. In response, many organiza-  shaping the landscape of youth skills de-
                                           tions have pivoted their efforts to pro-  velopment. By formulating policies that
                                           vide young people with the skills needed   prioritize vocational training, technical
                                           to navigate the post-pandemic world.   education, and lifelong learning, govern-
                                           For example, online learning platforms   ments can create an enabling environ-
                                           and virtual training programs have   ment for skill development. Investing in
                                           gained prominence, offering courses in   quality education infrastructure, promot-
         Young woman working on a computer  their education and skill development   direction. Additionally, governments can
                                                                           ing public-private partnerships, and en-
                                           digital literacy, remote work skills, and
                                           mental health resilience. These initia-
                                                                           suring equitable access to training pro-
                                           tives ensure that youth can continue
                                                                           grams are essential steps in this
                                                                           collaborate with industries to identify
                                           despite disruptions, preparing them for
                                                                           emerging skill needs and tailor training
                                           the future of work.
                                                                           programs accordingly, ensuring that

                                                                           youth are equipped with relevant and in-
                                           Success stories from around the
                                           world
                                                                           demand skills.

                                             World Youth Skills Day is also an op-
                                                                           Educational institutions
                                           portunity to celebrate the success stories
                                                                              Educational institutions, including
                                           of young individuals who have lever-











                                                                                                           Team-building or leadership activities















           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[schools, colleges, and universities, are at
           the forefront of imparting knowledge
           and skills to young people. By adopting
           a multidisciplinary approach that inte-
           grates academic learning with practical
           experience, these institutions can better
           prepare students for the workforce. Es-
           tablishing strong linkages with indus-
           tries, offering internship and apprentice-                                                      Young artisans working on traditional projects
           ship opportunities, and incorporating
           skill development modules into the cur-
           riculum are some ways in which educa-
           tional institutions can contribute to the
           cause of World Youth Skills Day.

           Private sector
             The private sector has a significant
           role to play in youth skills development,
           given its direct connection to the job
           market. Companies can invest in train-
           ing programs, provide mentorship and
           apprenticeship opportunities, and col-
           laborate with educational institutions to
           align curricula with industry needs. By                                                         Youth engaged in practical vocational training
           actively engaging in skill development
           initiatives, the private sector can ensure
           a steady pipeline of skilled talent, driv-
           ing innovation and competitiveness.

           Non-Governmental Organizations
           (NGOs)
             NGOs and community organizations
           are instrumental in reaching out to mar-
           ginalized and disadvantaged youth, pro-
           viding them with access to education
           and training opportunities. These organi-
           zations often operate at the grassroots
           level, addressing the unique needs of
           different communities and advocating
           for policies that promote inclusive skill
           development. By offering vocational                                                             A young girl giving an interview
           training, life skills education, and entre-
           preneurship support, NGOs play a criti-
           cal role in empowering youth and foster-
           ing social inclusion.

                                                                           A collective responsibility
                                                                              World Youth Skills Day serves as a
                                                                           powerful reminder of the collective re-
         International conferences on skill development                    let us reaffirm our commitment to in-
                                                                           sponsibility we share in empowering the
                                                                           youth with the skills they need to shape
                                                                           a better future. As we celebrate this day,

                                                                           vesting in youth skills development, fos-
                                                                           tering a culture of lifelong learning, and
                                                                           creating an inclusive environment where
                                                                           every young person has the opportunity
                                                                           to thrive.
                                                                              By harnessing the potential of youth,
                                                                           we can drive sustainable development,
                                                                           promote social equity, and build a more
                                                                           prosperous and resilient world for gener-
                                                                           ations to come. ■

           14                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE













































           Zoonotic Diseases



           The hidden threats to







           global health








           By Staff Writer


                  orld Zoonoses Day is ob-  from animals to humans. With over 60%   eases can be caused by a variety of
                  served annually on July 6th   of emerging infectious diseases being   pathogens including viruses, bacteria,
           Wto commemorate the signifi-    zoonotic in nature, understanding and   parasites, and fungi. Some well-known
           cant milestone of the first successful ad-  mitigating the risk of zoonoses is critical   zoonotic diseases include rabies, in-
           ministration of the rabies vaccine by   for global health security.   fluenza, Lyme disease, Ebola, and
           Louis Pasteur, a pioneer in microbiol-                          COVID-19. These diseases can be
           ogy, in 1885. This day not only honors   What are zoonotic diseases?   spread through direct contact with ani-
           Pasteur’s groundbreaking work but also   Zoonotic diseases, or zoonoses, are   mals, consumption of contaminated food
           raises awareness about zoonotic dis-  infections that are naturally transmitted   or water, vectors like mosquitoes, or
           eases—diseases that are transmitted   between animals and humans. These dis-  even environmental reservoirs such as

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[soil and water.                 to the health of animals and our shared
                                           environment. This holistic approach is
           Historical context and significance   vital for predicting, preventing, and con-
             The history of zoonotic diseases   trolling zoonotic diseases.
           dates back to ancient times, with numer-
           ous pandemics and epidemics tracing   The one health approach
           their origins to animal sources. The Bu-  The One Health approach advocates
           bonic Plague, also known as the Black   for interdisciplinary collaboration
           Death, which ravaged Europe in the   among human, veterinary, and environ-
           14th century, is believed to have been   mental health professionals. By foster-
           caused by the bacterium Yersinia pestis,   ing communication and cooperation ac-
           transmitted through fleas from rodents.   ross these sectors, One Health aims to
           More recently, the emergence of the   improve health outcomes for both hu-
           H1N1 influenza virus (swine flu) and   mans and animals. Key components of
           the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic high-  the One Health approach include:
           light the persistent threat posed by zoo-  Surveillance and early detection:
           notic pathogens.                Monitoring animal populations for signs                         Louis Pasteur
             World Zoonoses Day serves as a cru-  of disease can provide early warning for
           cial reminder of the intricate link be-  potential zoonotic outbreaks. This in-
           tween human, animal, and environmen-  volves regular veterinary check-ups,   Vaccination programs for both animals
           tal health. The day emphasizes the One   wildlife monitoring, and laboratory test-  and humans are crucial in preventing the
           Health approach, which recognizes that   ing.                   spread of zoonotic diseases. For exam-
           the health of people is closely connected   Vaccination and disease control:   ple, rabies vaccination campaigns in
                                                                           dogs have significantly reduced human
                                                                           rabies cases worldwide.
                                                                              Public education and awareness:
                                                                           Educating communities about the risks
                                                                           of zoonotic diseases and promoting
                                                                           practices such as handwashing, safe
                                                                           food handling, and responsible pet own-
         Pet lovers can contract zoonotic diseases                         tecting and managing ecosystems to re-
                                                                           ership can reduce the incidence of these
                                                                           diseases.
                                                                              Environmental management: Pro-
                                                                           duce contact between wildlife and
                                                                           human populations can help prevent the
                                                                           spillover of zoonotic pathogens. This in-
                                                                           cludes measures like habitat conserva-
                                                                           tion, sustainable agriculture, and waste
                                                                           management.

                                                                           Case Studies of Zoonotic Diseases
                                                                              Rabies: Rabies is one of the most
                                                                           well-known zoonotic diseases, caused
                                                                           by the rabies virus, which affects the
                                                                           central nervous system. It is primarily
                                                                           transmitted through the bite of an in-
                                                                           fected animal, most commonly dogs.
                                                                           Without prompt treatment, rabies is al-
                                                                           most always fatal. However, widespread
                                                                           vaccination of dogs and post-exposure
                                                                           prophylaxis (PEP) for humans have
                                                                           proven highly effective in reducing
                                                                           rabies-related deaths.
                                                                              Ebola: Ebola virus disease (EVD) is
                                                                           a severe, often fatal illness in humans
                                                                           caused by the Ebola virus. The virus is
                                                                           believed to be transmitted to humans
                                                                           from wild animals such as fruit bats, and
                                                                           then spread through human-to-human
         A pet owner                                                       transmission. The 2014-2016 Ebola out-
                                                                           break in West Africa highlighted the
                                                                           devastating impact of zoonotic diseases

           16                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Fostering global collaboration: In-
         Vintage laboratory scenes depicting Pasteur’s work                ternational cooperation and information
                                                                           sharing are essential for managing zoo-
                                                                           notic diseases. Organizations such as the
                                                                           World Health Organization (WHO), the
                                                                           World Organization for Animal Health
                                                                           (OIE), and the Food and Agriculture Or-
                                                                           ganization (FAO) play a critical role in
                                                                           coordinating global efforts.
                                                                              Investing in public health infras-
                                                                           tructure: Robust public health systems
                                                                           are crucial for effective disease preven-
                                                                           tion, detection, and response. This in-
                                                                           cludes training healthcare professionals,
                                                                           improving laboratory capacity, and en-
                                                                           suring access to essential medicines and
                                                                           vaccines.
           and underscored the importance of rapid   Strengthening surveillance and re-  World Zoonoses Day is a poignant
           response and international collaboration   search: Enhanced surveillance systems   reminder of the interconnectedness of
           in outbreak management.         and research initiatives are needed to   human, animal, and environmental
             COVID-19: The COVID-19 pan-   identify and monitor emerging zoonotic   health. By embracing the One Health
           demic, caused by the SARS-CoV-2   threats. This includes the development   approach and addressing the root causes
           virus, has demonstrated the global im-  of advanced diagnostic tools, genomic   of zoonotic diseases, we can build a
           pact of zoonotic diseases. While the   sequencing, and predictive modeling.   safer, healthier world for all. As we
           exact origin of the virus is still under in-  Promoting sustainable practices:   commemorate this day, let us renew our
           vestigation, it is widely believed to have   Sustainable agricultural and environ-  commitment to research, education, and
           originated in bats and possibly trans-  mental practices can help reduce the risk   collaboration in the fight against zoo-
           mitted to humans through an intermedi-  of zoonotic diseases. This includes inte-  notic diseases. Through concerted ef-
           ate host. The pandemic has highlighted   grated pest management, biodiversity   forts and a shared vision, we can miti-
           the need for robust surveillance systems,   conservation, and responsible land use   gate the impact of zoonoses and protect
           global cooperation, and investment in   planning.               the health of future generations. ■
           public health infrastructure to manage
           zoonotic threats.

           Challenges and future directions
             Despite significant progress in under-
           standing and controlling zoonotic dis-
           eases, numerous challenges remain.
           These include:
             Deforestation and habitat en-
           croachment: Human activities such as
           deforestation, urbanization, and agricul-
           tural expansion increase contact be-                                                            Animal vaccinations
           tween wildlife and human populations,
           creating opportunities for zoonotic spill-
           over.
             Climate change: Climate change can
           alter the distribution and behavior of
           wildlife and vectors, potentially expand-
           ing the range of zoonotic diseases. For
           instance, warming temperatures can in-
           crease the spread of vector-borne dis-
           eases like malaria and dengue fever.
             Antimicrobial resistance: The over-
           use and misuse of antibiotics in both
           human medicine and animal husbandry
           contribute to the emergence of anti-
           microbial-resistant pathogens, compli-
           cating the treatment of zoonotic infec-                                                         Human vaccination campaign
           tions.
             To address these challenges, a multi-
           faceted approach is required. Key
           strategies include:

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH































           PLASTIC SURGERY





           Art and science of








           transformation









           By  Riya Verma


               lastic Surgery Day, celebrated on   tion and appearance to those affected by   rudimentary form of skin grafting. The
               July 15th annually, is a day ded-  congenital defects, trauma, or disease.   knowledge of these early techniques
           Picated to recognizing the remark-                              spread through translations of Sushruta's
           able advancements and contributions in   The origins and evolution of plastic   texts, influencing medical practices in
           the field of plastic surgery. This day   surgery                Egypt, Greece, and Rome.
           honors the skilled surgeons, innovative   Plastic surgery, derived from the   During the Renaissance, surgical
           techniques, and transformative impacts   Greek word 'plastikos,' meaning to mold   techniques advanced significantly, but it
           of plastic surgery on individuals' lives. It   or shape, has ancient roots. The earliest   was not until the 19th and 20th centuries
           is a celebration of both the art and science   records of reconstructive procedures date   that plastic surgery emerged as a distinct
           behind surgical procedures that enhance   back to 800 BC in India, where Sushruta,   medical specialty. World War I and II cat-
           and reconstruct human bodies, boosting   often referred to as the father of surgery,   alyzed major developments in recon-
           self-esteem and restoring normal func-  performed nasal reconstructions using a   structive surgery as surgeons were tasked

           18                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Sir Harold Gillies                                                                                Cosmetic procedures in progress







           with repairing extensive war injuries.   Burn treatment and reconstruc-  The impact of plastic surgery on
           Pioneers like Sir Harold Gillies and his   tion: Managing severe burns and recon-  lives
           cousin Archibald McIndoe revolution-  structing damaged skin and tissues.   Plastic surgery has profound impacts
           ized facial reconstruction techniques,   Breast reconstruction: Restoring   on individuals' physical and
           laying the groundwork for modern plas-  breast shape and appearance post-mas-  psychological well-being. For
           tic surgery.                    tectomy.                        reconstructive surgery patients, it can
                                             Hand surgery: Treating conditions   mean the difference between a life of
           The dual facets: reconstructive and   like carpal tunnel syndrome, rheumatoid   limitation and one of possibility. For
           cosmetic surgery                arthritis, and congenital hand differ-  instance, children born with cleft lips and
             Plastic surgery encompasses two   ences.                      palates often face social stigma and
           primary branches: reconstructive sur-  Cosmetic surgery: Aimed at en-  speech difficulties. Surgical repair
           gery and cosmetic (or aesthetic) surgery.   hancing the aesthetic appearance of an   transforms their lives, enabling them to
           While they share underlying principles,   individual, cosmetic surgery includes   integrate more fully into society.
           each branch serves distinct purposes.   procedures such as:
             Reconstructive surgery: This branch   Rhinoplasty: Reshaping the nose to   Burn survivors, who endure physical
           focuses on repairing and restoring func-  improve appearance or function.   pain and emotional trauma, find solace
           tion and appearance to body parts af-  Facelifts: Reducing wrinkles and   in reconstructive surgery. By restoring
           fected by congenital abnormalities,   sagging skin for a more youthful ap-  damaged tissues and improving func-
           trauma, infections, tumors, or diseases.   pearance.            tionality, these procedures help them re-
           Common procedures include:        Liposuction: Removing excess fat   gain confidence and lead productive
             Cleft lip and palate repair: Correct-  deposits to contour the body.   lives. Breast cancer survivors, too,
           ing these congenital deformities enables   Breast augmentation: Enhancing   benefit immensely from reconstructive
           children to eat, speak, and breathe prop-  breast size and shape using implants or   surgery, which plays a crucial role in
           erly.                           fat transfer.                   their physical and emotional recovery














                                                                                                           Post cosmetic surgery markings













           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[life-changing procedures they need, par-
                                                                           ticularly in low-income and rural areas.
                                                                              In cosmetic surgery, the influence of
                                                                           media and societal standards of beauty
                                                                           can drive individuals to pursue unnec-
         Ancient surgical illustrations by Sushruta                        their mental and physical well-being.
                                                                           essary or extreme procedures. Surgeons
                                                                           must navigate the fine line between
                                                                           meeting patients' desires and ensuring
                                                                           The rise of social media has exacerbated
                                                                           body image issues, with trends like the
                                                                           "Instagram face" promoting unrealistic
                                                                           and homogeneous beauty standards.
                                                                              Moreover, the potential for compli-
                                                                           cations and the necessity of informed
                                                                           consent are paramount. Patients must be
                                                                           thoroughly educated about the risks,
                                                                           benefits, and realistic outcomes of
           post-mastectomy.                are among the most exciting devel-  procedures to make informed decisions
             Cosmetic surgery, while often per-  opments in plastic surgery. Custom-de-  about their care.
           ceived as purely aesthetic, has signifi-  signed implants and prosthetics, created
           cant psychological benefits. Individuals   using 3D printing, ensure a perfect fit   Celebrating plastic surgery day
           dissatisfied with certain aspects of their   and natural appearance. Tissue engi-  Plastic Surgery Day serves as a plat-
           appearance may experience low self-es-  neering holds the promise of growing   form to educate the public about the
           teem and social anxiety. Cosmetic   skin, cartilage, and even organs in the   various aspects and benefits of plastic
           procedures that align their physical ap-  lab, which could be used for reconstruc-  surgery. It is an opportunity to dispel
           pearance with their self-image can boost   tive purposes in the future.   myths and misconceptions surrounding
           self-confidence and improve overall   Additionally, the rise of non-surgical   the field and highlight the positive im-
           quality of life.                cosmetic procedures, such as Botox in-  pacts on patients' lives.
                                           jections, dermal fillers, and non-inva-  Medical institutions, professional or-
           The role of technology and      sive body contouring, has expanded the   ganizations, and advocacy groups often
           innovation                      options available to those seeking aes-  organize events, seminars, and work-
             Advancements in technology and in-  thetic improvements without undergoing   shops on this day. These activities aim
           novative techniques have propelled   surgery.                   to raise awareness about the importance
           plastic surgery into new frontiers. Mini-                       of plastic surgery in healthcare, share
           mally invasive procedures, such as en-  Ethical considerations and   the latest research and innovations, and
           doscopic surgery, have revolutionized   challenges              honor the contributions of plastic sur-
           the field by reducing recovery times and   Despite its many benefits, plastic   geons worldwide.
           minimizing scarring. Laser technology   surgery also faces ethical considerations   Stories of patients who have under-
           is widely used for skin resurfacing, hair   and challenges. In reconstructive sur-  gone transformative surgeries are
           removal, and treating vascular lesions,   gery, issues such as accessibility and af-  shared, showcasing the human side of
           offering precise and effective results.   fordability are significant. Not all pa-  plastic surgery. These narratives empha-
             3D printing and tissue engineering   tients have equal access to the   size the resilience and courage of indi-
                                                                           viduals who have overcome physical
                                                                           challenges through surgical interven-
                                                                           tion.
                                                                              Plastic Surgery Day is a celebration
                                                                           of the remarkable advancements in a
                                                                           field that marries art and science to
         Botox injections under non-surgical treatments                    hance self-esteem, plastic surgery has a
                                                                           transform lives. From reconstructive
                                                                           procedures that restore function and ap-
                                                                           pearance to cosmetic surgeries that en-

                                                                           profound impact on individuals' physi-
                                                                           cal and psychological well-being. As
                                                                           technology and innovation continue to
                                                                           propel the field forward, it is crucial to
                                                                           address ethical considerations and en-
                                                                           sure equitable access to care. On this
                                                                           day, we honor the skilled surgeons,
                                                                           groundbreaking techniques, and inspir-
                                                                           ing patients who embody the transfor-
                                                                           mative power of plastic surgery. ■

           20                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[FEATURE
































           A Global Love Affair



           Chocolate's










           universal appeal









           By Staff Writer



                very year, the calendar marks a   versal appeal that transcends age, geog-  drink often spiced with chili peppers,
                day dedicated to one of the most   raphy, and culture.     vanilla, and other flavorings. This bever-
           Ebeloved treats around the globe-                               age, known as xocoatl, was highly
           Chocolate Day. Celebrated on July 7th,   A brief history of chocolate   valued, used in religious ceremonies,
           this special day allows chocolate lovers   The origins of chocolate can be   and believed to possess medicinal prop-
           everywhere to indulge in their favorite   traced back to the ancient civilizations   erties.
           confection and appreciate the rich his-  of Mesoamerica, where the cacao tree   When Spanish explorers, including
           tory, cultural significance, and diverse   was first cultivated by the Olmecs as   Hernán Cortés, encountered cacao in the
           varieties of chocolate. Whether enjoyed   early as 1500 BCE. The Mayans and Az-  early 16th century, they brought it back
           in its pure form or as a key ingredient in   tecs followed, developing methods to   to Europe. Initially enjoyed by the Spa-
           countless recipes, chocolate has a uni-  process cacao beans into a bitter, frothy   nish elite, chocolate soon spread

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[throughout the continent, evolving into a
           sweetened beverage as sugar and milk
           were added. By the 19th century, ad-
           vancements in processing technology,
           such as the development of the cocoa
           press by Dutch chemist Coenraad van
           Houten, paved the way for solid choco-
           late as we know it today.

           The science behind chocolate
             Chocolate is derived from cacao
           beans, which are fermented, dried,
           roasted, and ground to produce cocoa
           mass. This mass is then separated into
           cocoa solids and cocoa butter. The pro-
           portions of these components, along
           with added ingredients like sugar and
           milk, determine the type of chocolate
           produced. The primary categories are
           dark chocolate, milk chocolate, and
           white chocolate.
             Dark chocolate, which contains a
           high percentage of cocoa solids and lit-
           tle to no milk, is celebrated for its rich,                                                     Popular chocolate bars
           intense flavor and potential health bene-
           fits. Milk chocolate, the most popular
           variety, blends cocoa solids with milk
                                                                           powder or condensed milk, resulting in a
                                                                           sweeter, creamier taste. White chocolate,
                                                                           made from cocoa butter without cocoa
                                                                           solids, has a delicate, buttery flavor.
                                                                              The unique allure of chocolate lies in
                                                                           its complex chemistry. It contains over
                                                                           600 volatile compounds that contribute
                                                                           to its aroma, along with theobromine
                                                                           and caffeine, which provide a mild stim-
                                                                           ulant effect. Chocolate also contains
                                                                           phenylethylamine and serotonin, which
         Cacao pods and beans                                              feelings of happiness.
                                                                           are known to elevate mood and induce

                                                                           Chocolate day traditions
                                                                              Chocolate Day is celebrated in nu-
                                                                           merous ways across different cultures.
                                                                           For many, it’s an opportunity to indulge
                                                                           in their favorite chocolate treats,
                                                                           whether it be a simple chocolate bar,
                                                                           decadent truffles, or elaborate desserts.
                                                                           Some enjoy visiting local chocolatiers or
                                                                           attending chocolate-themed events and
                                                                           festivals, where they can sample a vari-
                                                                           ety of creations and learn about the art
                                                                           of chocolate making.
                                                                              Gift-giving is another popular tradi-
                                                                           tion, with chocolates being a symbol of
                                                                           love, friendship, and appreciation. Ex-
                                                                           changing boxes of chocolates or hand-
                                                                           made treats is a common gesture, espe-
         Chocolate festival                                                cially among couples and close friends.
                                                                           For some, Chocolate Day also serves as
                                                                           a chance to explore new flavors and
                                                                           brands, discovering artisanal chocolates
                                                                           from around the world.

           22                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[and spheres.
                                                                              Savory dishes featuring chocolate
                                                                           have gained popularity, too. Traditional
                                                                           Mexican mole sauce, a rich blend of
                                                                           spices, chili peppers, and chocolate, is a
                                                                           prime example of chocolate’s versatility
                                                                           in savory cuisine. Chefs worldwide are
                                                                           incorporating chocolate into marinades,
                                                                           glazes, and sauces to add depth and
         Coffee fermentation process                                       excuse to indulge in a favorite treat; it’s
                                                                           complexity to their dishes.
                                                                              Chocolate Day is more than just an

                                                                           a celebration of a rich and fascinating
                                                                           history, a tribute to cultural diversity,
                                                                           and an appreciation of the artistry and
                                                                           innovation that chocolate inspires.
                                                                           olate bar, exploring new flavors, or sup-
                                                                           Whether you’re enjoying a simple choc-
           Health benefits of chocolate
             While chocolate is often seen as a
           guilty pleasure, it also boasts several
           health benefits, particularly when
           consumed in moderation. Dark chocolate,
           in particular, is rich in antioxidants, which
           help combat free radicals and reduce
           inflammation. These antioxidants,
           primarily flavonoids, have been linked to                                                       Ancient cacao drinking vessels and artifacts
           improved heart health, including lower
           blood pressure, reduced risk of heart
           disease, and better cholesterol levels.
             Furthermore, chocolate contains es-
           sential minerals like magnesium, iron,
           and zinc. Magnesium plays a crucial
           role in muscle and nerve function, while   and shade-grown cacao help protect the   porting ethical practices, Chocolate Day
           iron is vital for oxygen transport in the   environment and biodiversity.   offers a moment to savor the sweetness
           blood. Zinc supports immune function   Supporting ethical chocolate brands   of life and the connections we share
           and cellular metabolism.        and becoming informed about the   through this universally cherished de-
             The mood-enhancing properties of   origins of cacao can contribute to a more   light.
           chocolate are another well-documented   sustainable and just chocolate industry.   As you celebrate Chocolate Day, take
           benefit. The presence of compounds like   Celebrating Chocolate Day can also in-  a moment to reflect on the journey of
           phenylethylamine and serotonin can   volve raising awareness about these is-  cacao from bean to bar, appreciate the
           help boost mood and reduce stress. Ad-  sues and making conscious choices to   craftsmanship that goes into creating
           ditionally, the act of savoring chocolate   support fair and sustainable practices.   each piece, and enjoy the sensory pleas-
           can provide a sensory pleasure that con-                        ure that only chocolate can provide.
           tributes to overall well-being.   Innovative chocolate creations   Happy Chocolate Day!
                                             The versatility of chocolate has in-
           The ethical side of chocolate   spired countless innovative creations,
             Despite its popularity, the chocolate   ranging from gourmet desserts to savory
           industry faces significant ethical chal-  dishes. In the culinary world, chocolate
           lenges, particularly concerning labor   is used in various forms, including
           practices and environmental sustainabil-  cocoa powder, chocolate chips, and
           ity. Much of the world’s cacao is grown   melted chocolate, to create an array of
           in West Africa, where issues such as   delights.
           child labor, poor working conditions,   Pastry chefs and chocolatiers con-
           and deforestation are prevalent.   tinuously push the boundaries of choco-
             In response, many consumers and   late artistry, crafting intricate sculptures,
           companies are advocating for more ethi-  bonbons with exotic fillings, and luxu-
           cal and sustainable chocolate produc-  rious chocolate bars infused with unique
           tion. Fair Trade certification ensures that   flavors like lavender, sea salt, or chili.        Chocolate with red fruits
           farmers receive fair wages and work   Molecular gastronomy has also em-
           under humane conditions. Additionally,   braced chocolate, experimenting with
           initiatives promoting organic farming   techniques like chocolate caviar, foams,

           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION





































           Pedaling Through Time



           The bicycle's







           journey and impact








           By Ishita Desai

                  orld Bicycle Day, observed   cycle, highlighting why it deserves   trick Macmillan added pedals to the de-
                  on June 3rd, is a global cele-  global recognition and celebration.   sign, creating the first pedal-powered bi-
           Wbration recognizing the en-                                    cycle. However, it was not until the
           during and transformative power of the   The inception of the bicycle   1860s that the bicycle began to resemble
           bicycle. This day, established by the   The bicycle's journey began in the   the modern design. The French inven-
           United Nations General Assembly in   early 19th century with the invention of   tors Pierre Michaux and Pierre Lalle-
           2018, underscores the bicycle's role as a   the "running machine" or "draisine" by   ment introduced the "boneshaker,"
           simple, affordable, reliable, and environ-  Baron Karl von Drais in 1817. This pre-  which featured pedals attached directly
           mentally sustainable mode of transport.   cursor to the modern bicycle had no   to the front wheel, creating a more effi-
           The bicycle has a rich history and has   pedals and required riders to push off   cient propulsion mechanism.
           evolved significantly since its inception,   the ground with their feet. It marked the
           impacting society in myriad ways. This   first step towards mechanized personal   The evolution of bicycle design
           article delves into the origins, evolution,   transport.          The next major advancement came
           and contemporary significance of the bi-  In 1839, Scottish blacksmith Kirkpa-  with the introduction of the "penny-far-

           24                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Evolution of bicycle
                                                                            accessibility

                                                                               The evolution of bicycles has
                                                                            transformed them from luxury items
                                                                            to common transportation worldwide.
                                                                               Early days: Initially, bicycles
                                                                            were expensive and exclusive to the
                                                                            wealthy due to high production costs
                                                                            and limited manufacturing capabil-
                                                                            ities.
                                                                               Mass production: The late 19th
                                                                            and early 20th centuries saw mass
                                                                            production techniques by manufac-
                                                                            turers like Humber, Raleigh, and
         Penny-farthing                                                     Schwinn, reducing costs and making
                                                                            bicycles affordable for a broader pop-
                                                                            ulation.
                                                                               Manufacturing hubs: Regions
                                                                            such as the Midlands in England, the
                                                                            United States, and Western Europe
                                                                            became bicycle production centers,
                                                                            lowering costs and enhancing acces-
                                                                            sibility through localized manufactur-
                                                                            ing.
                                                                               Bicycle boom and second-hand
                                                                            markets: The mid-20th-century bi-
                                                                            cycle boom, driven by leisure cycling
                                                                            and the need for affordable transport,
                                                                            led to the growth of second-hand
                                                                            markets, making bicycles accessible
                                                                            to more people.
                                                                               Government initiatives and sub-
                                                                            sidies: Governments worldwide rec-
                                                                            ognized bicycles as a sustainable
                                                                            transport mode and implemented ini-
                                                                            tiatives like bike-sharing programs,
                                                                            purchase subsidies, and cycling in-
         Draisine                                                           frastructure development to increase
                                                                            accessibility.
                                                                               Technological advancements:
                                                                            Innovations such as lightweight ma-
                                                                            terials, efficient gear systems, and
                                                                            electric-assist bicycles have broad-
                                                                            ened options, making bicycles suit-
                                                                            able for diverse needs and prefer-
                                                                            ences.
                                                                               Global impact: In developing na-
                                                                            tions, bicycles provide vital transpor-
                                                                            tation where motor vehicles are unaf-
                                                                            fordable or impractical. Donation
                                                                            initiatives have further increased bi-
                                                                            cycle availability, empowering com-
                                                                            munities and improving livelihoods.
                                                                               Bicycles have evolved from lux-
                                                                            ury items to affordable, common
                                                                            transportation, promoting sustainabil-
                                                                            ity and improving lives globally
                                                                            through technological advancements,
         Road bikes                                                         mass production, and supportive ini-
                                                                            tiatives.


           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Cycling infrastructure

                                                                            in global cities
                                                                               Several cities worldwide have im-
                                                                            plemented effective cycling infras-
                                                                            tructure and policies to promote cy-
                                                                            cling as a sustainable transportation
                                                                            mode:
                                                                               Amsterdam, Netherlands: Am-
                                                                            sterdam is famous for its extensive
                                                                            cycling paths, bike parking, and cy-
                                                                            clist-specific traffic signals. With
                                                                            over 800,000 bicycles, the city em-
                                                                            phasizes cyclist safety through strict
         Cycling in the city                                                bridges and tunnels.
                                                                            liability laws and dedicated cyclist
                                                                               Copenhagen, Denmark: Copen-
                                                                            hagen boasts a comprehensive cy-
                                                                            cling network, including well-main-
                                                                            tained bike lanes, cycle tracks, and
           thing" in the 1870s. This design, charac-  The bicycle revolutionized personal   bicycle-friendly bridges. Traffic sig-
           terized by a large front wheel and a   transportation in the late 19th and early   nals are synchronized for cyclists,
           much smaller rear wheel, offered a   20th centuries. It offered a new level of   and the city provides ample bike
           smoother ride compared to its predeces-  mobility and independence, especially   parking.
           sors. However, it was also dangerous   for women, who found the bicycle a tool   Utrecht, Netherlands: Utrecht
           due to the rider's elevated position and   for liberation and empowerment. The bi-  has developed a vast network of
           the potential for "headers" – accidents   cycle played a significant role in the   cycle paths and cycling bridges, in-
           where the rider would be thrown over   women's suffrage movement, symboliz-  cluding the world's largest bicycle
           the handlebars.                 ing freedom and challenging traditional   parking facility. The city plans to
             The quest for a safer and more practi-  gender roles.          create a pedestrian and cyclist-only
           cal design led to the development of the   Economically, the bicycle created   city center, transforming former car-
           "safety bicycle" in the 1880s. John   new industries and job opportunities. Bi-  dominated areas.
           Kemp Starley, an English inventor,   cycle manufacturing, repair shops, and   Seville, Spain: Seville imple-
           created the Rover Safety Bicycle, which   accessory production became thriving   mented an ambitious cycling infras-
           featured equal-sized wheels, a chain-  businesses. The affordability and effi-  tructure plan, resulting in nearly 180
           driven rear wheel, and a diamond-  ciency of bicycles made them a popular   kilometers (112 miles) of cycling
           shaped frame. This design, still in use   choice for commuting, leisure, and even   lanes. This improvement has signifi-
           today, made bicycles more accessible   competitive sports.       cantly increased the cycling mode
           and practical for a wider audience.                              share, enhancing safety and connec-
                                           Bicycles and urban development   tivity.
           The bicycle's impact on society   The 20th century saw the rise of the   Bogota, Colombia: Bogota's Ci-
                                                                            clovia event closes over 120 kilo-
                                                                            meters (75 miles) of major streets to
                                                                            vehicles every Sunday and public
                                                                            holiday. This initiative promotes cy-
                                                                            cling, physical activity, community
                                                                            engagement, and public space revital-
                                                                            ization.
                                                                               Portland, Oregon, USA: Port-
                                                                            land is known for its extensive net-
                                                                            work of bike lanes, paths, and green-
                                                                            ways. The city supports cycling
                                                                            through bike parking, bike-sharing
                                                                            programs, and community education,
                                                                            fostering a strong cycling culture.
         A cycling festival scene                                           panded its cycling network with sep-
                                                                               Tokyo, Japan: Tokyo has ex-
                                                                            arate bike lanes and enhanced cycling
                                                                            facilities. These efforts aim to pro-
                                                                            mote sustainable transportation and
                                                                            reduce traffic congestion.


           26                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Effective
           Measures

              Several cities enhance cyclist
           safety through comprehensive meas-
           ures alongside dedicated infrastruc-
           ture:
              Amsterdam, Netherlands:
              Strict Liability Laws: Motorists are
           presumed liable in collisions with cy-
           clists, promoting responsible driving.                                                          Environmental benefits of cycling
              Traffic Education Programs: Cam-
           paigns educate both cyclists and mo-
           torists about road safety and proper
           interactions.
              Copenhagen, Denmark:
              Green Wave for Cyclists: Traffic   automobile, which overshadowed the bi-  promote cycling is its environmental
           signals synchronize to minimize stops   cycle as the primary mode of transport.   impact. Bicycles produce zero emissions
           for cyclists along popular routes.   However, the bicycle never lost its sig-  and have a minimal carbon footprint
              Continuous Bike Lane Mainte-  nificance. In cities around the world, bi-  compared to motor vehicles. As concerns
           nance: Regular maintenance ensures   cycles remained a practical solution for   about climate change and environmental
           bike lanes are safe and hazard-free.   short-distance travel and a means to   sustainability grow, cycling offers a
              Utrecht, Netherlands:        navigate congested urban areas.   practical solution for reducing greenhouse
              Bicycle-Friendly Traffic Signals:   In recent decades, urban planners and   gas emissions and dependence on fossil
           Signals at intersections prioritize cy-  policymakers have increasingly recog-  fuels.
           clists, reducing conflicts with ve-  nized the benefits of cycling for sustain-  Cycling also promotes healthier life-
           hicles.                         able urban development. Cities like Co-  styles. Regular physical activity, such as
              Barrier-Separated Bike Paths:   penhagen and Amsterdam are renowned   cycling, reduces the risk of chronic dis-
           Physical barriers protect cyclists by   for their cycling infrastructure, where   eases like heart disease, diabetes, and
           separating bike lanes from motor traf-  dedicated bike lanes, traffic signals, and   obesity. It also improves mental health
           fic.                            parking facilities create a cyclist-  by reducing stress and promoting well-
              Seville, Spain:              friendly environment. These cities dem-  being. Communities that encourage cy-
              Network Expansion: Rapid expan-  onstrate how integrating cycling into   cling often report lower healthcare costs
           sion of separated cycle paths provides   urban planning can reduce traffic con-  and a higher quality of life.
           safe and comfortable routes.    gestion, lower pollution levels, and im-  Global initiatives and world bicycle
              Educational Campaigns: Public   prove public health.         day
           initiatives promote cycling safety and                             World Bicycle Day is more than just
           mutual respect among road users.   The environmental benefits of   a celebration; it is a call to action. The
              Bogota, Colombia:            cycling                         United Nations encourages member
              Ciclovia and Cicloruta: Ciclovia   One of the most compelling reasons to   states to develop and implement policies
           creates car-free zones on major
           streets, while Cicloruta offers a net-
           work of safe cycling routes.
              Portland, Oregon, USA:
              Bicycle Boulevards: Streets prior-
           itize bicycles over vehicles with traf-
           fic calming measures.
              Bike-Friendly Intersections: Fea-
           tures like green-painted bike boxes
           and bike-specific signals improve vis-
           ibility and safety.
              Tokyo, Japan:
              Cycle-Friendly Infrastructure De-
           sign: Redesigned roads with dedicated
           bike lanes and protective barriers en-
           hance cyclist safety.
              Traffic Calming Measures: Speed
           reductions and improved pedestrian
           crossings contribute to safer con-                                                              Cycling for fitness
           ditions for cyclists.


           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[that promote cycling as a means of sus-
                                                                           tainable development. This includes in-
                                                                           vesting in infrastructure, education, and
                                                                           awareness campaigns to highlight the
                                                                           benefits of cycling.
                                                                              Numerous global initiatives align
                                                                           with the goals of World Bicycle Day.
                                                                           The European Cyclists' Federation
                                                                           (ECF) advocates for cycling-friendly
                                                                           policies across Europe, while organiza-
                                                                           tions like PeopleForBikes work to im-
                                                                           prove cycling conditions in the United
                                                                           States. International events like Bike to
                                                                           Work Day and various cycling festivals
                                                                           further promote the benefits of cycling
                                                                           and encourage more people to adopt this
                                                                           sustainable mode of transport.

                                                                           The future of cycling
                                                                              The future of cycling looks promis-
                                                                           ing as technology and innovation con-
                                                                           tinue to enhance the cycling experience.
                                                                           E-bikes, or electric bicycles, are gaining
                                                                           popularity for their ability to make cy-
                                                                           cling more accessible to people of all
                                                                           ages and fitness levels. E-bikes provide
                                                                           assistance with pedaling, making it eas-
                                                                           ier to tackle hills and longer distances,
         Women cycling                                                     thus broadening the appeal of cycling.
                                                                              Smart technology is also transform-
                                                                           ing the cycling experience. GPS navi-
                                                                           gation, fitness tracking apps, and bike-
                                                                           sharing programs are making cycling
                                                                           more convenient and enjoyable. Cities
                                                                           are increasingly adopting bike-sharing
                                                                           schemes, providing residents and tour-
                                                                           ists with easy access to bicycles for
                                                                           short trips.
                                                                              World Bicycle Day on June 3rd is an
                                                                           opportunity to celebrate the remarkable
                                                                           journey of the bicycle and its profound
                                                                           impact on society. From its humble be-
                                                                           ginnings as a rudimentary running ma-
                                                                           chine to its current status as a symbol of
                                                                           sustainable transport, the bicycle has
                                                                           continually adapted to meet the needs of
                                                                           its users. It has empowered individuals,
                                                                           shaped urban landscapes, and offered an
                                                                           environmentally friendly alternative to
                                                                           motorized transport.
                                                                              As we look to the future, promoting
                                                                           cycling remains crucial for achieving
                                                                           sustainable development goals, improv-
                                                                           ing public health, and combating climate
                                                                           change. On this World Bicycle Day, let
                                                                           us acknowledge the bicycle's enduring
                                                                           legacy and commit to creating a world
                                                                           where cycling is safe, accessible, and
                                                                           celebrated by all. By doing so, we honor
                                                                           not only the past and present of the bi-
         Road bikes                                                        cycle but also pave the way for a
                                                                           greener, healthier, and more sustainable
                                                                           future. ■

           28                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY
                                                             July 01-15, 2024
             HOROSCOPES




           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     This period brings a burst of energy for Aries. You   Partnerships, both personal and professional,
                     will find yourself tackling projects with renewed   will be in the spotlight. Cooperation and com-
                     vigor. Relationships may require extra attention;   promise will lead to success. Creativity will be
                     ensure open communication to avoid              high, so engage in activities that inspire you. Fi-
                     misunderstandings.                              nancially, avoid impulsive decisions.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Taurus, you might feel the need to retreat and   Scorpios might feel a surge of motivation to im-
                     reflect. This is a good time for introspection and   prove their daily routines and health habits.
                     self-care. Professional matters might be slow, but   Work-related matters will require diligence and
                     patience will pay off. Relationships will be    attention to detail. Relationships will benefit
                     supportive, providing comfort and stability.    from your empathy and understanding.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Your social life will be bustling. Networking can   Sagittarius, this is a period of fun and creativity.
                     lead to exciting opportunities. Stay organized to   Engage in hobbies and activities that bring you
                     manage the busy schedule effectively. Health-   joy. Work projects will be exciting and might
                     wise, maintain a balanced diet and regular exer-  open doors for future growth. Financially, think
                     cise to keep your energy levels up.             long-term and avoid unnecessary risks.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     This is a period of growth in your career. Take   Capricorn, focus on home and family. Domestic
                     advantage of new opportunities and don’t shy    matters will need your attention and care. Pro-
                     away from taking the lead. Family matters might   fessionally, steady progress is expected; remain
                     need your attention, so balance your time wisely.   patient and persistent. Financially, avoid major
                     Financially, a positive change is on the horizon.   expenditures and stick to your savings plan.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leos will feel a strong urge to explore and learn   Aquarius will experience a boost in communica-
                     new things. Travel might be on the cards,       tion skills. This is a great time for networking
                     whether for work or leisure. Professionally, col-  and sharing ideas. Professional life will be dy-
                     laborations will be fruitful. Pay attention to your   namic, and your innovative ideas will be appre-
                     health, particularly your mental well-being.    ciated. Health-wise, stay active.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Focus on your financial strategies. This is a good   Focus on your financial health. Review your
                     time to review investments and plan for the fu-  budget and make necessary adjustments. Rela-
                     ture. Personal relationships might feel intense,   tionships will be harmonious, providing emo-
                     but honest conversations will strengthen bonds.   tional support. Professionally, this is a good time
                     Keep an eye on your health.                     to complete pending tasks and set new goals.





           JULY 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Celebrating India's T20 Victory
                                             Congratulations to Team India for
             India's exhilarating victory in the T20
                                                                              In the current political climate, where
           match on 29th June 2024 is a testament to
                                           their outstanding performance and for
                                           bringing joy to millions of fans.
           our team's skill, determination, and   aspiring players.        tensions and divisions are increasingly
           sportsmanship. The match was a   Meenakshi Shukla, Bhopal, Madhya   pronounced, it would have been more
           rollercoaster of emotions, showcasing   Pradesh, India          prudent to elect a new Speaker by mu-
           outstanding performances from our                               tual consent. A fresh perspective could
           players. Virat Kohli's masterful batting                        have facilitated a more balanced ap-
           and Jasprit Bumrah's exceptional bowling   Modi's Historic Hat Trick   proach, fostering cooperation and ensur-
           were pivotal in securing this triumph.   Narendra Modi's unprecedented hat   ing that all voices are heard equally.
             The unwavering support from fans,   trick in the 2024 parliamentary elections   Democracy thrives on inclusivity and
           both in the stadium and across the nation,   marks a significant chapter in India's po-  fairness, and it is crucial that our parlia-
           played a significant role in boosting the   litical landscape. His leadership and vi-  mentary proceedings reflect these prin-
           team's morale. This victory not only   sion have resonated with millions, lead-  ciples.
           brings joy to millions of cricket   ing to this historic third-term victory.   Karan Sharma, Mumbai, Maharash-
           enthusiasts but also reinforces India's   Modi’s emphasis on economic growth,   tra, India
           dominance in the sport.         digital transformation, and social wel-
             Such moments of triumph inspire   fare has garnered widespread support.
           young athletes and remind us of the   This win reflects the electorate’s con-  Yoga’s Guiding Light: Shraddha
           unifying power of sports. Let's continue to   fidence in his governance and future   Gawande
           support and celebrate our team's   plans for India. It’s a testament to his   I am deeply impressed by your fea-
           achievements as they strive for excellence   ability to address the aspirations of di-  ture on Shraddha Gawande. Her ded-
           on the global stage.            verse demographics across the nation.   ication to yoga and her transformative
           Ajay Kumar, New Delhi, India    Congratulations to Prime Minister Modi   impact on so many lives is truly inspir-
                                           and the BJP for this remarkable achieve-  ing. Shraddha’s journey from overcom-
                                           ment.                           ing personal health challenges to becom-
           India's T20 Glory               Ravindera Rana, Delhi, India    ing a global yoga instructor highlights
             India’s spectacular victory in the T20                        her remarkable commitment.
           match on 29th June 2024 is a proud mo-                             Her innovative online teaching
           ment for all of us. Virat Kohli’s phenom-  Om Birla’s re-election as the   methods and personalized attention to
           enal batting and Jasprit Bumrah’s re-  Speaker                  students exemplify her passion and ex-
           markable bowling were key to this win.   While Om Birla’s re-election as the   pertise. Her impact on her students' lives
           The entire team’s performance was com-  Speaker of the Lok Sabha for the second   is profound, making her a true beacon of
           mendable and showcased their ded-  consecutive term might be seen as a pos-  health and positivity.
           ication and hard work.          itive step by some, it is essential to con-  Thank you for showcasing such an
             The electrifying atmosphere, fueled   sider the unique circumstances this time   extraordinary individual whose work
           by the passionate support of fans, added   around. The role of the Speaker is to   promotes health and well-being world-
           to the excitement of the match. This vic-  maintain impartiality and ensure fair   wide.
           tory is a reminder of India’s prowess in   decision-making for both the ruling   Aditi Narayan, Edmonton, Alberta,
           cricket and serves as an inspiration for   party and the opposition.   Canada



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 01 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>