<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 05  I  MARCH 01 2025       ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             15



                                                             8













                                                           18                                        24
















           4-Editorial: Closing the gender gap in          21-Traveling the world in a wheelchair
           tech                                            24-The emotional and cultural power of

           5-The architects of tomorrow’s digital          wigs

           world                                           27-Horoscopes

           8-How tech is revolutionizing sleep             28-Letters
           11-The truth about romance and obesity

           15-How fashion is protecting wildlife

           18-The hidden mathematics in

           everyday life









           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                   3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[The time is now
     EDITORIAL  Closing the                                                       Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           gender gap in tech                                                   Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                              he digital revolution is no longer a   Navormi Vats
                                              distant phenomenon, it is the very
                                        Tfabric of our present and the founda-
                                        tion of our future. At the heart of this trans-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        formation are visionaries who push the   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        boundaries of innovation, shaping a more
                                        connected, intelligent and inclusive world.   Social Media Editor
                                        Among them, women in technology stand        Vikas Babbar
                                        as architects of progress, challenging norms
                                        and redefining possibilities.            Art & Graphics Editor
                                           For decades, the tech industry remained   Vipin Kumar
                                        a male-dominated space, yet history tells a
                                        different story. Ada Lovelace envisioned the
                                        first algorithm, Grace Hopper pioneered   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           modern computing and today, women like Fei-Fei Li in artificial intelligence and
           Reshma Saujani in coding education continue to break new ground. Their contrib-  D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           utions are not mere footnotes but essential blueprints in the evolving digital land-  Editor, United News of India, New
           scape.                                                            Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             Yet, the road to equity is still being paved. Women make up nearly half of the   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           global workforce but remain significantly underrepresented in STEM fields. Biases,   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           systemic barriers and a lack of mentorship often hinder progress. Many women in   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           tech still face workplace discrimination, wage gaps and limited leadership opportuni-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           ties. However, the tide is turning. From coding boot camps designed for young girls   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           to global initiatives championing female-led startups, the movement toward inclusiv-  Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           ity is gaining momentum.
             Why does this matter? Because technology shapes societies. The apps we use, the   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           AI we trust and the cybersecurity that protects us must reflect diverse perspectives.
           When women lead in tech, innovation becomes more ethical, inclusive and attuned to   Phone +91 20 40199102
           global challenges. Consider Dr. Joy Buolamwini, who exposed racial and gender bias   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           in facial recognition software, forcing a reckoning in AI ethics. Her work is a testa-  Baner Road,
           ment to why representation in technology is not just about fairness, it is about the fu-  Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           ture of humanity.                                                Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
             International Women’s Day reminds us that progress is possible when voices are   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
           amplified and opportunities are equitably distributed. Businesses, educators and poli-  Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
           cymakers must actively support women in technology. Representation is not enough;   Founding year 2023
           empowerment, leadership and systemic change must follow. Encouraging young girls   Subject Multidisciplinary
           to explore STEM, funding women-led enterprises and dismantling workplace biases   Frequency Fortnightly
           are essential steps toward an equitable digital world.                   Format Online
             The innovators shaping tomorrow’s digital future are not defined by gender but by   Language English
           vision, resilience and ingenuity. True progress happens when diverse minds collabo-  Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           rate, bringing unique perspectives to innovation and problem-solving. A world where   Website www.revoir.in
           technology uplifts everyone is possible, but only if inclusivity drives its creation. The
           future is not just being built; it is being reimagined with purpose, equality and a com-  Legal Advisor
           mitment to change.                                                    Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[COVER STORY








































           Women and Technology                                            industry. Their relentless pursuit of inno-

                                                                           vation and determination to break bar-
                                                                           riers have led to significant advance-
           The architects of                                               ments in science, engineering and digital
                                                                           transformation. From developing cut-
                                                                           ting-edge artificial intelligence models
                                                                           to fortifying cyber security, women are
                                                                           making an undeniable impact on the fu-
           tomorrow’s digital                                              ture of technology.

                                                                           Breaking barriers: Women
                                                                           pioneers in technology
           world                                                           significant strides in the tech industry,
                                                                              Women entrepreneurs are making
                                                                           launching start-ups that solve global
                                                                           challenges. For instance, Reshma Sau-
           Women are redefining the future of technology by                jani, the founder of Girls Who Code, has
                                                                           been instrumental in closing the gender
           breaking barriers, leading innovations and advocating for       gap in programming by inspiring young
                                                                           girls to pursue careers in technology.
           inclusivity in the digital landscape. By Naina Kapoor           Similarly, Dr. Fei-Fei Li, a renowned AI
                                                                           researcher and co-director of the Stan-
                                                                           ford Human-Centered AI Institute, has
                he digital revolution has reshaped   only innovating but also pushing for in-  advanced artificial intelligence while ad-
                industries, economies and so-  clusivity and diversity in a traditionally   vocating for ethical and inclusive AI de-
           Tcieties and women are increas-  male-dominated sector. As technology   velopment.
           ingly at the forefront of this transfor-  continues to evolve, the contributions of   Other female-led start-ups are also
           mation. Despite facing systemic   women are proving indispensable in   revolutionizing industries. Whitney
           barriers, women in technology are pio-  shaping the future.     Wolfe Herd, the founder of Bumble, has
           neering breakthroughs in artificial intel-  As we celebrate International   redefined social networking by integrat-
           ligence, cybersecurity, biotechnology   Women’s Day, it is crucial to recognize   ing women-centric approaches into dat-
           and software development. They are not   the achievements of women in the tech   ing apps. Meanwhile, Anne Wojcicki,

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                   5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Ada Lovelace, the first computer programmer                                                       A young female engineer working with hardware


















           co-founder of 23andMe, has disrupted
           healthcare with consumer-driven genetic
           testing, offering individuals unprece-
           dented insights into their ancestry and
           health risks.
             The success of women-led start-ups
           is not just a testament to their talent but
           also to their resilience in overcoming
           challenges. Many female entrepreneurs
           face difficulties in securing venture cap-
           ital funding, as investors still tend to
           favor male-led businesses. However,                                                             A woman inspecting a communication server
           with increasing awareness and efforts
           towards gender equity, more funding op-
           portunities are opening up for women in
           tech. Organizations like SheEO and Fe-
           male Founders Fund are actively sup-
           porting women-led start-ups, ensuring
           that female entrepreneurs receive the fi-
           nancial backing they need to scale their   Despite their remarkable contrib-  bug bounty programs that allow ethical
           ventures.                       utions, women in AI still face barriers   hackers to find and fix security vulner-
                                           such as lack of representation in leader-  abilities. Her efforts have reshaped how
           Women in artificial intelligence   ship roles, pay gaps and workplace bi-  companies approach cybersecurity, mak-
           and machine learning            ases. However, organizations such as   ing digital spaces safer for everyone.
             Artificial intelligence (AI) is one of   Women in AI are advocating for more   The cybersecurity industry has long
           the most transformative technologies of   inclusivity, mentoring young women   been dominated by men, but more
           our era and women are playing a crucial   and offering scholarships to bridge the   women are entering the field, thanks to
           role in its development. Joy Buolam-  gender gap in AI research and devel-  initiatives like Women in Cybersecurity
           wini, the founder of the Algorithmic Jus-  opment.              (WiCyS). These programs provide men-
           tice League, has been a vocal advocate                          torship, networking opportunities and
           against AI bias, highlighting how facial   Women in cybersecurity:   training to help women advance in cy-
           recognition systems often fail to accu-  Defending the digital world   bersecurity careers. The growing pres-
           rately detect people of color, particularly   Cybersecurity is a critical aspect of   ence of women in cybersecurity is criti-
           women. Her work has prompted major   the digital age, with increasing threats   cal to fostering diverse perspectives and
           tech companies to reassess and refine   targeting both individuals and organiza-  improving global digital security.
           their AI algorithms to be more inclusive.   tions. Women are stepping up to en-
             Dr. Cynthia Breazeal, a robotics   hance global cybersecurity efforts. Pa-  Women in space and science:
           scientist and professor at MIT, has been   risa Tabriz, known as Google's "Security   Pushing boundaries beyond earth
           a pioneer in the development of social   Princess," leads Google Chrome’s secu-  Women in technology are not just
           robotics. Her groundbreaking work in   rity team, ensuring users worldwide re-  revolutionizing the digital world but also
           human-computer interaction has paved   main protected from cyber threats.   advancing space exploration and
           the way for emotionally intelligent AI,   Another key figure is Katie Mous-  science. Dr. Swati Mohan, an aerospace
           with applications in healthcare, educa-  souris, the founder of Luta Security, who   engineer at NASA, played a crucial role
           tion and personal assistance.   played a pivotal role in developing the   in the successful landing of the Perse-

           6                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ships to aspiring female technologists.
                                                                              Governments and educational institu-
                                                                           tions are also recognizing the impor-
                                                                           tance of inclusivity in STEM education.
                                                                           By integrating coding and robotics into
                                                                           early education and providing incentives
         A female entrepreneur pitching her idea                           Corporate initiatives and policies
                                                                           for female students in tech-related
                                                                           fields, more women can enter the indus-
                                                                           try with confidence.


                                                                           for gender equality
                                                                              Many companies are implementing
                                                                           policies to create a more inclusive work-
                                                                           place. Organizations like Microsoft,
                                                                           Google and IBM have established diver-
                                                                           sity and inclusion programs, offering
                                                                           mentorship, leadership training and flex-
                                                                           ible work arrangements to support
                                                                           women in technology.
                                                                              Additionally, venture capital firms
                                                                           are beginning to invest more in women-
                                                                           led start-ups, recognizing the innovation
                                                                           and profitability they bring to the indus-
                                                                           try. Increased funding opportunities en-
                                                                           able more women to launch their own
         Women in software development roles                               The role of advocacy and
                                                                           tech ventures and contribute to techno-
                                                                           logical advancements.


                                                                           networking
                                                                              Women in tech are increasingly
                                                                           forming networks and communities to
                                                                           support one another. Organizations like
                                                                           Women in Cybersecurity (WiCyS) and
                                                                           AnitaB.org provide platforms for
                                                                           women to share knowledge, find men-
                                                                           torship and advance their careers.
           verance rover on Mars. Her expertise in   challenges. Gender bias, underrepresen-  Public recognition and awards, such
           guidance and navigation systems con-  tation and workplace discrimination re-  as the Grace Hopper Celebration and
           tributed significantly to the mission’s   main prevalent in many tech companies.   Forbes' Most Powerful Women in Tech
           success.                        Studies show that women in tech often   list, also play a role in showcasing fe-
             Similarly, Dr. Katie Bouman, a com-  earn less than their male counterparts   male achievements and inspiring future
           puter scientist, led the team that devel-  and face limited opportunities for career   generations to enter the industry.
           oped the algorithm used to capture the   advancement.              Women are redefining the future of
           first-ever image of a black hole. Her   Additionally, the lack of mentorship   technology by breaking barriers, leading
           work demonstrated how interdiscipli-  and sponsorship programs makes it har-  innovations and advocating for inclusiv-
           nary collaboration in technology can   der for women to rise to leadership posi-  ity in the digital landscape. While chal-
           lead to ground-breaking scientific dis-  tions. Many women also encounter im-  lenges persist, the strides made by
           coveries.                       poster syndrome, where they feel   women in AI, cybersecurity, space ex-
             Women in space and science con-  undeserving of their achievements de-  ploration and tech entrepreneurship
           tinue to face challenges related to fund-  spite their qualifications and skills.   demonstrate that the industry is evolving
           ing and recognition. However, the rise                          towards a more equitable and diverse fu-
           of female-led research teams and initia-  Reshaping the industry: A more   ture.
           tives promoting women in STEM are   inclusive future               On International Women’s Day, it is
           ensuring that more women have the op-  One of the most effective ways to   essential to celebrate the remarkable
           portunity to contribute to space explora-  bridge the gender gap in technology is   women who continue to push the bound-
           tion and scientific innovation.   by encouraging young girls to pursue   aries of innovation and inspire future
                                           careers in science, technology, engineer-  generations.
           Challenges women face in the tech   ing and mathematics (STEM). Initiatives   The future of technology is not just
           industry                        such as Girls Who Code, Black Girls   about advancements, it is about inclusiv-
             Despite these achievements, women   Code and Women in Tech provide men-  ity, representation and the empowerment
           in technology continue to face numerous   torship, coding workshops and scholar-  of all. ■

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                   7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH



































           Reclaiming rest                                                 portant to recognize the significant
                                                                           strides technology has made in improv-
                                                                           ing sleep health. As research continues
           How tech is                                                     to highlight the impact of sleep on phys-
                                                                           ical and mental well-being, technology-
                                                                           driven solutions are helping individuals
                                                                           track, understand and optimize their
                                                                           sleep patterns like never before.
           revolutionizing                                                 enthusiast, a tech-savvy consumer, a
                                                                           Whether you are a health and wellness
                                                                           sleep-deprived professional, a medical
                                                                           expert, an athlete, or a caregiver, the la-
                                                                           test advancements in sleep technology
           sleep                                                           rest.
                                                                           offer promising ways to achieve better

                                                                           The evolution of sleep technology
                                                                              Sleep science has come a long way
                                                                           from traditional advice on counting
           Technology is no longer just a source of distraction, it        sheep or avoiding caffeine before bed.
                                                                           The modern approach to sleep improve-
           is becoming an essential tool in the quest for better           ment is now deeply intertwined with
           sleep. By Aarav Sharma                                          technology. Innovations such as wear-
                                                                           able sleep trackers, AI-powered smart
                                                                           mattresses and intuitive sleep apps are
               leep is a cornerstone of overall   of solutions designed to enhance sleep   providing real-time insights into sleep
               health, yet millions struggle to get   quality. From cutting-edge sleep track-  quality, helping users make data-driven
           Sthe restorative rest they need.   ing devices to smart home features that   adjustments to their routines.
           Whether due to stress, lifestyle habits, or   create optimal environments, innova-
           medical conditions, sleep deprivation is   tions in sleep technology are transform-  Wearable sleep trackers:
           a growing concern in modern society.   ing how people approach rest and   Monitoring sleep with precision
           However, technology, often blamed for   recovery.                  Wearable technology has revolution-
           disrupting sleep, is now at the forefront   In light of World Sleep Day, it is im-  ized how individuals monitor their sleep

           8                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Wearable sleep tracker device                                                                     A mother and child in deep sleep












                                                                           According to users, this has signifi-
                                                                           cantly reduced night-time awakenings
                                                                           caused by discomfort, leading to deeper
                                                                           and more restorative sleep.
         A woman sleeping in a smart home sleep setup                      models are now equipped with anti-
                                                                              In addition to personal comfort,
                                                                           smart mattresses are also making strides
                                                                           in sleep disorder management. Some

                                                                           snore technology, which gently adjusts
                                                                           the mattress position when snoring is
                                                                           detected. This can be a game-changer
                                                                           for those suffering from mild sleep
                                                                           apnea or chronic snoring.

                                                                           Sleep apps: Digital solutions for
                                                                           better sleep hygiene
                                                                              Sleep apps have surged in popularity,
                                                                           offering tools such as guided med-
                                                                           itation, white noise generators and cog-
           patterns. Devices such as the Oura   provements, future wearables may offer   nitive behavioral therapy for insomnia
           Ring, Fitbit and WHOOP Strap provide   even more accurate insights, including   (CBT-I). Apps like Calm, Sleep Cycle
           detailed analyses of sleep cycles, heart   early detection of sleep disorders like   and Headspace help users develop
           rate variability and oxygen levels. By   sleep apnea or restless leg syndrome.   better sleep habits through data-driven
           leveraging biometric data, these wear-                          insights and personalized recommenda-
           ables offer personalized recommenda-  Smart mattresses: AI-driven   tions.
           tions for better sleep hygiene.   comfort for a better night’s sleep   One particularly innovative sleep
             For example, WHOOP, a fitness and   Traditional mattresses are being re-  app, Rise, uses circadian rhythm science
           sleep optimization tool popular among   placed by high-tech alternatives that   to predict optimal sleep and wake times
           athletes, provides recovery scores based   adapt to an individual's unique sleeping   based on users’ energy cycles. By align-
           on sleep metrics and daily strain. Users   needs. Smart mattresses, such as the   ing daily activities with natural sleep-
           report improved sleep consistency and a   Eight Sleep Pod and Sleep Number 360,   wake rhythms, individuals report in-
           greater understanding of how factors   integrate sensors to track sleep stages,   creased alertness and reduced
           like late-night exercise or alcohol con-  heart rate and body temperature. These   grogginess upon waking. Many experts
           sumption impact their rest. Tech experts   mattresses adjust firmness, cooling and   believe that sleep apps will continue to
           emphasize that wearable sleep trackers   heating settings automatically to create   evolve, incorporating AI-driven coach-
           bridge the gap between subjective sleep   the most comfortable sleeping environ-  ing to provide more tailored recommen-
           experiences and objective data, enabling   ment.                dations for sleep improvement.
           individuals to make informed decisions   One of the most groundbreaking fea-  These applications are also being in-
           about their sleep habits.       tures of smart mattresses is their ability   tegrated with smart home systems to
             Moreover, many of these devices are   to respond to biometric data in real-  provide automated sleep solutions.
           now integrating with other health met-  time. For instance, Eight Sleep’s AI-  Imagine a scenario where your sleep
           rics, such as stress levels and activity   powered temperature regulation system   app detects that you're having trouble
           tracking, to provide a more holistic   ensures that a sleeper remains at an op-  falling asleep and automatically adjusts
           view of well-being. With AI-driven im-  timal temperature throughout the night.   the room temperature or plays soothing

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[background sounds to aid relaxation.

           The role of smart home
           technology in sleep optimization
             Beyond wearables and apps, smart
           home technology is also playing a piv-
           otal role in creating the ideal sleep envi-
           ronment. Smart lighting, temperature
           control and noise management systems
           help individuals maintain a consistent
           and soothing night time routine.                                                                A high-tech smart mattress
           Smart lighting: Regulating the
           body’s natural clock
             Circadian rhythm disruptions are one
           of the leading causes of poor sleep qual-
           ity. Smart lighting systems, such as   taining a cooler bedroom temperature   ing the potential of AI-powered sleep
           Philips Hue and Casper Glow, mimic   (around 60-67°F) enhances deep sleep   coaching, brainwave stimulation for
           natural light patterns by dimming in the   stages. Smart sleep solutions that auto-  deep sleep enhancement and even non-
           evening and gradually brightening in   mate this process reduce the need for   invasive sleep monitoring embedded in
           the morning. This helps regulate mela-  manual adjustments, allowing for a   furniture and bedding.
           tonin production, allowing users to fall   more seamless transition into rest.   One particularly exciting devel-
           asleep more easily and wake up feeling                          opment is the concept of smart pajamas
           refreshed.                      White noise and soundscaping:   and bed linens equipped with biometric
             Advanced lighting technology is also   Blocking out disruptions   sensors. These advanced textiles could
           incorporating color spectrum adjust-  Noise pollution can be a major bar-  provide real-time feedback on sleep
           ments, allowing users to create custom-  rier to restful sleep, especially in urban   quality without the need for external de-
           ized lighting that supports relaxation be-  environments. White noise machines   vices, making sleep tracking even more
           fore bedtime. Some sleep-focused   and soundscaping apps, such as Bose   seamless.
           lighting systems now integrate with   Sleepbuds and Noisli, create a calming   Furthermore, neurotechnology is
           voice assistants like Alexa and Google   auditory environment by masking dis-  being integrated into sleep solutions,
           Assistant, enabling seamless adjust-  ruptive sounds. Some smart sound sys-  with devices such as the Dreem head-
           ments with simple voice commands.   tems even analyze noise patterns and   band utilizing EEG (electroencephalog-
                                           automatically adjust their output to   raphy) to analyze brain activity and pro-
           Temperature control: Cooling and   block sudden disturbances.   mote deep sleep through targeted audio
           heating for restful sleep         New advancements are incorporating   stimulation. This kind of sleep enhance-
             The temperature of a bedroom sig-  AI-driven soundscaping, where back-  ment technology could prove invaluable
           nificantly impacts sleep quality. Smart   ground sounds dynamically adapt to   for those suffering from insomnia or
           thermostats like Nest and Ecobee allow   sleep cycles. This ensures that the brain   disrupted sleep patterns.
           users to set optimal nighttime tempera-  remains undisturbed during deep sleep,   Technology is no longer just a source
           tures, ensuring a cool and comfortable   further enhancing sleep quality.   of distraction, it is becoming an essen-
           sleep environment. Additionally, newer                          tial tool in the quest for better sleep.
           innovations like the BedJet system pro-  The future of sleep technology:   From AI-driven mattresses to smart
           vide personalized climate control, en-  What lies ahead?        lighting and wearable sleep trackers,
           abling couples to enjoy different sleep   As technology continues to evolve,   cutting-edge innovations are helping in-
           temperatures on the same bed.   the future of sleep innovation looks   dividuals optimize their sleep habits and
             Recent research suggests that main-  promising. Emerging research is explor-  improve overall well-being. While sleep
                                                                           challenges persist in modern life, the
                                                                           growing accessibility of sleep-enhanc-
         Smart pillow, the sleep-enhancing accessory                       tance of prioritizing rest, it is clear that
                                                                           ing technology offers hope for millions
                                                                           seeking to achieve deeper, more restor-
                                                                           ative rest.
                                                                              As this day reminds us of the impor-
                                                                           technology is not just revolutionizing
                                                                           how we work, communicate and exer-
                                                                           cise, it is also transforming how we
                                                                           sleep. With on-going advancements in
                                                                           AI, neuroscience and smart home in-
                                                                           tegration, the future of sleep technology
                                                                           holds immense potential to reshape our
                                                                           relationship with rest, making quality
                                                                           sleep an attainable goal for all. ■

           10                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[INSIGHT



































                ove is often described as an emo-
                tional and spiritual connection   Unconditional Love
           Lbetween two individuals, tran-
           scending physical appearances. Ho-
           wever, in reality, societal norms and per-
           sonal insecurities can make romantic   The truth about
           relationships challenging, particularly
           when one partner struggles with obesity.
           Body image issues, intimacy concerns
           and social pressures create complexities
           that couples must navigate together.   romance and
           While love should ideally go beyond
           physicality, weight-related stigma and
           biases often impact self-esteem and rela-
           tionship dynamics.
             On the occasion of World Obesity
           Day, it is crucial to discuss how obesity   obesity
           affects relationships and how couples
           can foster deeper connections beyond
           societal perceptions of attractiveness.
           Love, after all, is not about a perfect   Obesity and love intersect in complex ways, but
           body but about mutual support, emo-
           tional intimacy and respect.
                                           true relationships extend beyond physical
           The intersection of obesity and   appearances. By Riya Verma
           romantic relationships
             Obesity, defined by excessive body
           weight due to fat accumulation, is often   cantly influenced when one or both part-  gain feel unattractive, which can create
           linked to health concerns, but its impact   ners struggle with obesity.   emotional barriers in relationships.
           extends to personal and social dimen-  Body image and self-worth: Obesity   When a person does not feel confident
           sions. Romantic relationships, where   often leads to body image issues, affect-  about their body, they may shy away
           physical attraction, intimacy and exter-  ing self-esteem and self-perception.   from intimacy or feel unworthy of love,
           nal judgments play a role, can be signifi-  Many individuals struggling with weight   leading to emotional distance.

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Additionally, media portrayals of
           ideal body types can further diminish
           confidence, making it harder for individ-
           uals to see their own worth beyond soci-
           etal expectations.
           Societal pressures and external
           judgments
             Society frequently imposes rigid
           beauty standards that equate thinness
           with desirability. Couples where one
           partner is obese may face judgment, un-                                                         Radhika Merchant and Anant Ambani
           solicited advice, or ridicule. Social
           media, movies and even family expecta-
           tions reinforce the idea that love is re-
           served for those who meet certain physi-
           cal criteria. This societal scrutiny can
           create insecurities and strain a relation-
           ship if partners do not support each
           other through external pressures. It is
           crucial to recognize that attractiveness is
           subjective and that true beauty lies in
           confidence, kindness and emotional con-
           nection rather than a particular body
           shape or size.
           Intimacy and emotional
           connection                                                                                      A couple of different body sizes enjoying together
             Physical intimacy plays an essential
           role in relationships and obesity can
           sometimes introduce challenges. Some
           individuals experience mobility limita-
           tions, self-consciousness, or even
           health-related issues that can affect their
           physical relationship. However, couples
           who communicate openly and focus on
           emotional intimacy can create a deeper   judgments. Such stories challenge con-
           bond that transcends these obstacles.   ventional notions of attractiveness and
           Emotional connection is built through   redefine relationship goals beyond su-
           shared experiences, mutual respect and   perficial standards.
           understanding, which far outweigh
           physical attributes in sustaining long-  Fighting societal stigma together
           term relationships.               Take the case of Priya and Arjun, an
                                           Indian couple who have been together
           Real-life stories: Love beyond   for a decade. Priya, struggling with
           physicality                     obesity since her teenage years, often
             While challenges exist, many couples   faced criticism from relatives and peers.
           successfully navigate obesity-related   Initially, she struggled with self-accept-
           struggles through communication, un-  ance, but Arjun’s unwavering support
           derstanding and unwavering support.   helped her build confidence. Instead of
                                           pressuring her to lose weight for societal
           Anant Ambani and Radhika        approval, Arjun encouraged her to focus
           Merchant: Defying beauty        on health and self-love. Their journey
           stereotypes                     highlights how emotional security in a
             Anant Ambani, son of billionaire   relationship fosters personal growth and                   Support and partnership beyond physical appearance
           Mukesh Ambani, has publicly struggled   resilience against external negativity.
           with obesity. Despite intense scrutiny,
           his relationship with Radhika Merchant   Love in the face of health
           has remained strong, demonstrating that   challenges
           love is about more than outward appear-  Another inspiring story is that of Mi-
           ance. Their bond is an example of how a   chael and Sara from the U.S. Michael
           genuine emotional connection and mu-  gained significant weight after a medical
           tual respect can overpower societal   condition, leading to self-doubt and

           12                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[oritize emotional intimacy often find
                                                                           that their relationship remains strong, re-
                                                                           gardless of physical changes over time.

                                                                           Challenging societal beauty norms
                                                                              It is crucial for couples to reject unre-
                                                                           alistic beauty standards. Embracing
         An obese couple walking together                                  beyond weight. Love should never be
                                                                           body positivity and self-acceptance can
                                                                           help both partners appreciate their worth

                                                                           conditional on conforming to societal
                                                                           expectations. By celebrating individual-
                                                                           ity and embracing uniqueness, couples
                                                                           can create a secure and loving environ-
                                                                           ment where both partners feel valued.

                                                                           The role of body positivity in
                                                                           strengthening relationships
                                                                              The body positivity movement has
                                                                           played a crucial role in challenging
         A joyful wedding celebration between partners in love
                                                                           weight-related biases. Encouraging indi-
                                                                           viduals to love themselves regardless of
                                                                           size fosters self-acceptance, which, in
                                                                           turn, strengthens relationships. When
                                                                           both partners appreciate their bodies, it
                                                                           leads to a healthier self-image, greater
                                                                           intimacy and a more fulfilling connec-
                                                                           tion.
                                                                              Couples who actively practice body
                                                                           positivity cultivate an environment
                                                                           where love thrives beyond physicality.
                                                                           They understand that true attractiveness
                                                                           stems from confidence, kindness and
                                                                           emotional compatibility rather than a
                                                                           number on the scale. Partners who uplift
                                                                           and support each other’s self-image
                                                                           build stronger relationships based on
           withdrawal from intimacy. However,   deeper level and develop a stronger   mutual respect and admiration.
           Sara’s perspective never changed. She   emotional bond.
           reminded him that love is not measured                          Love is more than skin deep
           in pounds but in moments of kindness,   Encouraging health without   Obesity and love intersect in com-
           shared laughter and deep understanding.   pressure              plex ways, but true relationships extend
           Her reassurance helped Michael regain   Obesity is often linked to health risks   beyond physical appearances. While so-
           confidence, proving that a strong emo-  such as diabetes, heart disease and joint   cietal pressures and personal insecurities
           tional foundation can withstand physical   problems. While promoting a healthier   may create challenges, genuine love is
           changes.                        lifestyle is essential, it should never be   rooted in emotional intimacy, mutual re-
                                           about forced weight loss or body sham-  spect and unwavering support. Stories
           Navigating challenges as a couple   ing. A supportive approach, such as en-  like those of Anant Ambani and Radhika
             Every relationship has its hurdles, but   gaging in fun physical activities together   Merchant remind us that love is about
           when obesity is involved, couples can   or making nutritious meals, can help   the heart, not the body.
           take deliberate steps to strengthen their   couples prioritize health without damag-  As we observe World Obesity Day, it
           bond.                           ing self-esteem. It is essential to ap-  is essential to move beyond stereotypes
                                           proach health goals as a team rather than   and appreciate relationships for what
           Emphasizing communication       placing the burden solely on one partner.   truly matters, connection, compassion
             Open discussions about insecurities,                          and unconditional love. By fostering ac-
           societal judgments and physical con-  Focusing on emotional intimacy   ceptance and challenging conventional
           cerns help couples develop a deeper un-  Beyond physical attraction, emo-  beauty norms, we can create a world
           derstanding of each other’s emotions.   tional connection forms the foundation   where love is celebrated in all its forms,
           Instead of avoiding difficult topics, part-  of lasting relationships. Acts of love,   regardless of size. True love is built on
           ners should foster honest conversations   small gestures and words of affirmation   acceptance, shared values and the ability
           where they express fears and needs   can reinforce bonds, making weight-re-  to see beyond the superficial, making re-
           without judgment. Encouraging vulner-  lated concerns less significant in the   lationships resilient and fulfilling in the
           ability allows couples to connect on a   grand scheme of love. Couples who pri-  long run. ■

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT





































           Style with a Purpose


           How fashion is




           protecting wildlife





           Fashion, once an industry of excess, is becoming a

           champion of conservation. Through ethical material              Wildlife Day, a global initiative to raise
                                                                           awareness about endangered species and
           choices, advocacy and funding of wildlife protection,           the need for conservation. In recent
                                                                           years, the fashion industry has recog-
           brands are proving that sustainability and style can            nized its responsibility and potential to
           coexist. By Rajeev Khanna                                       contribute meaningfully to this cause.
                                                                           Designers, brands and activists are forg-
                                                                           ing new paths that blend style with sus-
               ashion has long been a statement   In this transformation, fashion is emerg-  tainability, ensuring that what we wear
               of self-expression, a means to   ing as an unexpected but potent force in   doesn’t cost the planet its biodiversity.
           Fcommunicate identity and an eco-  wildlife conservation, with brands incor-  From ethical sourcing to fundraising ef-
           nomic powerhouse. However, its envi-  porating eco-conscious practices to pro-  forts, fashion is proving to be a catalyst
           ronmental footprint has often come   tect endangered species and their hab-  for change, helping protect wildlife
           under scrutiny. The industry is notorious   itats.              while reshaping industry norms.
           for resource depletion, pollution and
           ethical concerns. But today, a paradigm   Fashion and wildlife conservation:   The rise of sustainable and ethical
           shift is occurring, one where sustainabil-  A timely convergence   fashion
           ity is not just an option but a necessity.   Every year, March 3rd marks World   For decades, fashion’s relationship

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[with wildlife has been controversial,
           luxury brands have historically used ex-
           otic furs, leathers and animal-derived
           materials. However, the rise of sustain-
           able fashion is challenging these con-
           ventions. Forward-thinking designers
           and brands are shifting to alternatives
           like plant-based leathers, cruelty-free
           textiles and recycled materials, elimi-
           nating the need for materials that exploit
           wildlife.
           Brands making a difference                                                                      An artisan creating upcycled clothing
             Numerous global and Indian brands
           are leading the way in merging fashion
           with conservation efforts.
             Stella McCartney has pioneered sus-
           tainable luxury, using vegan leather and
           eco-friendly textiles while advocating
           for animal welfare.
             Patagonia, known for its environ-
           mental activism, donates a portion of its
           profits to conservation initiatives, sup-
           porting habitat restoration and wildlife
           protection.
             Pangaia, an innovative brand, creates
           clothing from materials like seaweed
           fiber and recycled cotton, with profits
           funding biodiversity projects.
             House of Anita Dongre, an Indian
           luxury brand, has embraced sustainabil-                                                         Shoes made from pineapple leather on display
           ity by using organic fabrics and support-
           ing forest conservation efforts in Rajas-
           than.
             Rashki, an Indian accessories brand,
           crafts vegan leather bags, reducing de-
           pendence on animal-based products
           while maintaining high ethical stan-
           dards.                          Brands are increasingly turning to mate-
             Vaute Couture, one of the first com-  rials such as mycelium leather (derived
           pletely vegan fashion brands, focuses on   from mushrooms), pineapple leather (Pi-
           sustainable and high-performance out-  ñatex) and apple leather as ethical sub-
           erwear made without harming animals.   stitutes for traditional leather.
             People Tree, a pioneer in ethical   Recycled and upcycled fashion:
           fashion, collaborates with Fair Trade ar-  Companies like Ecoalf and Rimagined
           tisans and farmers to promote environ-  repurpose discarded materials, reducing
           mentally friendly clothing.     waste and protecting natural habitats
             These brands are not just reducing   from industrial pollution.
           their carbon footprint but actively con-  Organic and regenerative farming:
           tributing to wildlife conservation   Fashion labels are working with farmers
           through donations, advocacy and sus-  to adopt regenerative agriculture, which
           tainable material sourcing.     restores ecosystems and promotes bio-
                                           diversity.
           Ethical sourcing and eco-friendly   Natural dyeing techniques: Many
           materials                       brands are adopting plant-based dyes,
             One of the most significant ways the   reducing the harmful impact of synthetic               A model showcasing a wildlife-inspired collection
           fashion industry is protecting wildlife is   dyes on aquatic life and soil quality.
           through ethical sourcing. Over-extrac-
           tion of natural resources threatens bio-  Fashion as an advocacy tool for
           diversity, but sustainable brands are   wildlife protection
           mitigating these effects through innova-  Beyond material choices, fashion
           tive practices.                 brands are using their platforms to
             Vegan and plant-based alternatives:   spread awareness and fund conservation

           16                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[efforts. From runway collections in-  between consumer consciousness and   can contribute
           spired by endangered species to direct   tangible conservation efforts, reinforcing   While brands play a crucial role, con-
           financial support for wildlife organiza-  the idea that fashion can be a tool for   sumers hold the power to drive change
           tions, advocacy is becoming a core ele-  positive environmental change.   through their choices. By supporting
           ment of sustainable fashion.                                    sustainable and ethical brands, individ-
                                           India’s growing role in sustainable   uals can contribute to wildlife conserva-
           Wildlife-themed collections     fashion                         tion and environmental protection.
             Gucci’s off the grid collection fea-  India, with its rich textile heritage
           tures sustainable materials and donates a   and diverse ecosystems, is uniquely po-  Ways to make a difference:
           percentage of sales to global wildlife   sitioned to champion sustainable fash-  Choose ethical brands: Opt for com-
           conservation projects.          ion. However, challenges such as pollu-  panies that prioritize sustainable materi-
             Save the duck, an Italian outerwear   tion from textile manufacturing and   als and donate to conservation efforts.
           brand, promotes animal welfare by elim-  unethical labor practices persist. Despite   Reduce, reuse, recycle: Embrace a
           inating down feathers from its products   these hurdles, a new wave of Indian de-  circular fashion mindset by repurposing
           and funding environmental causes.   signers and brands is redefining the   old clothing and supporting upcycled
             Ralph Lauren’s earth polo is made   landscape by prioritizing eco-conscious   fashion.
           from recycled plastic bottles, reducing   materials and ethical production.   Advocate for change: Use social
           ocean pollution and indirectly benefiting   Grassroot by Anita Dongre supports   media to raise awareness and demand
           marine life.                    rural artisans while advocating for envi-  transparency from brands regarding
             Lacoste’s save our species campaign   ronmental conservation.   their environmental impact.
           replaced its iconic crocodile logo with   No Nasties, a 100% organic cotton   Support local and artisanal fashion:
           endangered animal motifs to raise   brand, ensures fair trade practices and   Handloom textiles and eco-friendly dyes
           awareness about species extinction.   eliminates harmful chemicals, reducing   not only preserve India’s cultural her-
             These initiatives help bridge the gap   harm to wildlife.     itage but also protect ecosystems.
                                             Doodlage, a brand specializing in up-  Educate yourself and others: Stay in-
                                           cycled fashion, repurposes industrial   formed about sustainability trends and
                                           waste to create unique, sustainable   encourage friends and family to make
                                           pieces.                         ethical fashion choices.
                                             Upasana, based in Auroville, inte-
                                           grates sustainability with traditional In-  The future of fashion and
                                           dian textiles, supporting biodiversity and   conservation
                                           local weavers.                     The intersection of fashion and wild-
                                             B Label, a hemp-based fashion   life conservation is still evolving, but the
                                           brand, promotes the use of biodegrad-  momentum is undeniable. The industry
                                           able fabrics and water-efficient produc-  is gradually shifting from an extractive
                                           tion methods.                   model to a regenerative one, where
                                             Government initiatives, like Project   profits are aligned with planetary well-
                                           Tiger and the Green India Mission, have   being. The integration of technology,
                                           also indirectly influenced the fashion in-  such as biodegradable fabrics, 3D knit-
                                           dustry by promoting ecological con-  ting and AI-driven sustainable supply
                                           sciousness, encouraging brands to align   chains, is further revolutionizing the
                                           with conservation values.       space.
                                                                              As consumers become more in-
                                           Consumer power: How individuals   formed and demand accountability,
                                                                           brands will have no choice but to prior-
                                                                           itize ethical practices. Governments,
         A protest against animal cruelty in the fashion industry
                                                                           corporations and individuals must work
                                                                           collectively to ensure that fashion not
                                                                           only enhances personal style but also
                                                                           safeguards the natural world.
                                                                              Fashion, once an industry of excess,
                                                                           is becoming a champion of conserva-
                                                                           tion. Through ethical material choices,
                                                                           advocacy and funding of wildlife protec-
                                                                           tion, brands are proving that sustainabil-
                                                                           ity and style can coexist. World Wildlife
                                                                           Day serves as a reminder that every pur-
                                                                           chase we make is a vote for the kind of
                                                                           world we want to live in. By supporting
                                                                           eco-conscious brands, we are not just
                                                                           following a trend, we are shaping a fu-
                                                                           ture where fashion respects both human-
                                                                           ity and the planet. ■

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Nature’s secret code


     DEEP DIVE  The hidden






           mathematics in





           everyday life














                                                                           long studied how the Fibonacci
                                                                           sequence appears in phyllotaxis, the ar-
                                                                           rangement of leaves around a stem to
                                                                           optimize sunlight exposure. The angle
                                                                           between consecutive leaves, known as
                                                                           the golden angle (~137.5 degrees), en-
                                                                           sures maximum efficiency in photosyn-
                                                                           thesis. Similarly, the spirals seen in pine-
                                                                           cones, pineapples and succulents adhere
                                                                           to Fibonacci ratios, creating patterns that
                                                                           are not just visually striking but func-
                                                                           tionally optimal.
                                                                              This sequence is also present in ani-
                                                                           mal morphology. The spirals of snail
                                                                           shells and the proportions of human
                                                                           anatomy reflect Fibonacci ratios, which
                                                                           contribute to structural stability and aes-
                                                                           thetic appeal. Even in microscopic life
                                                                           forms such as diatoms, the influence of
                 ature is a grand tapestry woven   plants grow to the migration patterns of   these mathematical principles is evident,
                 with intricate patterns, each   animals. Through this exploration, we   revealing nature’s deep-rooted reliance
           Nthread guided by the universal   uncover the hidden frameworks that   on mathematical order.
           language of mathematics. From the spi-  govern our universe, making complex
           rals of galaxies to the veins in leaves,   natural phenomena both accessible and   Fractals: Infinite complexity in
           the mathematical principles governing   awe-inspiring.          finite space
           these structures offer an extraordinary                            Another mathematical marvel found
           window into the logic behind nature’s   The Fibonacci sequence: Nature’s   in nature is the fractal, a self-replicating,
           beauty. This seamless relationship be-  code of design          infinitely complex pattern that appears
           tween math and the natural world is not   One of the most well-known math-  similar at different scales. Fractals are
           merely coincidental, it is foundational to   ematical patterns in nature is the Fibo-  evident in various natural structures,
         By Siddharth Mehta  tween mathematics and nature, the   ones (0, 1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, …). This   terns of snowflakes.
                                           nacci sequence, a series where each
                                                                           from the branching of trees to the jagged
           life itself.
             Recognizing the deep connection be-
                                           number is the sum of the two preceding
                                                                           edges of coastlines and the intricate pat-
                                           sequence is found in an astonishing
                                                                              One of the most famous fractals, the
           world celebrates the International Day
                                                                           Mandelbrot set, mirrors the recursive
                                           array of natural forms, from the arrange-
           of Mathematics on March 14 each year.
           This occasion serves as a reminder of
                                                                           patterns found in ferns, Romanesco
                                           ment of leaves on a stem to the spirals of
                                           sunflowers and pinecones.
           how mathematical principles shape our
                                                                           broccoli and river networks. The con-
           understanding of reality, from the way
                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025
           18                                Mathematicians and biologists have   cept of self-similarity allows nature to]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Top: Shell showcasing the logarithmic spiral  Bottom: A microscopic view of diatoms showcasing geometric patterns


















                                                                           sizing the fundamental role of math in
                                                                           nature.
                                                                           The role of math in evolutionary
                                                                           biology and ecosystems
                                                                              Mathematics also plays a crucial role
                                                                           in understanding evolutionary biology
                                                                           and ecosystem dynamics. The Lotka-
                                                                           Volterra equations, for example, model
                                                                           predator-prey relationships, demonstrat-
           maximize efficiency. For instance, in the   mals search for food, highlights the un-  ing how species populations fluctuate in
           respiratory system, the bronchi divide   derlying mathematical framework of   cycles based on resource availability and
           into smaller and smaller branches, en-  survival strategies.    competition.
           suring efficient oxygen exchange while   Birds, for example, follow Levy   Additionally, the concept of symme-
           maintaining structural integrity.   flight patterns, a type of random walk   try and tessellations can be seen in the
             Dr. Emily Carter, a biologist at the   that combines short movements with oc-  evolution of camouflage and defensive
           University of Cambridge, explains:   casional long-distance flights. This   adaptations. Many species, such as but-
           “Fractals demonstrate how nature man-  strategy, observed in species like alba-  terflies and zebras, exhibit bilateral sym-
           ages to fit complex structures into finite   trosses and honeybees, maximizes effi-  metry, which aids in survival by confus-
           space. This self-repeating pattern is not   ciency when searching for sparse re-  ing predators. In marine ecosystems, the
         Bottom: A school of fish swimming in synchronized motion
           just aesthetically pleasing but vital for   sources. Similarly, the synchronized   honeycomb pattern of coral structures
           biological functions, from blood circula-  movement of schools of fish and mur-  follows geometric principles that maxi-
       Top: A sunflower displaying the Fibonacci sequence
           tion to neural networks.”       murations of starlings follow rules of   mize space efficiency and structural re-
             In weather systems, fractals also   swarm intelligence, where simple math-  silience.
           emerge in cloud formations and light-  ematical algorithms dictate group be-  Dr. Laura Chen, an ecologist, re-
           ning patterns. The chaotic yet structured   havior without centralized control.   marks: “Mathematics allows us to pre-
           design of fractals enables scientists to   Mathematician Dr. Raj Patel, from   dict changes in ecosystems and under-
           model climate patterns, understand tur-  MIT, notes: “The movement of animals   stand how species interact. By modeling
           bulence and predict environmental   often mirrors mathematical equations   population dynamics, we can make in-
           changes more accurately.        that describe chaos and order. From traf-  formed conservation decisions.”
                                           fic flow to the spread of epidemics, the   Mathematics also aids in climate
           The mathematics of animal       same principles apply across different   modeling, helping scientists predict fu-
           behavior and movement           systems.”                       ture ecological shifts and biodiversity
             Beyond static structures, mathemati-  Patterns of migration, from monarch   changes. Understanding these patterns
           cal principles also govern the behavior   butterflies traveling thousands of miles   enables conservationists to develop sus-
           and movement of animals. The study of   to the V-formations of migrating birds,   tainable strategies to protect fragile eco-
           optimal foraging theory, which uses cal-  adhere to principles of aerodynamics   systems and mitigate the impact of cli-
           culus and probability to predict how ani-  and energy conservation, further empha-  mate change.

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Leonardo da Vinci's Vitruvian Man                                                                 A depiction of the Parthenon showcasing the golden ratio














           Mathematics in art and design:
           Inspired by nature
             Beyond science, mathematical pat-
           terns in nature have deeply influenced
           art, architecture and design. The golden
           ratio (approximately 1.618), derived
           from the Fibonacci sequence, has been
           used in the Parthenon, Da Vinci’s Vit-
           ruvian Man and even modern branding
           and UI/UX design. The mesmerizing
           symmetry of snowflakes, spirals of nau-
           tilus shells and fractal geometry of light-                                                     A high-speed train inspired by a bird’s beak for aerodynamics
           ning have inspired artists, sculptors and
           architects for centuries.
             Artists like M.C. Escher incorporated
           tessellations and symmetry into their
           work, showcasing how nature’s math-
           ematical blueprints transcend dis-
           ciplines. Fashion designers use fractals
           to create dynamic, organic textures,
           while architects implement Fibonacci
           spirals in structures like the Gherkin
           building in London.             understanding of the world’s underlying
             The field of biomimicry also incor-  mechanisms.
           porates nature’s mathematical principles   As we celebrate the International
           into innovative designs. Engineers and   Day of Mathematics, it is worth reflect-
           designers study the efficiency of honey-  ing on how deeply mathematics in-
           comb structures, the aerodynamics of   fluences everything around us. Whether
           bird wings and the fluid dynamics of   you are a scientist, artist, or philosopher,
           fish movement to develop sustainable   these patterns offer a profound sense of
           and high-performance technologies.   connection between numbers and nature.
                                           By exploring these hidden structures, we
           The poetry of numbers in nature   not only appreciate the beauty of math-
             Mathematics is often perceived as an   ematics but also gain valuable insights
           abstract, human-made construct, but its   into the delicate and intricate workings
           omnipresence in nature tells a different   of the universe.                                     The golden ratio in the Mona Lisa painting
           story. The hidden mathematical patterns   The next time you observe a sun-
           that shape life, from the spirals of galax-  flower or watch birds in flight, take a
           ies to the movement of fish, reveal a   moment to recognize the silent but om-
           world governed by logic and efficiency.   nipresent hand of mathematics at play, a
           These patterns not only make nature   language that nature has been speaking
           visually captivating but also enhance our   since the beginning of time. ■

           20                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Beyond barriers




           Traveling the world in                                                                                SPOTLIGHT






           a wheelchair






           As accessibility continues to improve worldwide, wheelchair users are proving that
           travel is for everyone. Whether exploring the historic streets of Europe, embracing the

           natural beauty of Australia, or navigating the bustling cities of Asia, the world is
           becoming more open to all travelers. By Ishita Desai





















         A wheelchair traveler enjoying the outdoors




















                ravel is often described as a jour-  destinations, hotels and airlines prioritiz-  celebrate achievements, acknowledge
                ney of discovery, a way to ex-  ing accessibility. Today, individuals who   remaining barriers and advocate for
           Tperience new cultures, landscapes   use wheelchairs can traverse the globe   further improvements in mobility rights.
           and traditions. However, for wheelchair   with greater ease, proving that adventure   As we mark this occasion, it is essential
           users, travel has historically been   and exploration are truly for everyone.   to explore the world of accessible travel,
           fraught with challenges, from inacces-  Recognized on March 1st each year,   highlight inspiring stories of wheelchair
           sible accommodations to transportation   International Wheelchair Day serves as   users who have defied limitations and
           hurdles. Fortunately, the landscape of   a reminder of the importance of acces-  provide practical insights for planning
           global tourism is changing, with more   sibility and inclusivity. It is a day to   seamless journeys.

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[The evolution of accessible
           tourism
             In recent years, accessible tourism
           has gained significant momentum,
           driven by a growing demand for inclu-
           sive travel experiences. The World
           Health Organization estimates that over
           a billion people live with some form of
           disability, with a considerable number
           requiring mobility aids. Recognizing
           this, the travel industry has begun mak-
           ing changes to accommodate wheelchair
           users, ensuring that destinations are not                                                       A wheelchair traveler at the Eiffel Tower
           just open to all but also enjoyable for
           everyone.
             Countries such as the United States,
           Canada, Australia and several European
           nations have led the way in promoting
           accessibility. Airports now feature step-
           free pathways, designated assistance
           services and accessible restrooms. Ho-
           tels offer rooms equipped with roll-in
           showers, grab bars and automatic doors.
           Public transportation systems in many
           cities have ramps, elevators and des-
           ignated wheelchair spaces. These im-
           provements reflect a broader movement
           towards universal design, benefiting not
           only wheelchair users but also elderly
           travelers, families with strollers and in-
           dividuals with temporary injuries.                                                              A wheelchair tourist enjoying the hillside view

           First-hand experiences: Stories of
           wheelchair travelers
             To truly understand the impact of ac-
           cessible tourism, it is invaluable to hear
           from those who have navigated the
           world in a wheelchair. John Morris, a
           travel blogger and founder of Wheelc-  cessible with proper planning. His blog
           hairTravel.org, has visited more than 40   provides practical guides for wheelchair
           countries despite being a triple amputee.   users, detailing everything from acces-
           He shares that while challenges still ex-  sible hotels to transportation options.
           ist, destinations like London, Tokyo and
           Sydney have made impressive strides in   Best wheelchair-friendly
           accessibility.                  destinations
             Similarly, British adventurer Sophie   While accessibility varies worldwide,
           Morgan, a television presenter and dis-  certain destinations stand out for their
           ability advocate, has embarked on jour-  commitment to inclusivity. Here are
           neys that many consider daunting. From   some top recommendations:
           riding adapted bikes in South America
           to exploring the historic sites of Greece,   Barcelona, Spain
           she emphasizes the importance of re-  Barcelona is a model city for acces-
           search and planning. "Traveling in a   sibility. Its extensive public transporta-               Beach accessibility
           wheelchair is about resilience and re-  tion system is wheelchair-friendly, with
           sourcefulness. The world is opening up   low-floor buses and accessible metro
           and we must take advantage of it," she   stations. Iconic sites such as Sagrada Fa-
           says.                           mília and Park Güell have ramps and el-  dam has made remarkable efforts to en-
             Other travelers, such as Cory Lee, an   evators, while the city’s beaches even   sure inclusivity. The city’s trams and
           award-winning travel writer, document   feature adapted pathways and amphibi-  buses are accessible and many of its fa-
           their experiences to help others. He has   ous wheelchairs for water access.   mous museums, including the Rijks-
           visited destinations as diverse as Mo-                          museum and Van Gogh Museum, cater
           rocco and Antarctica, demonstrating that   Amsterdam, Netherlands   to wheelchair users with lifts and step-
           even the most remote places can be ac-  Despite its historic nature, Amster-  free entry points.

           22                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[if needed. A portable ramp or foldable
                                                                           shower chair can also enhance comfort
                                                                           during your stay.

                                                                           Leverage local support
                                                                              Many cities have accessibility offices
                                                                           or disability-friendly tour operators. En-
                                                                           gaging with local resources can help in
         A wheelchair traveler at the airport                              Be prepared for challenges
                                                                           navigating challenges effectively.

                                                                              Even in the most accessible places,
                                                                           unexpected hurdles can arise. Maintain a
                                                                           flexible mindset and don’t hesitate to
                                                                           ask for assistance when needed.

                                                                           The future of accessible travel
                                                                              While progress has been made, there
                                                                           is still work to be done. Advocacy
                                                                           groups continue to push for greater ac-
                                                                           cessibility, from ensuring wheelchair-
                                                                           friendly sidewalks to improving trans-
         A wheelchair-accessible public transport system                   drive change.
                                                                           portation infrastructure in
                                                                           less-developed regions. The rise of ac-
                                                                           cessible travel influencers and bloggers
                                                                           is also helping to raise awareness and

                                                                              Hotels and airlines are increasingly
                                                                           recognizing that accessibility is not just
                                                                           a moral imperative but also a smart busi-
                                                                           ness move. A more inclusive tourism in-
                                                                           dustry benefits everyone, expanding the
                                                                           market to include travelers of all abil-
                                                                           ities. Governments, too, are playing a
                                                                           role by enacting regulations and funding
                                                                           initiatives to promote accessibility in
                                                                           public spaces.
                                                                              With advancements in technology,
           Sydney, Australia               is among the best for wheelchair users   accessibility is further improving. Apps
             Sydney is known for its welcoming   and many tourist sites, such as Shinjuku   that provide real-time information on ac-
           attitude toward travelers with disabil-  Gyoen and the Tokyo Tower, have been   cessible routes, voice-activated assis-
           ities. Major attractions, including the   adapted for inclusive access.   tance for booking services and AI-pow-
           Sydney Opera House and Taronga Zoo,   Tips for planning an accessible trip   ered solutions for navigation are making
           offer excellent accessibility features.   To make traveling as smooth as pos-  travel more convenient for wheelchair
           Even outdoor adventures, such as the ac-  sible, consider the following strategies:   users.
           cessible coastal walk from Bondi to
           Coogee, showcase Australia’s commit-  Research and plan ahead   Travel knows no bounds
           ment to inclusion.                Before booking, check accessibility   The ability to explore new destina-
                                           details of accommodations, transport   tions should not be restricted by mobil-
           Washington, D.C., USA           and attractions. Websites like Accessible   ity. As accessibility continues to im-
             As the capital of the United States,   Travel Online and WheelchairTravel.org   prove worldwide, wheelchair users are
           Washington, D.C., is a pioneer in acces-  offer firsthand reviews and insights.   proving that travel is for everyone.
           sible travel. Nearly all of its attractions,                    Whether exploring the historic streets of
           including the Smithsonian Museums, the   Contact airlines in advance   Europe, embracing the natural beauty of
           National Mall and the U.S. Capitol, pro-  Most airlines offer assistance for   Australia, or navigating the bustling
           vide step-free access. The Metro system   wheelchair users, but policies vary. In-  cities of Asia, the world is becoming
           is also one of the most wheelchair-  form the airline of your needs before-  more open to all travelers.This Inter-
           friendly in the country.        hand, ensuring a hassle-free airport and   national Wheelchair Day, let’s celebrate
                                           flight experience.              the remarkable resilience of those who
           Tokyo, Japan                                                    travel fearlessly against the odds and
             Tokyo has invested heavily in acces-  Pack smart              continue advocating passionately for a
           sibility in preparation for events like the   Bring essential repair tools for your   future where every beautiful corner of
           Paralympics. Its transportation network   wheelchair, as well as extra medication,   the world is fully accessible to all. ■

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY











































           More than just hair                                                     igs have long been a fascinat-
                                                                                   ing aspect of personal adorn-
                                                                           Wment, transcending mere
                                                                           practicality to become powerful symbols
           The emotional                                                   Throughout history, wigs have reflected
                                                                           of status, beauty and self-expression.
                                                                           societal values, class distinctions and
                                                                           evolving fashion trends. From the opu-
                                                                           lent courts of Europe to contemporary
                                                                           pop icons, these versatile hairpieces
           and cultural                                                    have undergone a remarkable transfor-
                                                                           mation, remaining as relevant today as
                                                                           they were centuries ago.
                                                                              As we celebrate International Wig
                                                                           Day, it is an opportune moment to delve
           power of wigs                                                   cultural significance. This journey takes
                                                                           into the rich history of wigs and their
                                                                           us from the elaborate headpieces of an-
                                                                           cient civilizations to the colorful and
                                                                           creative wigs that define modern enter-
                                                                           tainment, fashion and self-identity.
                                                                           Whether adorning the heads of mon-
           Wigs are more than just accessories; they are woven             archs or being a staple in the drag com-
                                                                           munity, wigs continue to shape personal
           into the very fabric of history, fashion, and self-             and collective expressions of style.
           expression. Their enduring presence in society speaks           Ancient beginnings: The origins of
                                                                           wigs
           to their versatility and the deeply personal connection            The history of wigs dates back to an-
           individuals have with hair. By Rohan Kapoor                     cient civilizations, where they served
                                                                           both functional and aesthetic purposes.

           24                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[came emblems of aristocratic distinc-
                                                                           tion, with courtiers competing to display
                                                                           the most voluminous and ornate hair-
                                                                           pieces.
                                                                              During this era, wigs were meticu-
                                                                           lously crafted from horsehair, goat hair,
                                                                           or human hair and were often powdered
                                                                           white for a refined, sophisticated look.
                                                                           These wigs, known as perukes, were in-
                                                                           tegral to courtly attire and legal profes-
         European aristocratic wigs                                        wigs played a role in shaping political
                                                                           sions—remnants of which can still be
                                                                           seen today in the British judicial system.
                                                                              Aside from their aesthetic appeal,
                                                                           dynamics. The grandeur of wigs became
                                                                           a way for rulers and nobles to reinforce
                                                                           their dominance, setting clear distinc-
                                                                           tions between the upper and lower
                                                                           classes. The labor-intensive maintenance
                                                                           of these wigs further emphasized the
                                                                           wealth and leisure of those who wore
                                                                           them, as only the affluent could afford
                                                                           the services of skilled wigmakers.

                                                                           The 18th and 19th centuries:
                                                                           Changing attitudes toward wigs
                                                                              As fashion evolved, so too did the
                                                                           role of wigs. By the late 18th century,
                                                                           the French and American revolutions
         Ancient Egyptian wigs                                             saw a decline in the extravagant wig cul-
                                                                           ushered in an era of social change that
                                                                           ture. The fall of the French aristocracy
                                                                           made wigs symbols of excess, leading to
                                                                           their decline in everyday fashion.
                                                                              By the 19th century, wigs were
                                                                           largely replaced by natural hairstyles, al-
           The earliest evidence of wigs can be   within a religious hierarchy. The signifi-
           traced to Ancient Egypt (circa 3000   cance of wigs in these early civilizations
           BCE), where they were worn by both   highlights their role as more than just
           men and women to protect their shaved   fashion statements—they were deeply
           heads from the sun and lice. Egyptian   intertwined with identity and spirituality.
           wigs, often made from human hair, palm
           fibers, or wool, signified social rank—  The renaissance of wigs: Status
           elaborate, thick wigs were reserved for   and power in European courts
           the elite, while simpler versions were   By the 16th and 17th centuries, wigs
           worn by commoners.              had become symbols of prestige and no-
             In Ancient Greece and Rome, wigs   bility, particularly in Europe. The Ren-
           were popular among the aristocracy.   aissance saw a revival of wig-wearing,
           Greek women often donned golden or   with Queen Elizabeth I of England fa-
           red wigs, sometimes emulating the di-  mously donning an array of elaborate
           vine beauty of deities, while Roman em-  red wigs, reinforcing her regal image.
           perors and patricians used wigs to con-  During this period, wigs were not only a
           vey authority. Julius Caesar, for   sign of wealth but also a practical solu-
           instance, was rumored to wear a wig to   tion to the rampant spread of lice and
           conceal his balding scalp, setting a   poor hygiene.
           precedent for hairpieces being associ-  The 17th century witnessed the rise
           ated with political power.      of extravagant wigs, particularly in
             Wigs in ancient societies were not   France. King Louis XIII, suffering from
           just for the wealthy; they also served re-  premature baldness, popularized the use
           ligious and ritualistic purposes. In some   of wigs among men, a trend that his suc-
           cultures, wigs were worn during cere-  cessor, Louis XIV (the Sun King), el-                    Roman wig styles
           monies to honor gods, while in others,   evated to new heights. The towering,
           they symbolized transformation or status   powdered wigs of the French court be-

           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Wigs showcased in a fashion show                                                                  18th-century French court wigs














           though they remained essential in cer-
           tain professions. Judges, lawyers and
           clergy members continued to wear tradi-
           tional wigs as markers of authority and
           decorum.
             During the Victorian era, wigs saw a
           subtle resurgence in the form of hair-
           pieces and extensions rather than full
           wigs. Women in high society used artifi-
           cial hair to create elaborate updos and
           voluminous styles, blending natural hair
           with enhancements to maintain a refined
           look. This shift marked the beginning of
           a more practical and discreet approach                                                          Wigs on the fashion runway
           to wig-wearing, setting the stage for fu-
           ture trends.

           The 20th century: Wigs in fashion,
           film and performance
             The 20th century marked a resur-  Gaga, with her ever-changing wig col-  The future of wigs: Innovation and
           gence of wigs, but in a more diverse and   lection, have continued to push the   cultural significance
           democratized fashion. No longer solely   boundaries of fashion and identity   With the rise of 3D printing, high-
           symbols of nobility, wigs became widely   through wigs.         tech synthetic fibers and custom lace-
           accessible due to advancements in syn-                          front wigs, the future of wigs looks
           thetic hair production.         Wigs in contemporary pop culture   promising. Innovations in wig-making
             Hollywood played a significant role   and identity            ensure greater comfort, realism and per-
           in revitalizing the popularity of wigs.   Today, wigs are more versatile and   sonalization, making wigs more acces-
           From Marlene Dietrich’s platinum   widely embraced than ever. They serve a   sible to diverse audiences. As societal
           waves to Marilyn Monroe’s iconic   myriad of functions, from aesthetic en-  norms around beauty and self-expres-
           blonde curls, wigs allowed actors and   hancement to self-empowerment. For   sion continue to evolve, wigs will likely
           entertainers to craft signature looks. The   cosplayers and costume designers, wigs   remain an integral part of personal style,
           1960s and 1970s saw the emergence of   are essential tools for transforming into   artistic performance and cultural iden-
           bold, voluminous wigs inspired by mod   fictional characters. In the drag and   tity.
           fashion and disco culture, with figures   LGBTQ+ communities, wigs symbolize   As we commemorate International
           like Diana Ross and Cher popularizing   freedom of expression, gender fluidity   Wig Day, it is clear that wigs are more
           glamorous, oversized styles.    and artistic creativity.        than just accessories; they are woven
             The entertainment industry further   The fashion world continues to cele-  into the very fabric of history, fashion
           embraced wigs with the rise of drag cul-  brate wigs, with designers such as Alex-  and self-expression. Their enduring
           ture. RuPaul, one of the most influential   ander McQueen and Vivienne Westwood   presence in society speaks to their ver-
           drag queens in history, used wigs as a   incorporating extravagant hairpieces   satility and the deeply personal connec-
           transformative tool, demonstrating their   into their runway shows. Celebrities like   tion individuals have with hair. From an-
           power in gender expression and per-  Katy Perry, Nicki Minaj and Cardi B   cient pharaohs to modern-day
           formance art. Similarly, musicians such   have embraced wigs as part of their pub-  superstars, wigs continue to empower,
           as David Bowie, with his flamboyant   lic personas, using them to craft ever-  transform, and inspire confidence and
           red mullet as Ziggy Stardust and Lady   evolving, dramatic looks.   artistry. ■

           26                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                  March 01-15, 2025






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Your energy is high, making it a great time to   Exciting opportunities in career and personal life
                     tackle new projects. Career growth is promising,   keep you engaged. Romantic life sees passion,
                     but avoid unnecessary conflicts. Romance is     but clear expectations are needed. Financially,
                     exciting, with deeper connections forming.      stay cautious with big investments. Prioritize
                     Financially, budgeting is key.                  physical and emotional well-being.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Stability defines this period. Work progresses   Change is on the horizon, embrace it for growth.
                     steadily, but patience is needed for major      Career shifts may bring long-term benefits. Love
                     breakthroughs. Love life sees harmony, with     life requires openness and trust. Financially,
                     strong emotional support. Financially, avoid    stick to practical decisions. Pay attention to men-
                     impulsive purchases.                            tal and emotional health.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     A socially vibrant period, networking brings un-  An adventurous time, with potential travel or
                     expected opportunities. Work requires adaptabil-  new experiences. Career moves bring satisfac-
                     ity; new collaborations may emerge. Love life is   tion. Love life is exciting, but commitment
                     full of surprises, but clear communication is es-  should be taken seriously. Physical activity
                     sential. Keep an eye on stress and get rest.    keeps you energized, focus on a healthy lifestyle.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     A period of deep introspection and emotional    Work success comes with patience and persist-
                     clarity. Career prospects improve with dis-     ence. Love life is stable, but make time for per-
                     ciplined efforts. Love life requires patience,   sonal connections. Financially, wise investments
                     avoid overreacting. Financially, steady planning   pay off. Maintain work-life balance to prevent
                     helps. Focus on mental health and self-care.    stress.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Your leadership skills shine, bringing rec-     Creativity soars, benefiting career and personal
                     ognition at work. Relationships are fulfilling, but   projects. Love life is fulfilling with meaningful
                     balance is key. Financial growth is likely      conversations. Financial gains are possible, but
                     through smart decision-making. Health remains   spending wisely is crucial. Prioritize mental
                     stable, maintain a regular exercise routine.    peace and mindfulness.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Work requires attention to detail, but your efforts   A period of strong intuition, trust your instincts.
                     will be appreciated. Relationships flourish with   Career decisions should be well thought out. Ro-
                     honest conversations. Financially, it’s a good   mance is rewarding, but avoid unrealistic expec-
                     time to save. Health-wise, avoid overworking    tations. Financial stability is within reach. Relax-
                     and ensure proper relaxation.                   ation and meditation benefit health.


           MARCH 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 www.revoir.in                                  27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Trump's Tariff Threat: A Challenge
                                           program, gaps remain in immunization
           for India
                                           coverage. Authorities must ensure full
             U.S. President Donald Trump's threat
                                                                           is not enhanced. His political future now
                                           vaccination, strengthen airport screen-
           to impose new tariffs on India has raised   its Measles-Rubella (MR) vaccination   other options if his role within Congress
           significant concerns for the country's   ing, and educate the public on preven-  hinges on whether the party acknowl-
           exporters. Trump has labeled India as a   tive measures. The government should   edges his contributions and provides
           "tariff king," criticizing its high tariffs on   also collaborate with international health   him with a more influential role, ensur-
           U.S. imports. This move could severely   agencies to track and contain potential   ing his active participation in key deci-
           impact India's export sectors, particularly   threats.          sions.
           chemicals, metals, and automobiles,   A single imported case can spark an   Rajeev Ranjan, Bhopal, Madhya Pra-
           which are already vulnerable to U.S.   outbreak in under-immunized areas. We   desh, India
           tariffs. India has taken steps to reduce   must act swiftly to safeguard public
           tariffs in its latest budget, aiming to   health. Prevention is our best defense
           mitigate potential U.S. actions.    against this highly infectious disease.   The cultural allure and reality of
             However, a more sustainable solution   Arvind K. Sharma, Delhi, India   smoking
           might involve sectoral free trade                                  I read Ishita Desai’s article, in the
           agreements to reduce tensions and boost                         current issue of Revoir. The piece is in-
           bilateral trade. It is crucial for India to   Shashi Tharoor's Uncertain Future   credibly engaging, not because I am a
           negotiate effectively and diversify its   in Congress!          fan of smoking cigars or pipes, but be-
           trade relationships to minimize the   Shashi Tharoor, a prominent Con-  cause of the writer’s ability to weave to-
           economic impact of these tariffs. The   gress leader, has sparked speculation   gether art, movies, culture, literature,
           upcoming meeting between Prime   about his future in the party. Tharoor has   values, and even fashion into a thought-
           Minister Modi and Trump could be   expressed frustration over being side-  provoking narrative. Desai’s exploration
           pivotal in addressing these issues and   lined and has hinted at leaving Congress   of pipe smoking as a symbol of sophisti-
           securing favorable trade terms for India.   if his services are not utilized effec-  cation and rebellion is both insightful
           Anushka Patel, Mumbai, Maharashtra,   tively. He has staked a claim for the   and captivating.
           India                           chief ministership of Kerala, citing his   While the article beautifully high-
                                           popularity in the state. Despite his asser-  lights the cultural and aesthetic signifi-
                                           tions of loyalty to Congress, Tharoor's   cance of smoking, it also subtly opens a
           Measles Outbreak in the USA: A   remarks have created unease among   dialogue about its health implications.
           Threat to India?                party leaders. His recent meeting with   On one hand, smoking has been roman-
             The recent measles outbreak in the   Rahul Gandhi aimed to address these   ticized in art and literature, symbolizing
           United States is alarming, with rising   concerns, but the outcome remains   freedom and style. On the other, it re-
           cases due to declining vaccination rates.   unclear.            mains a serious public health concern.
           Given global travel, India must remain   Tharoor's dissatisfaction stems from   Perhaps a future piece could delve
           vigilant to prevent the virus from   a perceived leadership vacuum in Kerala   deeper into this duality, balancing the al-
           spreading here. Measles is highly con-  and limited opportunities within the   lure with the realities. Thank you for
           tagious and can lead to severe complica-  party. While party leaders downplay the   publishing such a compelling read!
           tions, especially in children.   possibility of his exit, Tharoor's state-  Shahid Ali Siddiqui (I.R.S) Retd.,
             While India has made progress with   ments suggest he is open to exploring   Talimabad, New Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           28                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA["A boat is safe in the harbor, but

                                     that’s not what boats are for."

                                                – William G.T. Shedd








































































                                                                                                                Photo credit: wsilvasjb]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                      |

                                                                                      |
                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       |

                                                                                      |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                              ol. 3, No.3 |
                                                                             .in
                                                                             V
                                                                              .in
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                .in
                                                                                ol. 3, No.1 |
                                                                               V
                                                                               V
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                         |
                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                          | AUGUST

                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                                   16 2025

                                                                                          AUGUST
                                                                                                 Y


                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024


                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        FEBRUAR
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024

                                                                                        DECEMBER 01 2024
                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.5 | MARCH 01 2025 01 2025 01 2025OBER 16 2023
                                                      .revoir
                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025DECEMBER 16 2024OBER 01 2024
           3232
           3232
                                                        .revoir
                                                             .in
                                                              REVOIR Magazine
                                                             .in
                                                           .in
                                                            www
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32
           32
           32                                     wwwwwwwww .revoir www REVOIR Magazine  .in  ol. 3, No.2 |     OCT  Y 01 202432
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                       www
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                            .in
                                                                            .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                   www
                                                                    www
                                                                    www
                                                                .revoir
                                                                .revoir
                                                                   www
                                                                     www
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                     www
                                                                    .in
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in REVOIR
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>