<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 24 I  DECEMBER 16 2025  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: FOTOGRAPHIYA





              11



                                                             8













                                                            26                                       15
















           4-Editorial: When numbers knock on              23-Christmas celebrated on other dates
           the heart’s door                                26-How he sang for everyone and ev-

           5-What height means around the world  erything

           8-Is misfortune just math?                      29-Horoscopes

           11-Can numbers predict compatibility?           30-Letters
           15-Why December 31st was never the              31-Frame of thought

           end

           18-Can apps replace the table?

           20-Why Gen Z is quoting a 19th century
           poet







           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Mystery Remains
     EDITORIAL  When numbers knock                                                  Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           on the heart’s door                                                  Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                              here was a time when love arrived   Art & Culture Editor
                                              unannounced. It slipped into lives   Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Tthrough chance encounters, bor-
                                        rowed books, missed buses and mutual     Digital Strategy Editor
                                        friends who insisted, “Just meet once.”    Vishakha Sharma
                                        Today, love often begins with a calculation.
                                        A percentage. A suggestion made by a ma-  Social Media Editor
                                        chine that has never felt a heartbeat
                                        quicken.                                     Sushil Kumar
                                           We scroll, we swipe, we pause. Some-
                                        where between curiosity and hope, we    Art & Graphics Director
                                        allow numbers to guide us toward people      Vipin Agarwal
                                        we have never met. It’s a quiet shift, almost
                                        invisible. Romance hasn’t disappeared, but
           it has learned the language of data.                              EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             The idea is comforting. If compatibility can be measured, maybe heartbreak can
           be avoided. Maybe mismatches can be filtered out early, like unwanted emails. Algo-  D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           rithms promise efficiency in a space that has always been messy. They look at pat-  Editor, United News of India, New
           terns we don’t see. They remember what we forget. In a strange way, they feel objec-
           tive, almost wise.                                                Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             It doesn’t follow straight lines or predictable curves. It doubles back. It contradicts   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           itself. Two people who make no sense on paper sometimes make perfect sense in a   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           room. Others, who seem ideal in every measurable way, fail to connect beyond polite   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           conversation.                                                     Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
             Numbers are excellent at describing behaviour, but less skilled at understanding   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           meaning. They can tell us who we message, not why someone’s silence matters more   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           than another’s attention. They can predict attraction, but not devotion. They struggle
           with timing, with grief, with the quiet resilience that keeps people together when ex-  SUBSCRIPTIONS
           citement fades.
             In India, this tension feels especially familiar. For generations, compatibility was   Phone +91 20 40199102
           assessed through charts, family histories and community expectations. Today, the for-
           mat has changed, not the impulse. We still want reassurance. We still want proof that   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           a choice of the heart is also sensible. Technology simply offers a modern vocabulary   Baner Road,
           for an old human need.                                              Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
             Perhaps that’s why algorithms feel persuasive. They don’t claim to replace love.   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           They present themselves as helpers, gentle guides in a crowded world. And to be fair,   Website www.revoir.in
           they often succeed. They introduce people who would never have crossed paths
           otherwise. They create beginnings.                                       Legal Advisor
             That part remains stubbornly human. It lives in the decision to stay, to listen, to   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           forgive, to grow. It shows up in moments that cannot be logged or scored. A shared
           silence. An inside joke. The way someone reaches for your hand without thinking.
             They can open the door. They can’t walk us through it. Love, for all our attempts
           to decode it, still resists certainty. And perhaps that’s its quiet power. Even in an age   Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
           of algorithms, the heart keeps a little mystery to itself.       all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.


         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION



































           Inches and Identity                                             “Don’t worry, you’ll grow.”
                                                                              And the truth is: these tiny comments
                                                                           shape us long before we’re old enough
                                                                           to question why they matter.
           What height                                                     A cultural weight older than we

                                                                           realize
                                                                              Height has lingered for centuries as a
                                                                           symbol of strength and advantage. An-
                                                                           cient statues stretched warriors to heroic
                                                                           proportions. Kings and queens wore
                                                                           stacked heels to tower over crowds.
                                                                              Even now, data across several coun-
           means around  tries shows taller people are often
                                                                           viewed as more capable, more attractive,
                                                                           more authoritative, whether or not those
           the world                                                       things are actually true. Height became a
                                                                           lens through which societies evaluate
                                                                           people, sometimes without meaning to.
                                                                              But what that lens shows depends
                                                                           heavily on where in the world you’re
                                                                           standing.
           Height becomes a symbol, a shortcut for the qualities           India: Where inches carry stories
           we wish others saw in us. By Riya Verma                            India is one of the most complex and

                                                                           emotionally layered landscapes when it
                                                                           comes to height. Here, height doesn’t
                  hy do a few inches, earned by   The measure we don’t choose   just live in childhood growth charts; it
                  nothing more than biology,   Most people first learn their height   seeps into marriage negotiations, résumé
           Wshape how the world sees us?   from a school nurse or a relative an-  screenings, film casting, school teasing
             It’s odd if you really pause on it.   nouncing it aloud, as if declaring a ver-  and even family expectations.
           Height isn’t a talent. It isn’t a moral   dict. Suddenly, a random number be-
           strength. Yet from childhood onward,   comes part of identity.   Height and marriage: A social
           many of us are quietly taught that it   Some kids are told, “You’ll be so tall,   script hard to shake
           means something, sometimes every-  you’ll be unstoppable,” while others   Scroll through any matrimonial web-
           thing.                          hear softer, but sharper, lines like,   site and you’ll see it immediately:

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[“                             mally at least, favour
                                                                                        Some recruiters, infor-

                                                                                      taller candidates for
                                                                                      client-facing roles, as-
                                                        A few inches can feel like a
                                                                                      suming, again without
                                                        verdict, until we realise the   reason, that height sig-
                                                                                      nals confidence.
                                                        story they tell was never       In a country where
                                                                                      millions compete for lim-
                                                        ours to begin with.”          ited opportunities, these
                                                                                      biases, however subtle,
                                                                                      matter.

                                                                           Urban youth are rewriting the
                                                                           script
                                                                              And yet, something is changing.
                                                                              In Mumbai, Delhi, Bengaluru and
                                                                           other metros, young Indians are increas-
                                                                           ingly rejecting old insecurities. Dating
                                                                           apps have made preferences more vis-
                                                                           ible and more debatable. Women are ac-
                                                                           tively choosing partners shorter than
                                                                           them. Men are more open about chal-
                                                                           lenging the “tall, dark, handsome”
                                                                           cliché.
                                                                              Social media creators talk openly
                                                                           about being short, tall, or somewhere in
                                                                           between. Bollywood itself is evolving,
                                                                           slowly celebrating actors who don’t fit
                                                                           the earlier height stereotypes.
                                                                              The shift isn’t perfect, but it’s unmis-
                                                                           takable.
             “Tall, fair bride.”           equals presence, masculinity, power.
             “Well-settled, tall groom.”     For women, the pressure reverses,   Beyond india: a global patchwork
             These phrases sit like old furniture,   actresses too tall for a hero are often   While India offers one of the richest
           so familiar that many people forget how   quietly sidelined or paired tactically so   examples of how height becomes iden-
           deeply they shape perception. Height   height “doesn’t distract.” This re-  tity, other regions carry their own com-
           becomes a bargaining chip, a silent   inforces an odd cultural equation: men   plex stories.
           qualification for desirability.   should rise above the world, women
             Parents often talk about their chil-  should fit neatly within it.   East Asia: Height as progress
           dren’s height with anxious pride, as if a                          In South Korea, Japan and China,
           few inches can alter destiny. Girls who   Schools, friends and the first   height is often viewed as a symbol of
           are tall carry a strange double burden:   stings of height shame   modernity, nutrition and global stature.
           admired for their stature, yet told not to   Many Indians recall school experi-  It appears on résumés. Parents invest
           “intimidate” potential partners. Mean-  ences where height was either a boost   heavily in diet supplements. Teenagers
           while, boys who are shorter may grow   or a bruise. Short boys teased during   compare themselves relentlessly.
           up feeling a pressure that eats at con-  sports drills, tall girls slouching in class   A few inches become a shorthand for
           fidence in ways they rarely speak   to blend in, the annual “height and   success.
           about.                          weight day” that felt like a public
             None of this is universal, of course.   broadcast of private insecurities.   Africa: Diversity as identity
           But it’s common enough that nearly ev-  These small memories sit quietly in   Africa contains both some of the
           eryone in India has witnessed it.   adulthood. A tiny embarrassment here,   world’s tallest and shortest communities.
                                           a defensive joke there. For some, they   Height often reflects group identity more
           Bollywood and the tall hero     linger far longer than anyone admits.   than individual worth. Yet urbanization
           complex                                                         introduces Western standards that some-
             Cinema intensifies these expecta-  Workplaces and height filters   times clash with traditional norms.
           tions. Bollywood has long sold the   Height quietly influences profes-
           image of the tall, charismatic hero who   sional spaces too. Airlines often specify   Europe and North America: The
           commands the screen. Even actors of   minimum heights for cabin crew. Police   quiet advantage
           average height often appear larger-than-  and defence services do the same, tying   In much of the West, height isn’t dis-
           life thanks to clever camera angles and   height to “commanding presence,” even   cussed openly, yet data consistently
           thick boots.                    when competence has nothing to do   shows taller people enjoy social and
             This feeds a social story: height   with inches.              economic advantages. Society praises

           6                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[“



                                             Confidence isn’t
                                             measured in

                                             centimetres; it’s
                                             measured in the

                                             space we allow
                                             ourselves to take up
                                             in the world.”











              India’s height


                   paradox                                                 what desirability and confidence look
                                                                           like, even in India, where tradition holds
                India offers one of the world’s                            strong influence.
             most emotionally charged rela-                                   Globalization has also softened rigid
             tionships with height. From mat-                              beauty boxes. Exposure to diverse
             rimonial ads seeking “tall brides                             bodies makes it harder for any single
             and grooms,” to film heroes de-                               height ideal to dominate.
             signed to loom larger than life,
             height becomes a silent qualifica-                            Beyond inches: What we really
             tion woven through family con-                                want
             versations, friendships and early                                When people obsess about height,
             self-image. Children absorb ex-  What height does to the mind   they’re often reaching for something un-
             pectations long before they un-  Height is judged instantly, often sub-  derneath, belonging, confidence, fair-
             derstand them, tall girls told to   consciously. People internalize those   ness, love. Height becomes a symbol, a
             shrink, short boys urged to “grow   judgments, sometimes for life.   shortcut for the qualities we wish others
             soon.” Yet urban youth are chal-  Shorter men may feel the unspoken   saw in us.
             lenging the script. Dating apps   pressure to perform masculinity louder.   And symbols can change.
             normalise varied preferences, so-  Taller women may feel visible in ways
             cial media creators embrace all   they didn’t choose. People of any gender   A Closing Reflection
             body types and Bollywood is   who fall outside cultural norms can ex-  India, like many places, is full of
             slowly loosening its tall-hero   perience shame that doesn’t reflect their   adults who remember being measured
             template. India’s paradox re-  actual value.                  up against expectations they never asked
             mains: height still matters, but   But many of these insecurities aren’t   for. Some grew into those expectations;
             the next generation is learning to   ours to begin with. They’re inherited.   many grew around them. In hindsight,
             define themselves beyond it.  Passed down quietly through culture,   it’s almost tender, the way we believed
                                           media and family.               that standing a few inches taller or
                                             Once we recognize that, they lose   shorter could alter the shape of our fu-
           body diversity, yes, but hidden biases   some of their grip.    tures.
           still creep in.                                                    But the world doesn’t work that way,
                                           The narrative is evolving       not really. Growth isn’t just vertical.
           Latin America: History intertwined   Across the world, movements for   Confidence isn’t measured in cen-
           with height                     body positivity and mental health have   timeters. And the qualities people re-
             Latin American height norms carry   opened space to question old hierar-  member us for, kindness, humour, inte-
           remnants of colonial hierarchies. Some   chies.                 grity, don’t require height to stand tall.
           of these older ideas still echo softly in   Celebrities challenge stereotypes   Maybe that’s the quiet truth waiting
           beauty standards, though many cultures   simply by succeeding. Public health   underneath all the noise:
           celebrate diverse body types more   campaigns speak openly about stigma.   the parts of us that matter most rarely
           openly.                         Young people are louder about rewriting   come with a number. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[INSIGHT






























           The science of bad luck



           Is misfortune







           just math?                                                      patterns. It’s one of the reasons our

                                                                           species survived. Spotting repetition
                                                                           helped early humans predict weather,
                                                                           track animals and avoid danger. But that
                                                                           same instinct can turn against us. The
                                                                           brain rarely enjoys uncertainty. So when
           Randomness is the spice that keeps things surprising,           something random happens, especially
                                                                           something unpleasant, we fill the silence
           maddening, occasionally painful and sometimes                   with meaning.
           wonderful. By Anaya Gupta                                       ing. It’s why someone might remember
                                                                              Psychologists call this pattern seek-
                                                                           every time a black cat crossed the road
                                                                           before an unfortunate event but forget
                 ave you ever had one of those   But what if bad luck is simply our   the dozens of times nothing happened.
                 days when everything feels   brain struggling to interpret random-  Behavioural scientists say it’s just how
           Hslightly tilted, as if the universe   ness? What if misfortune isn’t fate but a   memory works: emotional moments
           nudged the table and your life slid to   story we tell ourselves when chaos hits   stick, bland moments fade.
           one side?                       too close?                         Probability, meanwhile, doesn’t care
             Most of us have. A missed bus, a   This is where psychology and prob-  at all. It has no memory and no emo-
           cracked phone screen, a job rejection   ability meet. It’s a surprisingly emo-  tional interest in your life. If you flip a
           that arrives exactly when you were al-  tional intersection.    coin ten times and get ten tails, the next
           ready feeling low. It’s tempting to think                       flip is still 50 percent. Yet most of us
           something bigger is at play. Something   Why we think the universe is   will feel, deep down, that the next one
           personal. Almost as if luck itself has a   watching             should be heads. It almost feels like the
           grudge.                           Human beings are wired to look for   coin owes us.

           8                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Bad luck often isn’t a
                                                                             curse. It’s our brain

                                                                             trying to make sense
                                                                             of randomness that

                                                                             never promised to be
                                                                             fair in the first place.”






                  Why randomness

                  feels personal

                We know randomness isn’t
             emotional, yet it can feel
             strangely targeted when life goes
             wrong. Psychologists say this
             happens because the brain hates
             uncertainty. So it fills the gaps
             with meaning, even when none
             exists. A spilled drink, a missed
             bus, a phone freezing at the worst
             possible moment. These moments
             hit harder when we’re already
             tired or stressed. What we inter-
             pret as “a streak of bad luck” is
             usually just probability unfolding   And then there’s confirmation bias.   But of course math doesn’t comfort
             in the background. Lots of tiny   Once you decide you’re unlucky, your   anyone at 2 am when you’re wondering
             independent chances stack and   brain quietly collects evidence to sup-  why everything feels heavy.
             one of them eventually happens.   port the claim. You lose your keys, spill
             It’s uncomfortable, but also free-  your tea or hit a pothole and suddenly   Why some cultures see luck
             ing. The universe isn’t plotting   the narrative is complete. When some-  everywhere
             anything. It’s simply indifferent.  thing good happens, you dismiss it as an   Different societies attach different
                                           exception.                      meanings to luck. In India, for example,
                                             We become the authors of our own   certain numbers, days or omens are
             This belief is known as the gambler’s   unlucky stories without even noticing.   wrapped in layers of tradition. An over-
           fallacy. Even people who don’t gamble                           turned shoe, a crow cawing at the win-
           fall for it every day.          The math behind misfortune      dow, a glass breaking, or a vehicle start-
                                             Here’s a less emotional explanation.   ing with the left foot instead of the right
           When randomness feels personal   Life is full of probabilities layered on   can still make many people pause.
             The trouble with bad luck is that it   top of each other. The chance of being   These beliefs have deep cultural
           feels targeted. If a meteor hits Earth,   stuck in traffic, missing a deadline, fall-  roots, often passed down with affection
           that’s just cosmic physics. If a bird   ing sick, losing money or making a mis-  rather than strict fear. They create a
           chooses your freshly ironed shirt to re-  take all exist independently. Over time,   sense of order. When life feels unpre-
           lieve itself on, that feels weirdly inten-  enough small possibilities pile up until   dictable, a familiar sign can at least offer
           tional.                         one of them happens. It feels like a   a narrative.
             Part of this comes from something   streak of bad luck even though it’s just   But modern India is also full of
           psychologists call illusory correlation.   statistics playing out.   people who live entirely in the world of
           We link two events because they hap-  Think of it this way: if you interact   data, statistics and risk analysis. Yet
           pened close together, not because   with hundreds of variables every day,   even they may slip into saying things
           they’re connected. It’s the same mental   some are bound to turn against you oc-  like “my luck has been bad this week”.
           glitch that makes people blame the day,   casionally. You could call it misfortune.   Which shows something important: be-
           the month, a number or their zodiac sign   Mathematicians would call it expected   lief in luck is less about culture and
           when life goes sideways.        distribution.                   more about being human.

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[there is only correla-

            Why we keep seeing                                                           tion. We build stories

                                                                                         out of coincidences.
                                                                                         We try to control
                  patterns in chaos                                                      chance with rituals
                                                                                         and beliefs.
                Humans are brilliant pattern                                               Some of that is ir-
             hunters. It helped our ancestors                                            rational. Some of it is
             survive, but now the same in-                                               beautifully human.
             stinct sometimes tricks us. We                                                The truth is, life’s
             link unrelated events, remember                                             unpredictability is
             coincidences that sting and forget                                          what makes it inter-
             the many times nothing hap-                                                 esting. If everything
             pened. This illusion of connec-                                             followed neat pat-
             tion can turn a random inconven-                                            terns, we’d be bored
             ience into a meaningful sign. In                                            out of our minds. Ran-
             cultures like India, where sym-                                             domness is the spice
             bolic omens and rituals are part                                            that keeps things sur-
             of daily life, these interpretations
             feel even more natural. But mod-  luckier in the mathematical sense.

             ern psychology shows that most   They’re simply more likely to notice   “
             “signs” are simply our attention   positive events. They interpret ambi-  Once you decide
             working overtime. When we     guity with generosity. They take more
             zoom out, the noise fades. We see   chances, which increases opportunities.   you’re unlucky, your
             what was always true: chaos is   Luck, in other words, becomes a behav-
             random, but our stories about it   iour rather than a force.    mind quietly collects
             are not.
                                           Why we love blaming luck anyway   evidence to prove it.
                                                             There’s some-   The world didn’t
                                                          thing gently com-
                                                          forting about say-  change. Your story
                                                          ing “I’m just
                                                          unlucky”. It re-   did.”
                                                          moves the pressure
                                                          of responsibility. If
                                                          the universe is the   prising, maddening, occasionally painful
                                                          problem, then you   and sometimes wonderful.
                                                          aren’t. And some-   So when a string of bad luck hits, it
                                                          times we genuinely   might help to remember that chaos does-
                                                          can’t explain what   n’t have a personal agenda. You’re not
                                                          happened. Humans   being targeted. You’re simply living in a
                                                          don’t like blank   world where probability does its quiet,
           The psychology of feeling cursed   spaces in stories, so luck becomes the   stubborn job.
             There’s one more layer. People who   filler.
           feel chronically unlucky are often deal-  There’s also entertainment in the   A small personal note
           ing with something deeper than super-  idea. Popular culture is full of unlucky   I sometimes think back to a day when
           stition. Researchers have found that low   heroes, tragic coincidences, comedic   everything went wrong for me. Missed a
           mood, anxiety and stress make individ-  disasters. We relate to them because   train, dropped my wallet, lost a file I’d
           uals more likely to interpret neutral   chaos is universal. No spreadsheet can   worked on for days. For a moment I did
           events negatively. When you’re men-  protect us from spilled coffee or awk-  what everyone does. I thought, why me?
           tally exhausted, randomness feels heav-  ward timing.           Later, when the irritation faded, I realised
           ier.                              Even in science, randomness is a   it wasn’t fate. It wasn’t destiny. It was a
             For example, if someone is already   tricky thing. Probability can give us   messy combination of timing, distraction
           worried about finances, even a small car   clarity, but it rarely gives answers that   and a few statistical odds that happened
           repair can feel like the universe piling   feel emotionally satisfying. You can   to converge.
           on. When someone is lonely, a cancelled   know the math and still feel stung by the   It didn’t make the day less annoying.
           plan feels sharper. When they’re burnt   outcome.               But it did make it less mysterious.
           out, one mistake can feel like evidence                            Maybe that’s all we can hope for. Not
           that everything is collapsing.   So is misfortune just math?    the end of bad luck, but the beginning of
             It’s not that luck changes; it’s that our   Mostly, yes. But humans aren’t math-  understanding it. Because once you stop
           perception shifts.              ematical creatures. We’re emotional ones   believing the universe is picking on you,
             Interestingly, studies show that   who keep trying to negotiate with ran-  life feels a little lighter, even on the days
           people who identify as lucky aren’t   domness. We look for causation where   that tilt. ■

           10                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[ANALYSIS



































                                                           The love equation



                  hat if the biggest decisions of
                  the heart are already being    Can numbers
           Wmade by lines of code before
           we even start talking?
             There’s something oddly charming
           about the idea that love, with all its
           chaos, could be distilled into neat cal-
           culations. People still like to believe at-                    predict
           traction is a spark, a glance, a scent car-
           ried by chance. But it’s also true that
           millions today swipe, match and mes-
           sage because an algorithm somewhere
           quietly whispered, “Hey, these two   compatibility?
           might work.”
             It’s tempting to ask: Can numbers
           really read us better than we read our-
           selves? Or are we letting technology
           convince us that patterns of affection are   Math can guide us, shape our choices and offer gentle
           predictable when they’re actually full of
           contradictions? The truth lies some-  probabilities. It can’t decide the depth of a relationship
           where in the middle, in a space where
           mathematics and emotion learn to share   or the resilience two people will show during
           a table.
                                           hardships. By Naina Kapoor
           The rise of the  compatibility
           algorithm
             Modern dating apps run on complex   dating at first, but it’s basically the same   stakes feel higher. It’s your heart.
           models that combine probability, behav-  math that recommends your next movie   One of the most common systems is
           ioural analytics and something called   on Netflix or suggests a new café in   the match score. Apps track the kind of
           collaborative filtering. It sounds intimi-  your neighbourhood. Only this time, the   profiles you pause on, the ones you re-

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Dating algorithms

                                                                                    working

                                                                                Compatibility algorithms
                                                                              don’t read your soul, but they do
                                                                              read your behaviour. Apps track
                                                                              patterns in your swipes, pauses,
                                                                              messages and profile interactions.
                                                                              They combine these signals with
                                                                              location, interests, education and
                                                                              dozens of small markers that in-
                                                                              dicate what you tend to prefer.
            “                                                                 Using collaborative filtering, the
                                                                              same method behind movie sug-

                                                                              gestions, the system compares
                                                                              you with thousands of similar
            Maybe numbers can
                                                                              matches. The score you see isn’t
            predict the first hello,                                          users and predicts potential
                                                                              a promise of perfect chemistry.
            but everything that                                               It’s just a probability that a con-
                                                                              versation might happen. Algo-
            matters comes after.”                                             rithms don’t create connection.
                                                                              They simply try to increase the
                                                                              odds of one.
           ject quickly, the messages you respond   posts.
           to, even the words you use. Add loca-  Still, most couples will tell you their
           tion, education, hobbies and hundreds of   connection was never just about shared   technology run parallel.
           micro-signals and you get a probability   traits. A quiet person falls for a chaotic   There’s a fascinating tension here.
           of “fit.”                       one. An introvert finds a home in an ex-  On one hand, algorithms widen choice
             A 78 percent match doesn’t mean   trovert’s energy. Two seemingly incom-  and help users break free from rigid so-
           someone is 78 percent your soulmate. It   patible people end up building some-  cial expectations. On the other, they can
           means that, based on past behaviour   thing solid just because they made each   unintentionally reinforce the same filters
           from users who resemble you, this pair-  other feel understood at the right mo-  society already uses. If you only match
           ing has worked often enough to be   ment.                       within your language or caste group,
           worth a shot. In other words, math is not   How do you measure that? How does   does it expand your world or shrink it?
           taking over your destiny. It’s just offer-  an equation capture a laugh that makes   Still, many Indian couples now say
           ing you a statistical nudge.    someone feel safe, or the odd but perfect   they met through “the app,” almost ca-
             Interestingly, many people don’t real-  way two people finish each other’s sen-  sually. The stigma has softened. The
           ise that dating algorithms evolve con-  tences? The math isn’t wrong, but it   math has quietly entered our living
           stantly. They learn from us as much as   isn’t complete.        rooms.
           we learn from them. Every swipe is a
           vote that shapes the next prediction.   The Indian scenario: Tradition   The illusion of precision
           Some sociologists jokingly say that   meets technology             One of the risks with algorithmic
           maybe algorithms don’t know what we   India adds its own flavour to this   love is that people start believing the
           want, but they know what we settle for.   conversation. For decades, compatibility   numbers hold some kind of objective
                                           was checked through handwritten bio-  truth. If someone sees a low match
           But can love be quantified?     data sheets, family networks and astro-  score, they may dismiss a potentially
             The deeper question is whether com-  logical charts. Today, the same logic has   good connection without even trying.
           patibility is something you can measure   migrated to screens, except the decoding   When apps tell us we’re compatible,
           at all.                         is done by algorithms rather than   we’re more likely to put in effort. When
             Psychologists have been trying to do   friendly aunties armed with recommen-  they tell us we’re not, we sometimes
           this long before apps existed. The fa-  dations.                give up too soon.
           mous Five Factor Model of personality,   Platforms like Shaadi.com and Jee-  This illusion of precision can shape
           for example, quantifies traits like open-  vansathi blend cultural filters with be-  behaviour in subtle ways. The match
           ness, conscientiousness and emotional   havioural prediction. They consider reli-  score becomes a psychological anchor,
           stability. Research suggests that similar-  gion, community, language, location and   not a scientific prediction.
           ity in values and emotional temperament   increasingly, personality markers. Many   Some researchers argue that compati-
           does increase chances of long-term rela-  young Indians use swiping apps along-  bility models are less about forecasting
           tionship satisfaction. So numbers are not   side arranged marriage platforms, living   emotional chemistry and more about in-
           the enemy here. They’re more like sign-  in a hybrid world where tradition and   creasing the likelihood of a conver-

           12                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Algorithms can nudge

                                                                             two people toward each

                                                                             other, but they can’t feel
                                                                             the spark when they

                                                                             finally meet.”


                                                                           app because of a 92 percent compatibil-
                                                                           ity score. They matched instantly online,
                                                                           but offline things were awkward for
                                                                           weeks. Odd pauses. Mixed signals. And
                                                                           yet, somehow, they kept showing up.
                                                                           Years later, they say the app predicted
                                                                           nothing. They built everything.
                                                                              Or the reverse story: two people
                                                                           matched at 40 percent who assumed it
                                                                           was a bad sign but decided to meet any-
                                                                           way. They fell for each other because of
                                                                           one shared joke that neither of them can
                                                                           now remember perfectly. The probabil-
                                                                           ity didn’t matter. The moment did.
                                                                              Love often grows in the spaces algo-
                                                                           rithms can’t see.
           sation. That’s it. Not marriage. Not life-  Where math often fails
           long devotion. Just a moment where two   The challenge with quantifying com-  So, can numbers predict
           strangers might click.          patibility is that relationships are dy-  compatibility?
             It’s a humbling thought. And maybe   namic, not fixed. You don’t stay the   The honest answer is: partly. Math
           a freeing one too.              same person year after year. Neither   can guide us, shape our choices and
                                           does your partner. Yet most algorithms   offer gentle probabilities. It can’t decide
           What the numbers actually do well   treat identity as something static.   the depth of a relationship or the resil-
             Despite their limitations, algorithms                         ience two people will show during hard-
           excel at a few things humans struggle   Emotions evolve         ships. It can’t measure kindness or com-
           with:                             The way you respond to conflict at   mitment or the strange comfort that
           1. Filtering noise              20 is different from how you respond at   comes from simply sitting beside some-
             In a world of endless profiles, apps   35.                    one in silence.
           save time by narrowing options. This                               Maybe the best way to see compati-
           isn’t about fate; it’s about reducing men-  Timing matters      bility scores is the way we see weather
           tal overload.                     Two perfect people can meet at the   forecasts. They help us prepare, but they
           2. Highlighting behavioural patterns   wrong moment and simply not work.   don’t control what the clouds will do.
             You might think you prefer a certain   Chemistry is unpredictable
           “type,” but the data sometimes reveals   The spark many people talk about   A personal closing
           otherwise. Maybe you match more with   doesn’t follow rules of probability. It   How strange and beautiful it is that
           people who love books, or maybe you   can appear suddenly, stubbornly or not   we let technology into the most delicate
           unconsciously favour those who use hu-  at all.                 corners of our lives. We let numbers
           mour in their bios.                                             whisper possibilities into our ears. But at
           3. Encouraging conversations    Human connection is messy       the end of the day, love is still some-
             A match score can give two hesitant   People contradict themselves. They   thing we choose. Not something we
           people the small confidence boost they   change their minds. They forgive. They   compute.
           need to talk.                   fail. They grow. This can’t be coded   So if an algorithm introduces two
           4. Protecting emotional bandwidth   easily.                     people, that’s wonderful. But what they
             By filtering out obviously incompat-  So the question isn’t whether math   do after that, the courage, the patience,
           ible options, apps help users avoid burn-  fails. It’s whether we expect too much   the laughter, the mess, the slow building
           out.                            from it.                        of trust, that’s all them.
             These are practical strengths. But                               Maybe numbers can predict the first
           they’re not the magic formula for love.   Stories behind the statistics   hello. But everything that matters comes
           They’re the warm-up act.          Take the couple who met on a dating   after. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE




































           The invented deadline




           Why December





           31st was never                                                  natural world resets at midnight. Birds

                                                                           don’t change their routines. Trees don’t
                                                                           shed guilt for their unfinished business.
                                                                           Even the seasons ignore our count-
           the end                                                         the planet we live on.
                                                                           downs. The big rush belongs to us, not
                                                                              This leaves an uncomfortable ques-
                                                                           tion in the air. If the deadline is in-
                                                                           vented, why does it hold so much
                                                                           power?
           The beginning that feels brand-new is just a
                                                                           How we created “the end”
           continuation. The story was already in motion and it               It’s easy to forget that the idea of an
           doesn’t hinge on a single night. By Rajeev Khanna               annual endpoint is a fairly modern con-
                                                                           venience. The calendar that dictates our
                                                                           feelings today wasn’t designed to shape
                                                                           emotions; it was built to coordinate agri-
                  hat if the finish line we’re all   tive tension rise as people scramble to   culture, taxes and politics. Earlier so-
                  racing toward isn’t really a   wrap up projects, clean closets, polish   cieties observed cycles that didn’t begin
           Wfinish line at all?            résumés, finalize plans, or squeeze in   or end neatly. Some tracked time
             We talk about “the end of the year”   that one last self-improvement goal be-  through moon phases, others through
           as if the universe itself hits a hard stop,   fore the clock runs out. But if you step   harvests, migrations, or rituals tied to
           the cosmic equivalent of a school bell   back for a moment, you notice some-  weather. Many didn’t have a sense of
           ringing. You can almost feel the collec-  thing strangely obvious: nothing in the   “the year ends here” at all.

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[The calendar was

                                                                              never emotional


                                                                                We often forget that the mod-
                                                                              ern calendar wasn’t built to stir
                                                                              feelings of pressure or rebirth. It
                                                                              was a logistical tool, meant for
                                                                              coordinating farming seasons, tax
                                                                              records and administrative order.
                                                                              The emotional weight we now at-
                                                                              tach to “year’s end” is a recent
                                                                              cultural evolution, not an ancient
                                             “                                truth. Earlier societies followed
                                                                              looser cycles guided by moon

                                                                              phases, harvests, or local rituals,
                                                                              none of which demanded a dra-
                                             Nature doesn’t reset at
                                                                              helps loosen the grip of the in-
                                             midnight. Only we do             matic finish line. Realizing this
                                                                              vented deadline. It reminds us
                                             and sometimes we                 that much of our urgency is in-
                                                                              herited, not inevitable and cer-
                                             forget that the choice is        tainly not dictated by nature.
                                             ours.”
                                                                              The truth is that most personal goals
                                                                           don’t expire. Learning a language does-
                                           Yet our social lives demand urgency.   n’t stop being meaningful. Improving
                                           Companies push for targets. Schools   your health doesn’t become irrelevant.
                                           close terms. Families expect rituals. Ev-  Repairing a friendship isn’t limited to
             Human beings eventually settled on   erywhere, the pressure to “complete”   one season. Yet the invented deadline
           more precise counts because precision   something intensifies. It’s almost ironic   tricks us into believing opportunities are
           made life easier. Empires needed struc-  that the time we’re biologically inclined   shrinking when they’re not.
           ture. Farmers wanted predictability. Ad-  to slow down is the time we force our-  Is it possible that we’re evaluating
           ministrators needed fixed dates to col-  selves to sprint.      our lives with a ruler that someone else
           lect dues or record births. But at no   Maybe that’s why so many people   carved?
           point did the universe assign special   feel worn out by year’s end. We’re
           meaning to the last page of a calendar. It   working against our own rhythms.   How calendars became emotional
           was simply the square where someone                             frameworks
           decided the cycle would roll back to   The psychology of invented   There’s another layer to this story.
           one.                            endings                         The calendar isn’t just a tool anymore; it
             It’s strange, really, how our emo-  Psychologists call it the “fresh start   has become a cultural narrative. We use
           tional lives are still shaped by this old   effect” the belief that a new beginning   it to measure progress, identity, success,
           administrative tool. A bureaucratic con-  cleans the slate. It’s the same mental   even morality. It becomes a yearly re-
           venience became a spiritual checkpoint.   trick that makes Monday feel like a reset   port card, a subtle invitation to judge
                                           or the first page of a new notebook feel   ourselves. Did you travel enough? Save
           Nature doesn’t know the clock has   full of promise. We’re drawn to   enough? Grow enough? Become
           struck                          markers. They help us reorganize our   enough?
             If you’ve ever been outside on a cold   thoughts, our ambitions and even our   What’s fascinating is that many tradi-
           night around the year’s turning point,   guilt.                 tional cultures don’t pressure individuals
           you notice something calming. The   But the flip side is the “deadline ef-  this way. Their time cycles are com-
           wind doesn’t speed up just because hu-  fect,” which nudges people into frantic   munal, not personal. The focus is on
           mans are panicking about unfinished   action as a due date approaches. When   collective rituals, not individual produc-
           lists. Waves don’t crash louder because   that deadline is a truly urgent one a bill,   tivity. Time isn’t something to win or
           we feel behind. It’s a quiet reminder that   a medical test, a real-world consequence   lose; it’s something you move through
           the natural world doesn’t frame time as   it’s understandable. When it’s an inher-  with your community.
           we do.                          ited cultural script, though, it can create   Our modern relationship with time is
             This mismatch creates a subtle kind   unnecessary anxiety. You may find   more individualistic. That’s why the in-
           of cognitive dissonance. Our bodies   yourself asking, “Am I behind?” or “Did   vented “end” feels so personal, almost
           sense winter as a slow season, a period   I waste the year?” even when nothing   intimate. It shines a bright light on ev-
           that encourages rest and introspection.   material hangs in the balance.   erything we didn’t get to.

           16                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[The myth of catching up
             Every December, you hear the same
           jokes: “I’ll finish the whole to-do list be-
           fore the year ends,” or “Let me fix my
           life in two weeks.” They’re meant
           lightly, but they reveal something
           deeper. Many people think they need to
           arrive at the new cycle having perfected
           themselves. No loose threads. No half-
           done dreams.
             But no one actually catches up. Not
           really. Life isn’t a race where everyone
           starts the next lap at the same level of
           readiness. Some years go smoothly.
           Some years are messy. Some years feel
           like they gave you more than you could
           hold. And some years take things from
           you.
             Maybe the problem isn’t that we fail
           to meet the invented deadline. Maybe
                                                            not much
                                                            happens. That’s
                                                            still movement.   Why we feel the

                                                            It still counts.

                                                            Breaking the         rush anyway
                                                            spell of the
                                                            invented            Even though the end of the
                                                            ending            year is artificial, the feelings
                                                              It doesn’t      around it are real. Psychologists
                                                            mean abandon-     explain this through the “fresh
                                                            ing rituals or ig-  start effect,” our natural tendency
                                                            noring the        to crave clean beginnings. Along-
                                                            sweetness of      side it sits the “deadline effect,”
                                                            transition.       which pushes us into frantic ac-
                                                            People like       tion as a final date approaches.
                                                            marking time be-  When these two forces collide,
           the problem is believing that this dead-  cause it makes life feel storied. What it   the result is a yearly rush that
           line matters as much as we’ve been told.   does mean is releasing the idea that your   feels both meaningful and ex-
                                           worth is tied to the final tally of what   hausting. Understanding this
           A gentler way to understand the   you accomplished by a specific date.   doesn’t erase the emotions, but it
           year                              You can create your own markers.   helps us interpret them more
             If you look at time the way nature   Maybe your personal cycle begins on   gently. We’re not failing or fall-
           does in slow transitions it opens up a dif-  your birthday. Maybe it starts with the   ing behind; we’re responding to a
           ferent way of thinking. The shift from   first warm day after winter. Maybe you   story we’ve been told for genera-
           one cycle to the next isn’t a door slam-  don’t need a cycle at all; maybe your life   tions one we’re free to rewrite.
           ming; it’s more like a gradual fade in   is a series of revisited chapters, not a line
           light. Trees don’t spring to life on a spe-  with numbered checkpoints.
           cific date. Flowers don’t bloom on com-  The ending that feels so absolute is   your goals.
           mand. Even sunrise and sunset shift   really just a pause. The beginning that   So maybe this year doesn’t need to
           gradually, almost shyly.        feels brand-new is just a continuation.   end neatly. Maybe it doesn’t need to end
             What happens when we allow our   The story was already in motion and it   at all. Maybe the idea of an “end” was
           own lives to work this way?     doesn’t hinge on a single night.   just a chapter title someone wrote long
             Progress becomes continuous. Self-                            ago and we’ve been treating it like a ver-
           reflection happens without panic. Inten-  A quiet reflection    dict ever since.
           tions form slowly. You can acknowledge   If you sit still for a moment and imag-  And if that’s true, then you’re al-
           what hasn’t been done without feeling   ine the planet turning, slowly, steadily,   lowed to carry things forward. You’re al-
           like you’ve failed a cosmic exam.   without any awareness of our pressures,   lowed to begin whenever you feel ready.
             One therapist I once spoke to put it   it’s oddly comforting. Time keeps mov-  You’re allowed to let the cycle be yours,
           neatly: “A year is not a box you fill or   ing whether you rush or not. There’s   not the calendar’s.
           empty. It’s a landscape you walk   something freeing in that. Nature doesn’t   Even if the whole world is counting
           through.” And every landscape has val-  demand that you perfect yourself before   down, you can quietly remind yourself:
           leys, slopes and long flat stretches where   a certain hour. It doesn’t judge the lag in   this isn’t really the end. It never was. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY  The digital shuffle                                    less, something you can keep in your


                                                                           pocket and pull out when you have five
                                                                           minutes to spare.
                                                                              In India, where card games have long
           Can apps replace
                                                                           been tied to family gatherings and fes-
                                                                           tive nights, this shift feels especially in-
                                                                           teresting. A game like Teen Patti, once
                                                                           relying on a room full of cousins, is now
                                                                           played by strangers scattered across
           the table?                                                      cities. Some say it’s convenient. Others
                                                                           feel it’s a little lonely. Both are probably
                                                                           right.

                                                                           The promise of digital play
                                                                              There’s no denying the upside. Apps
           As apps evolve, developers are trying to rebuild that           solve problems the old table couldn’t.
           missing human layer. Voice rooms. Multiplayer                   You don’t need four people physically
                                                                           present. You don’t need a deck. You
           lounges. By Rohan Kapoor                                        don’t need space. For many players, dig-
                                                                           ital card games became a lifeline during
                                                                           times when meeting in person wasn’t
                                                                           possible.
                  hat if the soft thud of cards   everything’s-different-now sort of way,   You also get options. Tutorials for
                  on a wooden table could be   but quietly, almost naturally, as life   beginners. Stats for competitive types.
           Wreplaced by a tap on glass and   tends to change.              Quick matches for those who just want a
           no one at the table even noticed the dif-                       few minutes of escape between work
           ference?                        A new kind of table             emails. It’s card playing made friction-
             Card games have always carried a   The modern card table is often a   less. A smooth, always-ready experience
           kind of magic. The circle of players, the   smartphone held at arm’s length. Apps   that blends neatly into the routines of
           slow reveal of a hand, the laughter that   promise instant matches, endless decks,   people who live on their phones anyway.
           rises a little too loudly. Many of us grew   no need to reshuffle. And while it’s   And then there’s access. Older adults
           up watching relatives play rummy while   tempting to say technology has “re-  who never learned rummy can now do
           the ceiling fan hummed above. Yet here   placed” the real thing, that doesn’t feel   so privately without embarrassment.
           we are today, watching that old tradition   entirely true. It’s more like the table has   Teens in small towns can find players
           tilt toward screens. Not in a dramatic,   stretched. It’s become portable, border-  from across the world. Friends who live







































           18                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Digital cards connect us
                                                                             quickly, but real tables

                                                                             remind us why we play
                                                                             at all.”


                                                                           venience. One asks you to show up, the
                                                                           other meets you wherever you already
                                                                           are. Some days you want the noise of
                                                                           people around you. Other days you want
                                                                           silence and speed. Both are valid and
                                                                           both reflect how modern life actually
                                                                                            works.


              What the physical                                                             Where we
                                                                                            might be

                                                                                            heading
                 table still teaches us                                                        As apps
                                                                                            evolve, devel-
               For all the convenience that                                                 opers are trying
             apps offer, physical card tables                                               to rebuild that
             continue to shape a kind of social                                             missing human
             learning that screens can’t fully                                              layer. Voice
             replace. When people sit to-                                                   rooms. Multi-
             gether, they pick up nonverbal                                                 player lounges.
             cues, read expressions, learn pa-                                              Animated ava-
             tience and negotiate real-time                                                 tars that mimic
             emotions. Disagreements are                                                    expressions.
             sorted face to face, jokes flow   instead of expressions. Quick chat lines   Maybe one day we’ll see virtual tables
             naturally and the game becomes a   instead of messy, overlapping conver-  that actually feel like rooms. Maybe
             shared memory instead of just a   sations. It works, but it doesn’t land in   they’ll never fully get there. That uncer-
             completed match. Many families   the same way.                tainty is part of the story.
             say that in-person games help   There’s also a certain honesty in sit-  What is clear is that playing cards is
             bridge generational gaps, espe-  ting together. You can see who’s dis-  no longer just something you do in a
             cially during gatherings. The dig-  tracted, who’s bluffing badly, who’s pre-  room with a deck. It’s something you do
             ital shuffle adds new opportuni-  tending to be calm even though they’re   on trains, in airport queues, late at night
             ties, but the physical table still   on the verge of losing. Humans com-  when you can’t sleep. The game has
             teaches presence, empathy and   municate with more than words. A   slipped into more corners of life, not
             the subtle art of reading the room,   screen simplifies all of that into some-  fewer.
             something no algorithm can per-  thing cleaner, maybe too clean.
             fectly replicate.               Some players say online games feel   Closing reflection
                                           transactional. You play your hand, you   In the end, the shift from physical
                                           exit. No lingering for one more round.   tables to digital ones reveals more than a
           in different countries can still sit around   No inside jokes that get recycled years   change in how people play. It shows
           a virtual table and talk trash as convinc-  later. The social glue weakens. And even   how connection adapts. The memories
           ingly as before. In many ways, the digi-  though apps try to recreate the mood   made around real card tables still carry a
           tal shuffle has expanded the definition of   with sound effects and visuals, the tex-  warmth that’s hard to digitize, shaped by
           community.                      ture of a shared space is hard to simu-  shared glances, overlapping conver-
                                           late.                           sations and the easy comfort of being in
           What we lose when the table                                     the same room. Yet digital games have
           disappears                      The middle ground: coexistence   created their own kind of closeness, al-
             But something shifts when you re-  Still, it’s not a battle between the old   lowing friends separated by distance to
           move the physical setting. At a real   and the new. Most people who play digi-  gather instantly, even if only through a
           table, the game is only half the story.   tally also enjoy cards in person. It’s not   screen. It isn’t a matter of one replacing
           The other half is the energy between   a replacement, it’s an alternative. A kind   the other. Both forms simply offer dif-
           people. The teasing, the side conver-  of dual life for a centuries-old pastime.   ferent ways to stay linked in a world
           sations, the shared snacks. On an app,   Think of it this way. The physical   that’s moving faster, yet still hungry for
           those elements shrink. You get emojis   table is ritual. The digital table is con-  moments of togetherness. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[IN FOCUS














           GHALIB FOR THE DIGITAL SOUL



           Why Gen Z is quoting




           a 19th century poet


                                                                           certainty. Somehow, he fits into conver-
                                                                           sations about burnout, hustle culture and
           Keeping Ghalib alive isn’t about rigid preservation.            navigating your twenties.
                                                                              Even the playful Ghalib has fans. A
           It’s about allowing him to speak to new emotions,               popular meme makes rounds every few
           new crises, new types of heartbreak. By Pooja Mehta             weeks: a picture of Ghalib with sun-
                                                                           glasses photoshopped on, captioned with
                                                                           his mischievous:
                                                                              “Ishq par zor nahi hai yeh woh aa-
                  hat makes a 19th century poet   users pairing it with rainy-window vi-  tish Ghalib,
                  unexpectedly compatible   deos, yet here we are.            Jo lagaye na lage aur bujhaye na
           Wwith the swipe-and-scroll        The digital world thrives on distilled   bane.”
           generation? Maybe it’s because Ghalib   emotion. Short formats. Punchy lines. A   It’s the digital generation’s way of
           wrote like someone who’d already lived   sentence that says what your heart’s   saying: feelings don’t obey logic, deal
           through every kind of heartbreak the in-  been trying to articulate for weeks. Gha-  with it.
           ternet now tries to meme its way out of.   lib does that effortlessly. His couplets
             There’s something almost cinematic   are naturally made for screenshots.   WhatsApp wisdom and late-night
           about Mirza Ghalib’s resurgence online.   And yes, memes too.   sharing
           His birth anniversary, December 27,                                WhatsApp, especially among South
           rolls around each year and suddenly so-  The instagrammable Ghalib   Asians, has become its own literary eco-
           cial media is filled with sepia portraits,   Scroll through any poetry page and   system. There are family groups where
           soft Urdu couplets and reels that stitch   you’ll find Ghalib everywhere: minimal-  someone’s uncle shares a daily Ghalib
           together heartbreak with lo-fi music. It’s   istic beige templates, carousel posts,   quote with a good morning message.
           quiet proof that a poet long gone still   reels overlaying his sher with piano   There are college groups where Ghalib’s
           knows how to make himself heard.   chords. His lines offer a kind of emo-  sher surface at 2 a.m. when heartbreak
                                           tional shorthand.               or homesickness kicks in.
           Why Ghalib feels like a digital   Take the classic:                Students who rarely read long texts
           native                            “Hazaron khwahishein aisi ki har   still find themselves forwarding lines
             Ghalib was never writing for Gen Z,   khwahish pe dam nikle.”   like:
           of course. But today’s young readers   It’s poetic, but it also doubles as a   “Ranj se khugar hua insan to mit
           seem to recognize something strangely   caption for a reel titled “POV: You have   jaata hai ranj.”
           familiar in him: his emotional honesty,   a new dream every 5 minutes.” It’s relat-  It gives comfort without demanding
           his cleverness, his self-aware humor.   able in a way Ghalib might actually grin   explanation. The sher works like a voice
           Ghalib was, in many ways, the original   at.                    note from a wise friend who speaks in
           chronicler of inner chaos. When he   Another line, “Na tha kuch to khuda   metaphors.
           wrote “Dil hi to hai na sang o khisht,   tha, kuch na hota to khuda hota,” finds   And then there’s the confession cul-
           dard se bhar na aaye kyun”, he probably   itself quoted in podcasts that explore   ture. When people can’t say how they
           didn’t imagine millions of Instagram   spirituality, identity and existential un-  feel, they send Ghalib instead. It’s easier

           20                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[“                             lines into indie songs, spoken-word per-


                                                                           formances and podcast episodes. Spo-
                                                                           tify and YouTube have hundreds of re-
                                             Ghalib wrote centuries
                                                                           sometimes paired with electronic beats
                                             before the internet, yet      interpretations of his ghazals,
                                                                           or acoustic guitar.
                                                                              A hit example is how “Dil-e-naa-
                                             his couplets feel like they   daan tujhe hua kya hai” finds a place in
                                                                           breakup playlists where the original
                                             were designed for the         melody has been stripped down to just
                                             scroll-hungry soul.”          soft humming and atmospheric sound.
                                                                           It’s not traditional, but it works because
                                                                           the emotion is intact.








           to reveal emotion when the words be-
           long to someone else.
             Why Gen Z finds Ghalib “relatable”
             The simplest answer might be this:
           his poetry mirrors the emotional inten-
           sity of youth.
             But there’s more to it.
           1. He embraced vulnerability
           without apology                                                    Podcasts, especially those that dive
             Gen Z values emotional authenticity.                          into mental health and culture, often
           Ghalib lived it. He wrote about debt,                           bring up Ghalib’s worldview. Hosts de-
           grief, longing, loneliness. His admission  Why Ghalib works     code lines like “Bas ki dushwaar hai

           of imperfection feels modern, almost                            har kaam ka aasan hona” to explore the
           therapeutic.                           in the age of reels      pressure of doing everything right in
                                                                           your twenties.
           2. He balanced depth with humor      There’s a reason Ghalib ap-   His poetry becomes a doorway to
             Ghalib’s wit was legendary. In   pears in reels, WhatsApp for-  bigger conversations.
           letters, he joked about money troubles   wards and podcast snippets. His
           and societal absurdities. This mix of   couplets are already compact,   The diaspora connection
           self-awareness and sarcasm resonates   emotionally charged and rhyth-  There’s something touching about
           with a generation raised on ironic   mically sharp. In a world that re-  how South Asian students abroad cling
           memes.                            wards short-form content, Ghalib   to Ghalib’s lines. For many, quoting him
                                             feels unexpectedly modern. His   becomes a way of staying tethered to
           3. His sher are short. Very short.   sher travel well across formats   home.
             Brevity is currency in the digital   because they capture big emo-  A student in Toronto might post:
           world. Ghalib mastered it centuries ago.   tions in small sentences. Heart-  “Woh firaaq aur woh visaal kahan” on a
           He could express an entire storm in two   break, longing, self-irony, exis-  snowy evening, not fully translating it
           lines. That makes his work perfect for   tential confusion, spiritual   for their non-Urdu-speaking friends. It
           reels, stories and captions.      questioning these are universal   becomes a quiet homage to roots, a cul-
                                             themes. And when creators add   tural fingerprint they carry proudly.
           4. He understood contradiction    lo-fi beats or slow-motion visu-  Language itself becomes identity and
             Gen Z lives in contradictions: crav-  als, Ghalib becomes even more   Ghalib is often the bridge.
           ing meaning yet joking about existential   accessible. For a generation that
           dread, seeking connection yet struggling   often struggles to articulate what   So why this revival now?
           with vulnerability. Ghalib captured that   they feel, his poetry becomes a   It’s tempting to say it’s just nostal-
           duality beautifully.              ready-made language of expres-  gia. But that’s only partly true.
             “Ishq ne Ghalib nikamma kar diya,   sion.
             Warna hum bhi aadmi the kaam ke.”                             1. Digital burnout has made people
             Is it tragic? Humorous? Self-dep-                             crave depth
           recating? All at once. And that layered   Ghalib in music, podcasts and pop   In a world full of noise, Ghalib
           tone mirrors the emotional texture of in-  culture              offers stillness. His lines slow you
           ternet culture.                   Young artists are blending Ghalib’s   down.

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[“



            Gen Z isn’t just reading
            Ghalib. They’re remixing
            him, captioning him and

            turning his emotion into
            digital shorthand.”



           2. The loneliness epidemic has
           created space for poetry
             People don’t want surface-level in-
           spiration anymore. They want words
           that feel lived-in. Ghalib gives them
           that.
           3. Content creators are
           rediscovering classical literature
             Reels that explain couplets, anima-  tached from their ghazals. But maybe
           tions illustrating ghazals and in-  this is how poetry survives: by shape-
           fluencers reading poetry have turned   shifting. By meeting new audiences     The most shared
           old literature into new content formats.   where they are.
           Ghalib benefits immensely from this   And Gen Z isn’t just consuming     Ghalib lines online
           wave.                           Ghalib. They’re remixing him, recon-
                                           textualizing him, pulling his work into   Some couplets have practi-
           4. Urdu is trending again       conversations he never imagined. That’s   cally become digital currency.
             Language cycles in and out of fash-  not dilution. That’s evolution.   “Hazaron khwahishein aisi ki har
           ion. Thanks to Bollywood dialogues,                                khwahish pe dam nikle” appears
           songs and reels, Urdu is having a cul-  What it means to carry Ghalib   everywhere from mood boards to
           tural moment. Even those who don’t   forward                       mental health podcasts. “Ishq par
           fully understand it feel drawn to its   Keeping Ghalib alive isn’t about   zor nahi” is a favourite for heart-
           softness.                       rigid preservation. It’s about allowing   break reels. “Dil-e-naadaan tujhe
                                           him to speak to new emotions, new   hua kya hai” gets used for nostal-
           But there’s a subtle irony too   crises, new types of heartbreak. If any-  gia edits about friendships and
             Ghalib wrote in an era before elec-  thing, Gen Z’s adoption of Ghalib   past relationships.
           tricity, let alone the internet. Yet his   shows that poetry doesn’t fade when   Even “Bas ki dushwaar hai
           work thrives on platforms built for   times change. It adapts.     har kaam ka aasan hona” ap-
           speed and distraction. It’s odd and   As long as people feel deeply, as   pears in productivity videos and
           beautiful at the same time.     long as they search for words to ex-  burnout discussions. Each line
             Some purists worry about oversim-  press what they can’t quite articulate,   carries depth without demanding
           plification, about his sher being de-  poets like Ghalib will survive.   explanation. That simplicity
                                                                              makes the sher perfect for Gen
                                                                              Z’s rapid, visually driven com-
                                                                              munication style.


                                                                           Closing reflection
                                                                              Looking at Ghalib’s unexpected digi-
                                                                           tal comeback, one realizes something
                                                                           simple. Every era believes it’s unique in
                                                                           its confusion, its loneliness, its longing.
                                                                           Yet a poet from 200 years ago can still
                                                                           hold up a mirror to today’s world. His
                                                                           words comfort people he never knew, in
                                                                           formats he never saw.
                                                                              And maybe that’s the quiet magic of
                                                                           literature. It reminds us that human emo-
                                                                           tions don’t really change, even when our
                                                                           technology does. ■

           22                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE







































           Not on December 25                               th             shaped by ancient calculations, cultural
                                                                           memory and the quiet defiance of tradi-
                                                                           tions that refuse to flatten themselves
                                                                           into a single date.
           Christmas                                                       How calendars parted ways

                                                                              If all of Christianity once followed
                                                                           the same timeline, what changed? In
                                                                           short, the world updated its clocks. The
           celebrated on                                                   early church used the Julian calendar, in-
                                                                           troduced by Julius Caesar and remark-
                                                                           ably accurate for its time. Over cen-
                                                                           turies, though, that calendar drifted
                                                                           slightly away from the solar year. By the
           other dates                                                     enough that the Western world replaced
                                                                           1500s, the mismatch was significant
                                                                           it with the Gregorian version, which
                                                                           fixed the drift.
                                                                              Not everyone switched. And that’s
                                                                           where the dates split.
           Maybe that’s the quiet lesson behind these alternate               Orthodox communities in countries
                                                                           like Russia, Georgia and Serbia still rely
           dates. That joy doesn’t expire when the rest of the             on the older Julian calendar for their li-
           world moves on. By Aarav Sharma                                 turgical seasons. What for many is late
                                                                           December becomes, for them, early
                                                                           January. The gap feels small on paper
                                                                           but immense in lived experience. Streets
                  hy do some people wake up   makes them feel like themselves.   are quieter. Shops have already removed
                  to carols weeks after the rest   Many of us grow up assuming there’s   their decorations. But inside Orthodox
           Wof the world has taken down    one universal day when most of the   homes, something is just beginning.
           the lights? It’s a small curiosity at first.   world celebrates the birth of Jesus. Yet
           But once you look closer, the answer   millions of Christians across continents   The Orthodox rhythm
           opens a doorway into history, theology,   keep that sacred moment on an entirely   Spend time in an Orthodox house-
           identity and, maybe, the complicated   different page of the calendar. And it’s   hold in Eastern Europe or the Middle
           ways communities hold on to what   not accidental or contrarian. It’s a story   East and you notice the pace is different.

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[There’s a long fast leading up to the
           feast. The meals are simple, even aus-
           tere. And then the celebration arrives,                                Why different
           warm and full: candlelit services, choral
           chants, incense that clings to clothes.                                dates exist
             Many Orthodox Christians living in
           the diaspora talk about the odd beauty of                            The split in celebration dates
           celebrating after everyone else. One Ar-                           goes back to a simple but far-
           menian family in Los Angeles once de-                              reaching shift in calendars. Early
           scribed it to me as “a second chance at                            Christians followed the Julian
           joy”, especially for kids who watch their                          calendar, which gradually drifted
           friends unwrap gifts weeks earlier. For                            from the solar year. When the
           them, celebration isn’t about matching                             West adopted the more accurate
           the world’s schedule. It’s about honoring                          Gregorian version, most Ortho-
           continuity. “We follow our ancestors’                              dox churches held on to the older
           calendar,” a young Russian-American                                system, preserving centuries of li-
           once said. “It’s the one thing time zones                          turgical rhythm. Armenia chose a
           can’t change.”                                                     combined feast of Nativity and
                                                                              Epiphany, while Coptic and
           Armenia’s unique path                                              Ethiopian churches continued
             Armenian Christians add another                                  with their inherited timelines.
                                                                              These aren’t random variations.
                                                                              They’re decisions rooted in theol-
                                                                              ogy, identity and the belief that
                                                                              sacred time should reflect more
                                                                              than numerical correction. For
                                                                              millions, the older date feels like
                                                                              home.
                                                                             “



                                                                             For many Orthodox,

                                                                             Coptic, Armenian and
                                                                             Ethiopian Christians,

                                                                             celebration isn’t about
                                                                             matching the world’s
           layer to the story. The Armenian Aposto-  Coptic Christians and a story of   schedule. It’s about
           lic Church celebrates the Nativity and   resilience
           the Baptism of Jesus together as one   In Egypt, the Coptic Orthodox   honoring continuity.”
           feast. It isn’t just a date on the calendar,   Church celebrates on another date as
           it’s a theological statement that the birth   well, again tied to the older calendar.
           and revelation of Christ belong to the   The celebration comes after a long   whether in Canada or Australia, the date
           same sacred arc.                vegan fast that lasts more than forty   becomes a quiet link to home.
             In Armenia, the season feels quieter   days. That fast ends with a feast that
           than the highly commercialized De-  feels as much about community as it   Ethiopia’s Timkat season
           cember rush seen elsewhere. The em-  does about faith. Many Coptic families   In Ethiopia, the celebration is called
           phasis is on church services, family   describe it as a moment of resilience,   Gena and it falls during a season filled
           meals and moments of stillness. Even   especially because their community has   with festivals that blend Christian devo-
           the traditional dish of rice, dried fruits   often lived with uncertainty and discrim-  tion with vibrant cultural expression.
           and nuts feels symbolic: simple ing-  ination.                  Gena isn’t just a religious observance.
           redients carrying centuries of meaning.   The late-night liturgy is the heart of   It’s also a national mood. You can hear it
             Armenian communities scattered   it. Families leave church in the early   in the rhythms of drums, in the white
           around the world recreate these mo-  hours, children half-asleep, carrying the   cotton garments worn by worshippers,
           ments in apartments in Beirut, in sub-  smell of frankincense. Streets in Cairo,   in the games played by children.
           urbs of Paris, in pockets of Kolkata. It’s   Alexandria and Upper Egypt light up   Rural communities host gatherings
           a reminder that identity travels, even   with small bakeries selling special   that last for hours. Pilgrims walk long
           when borders shift.             Christmas bread. For Copts abroad,   distances to historic monasteries. And

           24                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             While one city packs

                                                                             away its ornaments,

                                                                             another is just

                                                                             beginning to glow.

                                                                             The same story,
                                                                             sung in a different

                                                                             tempo.”



                                           India’s layered picture         They’re about food, weather, geography
                    How the                  India adds its own complexity. The   and memory. A winter feast in Moscow
                                           majority of Christians here follow the   feels different from one in Cairo or

             celebrations differ           globally familiar December celebration,   Yerevan. Even the timing of seasonal

                                           especially Catholics and many Protes-
                                                                           harvests once shaped these practices.
                                           tants. But there are notable exceptions.
                Although the story commem-  Kerala’s Orthodox and Jacobite com-  A season that refuses to shrink to
             orated is the same, how com-  munities keep the alternate calendar for   one day
             munities celebrate can feel won-  certain observances, creating a fascinat-  Some people find it odd that Christ-
             derfully different. Orthodox   ing landscape where multiple traditions   mas doesn’t land on one universal date.
             Christians focus on fasting, can-  overlap.                   But perhaps that diversity is the point.
             dlelit liturgies and choral chant.   In cities like Kochi or Thiruvanantha-  Faith has never been monolithic. It
             Armenian families emphasize   puram, you may see one neighbourhood   stretches across oceans and centuries. It
             simplicity and the symbolic join-  lighting up for Christmas earlier and   absorbs local flavour. It adapts without
             ing of birth and baptism in one   another preparing for it later. It’s a sub-  entirely losing itself.
             feast. Coptic Christians break a   tle reminder of India’s religious and cul-  There’s something strangely comfort-
             long vegan fast with joyous   tural layering, where parallel histories   ing about a world where festivals don’t
             meals after midnight services.   coexist rather comfortably. Families   sync perfectly. While some families are
             Ethiopia’s Gena blends worship   who observe the later celebration often   packing ornaments into boxes, others
             with cultural traditions, from   say they enjoy the breathing room.   are gathering candles and preparing to
             white cotton garments to lively   “There’s no rush,” one Syrian Christian   sing hymns. While one city’s streets
             games.                        teacher once told me. “By the time ours   grow quiet, another’s are about to glow.
                Even in India, multiple time-  arrives, everything feels peaceful.”   It’s like listening to the same song
             lines coexist across churches.                                sung in different tempos.
             These variations show how one   Why the dates matter
             sacred story can take on distinct   So why hold on to these alternate   A closing reflection
             textures, shaped by geography,   dates in a world trying so hard to stan-  Every year, when the familiar De-
             memory and the resilience of   dardize everything, from time zones to   cember frenzy winds down, I find my-
             long-carried traditions.      holidays to school calendars?   self thinking of communities whose
                                             Part of it is faith. Traditions give   celebration is still ahead of them.
                                           shape to belief. When a community has   There’s something gentle about their
           for many Ethiopians living abroad,   prayed on the same date for centuries,   timing, almost countercultural. In a
           keeping the alternate date isn’t only   shifting it feels like unrooting something   world that insists everything should
           about faith. It’s a way of keeping Addis,   fragile.            happen at once, they remind us that
           Gondar or Lalibela alive in memory.   Part of it is identity. For diaspora   sacred moments don’t need to follow a
             There’s a lovely irony that while   communities especially, the date be-  single clock.
           some parts of the world are packing up   comes a quiet act of remembrance. If   Maybe that’s the quiet lesson behind
           their decorations, Ethiopians are just   you’re an Ethiopian living in Chicago or   these alternate dates. That joy doesn’t
           getting started. The season goes on to   a Serbian living in Melbourne, celebrat-  expire when the rest of the world moves
           Timkat, the feast of the Epiphany, where   ing later can feel like stitching yourself   on. That tradition can be an anchor. And
           entire towns take part in processions car-  back to a place you left behind. It’s a   that sometimes, the most meaningful
           rying replicas of the Ark of the Cov-  way of saying: I still belong.   celebrations are the ones unfolding just
           enant. It’s one of the most visually strik-  And part of it is cultural rhythm. Fes-  slightly out of sync with the noise
           ing Christian festivals anywhere.   tivals aren’t only about doctrine.   around them. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT
































           Remembering Rafi                                                A voice that belonged to everyone
                                                                              Rafi was often celebrated for his ver-
                                                                           satility, a word used so frequently that it
                                                                           almost feels inadequate now. But it’s
           How he sang for                                                 true. He could shift from youthful mis-
                                                                           chief to devotional surrender within mi-
                                                                           nutes. Listen to his bright, playful
                                                                           energy in songs like “Badan Pe Sitare”
                                                                           then drift to the serene reverence of “O
           everyone and                                                    Duniya Ke Rakhwale”. It’s almost hard
                                                                           to believe the same vocal cords made
                                                                           both possible.
                                                                              That ability gave him a rare univer-
                                                                           sality. He didn’t simply sing for actors
           everything                                                      or characters. He sang for emotions
                                                                           themselves. Whether it was Dilip Ku-
                                                                           mar’s classic restraint, Shammi Ka-
                                                                           poor’s flamboyance or Dev Anand’s ef-
                                                                           fortless charm, Rafi seemed to borrow a
                                                                           bit of their soul, fold it into his voice
           What does it take for a single voice to feel like it            and send it soaring across cinema halls.
                                                                              Some singers match voices with
           belongs to an entire nation? By Ishita Desai                    faces. Rafi blended souls with stories.

                                                                           The man who could sing anything
               ome singers carry a tune. Mo-  panion through their own unfolding   If you try sorting Rafi’s songs by
               hammed Rafi carried emotions,   lives.                      genre, you’ll quickly lose track. Not be-
           Scharacters, entire worlds. It didn’t   On 24 December 1924, a boy was   cause the list is long, but because the
           matter if the scene needed heartbreak or   born in Kotla Sultan Singh who would   lines between genres almost dissolve in
           celebration, mischief or prayer. Rafi   one day sing for India in a way few   the shadow of his voice.
           somehow found the right shade of   others ever have. His birth anniversary
           human feeling each time. And though   arrives each year as a gentle reminder of   When the divine needed a voice
           decades have passed, listeners still de-  the enormous room he built inside his   Rafi’s devotional songs weren’t just
           scribe his voice with a strange mix of in-  music, a room wide enough for every   performances. They were quiet offer-
           timacy and awe, as if he wasn’t just a   mood, every face on screen and every   ings. There’s a sincerity in “Mann Tarpat
           great playback singer but a quiet com-  listener in their own private auditorium.   Hari Darshan Ko Aaj” that makes even

           26                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[“



            Some singers

            matched voices with
            faces. Rafi blended

            souls with stories.”



           the uninitiated pause for a second. His
           pitch, soft vibrato and gentle restraint
           turned religious music into something
           deeply human. It wasn’t about which
           god the song addressed. It was about
           longing itself.

           When romance needed softness
             Hindi cinema has had no shortage of
           love songs, but Rafi had the uncanny
           ability to make each one sound like it
           belonged to a different kind of love.
           Simple love, complicated love, young
           love, love that arrives late in life.
           “Chaudhvin Ka Chand” floats like silk.
           “Likhe Jo Khat Tujhe” feels like an inti-
           mate confession whispered on a quiet   stood both tradition and performance. It
           evening. No two romantic Rafi songs   wasn’t only technique. It was attitude.
           feel like twins.
                                           And yes… even cabaret                  The many faces
           When joy needed to dance          What’s remarkable is not that he sang
             There’s a reason filmmakers went to   cabaret songs but that he did it convinc-  of Rafi’s voice

           him for songs that needed pure, unfil-  ingly. He would adjust his tone, add a
           tered energy. In “Yahoo! Chahe Koi   smoky texture, change phrasing and   Mohammed Rafi didn’t just
           Mujhe Junglee Kahe” he wasn’t just   suddenly he fit the mood of dim lights   sing different genres. He shaped
           matching Shammi Kapoor’s intensity.   and nightclub glitz. Many singers strug-  them. His voice folded itself into
           He was setting the tempo for Kapoor’s   gled with these shifts, but for Rafi this   whatever a moment needed. Ro-
           entire screen persona.          fluidity felt almost effortless.   mance, devotion, mischief, long-
                                                                              ing, celebration. Rafi didn’t treat
           When sorrow needed dignity      Singing for the stars, yet staying   these moods as categories. He
             Even his sad songs refused melo-  invisible                      treated them as human experi-
           drama. “Din Dhal Jaye” doesn’t ask for   Playback singing is a strange profes-  ences worth honoring. That’s
           sympathy. It simply sits with pain. And   sion. You’re heard by millions but rarely   why his qawwalis feel spiritual
           somehow that makes it more powerful.   seen. Your voice becomes inseparable   yet theatrical, why his cabaret
           He felt sorrow without drowning in it   from the actors, yet you remain a quiet   numbers carry a smoky charm
           and that made listeners trust him more.   presence behind the screen. Rafi em-  and why his romantic melodies
                                           braced that invisibility. He didn’t seem   feel like they were written for
           When mischief needed sparkle    to crave the spotlight. The stories from   one listener at a time. His talent
             Rafi had a playful side that’s some-  those who knew him describe a gentle,   wasn’t just range. It was empathy
           times overlooked. “Sar Jo Tera Chak-  almost shy man whose humility became   set to music.
           raye” is practically a comedic mono-  as legendary as his voice.
           logue set to music. The warmth in his   His collaborations reveal how deeply
           tone turned even lighthearted songs into   he shaped the golden era of Hindi   changed playback singing forever, yet
           small moments of joy.           cinema. From Naushad to Shankar Jai-  he did it so gracefully that he rarely
                                           kishan, SD Burman to OP Nayyar, Rafi   seemed to be asserting anything at all.
           When qawwali needed fire        worked with composers who pushed   He let the music speak first.
             He could switch into the qawwali   him into new territory again and again.
           style with astonishing ease. The rhyth-  And he accepted each challenge like a   How younger generations are
           mic force of “Na To Caravan Ki Talash   craftsman who loved the feel of his   finding him again
           Hai” or the dramatic build of “Pardah   tools.                     It’s surprising, though maybe not
           Hai Pardah” shows a singer who under-  There’s a small irony here. Rafi   really, that young listeners still stream

           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[How Gen Z is


                                                                                  rediscovering Rafi

                                                                                It’s surprising but true:
                                                                              younger listeners are streaming
                                                                              Rafi in large numbers. Some ar-
                                                                              rive through remixes, others
                                                                              through grandparents’ playlists or
                                                                              algorithmic suggestions. What
                                                                              keeps them there is the clarity
                                                                              and sincerity of his singing. In an
                                                                              age of fast-paced production and
                                                                              auto-tuned gloss, Rafi represents
                                                                              something steady and real. Gen Z
                                                                              listeners describe his voice as
                                                                              comforting, almost like an emo-
                                                                              tional anchor they didn’t expect
                                                                              to find in old cinema. His time-
                                                                              lessness isn’t nostalgia. It’s res-
                                                                              onance.

                                                                             “



                                                                             His voice didn’t just

                                                                             hit notes. It reached

           Rafi today. Some discover him through   say they feel like they know him. Rafi   people, slipping
           remixes then wander into the originals.   didn’t impose his personality on songs.
           Others through old films their grandpar-  He shaped himself around them. This   quietly into their
           ents watched. Many find him through   willingness to disappear into the music
           playlists titled “Timeless Voices” or   made him strangely present in the lives   lives and staying
           “Golden Hits”.                  of listeners. Everyone could find their
             What’s interesting is the language   own emotion reflected back at them.   there.”
           they use. They talk about his voice like   Some artists are admired. Rafi was
           it’s a feeling. Something warm, some-  held close.
           thing steady, something honest. In an era                       cession knows it’s true. His songs are
           of auto-tune and fast production cycles,   A Legacy that refuses to fade   still bookmarks in people’s lives.
           Rafi represents a kind of authenticity   How many singers can claim to have
           that feels refreshing. Even Gen Z,   sung for every kind of character, every   Closing reflection
           steeped in global sounds, seems to find   genre, every emotional palette available   Remembering Rafi isn’t just about
           something soothing in his clarity.   in Hindi cinema? Not many. Fewer still   remembering a singer. It’s about remem-
             Music historians often label him a   can say their songs continue to breathe   bering how one voice helped define
           bridge between classical training and   new life decades later.   what emotion sounds like in Indian
           cinematic storytelling. Younger listeners   Rafi’s legacy isn’t just in the thou-  cinema. Everyone has their own Rafi
           simply call him comforting.     sands of tracks he recorded. It’s in the   song and in some quiet way, that means
                                           unseen way he shaped how actors per-  everyone has their own Rafi. His music
           Why Rafi feels personal, even now   formed, how composers composed and   continues to arrive in unexpected mo-
             Maybe this is why Rafi remains un-  how audiences felt film music. Without   ments.
           matched for many. His voice didn’t just   trying too hard, he set a standard for   A street vendor humming a tune. A
           hit notes. It reached people. He had that   playback singing that still towers above   grandparent tapping a rhythm. Someone
           rare quality of sounding intimate even in   the industry.       streaming an old film late at night. And
           the grandest orchestral compositions.   His voice has become part of India’s   maybe that’s the real legacy. A voice that
           And he never sang to show off. He sang   collective memory. That’s a big claim,   keeps finding people, long after the man
           to express something.           but anyone who’s heard a Rafi song   is gone.
             There’s a reason so many Indians,   float out of a shop radio on a humid af-  He sang for everyone and everything.
           even those born long after his passing,   ternoon or drift through a wedding pro-  And somehow, he still does. ■

           28                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                December 16-31, 2025







           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Career and responsibility dominate your thoughts   Libra, home, family and emotional security draw
                     now. You may feel pressure to prove yourself, but   focus. You may reflect on where and with
                     steady effort speaks louder than force.         whom, you feel safest. Career matters slow
                     Relationships benefit from patience and emotional   slightly, offering space to recalibrate personal
                     maturity. Avoid rushing year-end decisions.     priorities.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     A broader perspective emerges. Travel plans,    Scorpio, your voice carries weight now. Impor-
                     learning, or philosophical conversations bring   tant discussions, writing, or negotiations move
                     clarity. Emotionally, you’re lighter than you’ve   forward. Stay clear and calm, intensity isn’t al-
                     been in weeks. Trust the long view, what feels slow   ways required. A short trip or reconnection
                     now is aligning quietly.                        brings insight.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Deep conversations and emotional truths come    Sagittarius, finances and self-worth come under
                     to the surface. Shared finances or commitments   review. This is a moment to value what you
                     may need review. Vulnerability strengthens      bring to the table. Avoid impulsive spending.
                     bonds, even if it feels uncomfortable. Let hon-  Emotionally, stability feels grounding after a
                     esty guide you into the new year.               restless month.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Relationships take center stage. Partnerships, ro-  Happy Birthday, Capricorn. This is your per-
                     mantic or professional, ask for balance and un-  sonal reset. New goals take shape and con-
                     derstanding. A meaningful conversation could    fidence returns quietly but firmly. Lead with in-
                     redefine a connection. Give without losing your-  tegrity. Be happy the year ahead begins with
                     self.                                           self-trust.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, daily routines, health and responsibilities   Aquarius, a reflective phase encourages rest and
                     demand attention. Small adjustments now pre-    release. Don’t  worry, Old patterns are dissolv-
                     vent future stress. Work feels demanding, but   ing. Don’t rush clarity, it will come naturally.
                     your consistency pays off. Make space for rest,   Solitude now prepares you for a stronger, clearer
                     it’s not a luxury.                              start ahead.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, creativity and emotional warmth return.   Pisces, friends, networks and shared dreams up-
                     Love feels expressive and sincere. This is a    lift you shortly. A meaningful connection re-
                     beautiful time to reconnect with joy, art, or chil-  minds you that you’re not alone. Don’t worry, as
                     dren. Let go of overthinking and allow yourself   the year closes, hope feels realistic, not fragile.
                     to feel.                                        The year ahead begins with self-trust..


           DECEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Delhi’s air emergency: A wake-up
                                           partisan interests.
           call
                                           Sachin Kumar, Delhi, India
             Britain, Canada and Singapore issuing

                                                                           regular inspections and swift legal ac-
           advisories asking their citizens to avoid   institutions, values that must rise above   mere formalities. Strict enforcement,
           visiting Delhi due to the city’s record-high                    tion are essential to prevent such
           AQI of 493 and above is deeply alarming   Hijab controversy and political   tragedies from recurring.
           and frankly humiliating. When the air   responsibility in Bihar   Roopesh R. Patil, Mumbai, Maha-
           becomes a global warning, it reflects not   The recent controversy involving   rashtra, India
           just an environmental crisis but a   Bihar Chief Minister Nitish Kumar,
           governance failure.             where he was seen pulling down the
             Such extreme pollution is not a sudden   hijab of a Muslim woman during a pub-  Barbet’s Nest: A serene stay at
           event; it is a predictable, annual disaster   lic interaction, has triggered sharp politi-  Mussoorie
           driven by unchecked emissions,   cal backlash across the state. Whether   Through the columns of your es-
           construction dust, crop burning and weak   intentional or a moment of poor judg-  teemed magazine, I wish to highlight
           enforcement. While emergency measures   ment, the incident has caused wide-  Barbet’s Nest, a homestay in Mussoorie
           are announced each year, long-term   spread hurt and raised serious questions   that truly reflects the charm of mindful
           solutions remain missing.       about sensitivity and respect in public   tourism. Owned and thoughtfully man-
             Delhi needs sustained political will,   life.                 aged by Mr. Anil Rawat, the property is
           regional coordination and accountability,   In a diverse democracy like India,   located just a short walk from Mall
           before clean air becomes a luxury and   symbols of faith and personal dignity   Road and close to the Mussoorie Li-
           warnings turn permanent.        must be handled with utmost care, espe-  brary, it offers both convenience and
           Nutan Sharma, Delhi, India      cially by those holding constitutional   calm. The availability of free Wi-Fi and
                                           positions. Public leaders are constantly   on-site parking further adds to guest
                                           under scrutiny and their actions, small or   comfort.
           Congress rally against ‘Vote Chori’   large, carry powerful messages.   What sets Barbet’s Nest apart is its
             The Congress party’s rally at Delhi’s   The incident has provided ammu-  breathtaking view of the Dehradun Val-
           Ram Lila Ground against alleged “vote   nition for political sparring, but beyond   ley, with the rare winter line visible on
           chori” has once again brought the issue   party lines lies a deeper concern: the   clear days. The treehouse-style accom-
           of electoral trust into public focus. Large   need for empathy, cultural awareness   modation, complete with a private bal-
           crowds and fiery speeches may reflect   and accountability from those in power.   cony, creates a memorable experience.
           public anxiety, but they must also be   Rakesh Jha, Patna, Bihar, India   Well-equipped with modern amenities,
           backed by concrete evidence and re-                             comfortable bedding, heating, kitche-
           sponsible dialogue.                                             nette essentials and quality linens, it bal-
             India’s democracy rests on the cred-  Goa nightclub fire and the long   ances nature with comfort.
           ibility of its electoral process. Allega-  road to justice         Such thoughtfully designed stays
           tions of manipulation, if unsubstanti-  The deportation of the Luthra   promote sustainable tourism while al-
           ated, risk weakening public faith in   brothers to India by Thai authorities in   lowing visitors to connect deeply with
           institutions that have long been the   connection with the Goa nightclub fire   the hills.
           backbone of free and fair elections. Gen-  is a significant step toward accountabil-  Nitin Agarwal, Mussoorie, Uttarak-
           uine concerns deserve transparent inves-  ity. The tragic incident, which claimed   hand, India
           tigation and open debate.       lives and exposed glaring lapses in
             Political parties should pursue griev-  safety norms, had shocked the nation
           ances through constitutional and legal   and raised serious questions about regu-  Letters (limited to one hundred
           channels rather than street confron-  latory oversight in nightlife establish-  words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           tations that deepen polarization. Safe-  ments.                    Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           guarding democracy requires accounta-  This case should serve as a stern re-
           bility, restraint and respect for   minder that safety regulations are not


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Carlos Misael Cruz López








                                                     Merry Christmas]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>