<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="38"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                       VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 12  I  JULY 16 2024  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL, PHOTO: ANYA TAYLOR





               5



                                                            24













                                                            20                                       12
















           4-Editorial: Honoring the guiding lights  30-The Guru's Legacy
           of humanity                                     31-The Magic of Teaching and Learning

           5-Dispelling darkness with wisdom               32-The Transformative Power of

           8-Global Efforts to Enhance Brain               Inspirational Teachers

           Health                                          33-Qualities of an Inspiring Teacher
           12-Collaborative Efforts to Protect             34-Mentors, Guides, and Second

           Tigers                                          Parents

           16-Broadcasting in the digital age              35-The Profound Role of a Guru in

           20-A global game of kings and queens            Indian Tradition
           24-The ultimate Nature’s Paradise               36-Horoscopes

           28-Guru Purnima Special                         37-Letters

           29-Wisdom and Enlightenment

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Guru Purnima
     EDITORIAL  Honoring the guiding                                               Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           lights of humanity                                                     Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n a world driven by technological    Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           advancements and rapid change, the
                                        Itimeless role of the guru stands as a      Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        beacon of wisdom and guidance. Guru
                                        Purnima, the festival dedicated to honoring   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        these revered teachers, holds profound       Sushil Kumar
                                        significance not only in religious contexts
                                        but also in the broader spectrum of human   Social Media Editor
                                        learning and spiritual growth.             Vishakha Sharma
                                           The word "guru" itself holds deep
                                        meaning in various spiritual and cultural   Art & Graphics Director
                                        traditions. Derived from Sanskrit, "gu"      Vipin Agarwal
                                        signifies darkness and "ru" symbolizes the
                                        dispeller of darkness. A guru, therefore, is
           more than a teacher; they are a mentor who illuminates the path of knowledge,
           dispelling ignorance and nurturing the intellectual and spiritual growth of their   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           disciples.
             Across ages and civilizations, the guru-shishya parampara (tradition) has been   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           integral to the preservation and dissemination of knowledge. From ancient Indian   Editor, United News of India, New
           gurukuls where sages imparted not just academic but also moral and ethical   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           teachings, to modern classrooms where educators inspire and shape future   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           generations, the role of the guru remains indispensable.         Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             Guru Purnima, observed on the full moon day of Ashadha, transcends religious   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           boundaries to celebrate this profound relationship between teacher and student. It is a   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           day when disciples express their gratitude, reverence, and devotion to their gurus
           through rituals, prayers, and introspection. More than a festival, Guru Purnima serves   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           as a reminder of the guru's pivotal role in shaping minds and nurturing souls.   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             In today's fast-paced world, where information is abundant yet wisdom is scarce,
           the significance of the guru becomes even more pronounced. Beyond imparting   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           knowledge, gurus instill values, ignite curiosity, and inspire critical thinking. They
           cultivate a holistic approach to learning, emphasizing not just academic excellence   Phone +91 20 40199102
           but also compassion, integrity, and resilience.                   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             Guru Purnima serves as a poignant reminder of the invaluable role that gurus play   Baner Road,
           in shaping individuals and societies. As we pay homage to these guiding lights, let us   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           renew our commitment to honoring knowledge, embracing wisdom, and fostering a   Email revoir@post.com
           world where the teachings of our gurus continue to illuminate the path ahead.   Website www.revoir.in
             As we celebrate Guru Purnima, let us reflect on the profound impact that gurus
           have had on our lives and society at large. Let us acknowledge their tireless
           dedication and unwavering commitment to the pursuit of truth and enlightenment.   Legal Advisor
           May this day inspire us to honor and cherish the invaluable presence of gurus in our   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           journey of learning and self-discovery.
             As we pay homage to these guiding lights, let us renew our commitment to   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           honoring knowledge, embracing wisdom, and fostering a world where the teachings   all rights reserved. This publication
           of our gurus continue to illuminate the path ahead.              may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY













































           THE ROLE OF THE GURU


           Dispelling darkness









           with wisdom






           By Naina Kapoor

                 uru Purnima, an auspicious fes-  gious boundaries, revered by Hindus,   mythology. The term "guru" itself is de-
                 tival celebrated predominantly   Buddhists, Jains, and even those with   rived from two Sanskrit words: "gu"
           Gin India, Nepal, and Bhutan,   secular inclinations, acknowledging the   meaning darkness and "ru" meaning dis-
           holds profound significance in the spiri-  timeless role of the guru in personal and   peller. Thus, a guru is one who dispels
           tual and academic realms. This sacred   societal transformation.   the darkness of ignorance, illuminating
           day, dedicated to venerating gurus (spir-                       the path of wisdom and self-realization.
           itual and academic teachers), is ob-  Historical and mythological   Vedic tradition: In Hinduism, Guru
           served on the full moon day (Purnima)   significance            Purnima is linked to the worship of Veda
           in the Hindu month of Ashadha (June-  The origins of Guru Purnima are   Vyasa, a revered sage and author of the
           July). Guru Purnima transcends reli-  steeped in ancient traditions and rich   Mahabharata, who is considered the epi-

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[tome of wisdom. Vyasa is credited with
           compiling the four Vedas, categorizing
           them for easy comprehension and propa-
           gation. In his honor, this day is also
           known as Vyasa Purnima. Disciples and
           scholars pay homage to Vyasa, express-
           ing gratitude for his unparalleled con-
           tributions to the preservation and dis-
           semination of Vedic knowledge.
             Buddhist tradition: Guru Purnima is                                                           The Ancient Indian Education System
           equally significant in Buddhism as it
           commemorates the day when Lord Bud-
           dha delivered his first sermon at Sarnath
           after attaining enlightenment. Known as
           Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta, this ser-
           mon laid the foundation for the Dharma
           (Buddhist teachings), marking the estab-
           lishment of the Sangha (community of
           monks). Buddhists celebrate this day by
           participating in prayer meetings, reciting
           Buddhist scriptures, and engaging in
           acts of charity.
             Jain tradition: In Jainism, Guru Pur-
           nima is observed as Treenok Guha Pur-
           nima, marking the day when Lord Ma-
           havira, the 24th Tirthankara, made
           Indrabhuti Gautam his first disciple, es-
           tablishing the guru-disciple tradition
           within the Jain community.
                                                                                                           A teacher is regarded as a mentor
           The role of the guru in Indian
           culture
             The guru-shishya (teacher-student)
           relationship is a cornerstone of Indian
           culture, deeply rooted in ancient tradi-
           tions. In the Gurukul system, students   spiritual growth of their disciples. This   of Guru Purnima has evolved, adapting
           lived with their guru, absorbing not only   relationship is built on trust, respect, and   to the changing dynamics of society.
           academic knowledge but also life skills,   a deep sense of gratitude. The guru’s   While the traditional rituals continue to
           ethical values, and spiritual insights.   role extends beyond mere academic in-  be observed with reverence, new forms
           This holistic education system empha-  struction, encompassing moral and spiri-  of celebration have emerged, reflecting
           sized character building and the har-  tual guidance, helping students navigate   the diverse ways in which people honor
           monious development of the mind,   the complexities of life.    their teachers.
           body, and spirit.                                                  Spiritual observances: Devotees ac-
             A guru is seen as a mentor, guide,   Modern interpretations and   ross India visit temples and ashrams to
           and a parental figure who imparts wis-  celebrations            offer prayers and seek blessings from
           dom and nurtures the intellectual and   In contemporary times, the essence   their spiritual gurus. Special pujas (rit-
                                                                           uals) and satsangs (spiritual discourses)
                                                                           are organized, emphasizing the guru’s
                                                                           teachings and their relevance in today’s
                                                                           world. Meditation sessions, bhajans (de-
         A teacher who is popular among students                           and educational institutions, Guru Pur-
                                                                           votional songs), and charitable activities
                                                                           are common practices, fostering a sense
                                                                           of community and spiritual solidarity.
                                                                              Academic celebrations: In schools

                                                                           nima is marked by various activities that
                                                                           honor teachers and their contributions.
                                                                           Students express their gratitude through
                                                                           speeches, cultural performances, and by
                                                                           presenting tokens of appreciation to
                                                                           their teachers. Workshops and seminars
                                                                           are conducted, focusing on the impor-
                                                                           tance of education and the enduring im-

           6                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[cessions.
                                                                              Eastern India: In West Bengal and
                                                                           Odisha, the day is celebrated with
                                                                           readings from the Bhagavad Gita and
                                                                           other sacred texts, along with discus-
                                                                           sions on philosophical and spiritual
                                                                           topics.

                                                                           Guru Purnima: A Day of Gratitude
                                                                           and Reflection
         Interacting with the students                                     of the invaluable role of the guru in our
                                                                              Guru Purnima is more than just a fes-
                                                                           tival; it is a profound acknowledgment

                                                                           lives. It is a day to express gratitude,
                                                                           seek blessings, and renew our commit-
                                                                           ment to the path of learning and self-im-
                                                                           provement. The timeless teachings of

                                                                           pose, integrity, and wisdom.
                                                                              As we celebrate Guru Purnima, let us
           pact of teachers on society.    Special kirtans (devotional singing) and   the guru inspire us to lead a life of pur-
             Secular celebrations: Beyond reli-  yagnas (sacrificial rituals) are per-  remember the words of Swami Viveka-
           gious and academic contexts, Guru Pur-  formed, invoking divine blessings for   nanda: “The guru is the means of real-
           nima has found resonance in the corpo-  wisdom and prosperity.   ization. There is no knowledge without a
           rate world and among individuals who   South India: In South India, Guru   teacher.” This day, dedicated to honor-
           seek personal growth. Mentorship pro-  Purnima is observed with great fervor in   ing the light of knowledge, encourages
           grams, motivational talks, and self-im-  the ashrams of spiritual gurus like   us to embrace the guru within and strive
           provement workshops are organized,   Shankaracharya and Ramana Maharshi.   towards the ultimate goal of self-realiza-
           celebrating the role of mentors and   Devotees participate in elaborate rituals,   tion.
           guides in professional and personal de-  meditation sessions, and discourses on   In a world that is constantly evolv-
           velopment. This secular interpretation   Vedantic teachings.    ing, the essence of Guru Purnima re-
           highlights the universal appeal of the   Western India: In Maharashtra and   mains unchanged – a tribute to the eter-
           guru-disciple relationship, transcending   Gujarat, the Warkari community pays   nal bond between the guru and disciple,
           traditional boundaries.         homage to their spiritual leaders, par-  a celebration of wisdom, and a reminder
                                           ticularly Sant Tukaram and Sant Dnya-  of the transformative power of knowl-
           The spiritual significance      neshwar, with devotional songs and pro-  edge. ■
             The spiritual essence of Guru Pur-
           nima lies in its reminder of the guru’s
           role in dispelling ignorance and leading
           disciples towards enlightenment. The
           guru is often equated with God, consid-
           ered the ultimate source of knowledge
           and wisdom. In the words of the Adi
           Shankaracharya, “Guru is Brahma, Guru
           is Vishnu, Guru is Maheswara; Guru is
           the Supreme Brahman itself. Salutations
           to that Guru.”
             The day is an opportunity for dis-
           ciples to reflect on their spiritual jour-
           ney, assess their progress, and renew
           their commitment to the path of self-re-
           alization. It is a time to seek the guru’s
           guidance, express gratitude, and
           strengthen the bond between guru and
           disciple.

           Guru Purnima in different regions                                                               A student keenly watching the teacher’s lesson
             Guru Purnima is celebrated with
           unique customs and rituals across var-
           ious regions of India, each adding its
           distinct flavor to the festivities.
             North India: In the northern states,
           devotees visit temples dedicated to
           Shiva, Vyasa, and other revered sages.

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH



































           MIND MATTERS



           Global Efforts to







           Enhance Brain Health







           By Staff Writer


                  orld Brain Day, observed an-  theme of World Brain Day changes to   World Brain Day is to draw attention to
                  nually on July 22nd, is a   highlight specific aspects of neurological   the pressing neurological issues facing
           Wglobal event dedicated to rais-  health, reflecting current trends, research   populations worldwide, ranging from
           ing awareness about neurological dis-  breakthroughs, and emerging concerns.   common conditions like migraines and
           orders and promoting brain health. Initi-                       strokes to more complex disorders such
           ated by the World Federation of   Historical context and purpose   as Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's dis-
           Neurology (WFN) in collaboration with   The World Federation of Neurology,   ease, and multiple sclerosis.
           various neurological societies world-  established in 1957, has been at the fore-
           wide, this day aims to educate the public   front of promoting neurological health   Themes and focus areas
           about the importance of brain health and   and education. In 2014, the WFN   Each year, World Brain Day adopts a
           the need for increased research and re-  launched World Brain Day to coincide   specific theme to focus its awareness
           sources to combat neurological con-  with its own founding anniversary on   campaigns and educational efforts.
           ditions. With each passing year, the   July 22nd. The primary purpose of   These themes are carefully chosen based

           8                                                              www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[on the current needs and challenges in
           the field of neurology. For instance, past
           themes have included topics like "Epi-
           lepsy: It's More Than Seizures," "Stop
           Multiple Sclerosis," and "Migraine: The
           Painful Truth." By centering the day
           around a particular theme, the WFN and
           its partners can concentrate their efforts
           on addressing specific issues, dissemi-
           nating targeted information, and foster-
           ing a more profound understanding of
           each condition.

           Importance of brain health                                                                      MRI scan of the brain
             The brain is the most complex organ
           in the human body, responsible for con-
           trolling every aspect of our lives, from
           basic physiological functions to com-
           plex cognitive processes. Maintaining
           brain health is crucial for overall well-
           being. Neurological disorders can signif-
           icantly impact an individual's quality of
           life, leading to physical, cognitive, and
           emotional challenges. Early diagnosis,
           effective treatment, and preventive
           measures are essential in mitigating the
           effects of these conditions.
             Neurological disorders are among the                                                          A patient under observation in an EEG machine
           leading causes of disability and death
           worldwide. According to the World
           Health Organization (WHO), neurolog-
           ical conditions such as stroke,
           Alzheimer's disease, and other demen-
           tias are significant contributors to the
           global burden of disease. The impact of
           these disorders extends beyond the indi-
           vidual, affecting families, communities,   Alzheimer's disease and dementia:   havior. As the disease progresses, indi-
           and healthcare systems. By promoting   Alzheimer's disease is a progressive   viduals may require full-time care.
           brain health, we can reduce the inci-  neurological disorder that affects mem-  While there is currently no cure for
           dence of these debilitating conditions   ory, thinking, and behavior. It is the   Alzheimer's, treatments are available to
           and improve the quality of life for mil-  most common cause of dementia among   help manage symptoms and improve
           lions of people.                older adults. Early symptoms include   quality of life.
                                           difficulty remembering recent events,   Parkinson's disease: Parkinson's
           Common neurological disorders   confusion, and changes in mood and be-  disease is a neurodegenerative disorder
                                                                           that primarily affects movement. It is
                                                                           characterized by tremors, stiffness,
                                                                           slowness of movement, and balance
                                                                           problems. The cause of Parkinson's is
                                                                           not fully understood, but it involves the
                                                                           loss of dopamine-producing neurons in
                                                                           the brain. Treatments, including medi-
                                                                           cations and surgical interventions, can
                                                                           help manage symptoms and improve
                                                                           quality of life for individuals with Par-
         Electroencephalogram (EEG)                                        blood supply to part of the brain is inter-
                                                                           kinson's disease.
                                                                              Stroke: A stroke occurs when the
                                                                           rupted or reduced, depriving brain tissue
                                                                           of oxygen and nutrients. There are two
                                                                           main types of stroke: ischemic stroke,
                                                                           caused by a blood clot, and hemorrhagic
                                                                           stroke, caused by a ruptured blood ves-


           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             sel. Symptoms of stroke can include   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[sudden weakness or numbness, con-
                                                                           fusion, difficulty speaking or under-
                                                                           standing speech, and loss of balance or
                                                                           coordination. Immediate medical atten-
                                                                           tion is crucial to minimize brain damage
                                                                           and improve outcomes.
                                                                              Epilepsy: Epilepsy is a neurological
                                                                           disorder characterized by recurrent sei-
                                                                           zures. Seizures are sudden bursts of
                                                                           electrical activity in the brain that can
                                                                           cause a variety of symptoms, including
                                                                           convulsions, loss of consciousness, and
                                                                           abnormal sensations. Epilepsy can result
                                                                           from genetic factors, brain injury, infec-
         Human brain anatomy                                               Treatment typically involves antiepilep-
                                                                           tions, or other underlying conditions.
                                                                           tic medications, lifestyle modifications,
                                                                           and, in some cases, surgical interven-
                                                                           tions.
                                                                              Multiple Sclerosis (MS): Multiple
                                                                           sclerosis is an autoimmune disease that
                                                                           affects the central nervous system. It oc-
                                                                           curs when the immune system attacks
                                                                           the protective covering of nerve fibers,
                                                                           leading to communication problems be-
                                                                           tween the brain and the rest of the body.
                                                                           Symptoms of MS can vary widely but
                                                                           may include fatigue, difficulty walking,
                                                                           numbness or tingling, muscle weakness,
                                                                           and problems with coordination and bal-
                                                                           ance. There is no cure for MS, but treat-
                                                                           ments are available to manage symp-
                                                                           toms and slow disease progression.

                                                                           Advances in neurological research
         Virtual reality therapy                                           have led to significant improvements in
                                                                              Advances in neurological research
                                                                           the diagnosis, treatment, and manage-
                                                                           ment of neurological disorders. Techno-
                                                                           logical innovations, such as neuroimag-
                                                                           ing techniques (MRI, CT scans, PET
                                                                           scans), have revolutionized the field by
                                                                           allowing for more accurate and early
                                                                           diagnosis of conditions. Additionally,
                                                                           advancements in genetics and molecular
                                                                           biology have provided insights into the
                                                                           underlying mechanisms of various neu-
                                                                           rological disorders, paving the way for
                                                                           the development of targeted therapies.
                                                                              In recent years, there has been grow-
                                                                           ing interest in neuroplasticity—the
                                                                           brain's ability to reorganize itself by
                                                                           forming new neural connections. This
                                                                           has important implications for rehabili-
         Virtual reality used in therapy                                   niques such as cognitive training,
                                                                           tation and recovery following brain in-
                                                                           juries or neurological diseases. Tech-
                                                                           physical therapy, and neurostimulation
                                                                           are being explored to harness the brain's
                                                                           plasticity and improve outcomes for in-
                                                                           dividuals with neurological conditions.



           10                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Promoting brain health
             Promoting brain health involves
           adopting a holistic approach that encom-
           passes lifestyle modifications, preven-
           tive measures, and early intervention.
           Here are some key strategies for main-
           taining brain health:
             Healthy diet: A balanced diet rich in
           fruits, vegetables, whole grains, lean
           proteins, and healthy fats can support
           brain health. Certain nutrients, such as
           omega-3 fatty acids, antioxidants, and
           vitamins, have been shown to have neu-
           roprotective properties.
             Regular exercise: Physical activity
           has numerous benefits for the brain, in-                                                        Physical exercise is beneficial
           cluding improving cognitive function,
           reducing the risk of neurological dis-
           orders, and promoting neuroplasticity.
           Aim for at least 150 minutes of mod-
           erate-intensity aerobic exercise per
           week, along with muscle-strengthening
           activities.
             Mental stimulation: Engaging in in-
           tellectually stimulating activities, such
           as reading, puzzles, and learning new
           skills, can help keep the brain sharp and
           may reduce the risk of cognitive decline.
             Adequate sleep: Sleep is essential
           for brain health, as it allows the brain to
           rest, repair, and consolidate memories.
           Aim for 7-9 hours of quality sleep per
           night.
             Stress management: Chronic stress
           can have detrimental effects on the
           brain. Practice stress-reducing tech-
           niques, such as mindfulness, meditation,
           and relaxation exercises, to promote                                                            Mindfulness and meditation
           mental well-being.
             Social engagement: Staying socially
           active and maintaining strong social
           connections can have positive effects on
                                                                           brain health. Participate in social activ-
                                                                           ities, join clubs or groups, and stay con-
                                                                           nected with family and friends.
                                                                              World Brain Day serves as a crucial
                                                                           reminder of the importance of brain
                                                                           health and the need for continued re-
                                                                           search, education, and advocacy in the
                                                                           field of neurology. By raising awareness
                                                                           about neurological disorders and pro-
                                                                           moting strategies for maintaining brain
                                                                           health, we can work towards a future
                                                                           where individuals can lead healthier,
                                                                           more fulfilling lives. On this World
                                                                           Brain Day, let us all commit to taking
                                                                           proactive steps to protect our brain
         Eating nutritious food                                            neurological conditions. Together, we
                                                                           health and support those affected by
                                                                           can make a significant impact in the
                                                                           fight against neurological disorders and
                                                                           improve the quality of life for millions


           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             around the world. ■         11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT











































           STRIPES OF SURVIVAL




           Collaborative Efforts to






           Protect Tigers







           By Aarav Sharma



             nternational Tiger Day, also known   family, are iconic species that play a   ticular focus on India, and the collective
             as Global Tiger Day, is celebrated   critical role in maintaining the balance   efforts needed to ensure their survival.
           Iannually on July 29th to raise aware-  of ecosystems. However, they face nu-  The plight of tigers: Tigers once
           ness about tiger conservation. Estab-  merous threats, including habitat loss,   roamed across Asia, from Turkey in the
           lished in 2010 at the Saint Petersburg   poaching, and human-wildlife conflict.   west to the eastern coast of Russia. Ho-
           Tiger Summit, this day highlights the   This article delves into the significance   wever, over the past century, their
           need to protect tigers and their habitats.   of International Tiger Day, the current   numbers have dwindled dramatically. As
           Tigers, the largest members of the cat   status of tigers worldwide, with a par-  of the latest estimates, there are fewer

           12                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Subspecies of

            tigers and their

            conservation

            status


              Tigers, the largest cats in the
            world, are classified into several sub-
            species, each with its own geographic
            range and conservation status. As of
            the knowledge cutoff date in De-
            cember 2023, tigers are categorized
            into the following subspecies, with                                                            A tiger cub playing with its mother
            some being critically endangered:
              1. Bengal Tiger (Panthera tigris
            tigris) Range: Found in India, Ban-
            gladesh, Nepal, Bhutan, and Myan-
            mar, Population: Approximately 2,967
            (as of 2020), Conservation Status: En-  than 4,000 tigers left in the wild, a stark   bones, and other body parts, which are
            dangered                       contrast to the 100,000 that roamed a   highly valued in traditional medicine
              2. Siberian Tiger (Panthera ti-  century ago. This decline is primarily   and as status symbols.
            gris altaica) Range: Primarily in the   due to human activities such as defores-
            Russian Far East, with a small   tation, poaching, and the illegal wildlife   The significance of international
            number in China and possibly North   trade. Tigers are hunted for their skin,   tiger day
            Korea. Population: Around 562 (as of
            2020), Conservation Status: Endan-
            gered
              3. Sumatran Tiger (Panthera ti-
            gris sumatrae) Range: Found only on
            the Indonesian island of Sumatra,
            Population: Approximately 400 (as of
            2021) Conservation Status: Critically
            Endangered
              4. Malayan Tiger (Panthera ti-
            gris jacksoni) Range: Peninsular Ma-
            laysia and possibly parts of southern
            Thailand. Population: Around 180-
            260 (as of 2021) Conservation Status:
            Critically Endangered
              5. South China Tiger (Panthera
            tigris amoyensis) Range: Historically
            in China but is considered extinct in
            the wild, Population: Possibly a few
            individuals in captivity, Conservation
            Status: Critically Endangered (pos-
            sibly extinct in the wild)
              6. Indochinese Tiger (Panthera
            tigris corbetti) Range: Thailand,                                                              Close-up shots highlighting the tiger's distinctive stripes and intense gaze
            Myanmar, Cambodia, Vietnam, and
            Laos, Population: Approximately
            250-375 (as of 2020), Conservation
            Status: Endangered
              7. Javan Tiger (Panthera tigris
            sondaica), Status: Extinct (last seen
            in the 1970s)
              8. Caspian Tiger (Panthera tigris
            virgata) Status: Extinct (last seen in
            the 1950s)


           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[International Tiger Day serves as a
           reminder of the urgent need to protect
           these majestic animals. It aims to:
             Raise awareness: Educate the public
           about the critical threats facing tigers
           and the need for conservation efforts.
             Promote conservation: Encourage
           governments, NGOs, and individuals to
           support and participate in conservation
           activities.
             Celebrate successes: Highlight suc-
           cessful conservation stories and the pos-                                                       Special Tiger Protection Force (STPF) in action
           itive impact of collaborative efforts.
             Foster global collaboration: Pro-
           mote international cooperation to tackle
           the cross-border issues related to tiger
           conservation.
             Tigers in India: A case study
             India is home to approximately 70%
           of the world’s wild tiger population. The
           country’s commitment to tiger conserva-
           tion is exemplified by Project Tiger,
           launched in 1973. This initiative aims to
           ensure a viable population of Bengal
           tigers in their natural habitats, protect
           them from extinction, and preserve areas
           of biological importance.

           Project tiger and its impact
             Project Tiger began with nine tiger
           reserves covering an area of 18,278
           square kilometers. Today, there are 50
           tiger reserves spread over 72,749 square
           kilometers. The project focuses on hab-
           itat management, anti-poaching meas-                                                            Poaching of tigers in India
           ures, and fostering a sense of com-
           munity participation.

           Key achievements:
             Population recovery: According to   Enhanced protection: The creation   Community involvement: Initia-
           the All India Tiger Estimation Report   of the Special Tiger Protection Force   tives like the Eco-Development Com-
           2018, India’s tiger population increased   (STPF) and the use of technology such   mittees (EDCs) involve local com-
           from 2,226 in 2014 to 2,967 in 2018,   as camera traps and satellite imaging   munities in conservation activities,
           demonstrating a positive growth trend.   have strengthened anti-poaching efforts.   providing them with alternative liveli-
                                                                           hoods to reduce their dependence on for-
                                                                           est resources.

                                                                           Challenges in tiger conservation
                                                                              Despite the successes, several chal-
                                                                           lenges persist:
                                                                              Habitat fragmentation: Rapid ur-
                                                                           banization and infrastructure devel-
                                                                           opment have led to habitat fragmenta-
                                                                           tion, isolating tiger populations and
                                                                           reducing genetic diversity.
                                                                              Human-wildlife conflict: As human
                                                                           populations expand, the likelihood of
                                                                           encounters between tigers and people in-
         Tiger bone claws                                                  tory killings.
                                                                           creases, leading to conflict and retalia-
                                                                              Illegal trade: The demand for tiger
                                                                           parts in traditional medicine and as tro-
                                                                           phies fuels poaching, despite strict laws

           14                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[and international agreements like CITES
           (the Convention on International Trade
           in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna
           and Flora).

           The role of technology in
           conservation
             Modern technology plays a crucial
           role in tiger conservation. Innovations
           such as camera traps, drones, and satel-
           lite telemetry provide valuable data on
           tiger movements, population dynamics,
           and habitat use. These technologies en-
           able more effective patrolling, monitor-                                                        Smuggling tigers
           ing, and management of tiger reserves.

           Global efforts and cooperation
             Tiger conservation requires global   wild tiger population by 2022 through a   Eco-tourism, when managed respon-
           cooperation, as tigers do not recognize   range of measures including habitat   sibly, can be a powerful tool for tiger
           national boundaries. The Global Tiger   preservation, anti-poaching efforts, and   conservation. By generating revenue for
           Recovery Program (GTRP), initiated   reducing demand for tiger products.   local communities and conservation ef-
           during the 2010 Tiger Summit, is a no-                          forts, sustainable tourism creates eco-
           table example of international collabo-  The importance of sustainable   nomic incentives to protect tigers and
           ration. The GTRP aims to double the   tourism                   their habitats. It also raises awareness
                                                                           among visitors about the importance of
                                                                           conservation.

                                                                           Education and advocacy
                                                                              Education and advocacy are vital
                                                                           components of tiger conservation.
                                                                           Awareness campaigns, school programs,
                                                                           and media coverage help to inform the
                                                                           public about the plight of tigers and the
                                                                           need for conservation efforts. Organiza-
                                                                           tions like the World Wildlife Fund
         Technology in conservation                                        servation Authority (NTCA) play crucial
                                                                           (WWF), the Wildlife Conservation Soci-
                                                                           ety (WCS), and the National Tiger Con-

                                                                           roles in these efforts.
                                                                              International Tiger Day is a crucial
                                                                           platform for highlighting the plight of
                                                                           tigers and the need for concerted conser-
                                                                           vation efforts. The story of tiger conser-
                                                                           vation in India, marked by significant
                                                                           successes and ongoing challenges, un-
                                                                           derscores the importance of sustained
                                                                           commitment and collaboration. By lev-
                                                                           eraging technology, fostering com-
                                                                           munity involvement, and promoting
                                                                           global cooperation, we can work to-
         A Bengal tiger roaming in its natural habitat                     Day, let us renew our commitment to
                                                                           wards a future where tigers not only sur-
                                                                           vive but thrive in the wild.
                                                                              As we celebrate International Tiger
                                                                           protecting these magnificent creatures
                                                                           and ensuring that future generations can
                                                                           witness the beauty and majesty of tigers
                                                                           in their natural habitats.
                                                                              Through awareness, action, and ad-
                                                                           vocacy, we can make a significant im-
                                                                           pact on the conservation of tigers and

                                                                           sity. ■

                                                                                                       15
           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             the preservation of our planet’s biodiver-]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[INSIGHT





































           Technological Triumphs





           Broadcasting








           in the digital age






            By Staff Writer

                                                                           communication. The IBC was a private
                 ational Broadcasting Day, cele-  played a vital role in shaping India's   entity that faced numerous challenges,
                 brated annually on July 23rd,   socio-political and cultural landscape.   including financial instability, leading to
           Nholds significant importance in                                its takeover by the government in 1930.
           India. It marks the day in 1927 when the   Historical background   This transition marked the birth of All
           Indian Broadcasting Company (IBC)   The journey of broadcasting in India   India Radio (AIR), a pivotal institution in
           made the first-ever radio broadcast in   began with the establishment of the IBC in   Indian broadcasting history.
           the country. This event laid the founda-  Bombay (now Mumbai). On July 23,
           tion for a comprehensive and expansive   1927, a historic radio broadcast was made,   All India Radio, initially named the
           broadcasting network that has since   signaling the advent of a new era in   Indian State Broadcasting Service, was

           16                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[in disseminating information on health,
                                                                           agriculture, education, and other critical
                                                                           sectors, reaching millions of households
                                                                           across the country.
                                                                                Broadcasting has played an instru-
                                                                           Role of broadcasting in nation
         Akashwani Bhawan on Parliament Street, Delhi                      process. It has served as a medium for
                                                                           building
                                                                           mental role in India's nation-building

                                                                           disseminating information, promoting
                                                                           education, preserving cultural heritage,
                                                                           and fostering national integration. The
                                                                           diverse linguistic and cultural tapestry of
                                                                           India necessitated a broadcasting ap-
                                                                           proach that could cater to various re-
                                                                           gional preferences while promoting a
                                                                           sense of unity.

                                                                           Information dissemination
                                                                              Radio and television have been piv-
                                                                           otal in spreading awareness about gov-
                                           Evolution of broadcasting in    ernment policies, developmental pro-
                                           independent India               grams, and emergency information.
                                             Post-independence, India's broadcast-  During natural disasters, such as floods,
                                           ing landscape underwent significant   earthquakes, and cyclones, broadcasters
                                           transformations. The government recog-  provide real-time updates, guiding
                                           nized the potential of radio and later tel-  people to safety and informing them
                                           evision as tools for nation-building and   about relief measures.
                                           socio-economic development. The ex-
                                           pansion of AIR continued, and the intro-  Educational initiatives
                                           duction of regional language services   Educational broadcasting has been a
                                           ensured that diverse linguistic and cul-  cornerstone of India's broadcasting
           formally inaugurated on June 8, 1936.   tural groups were catered to.   strategy. Programs aimed at literacy, vo-
           AIR aimed to serve the information,   The introduction of television in   cational training, and adult education
           education, and entertainment needs of   India in 1959 marked another milestone.   have empowered millions. Initiatives
           the Indian populace. Over the years, it   Initially limited to educational broad-  like 'Gyan Darshan' and 'Swayam
           expanded its reach, covering even the   casts, television's role expanded rapidly.   Prabha' channels have made educational
           remotest corners of the country. AIR   The establishment of Doordarshan as a   content accessible to students across the
           played a crucial role during India's   national broadcaster in 1976 further so-  country, bridging the gap between urban
           struggle for independence, providing a   lidified the government's commitment to   and rural education.
           platform for nationalist leaders to reach   leveraging broadcasting for devel-
           the masses and propagate their message.   opment. Doordarshan played a vital role   Cultural preservation











         A man working at an old radio station                                                             Broadcasting tower















           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[parts of the country are aware of each
                                                                           other's cultural practices and issues, pro-
                                                                           moting a sense of empathy and solidar-
                                                                           ity.

                                                                           Technological advancements and
                                                                           the digital age
                                                                              The advent of the digital age has rev-
                                                                           olutionized the broadcasting industry in
                                                                           India. The transition from analog to dig-
                                                                           ital broadcasting has improved the qual-
                                                                           ity of content and expanded the range of
         Vintage radio                                                     teners. The proliferation of satellite tele-
                                                                           services available to viewers and lis-
                                                                           vision, FM radio, and online streaming
                                                                           platforms has democratized access to in-
                                                                           formation and entertainment.

                                                                           Satellite television
                                                                              The introduction of satellite televi-
                                                                           sion in the 1990s transformed the Indian
                                                                           broadcasting landscape. Private players
                                                                           entered the market, offering a plethora
         An old studio at Akashvani Bhawan                                 ronment led to improved content quality
                                                                           of channels catering to diverse tastes
                                                                           and preferences. This competitive envi-

                                                                           and variety, benefiting consumers across
                                                                           the country.

                                                                           FM radio
                                                                              The liberalization of FM radio in the

                                                                           the radio industry. Private FM stations
                                                                           mushroomed in urban and semi-urban
                                                                           areas, offering localized content, music,
             India's rich cultural heritage finds a                        early 2000s gave a significant boost to
           prominent place in its broadcasting   National integration      and interactive shows. FM radio's pop-
           content. AIR and Doordarshan have   Broadcasting has played a crucial   ularity soared, especially among the
           been instrumental in promoting classical   role in promoting national integration.   youth, making it a vital medium for ad-
           music, dance, theatre, and folk tradi-  Programs that highlight the achieve-  vertisers and marketers.
           tions. Special programs dedicated to fes-  ments and contributions of various states
           tivals, regional customs, and historical   and communities help in breaking down   Online streaming
           events celebrate the nation's cultural di-  regional prejudices and fostering a sense   The rise of the internet and mobile
           versity, fostering a sense of pride and   of unity. The national broadcaster's   technology has ushered in a new era of
           identity among citizens.        reach ensures that people from different   broadcasting. Online streaming plat-










         Classical music recording in a studio















           18                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[forms, podcasts, and social media chan-
           nels have gained immense popularity,
           especially among the younger demo-
           graphic. These platforms offer on-de-
           mand content, personalized recommen-
           dations, and interactive features,
           redefining the way people consume
           media.

           Challenges and future prospects
             While the broadcasting industry in                                                            Satellite dishes for receiving TV programs
           India has made significant strides, it
           faces several challenges in the digital
           age. Issues such as digital divide,
           content regulation, and competition
           from global platforms require careful
           consideration.

           Digital divide                  this digital divide is crucial to ensure   The proliferation of content on digi-
             Despite the rapid expansion of digital   that the benefits of modern broadcasting   tal platforms has raised concerns about
           infrastructure, a significant portion of   reach all sections of society.   quality, accuracy, and appropriateness.
           the Indian population still lacks access                        Striking a balance between freedom of
           to reliable internet services. Bridging   Content regulation    expression and content regulation is es-
                                                                           sential to maintain the integrity of
                                                                           broadcasting.

                                                                           Competition from global platforms
                                                                              Global streaming giants like Netflix,
                                                                           Amazon Prime Video, and YouTube
                                                                           pose a formidable challenge to tradi-
                                                                           tional broadcasters. To stay relevant, In-
                                                                           dian broadcasters need to innovate, in-
                                                                           vest in original content, and leverage
                                                                           their deep understanding of local prefer-
                                                                           ences.

                                                                           Future prospects
         Indian OTT platforms                                              lies in embracing technological ad-
                                                                              The future of broadcasting in India
                                                                           vancements while staying true to the
                                                                           core values of information dissemi-
                                                                           nation, education, and cultural preserva-
                                                                           tion. The convergence of traditional and
                                                                           digital media offers exciting possibilities
                                                                           for reaching wider audiences and cre-
                                                                           ating engaging content.
                                                                              National Broadcasting Day serves as
                                                                           a reminder of the transformative power
                                                                           of broadcasting in India. From its hum-
                                                                           ble beginnings in 1927 to the dynamic
                                                                           digital age, broadcasting has played a
                                                                           pivotal role in shaping the nation's
                                                                           socio-political and cultural landscape.
                                                                           As India marches towards a digital fu-
                                                                           ture, the broadcasting industry must
                                                                           continue to innovate, adapt, and uphold
                                                                           its responsibility as a vital pillar of de-
         Streaming platforms                                               formed and inclusive broadcasting, India
                                                                           mocracy and development. Through in-
                                                                           can harness the full potential of its di-
                                                                           verse and vibrant population, fostering a
                                                                           more informed, educated, and united na-


           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             tion. ■                     19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE















































           CHESS



           A global game of







           Kings and Queens








           By Karan Malhotra



                  orld Chess Day, celebrated   lennium. The celebration of World   back to India around the 6th century
                  annually on July 20th, marks   Chess Day is an homage to this timeless   AD, where it was known as "chatu-
           Wa global recognition of chess,   game, its impact on education, its cul-  ranga." The game gradually spread to
           a game that transcends boundaries and   tural significance, and its role in foster-  Persia, where it became known as "sha-
           cultures, embodying the art of strategy   ing global unity and mental acuity.   tranj," and eventually made its way to
           and intellectual prowess. Chess, often                          Europe through Islamic expansion in
           referred to as the "game of kings," has a   Historical background   Spain. By the 15th century, the game
           rich history that dates back over a mil-  The origins of chess can be traced   had evolved into the modern form we

           20                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[recognize today.
             The establishment of World Chess
           Day was formalized by the United Na-
           tions General Assembly on December
           12, 2019. The resolution, co-sponsored
           by over 50 countries, highlights the im-
           portance of chess in promoting fairness,
           inclusion, and mutual respect. The date,
           July 20th, was chosen to honor the Inter-
           national Chess Federation (FIDE),                                                               Anya Taylor-Joy in ‘The Queen's Gambit’ Netflix series
           which was founded on this day in 1924
           in Paris.

           The game of strategy and
           intelligence
             Chess is a two-player strategy board
           game played on an 8x8 grid, with each
           player starting with 16 pieces: one king,
           one queen, two rooks, two knights, two
           bishops, and eight pawns. The objective   players to think several moves ahead,   chess has made it a subject of interest
           is to checkmate the opponent's king,   anticipate their opponent's strategy, and   not only for casual players but also for
           meaning it is under attack and has no   adapt to changing circumstances on the   scholars and scientists. Studies have
           legal move to escape capture. The game   board.                 shown that playing chess can improve
           is renowned for its complexity, requiring   The depth of strategy involved in   cognitive abilities such as problem-solv-
                                                                           ing, memory, and critical thinking.
                                                                           Moreover, chess is used in educational
                                                                           settings around the world to enhance
                                                                           students' concentration and strategic
                                                                           planning skills.

                                                                           Chess in education
                                                                              The educational benefits of chess are
                                                                           well-documented. In many countries,
                                                                           chess is integrated into school curricula
                                                                           to aid in the development of young
                                                                           minds. The game helps children improve
                                                                           their mathematical and verbal skills, en-
                                                                           hances their ability to concentrate, and
                                                                           fosters logical and analytical thinking.
         Women's Chess                                                     mandatory subject in primary schools.
                                                                              In Armenia, for instance, chess is a
                                                                           The country has seen remarkable suc-
                                                                           cess in international chess competitions,
                                                                           reflecting the positive impact of this pol-
                                                                           icy. Similarly, countries like Russia,
                                                                           India, and the United States have robust
                                                                           programs to promote chess among stu-
                                                                           dents, recognizing its potential to culti-
                                                                           vate future leaders and innovators.

                                                                           Cultural significance
                                                                              Chess has a profound cultural impact,
                                                                           inspiring art, literature, and cinema. The
                                                                           game has been a central theme in nu-
                                                                           merous works of fiction, from Vladimir
                                                                           Nabokov's "The Defense" to Walter Te-
                                                                           vis's "The Queen's Gambit," which was
         Egyptian Chess Set                                                series. These cultural representations un-
                                                                           adapted into a highly acclaimed Netflix
                                                                           derscore the allure of chess and its meta-
                                                                           phorical significance in the struggle for
                                                                           mental supremacy and personal redemp-


           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                             tion.                       21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[In many cultures, chess is more than
                                                                           just a game; it is a symbol of intellect
                                                                           and sophistication. Historically, it was
                                                                           played by royalty and nobility as a dem-
                                                                           onstration of strategic acumen. Today, it
                                                                           continues to be a popular pastime for
                                                                           people of all ages and backgrounds,
                                                                           bringing together individuals from di-
                                                                           verse walks of life.
                                                                                World Chess Day serves as a re-
                                                                           Global unity and cooperation
         Women’s Chess Championship                                        minder of the unifying power of chess.

                                                                           The game is played and celebrated in
                                                                           nearly every country, bridging linguistic,
                                                                           cultural, and political divides. Inter-
                                                                           national tournaments and matches, such
                                                                           as the Chess Olympiad and the World
                                                                           Chess Championship, draw participants
                                                                           and spectators from all over the globe,
                                                                           fostering a sense of global community.
                                                                              The International Chess Federation
                                                                           (FIDE) plays a pivotal role in promoting
                                                                           chess worldwide. Founded in 1924,
                                                                           FIDE organizes international competi-
                                                                           tions, sets the rules and standards for the
                                                                           game, and works to make chess acces-
                                                                           sible to everyone. On World Chess Day,
                                                                           FIDE and various national chess feder-
                                                                           ations host events, tournaments, and
                                                                           educational programs to encourage more
                                                                           people to take up the game.
         Chess is popular among women                                      olutionized the way chess is played and

                                                                           Chess and technology
                                                                              The advent of technology has rev-

                                                                           studied. Online platforms like
                                                                           Chess.com and Lichess have made it
                                                                           possible for millions of people to play
                                                                           chess anytime, anywhere, and against
                                                                           opponents from around the world. These
                                                                           platforms offer tutorials, puzzles, and
                                                                           analysis tools that help players improve
                                                                           their skills.
                                                                              Artificial Intelligence (AI) has also
                                                                           had a significant impact on chess. The
                                                                           development of chess engines like
                                                                           Stockfish and AlphaZero has pushed the
                                                                           boundaries of the game, providing new
                                                                           insights into strategy and tactics. These
                                                                           engines are used by top players to ana-
                                                                           lyze their games and prepare for
                                                                           matches, leading to an overall increase
                                                                           in the level of play at the highest levels.

                                                                           World chess day celebrations
                                                                              On World Chess Day, a wide array of
                                                                           events and activities take place around
         Indian Chaturanga                                                 community centers organize tourna-
                                                                           the globe. Chess clubs, schools, and
                                                                           ments, exhibitions, and workshops to
                                                                           celebrate the day. These events are de-
                                                                           signed to promote the game, encourage

           22                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Iconic chess player Anatoly Karpov  Bobby Fischer














                                                                           new players to learn, and provide a plat-
                                                                           form for seasoned players to showcase
                                                                           their skills.
                                                                              In recent years, online celebrations
                                                                           have become increasingly popular. Vir-
                                                                           tual tournaments and live-streamed
         Teacher instructing students on chess strategy                    grandmasters often host special events,
                                                                           matches attract thousands of participants
                                                                           and viewers. Chess influencers and
                                                                           such as simultaneous exhibitions and
                                                                           Q&A sessions, to engage with fans and
                                                                           promote the game.

                                                                           The future of chess
                                                                              As we look to the future, the popular-
                                                                           ity of chess shows no signs of waning.
                                                                           The game's timeless appeal, combined
                                                                           with modern technological advance-
                                                                           ments, ensures that chess will continue
                                                                           to captivate and challenge new genera-
                                                                           tions of players. Efforts to integrate
                                                                           chess into educational systems and pro-
                                                                           mote it in underserved communities are
                                                                           vital to ensuring that the game remains
                                                                           inclusive and accessible.
                                                                              Moreover, the global chess com-
                                                                           munity is continually evolving, with
                                                                           more women and young players rising
                                                                           to prominence. Initiatives like the FIDE
                                                                           Women's World Championship and the
                                                                           World Junior Chess Championship high-
                                                                           light the diverse talent within the chess
                                                                           world and inspire future champions.
                                                                              World Chess Day is a celebration of a
                                                                           game that has stood the test of time, cap-
                                                                           tivating minds and fostering connections
                                                                           across the globe. As we commemorate
                                                                           this day, we honor the rich history of
                                                                           chess, its educational and cultural signif-
                                                                           icance, and its role in promoting unity
                                                                           and intellectual growth. Whether you are
                                                                           a seasoned grandmaster or a novice
         Chess Olympiad                                                    and discovery. So, on July 20th, let's
                                                                           player, chess offers a world of challenge
                                                                           celebrate the game of kings and queens,
                                                                           and the countless ways it enriches our
                                                                           lives. ■

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[TRAVEL







































           Switzerland




           The ultimate






           Nature’s Paradise








           By Ishita Desai

                 estled in the heart of Europe,   an adventure enthusiast, a history buff,   vide a breathtaking backdrop of snow-
                 Switzerland is a land of stun-  or someone seeking tranquility, Switzer-  capped peaks, lush valleys, and crystal-
           Nning natural beauty, world-class   land has something to captivate your   clear lakes.
           cities, and rich cultural heritage. From   heart and soul.
           the majestic Alps to the serene lakes,                          The Swiss Alps
           from the bustling streets of Zurich to the   The splendor of Swiss nature   The Swiss Alps are an adventurer's
           historic charm of Lucerne, Switzerland   Switzerland’s landscapes are a testa-  paradise. In winter, they transform into a
           offers a plethora of experiences for   ment to the grandeur of nature. The   wonderland for skiing, snowboarding,
           every kind of traveler. Whether you are   Alps, stretching across the country, pro-  and other winter sports. Famous resorts

           24                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[A serene view of a lake in Switzerland
















         Swiss landscape with mountains, lakes, and valleys









                                                                                                           Lake Lucerne, Switzerland











           like Zermatt, St. Moritz, and Davos   easy access to high-altitude viewpoints   lages, rolling hills, and dramatic peaks.
           offer world-class facilities and stunning   and hiking trails.   The historic city of Lucerne, with its
           views. Zermatt, located at the base of                          well-preserved medieval architecture, is
           the iconic Matterhorn, is particularly re-  The lakes of Switzerland   a highlight. Don't miss the Chapel
           nowned for its car-free village at-  Switzerland’s lakes are serene and   Bridge, a symbol of the city, and the
           mosphere and extensive ski terrain.   inviting. Lake Geneva, shared with   poignant Lion Monument.
             In summer, the Alps are equally en-  France, is one of the largest in Europe.   Lake Zurich, in the heart of Switzer-
           chanting. Hiking trails, such as the   The city of Geneva, situated at its western   land, combines urban sophistication
           Haute Route and the Eiger Trail, lead   tip, is known for its cosmopolitan vibe,   with natural beauty. The city of Zurich,
           through picturesque landscapes of alpine   historical sites, and the iconic Jet d'Eau   a global financial hub, offers a vibrant
           meadows, glacial lakes, and rugged   fountain. Montreux, on the lake's eastern   arts scene, excellent shopping, and
           peaks. The Jungfrau Region, with its   shore, is famous for its annual jazz festival   lively nightlife. The lake itself is perfect
           Eiger, Mönch, and Jungfrau mountains,   and the stunning Chillon Castle.   for swimming, sailing, and picnicking
           offers a spectacular setting for outdoor   Lake Lucerne, surrounded by moun-  along its shores.
           activities. Cable cars and cogwheel   tains, offers a mix of natural beauty and
           trains, like the one to Jungfraujoch –   cultural experiences. A boat ride on its   Cultural and historical treasures
           known as the "Top of Europe" – provide   waters provides views of charming vil-  Switzerland's cities and towns are

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[rich in cultural heritage and history, re-  aters. The Kunsthaus Zurich houses an
           flecting the country’s diverse influences   impressive collection of modern and
           and storied past.               contemporary art, while the Swiss Na-
                                           tional Museum offers insights into the
           Zurich: A blend of modernity and   country’s history and culture.
           tradition                         The Bahnhofstrasse, one of the
             Zurich, the largest city in Switzer-  world’s most exclusive shopping streets,
           land, is a dynamic blend of old and new.   is lined with luxury boutiques, depart-
           The medieval Old Town (Altstadt) is a   ment stores, and cafés. For a taste of
           maze of narrow, winding streets, historic   local cuisine, explore Zurich’s tradi-
           buildings, and hidden courtyards. Land-  tional restaurants and try dishes like
           marks like the Grossmünster and Frau-  Zürcher Geschnetzeltes (sliced veal in
           münster churches showcase impressive   cream sauce) and fondue.
           architecture and art, including stained
           glass windows by Marc Chagall in the   Lucerne: The heart of Swiss
           latter.                         heritage
             Modern Zurich is a hub of finance,   Lucerne, located at the foot of Mount
           technology, and education, home to the   Pilatus, is a city of postcard-perfect
           Swiss Stock Exchange and ETH Zurich,   beauty. Its well-preserved medieval ar-                  Modern tram on a city street
           one of the world’s leading universities.   chitecture, picturesque lakeside setting,
           The city’s cultural scene is vibrant, with   and vibrant cultural scene make it a
           numerous museums, galleries, and the-  must-visit destination. The Chapel
                                                                           Bridge, adorned with 17th-century
                                                                           paintings, spans the Reuss River and is
                                                                           one of the oldest wooden bridges in Eu-
                                                                           rope. Nearby, the Water Tower is a sym-
                                                                           bol of the city.
                                                                              The Lion Monument, carved into a
                                                                           sandstone rock face, commemorates
                                                                           Swiss Guards who died during the
                                                                           French Revolution. The Swiss Transport
                                                                           Museum offers interactive exhibits on
                                                                           the history of transportation, making it a
                                                                           great attraction for families.
                                                                              Lucerne’s location makes it an excel-
         Bahnhofstrasse, Zürich                                            mountains. The Golden Round Trip,
                                                                           lent base for exploring the surrounding
                                                                           combining a boat ride on Lake Lucerne,
                                                                           a cogwheel train to Mount Pilatus, and a
                                                                           cable car descent, offers a spectacular
                                                                           way to experience the region’s natural
                                                                           beauty.

                                                                           Geneva: A city of diplomacy and
                                                                           culture
                                                                              Geneva, often called the “Capital of
                                                                           Peace,” is home to numerous inter-
                                                                           national organizations, including the
                                                                           United Nations and the Red Cross. Its
                                                                           international flavor is reflected in its di-
                                                                           verse population and cultural offerings.
                                                                              The city’s old town, with its cobble-
         Grossmünster Cathedral Church                                     dral, where John Calvin preached, offers
                                                                           stone streets and historic buildings, is a
                                                                           delight to explore. The St. Pierre Cathe-
                                                                           panoramic views from its towers. The
                                                                           Reformation Wall, a monument to the
                                                                           leaders of the Protestant Reformation, is
                                                                           located in the Parc des Bastions.
                                                                              Geneva’s museums cater to a variety
                                                                           of interests. The International Red Cross
                                                                           and Red Crescent Museum provides in-

           26                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Getting around: Switzerland’s effi-
                                                                           cient public transportation system makes
                                                                           it easy to explore the country. The Swiss
                                                                           Travel Pass offers unlimited travel on
                                                                           trains, buses, and boats, as well as free
                                                                           entry to many museums and attractions.
                                                                           The scenic trains, such as the Glacier
                                                                           Express and Bernina Express, provide
                                                                           breathtaking views of the landscapes.

                                                                           Language
         The St. Pierre Cathedral                                          guages: German, French, Italian, and
                                                                              Switzerland has four official lan-
                                                                           Romansh. While German is the most
                                                                           widely spoken, English is commonly
                                                                           understood in tourist areas, making
                                                                           communication relatively easy.


                                                                              Switzerland uses the Swiss Franc
           sights into humanitarian efforts world-  for its quality and craftsmanship. The   Currency
           wide, while the Patek Philippe Museum   country’s chocolatiers, like Lindt, Toble-  (CHF). Credit cards are widely ac-
           showcases the art of watchmaking.   rone, and Sprüngli, offer a range of de-  cepted, but it’s a good idea to carry
             The city’s lakeside promenade, with   lectable treats. Visiting a chocolate fac-  some cash for smaller purchases and in
           its flower clock and views of the Jet   tory, such as Maison Cailler, provides an   more remote areas.
           d'Eau, is perfect for a leisurely stroll.   opportunity to learn about the chocolate-
           For a taste of Geneva’s culinary scene,   making process and indulge in tastings.   When to Visit
           try local specialties like fondue, raclette,                       Switzerland is a year-round destina-
           and chocolate.                  Local specialties               tion, with each season offering its own
                                             Each region of Switzerland has its   charm. Winter is perfect for skiing and
           Culinary delights               own culinary specialties. In the German-  snow sports, while summer is ideal for
             Swiss cuisine is a reflection of its di-  speaking regions, dishes like Rösti (a   hiking and outdoor activities. Spring and
           verse cultural influences, combining   potato pancake) and Zürcher Geschnet-  autumn are less crowded and offer mild
           German, French, and Italian traditions.   zeltes are popular. The Italian-speaking   weather, making them great times to ex-
           Cheese and chocolate are integral to   Ticino region offers Mediterranean-in-  plore the cities and countryside.
           Swiss food culture, and no visit is com-  spired cuisine, including risotto and   Switzerland is a land of enchanting
           plete without sampling these delights.   polenta. In the French-speaking areas,   beauty, rich culture, and endless adven-
                                           you’ll find dishes like Papet Vaudois   tures. Its stunning landscapes, historic
           Cheese and chocolate            (leek and potato stew) and Malakoff   cities, and culinary delights make it a
             Switzerland is famous for its cheese,   (cheese fritters).    dream destination for travelers.
           particularly varieties like Emmental,   Switzerland’s vibrant café culture is   Whether you’re seeking the thrill of
           Gruyère, and Appenzeller. Fondue, a   perfect for enjoying a leisurely coffee   the mountains, the serenity of the lakes,
           communal dish of melted cheese served   and pastry. Try a slice of Zuger Kir-  or the cultural richness of the cities,
           with bread, is a quintessential Swiss ex-  schtorte, a cherry liqueur-infused cake,   Switzerland promises an unforgettable
           perience. Raclette, another popular dish,   or a traditional Swiss pastry like a Ber-  journey.
           involves melting cheese and scraping it   liner or a Nusstorte.    Pack your bags and get ready to ex-
           over potatoes, pickles, and onions.                             plore this Alpine paradise – Switzerland
             Swiss chocolate is world-renowned   Practical travel tips     awaits! ■














         Oberhofen Castle







           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[GURU

















                                  PURNIMA











                                              SPECIAL



















                Jupiter which is also known as “Guru” or “Brihaspati” (Teacher of God)
                 carries attributes like wealth, sound health, prosperity, wisdom for its
                  wearer. It is also acknowledge to be the most auspicious planet as

                                      being teacher of the God “Devas”

           28                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[The Guru's Path


           Wisdom and                                                                                            PERSPECTIVE








           Enlightenment










                                                 s the world celebrates Guru   her husband, Sandesh Dhamne, who has
                                                 Purnima, a day dedicated to   been her guru since their marriage.
                                           Ahonoring our teachers and      "Though he sometimes gets irritated at
                                           spiritual guides, we shine a light on   my mistakes," she shares with a smile,
                                           Shraddha Dhamne, a globally recog-  "he never stops teaching me." This per-
                                           nized yoga expert whose teachings   sonal connection underscores the deep
                                           resonate with the essence of this aus-  respect and mutual growth that charac-
                                           picious occasion. Through her online   terize their relationship.
                                           sessions, Shraddha has been spread-  Another influential teacher in
                                           ing the benefits of yoga across the   Shraddha's life is Mrs. Kabita Swain,
                                           globe, enriching lives with her pro-  her Science Math teacher from CDS
                                           found wisdom and unwavering ded-  School in Nagpur. "Mrs. Swain left a
                                           ication.                        lasting impact on me," she says. "She
                                             For Shraddha, the concept of a   took me to her house after school and,
                                           Guru is beautifully encapsulated in   apart from education, taught me social
                  Shraddha Dhamne          the sacred shlok "Guru Brahma Guru   etiquettes, cooking, and other skills
                 Renowned Yoga Guru        Vishnu, Guru Devo Maheshwara    beneficial for my future life." Equally
                Pune, Maharashtra, India
                                           Guru Sakshat Parabrahma, Tasmai   significant is Mrs. Sandhya Waghmare
                                           Shri Guruve Namah." This verse,   of Pune, who motivated Shraddha to
                                           which she recites at the beginning of   start her first online yoga session and
                                           every yoga session, signifies the Guru   has been a moral pillar, always encour-
           A true Guru should never        as the embodiment of the divine   aging her to move forward.
                                                                              One of the most memorable experi-
                                           trinity—Brahma the creator, Vishnu
                     be proud of their     the sustainer, and Shiva the destroyer   ences Shraddha recounts is with Shweta,
                                                                           a student from Minnesota, USA.
                                           of ignorance. "By starting each ses-
              knowledge but should         sion with this shlok," she explains, "I   "Shweta's dedication to yoga was awe-
                                           honor the spiritual lineage and set a
                                                                           inspiring," she recalls. "Despite severe
                    share it selflessly    reverent tone for our practice. It re-  health issues, she never missed a ses-
                                           minds us that the Guru embodies the   sion. Her perseverance and passion for
                                           universal principles of creation, pres-  yoga left a significant impression on me.
                                           ervation, and transformation, guiding   I salute her dedication."
                                           us on our path to enlightenment."   Shraddha believes that certain qual-
                                             Shraddha's journey is a testament   ities make an effective and inspiring
                                           to her belief that learning is a lifelong   teacher. "Communication skills are the
                                           process with no age limit. "My par-  foundation," she emphasizes. "Through
                                           ents were my first Gurus," she re-  clear communication, a teacher can ex-
                                           flects. "They taught me humility, li-  plain any subject to all students. Listen-
                                           kening a river's humility to a Guru's.   ing is another crucial quality, as it helps
                                           A true Guru should never be proud of   a teacher understand and address stu-
                                           their knowledge but should share it   dents' needs. Lastly, being friendly with
                                           selflessly." This philosophy has pro-  students fosters a closer relationship and
                                           foundly influenced her life and teach-  a more conducive learning environ-
                                           ing methods.                    ment."
                                             A pivotal figure in her journey is   ...Continued on page 30

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  From Vedas to Classrooms








           The Guru's Legacy









                                                 uru is the most revered position   to nobel laureates and his keen improvi-
                                                 in Indian culture. From ancient   sation skills made the most complex
                                           GVedic period the acquisition of   concepts so easy to understand. When I
                                           knowledge was based on three steps,   taught Microelectronics for twenty
                                           namely, (1) Śravaṇa (listening to words   years, I always endeavored to emulate
                                           uttered by the teacher) (2) Manana (re-  Prof Khare as the ideal teacher.
                                           flection and contemplation of what is   I am forever grateful to my favorite
                                           heard) and (3) Nididhyāsana (meditation   teacher for inspiring me to always re-
                                           on the topic in question).      main curious and inquisitive while stu-
                                             Out of these three steps, the first step   dying. His style of teaching reminds me
                                           is related with the teacher. It is the   of the ancient Indian system of acqui-
                                           teacher who kindles the spark for learn-  sition of knowledge based on Indian
                                           ing, the teacher who initiates the process   epistemology. He taught a particular
                                           of learning. His instructions enable us to   subject but his teaching was primordial
                                           live a meaningful life. We know that   in shaping my learning instinct.
                                           vast knowledge is available in the world   In my opinion, a teacher should have
                                           but it is the Guru who guides us system-  creativity, patience, expertise in his
                    Guru Prabhat           atically through that knowledge. I be-  field, inclination to research and good
                   Professor Physics       lieve that teaching is such a noble pro-  communication skill. Moreover, he
                 Lectures on YouTube:      fession because the teacher imparts   should always be welcoming to the
           https://youtube.com/@guruexplain9683   knowledge which shapes the lives of his   queries put up by students.
                   Noida, NCR, India       students.                          In my teaching experience I have ob-
                                             I have forever lasting memory of my   served that every student is a gem, every
                                           favorite teacher Prof. (Retd.) S.P.Khare,   student wants to learn and excel. Stu-
                                           who taught Quantum Physics in the late   dents carefully watch teacher as a role
                “I have observed that      seventies at The Institute of Advanced   model.
                                           Studies, Meerut University, where he   The role of the Guru holds such rev-
             every student is a gem,       was Head of The Department of   erence in our Indian tradition that even
                                           Physics.                        to comprehend the concept of Con-
             every student wants to          Even an extremely abstruse subject   sciousness, as mentioned in the Kena
                                           like Quantum Physics became infinitely   Upanishad, it is the conversation be-
                     learn and excel”      interesting due to his lucid and thought   tween the erudite Guru and one pro-
                                           provoking explanations. His knack of   found student that paves the way to pro-
                                           using many examples and facts relating   found understanding. ■


                                           ...Continued from page 29       This initiative not only helps my stu-
                                             Shraddha's innovative approach to   dents but also serves as a model for
                                           teaching is evident in her 'Bindas Call'   other teachers interested in truly solving
                                           sessions, held every Saturday. "Some   their students' problems."
                                           think that a teacher-student relationship   As we celebrate Guru Purnima,
                                           is not possible online, but that's not   Shraddha Dhamne's journey reminds us
                                           true," she explains. "These sessions   of the timeless value of a Guru's guid-
                                           allow students to call me with their per-  ance. Her life and work embody the
                                           sonal problems, and I treat these inter-  principles of humility, lifelong learning,
                                           actions as parent-teacher meetings. Act-  and selfless sharing of knowledge, in-
                                           ing as a psychiatrist, I help them with   spiring countless individuals on their
                                           health-related issues or stress problems.   path to wellness and enlightenment. ■

           30                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE


          Transforming Lives




           The Magic of





           Teaching and Learning








                                                he teacher-student relationship is   upon her family repeatedly. When I last
                                                lifelong, with characters chang-  heard about her, she had moved abroad
                                           Ting but the bond enduring. A stu-  with her mother and held quite a high
                                           dent should always have an inquisitive   position in a conglomerate.
                                           heart and an inextinguishable desire to   The concept of a 'Guru' represents a
                                           learn, allowing anyone to become their   beacon of wisdom and guidance, em-
                                           teacher. This teacher could be a gar-  bodying more than just an instructor but
                                           dener filling a vessel for birds to quench   also a mentor and source of inspiration.
                                           their thirst in the intense summer heat or   In the Indian tradition, a Guru imparts
                                           a beggar on the street putting scattered   both academic knowledge and life les-
                                           litter into a dustbin.          sons, nurturing the spiritual and moral
                                             Formally speaking, as a school stu-  growth of their disciples. This holistic
                                           dent, I remember my mathematics   approach to teaching emphasizes the
                                           teacher, Mr. DVS Chauhan. What a   cultivation of well-rounded individuals,
                                           strict disciplinarian he was! But what I   capable of critical thinking and compas-
                                           loved about him was his clarity regard-  sionate action, rooted in respect, trust,
                                           ing his subject. In X Boards, he would   and a shared journey towards enlight-
                     Rashmi Rai            produce some sheets with a set of ques-  enment.
                    Senior Teacher         tions on them and confidently say, "This   An effective and inspiring teacher
               Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India   is all you need to practice to score 100%   embodies patience, creativity, and deep
                                           marks." Such was his command over the   subject knowledge, with excellent com-
                                           subject. What I learned from him was   munication skills that make complex
                                           that whatever career you choose, get in-  concepts accessible and engaging. Em-
                                           volved in it so deeply that there is no   pathy, understanding diverse learning
                                           one better than you in that realm. Make   needs, and fostering a supportive envi-
                The teacher-student        it your lifelong pursuit, and excellence   ronment are key. Lifelong learners
                                           coupled with success will kiss you on   themselves, such teachers continually
              relationship is lifelong,    your forehead one day.          expand their knowledge and methods,
                                             Today, I feel blessed to be a teacher   encouraging curiosity, critical thinking,
                     with characters       myself because I love the magic of   and a love for learning while serving as
                                           transforming lives. It’s been more than   role models of integrity and passion.
             changing but the bond         25 years now, and thousands of students   My relationships with teachers and
                                           have graduated from the school where I   students have profoundly shaped my
                             enduring      teach. For a teacher, every student is   perspective on education. Passionate
                                           precious, but a few leave an indelible   mentors instilled a love for learning and
                                           mark on your heart. Ananya Pandey is   a commitment to excellence, teaching
                                           one such student I still remember. I   that education is about character and
                                           taught her years ago. The daughter of a   wisdom development. As a teacher, em-
                                           single mother with limited means, she   pathy and adaptability are crucial, hon-
                                           had a tough life but was always full of   oring each student's individuality. This
                                           energy and positivity. She never sought   dynamic, reciprocal relationship under-
                                           sympathy or indulged in self-pity de-  scores that both teacher and student con-
                                           spite the pangs of ill fate descending   tinually learn and grow together. ■

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  Honoring Gurus










           The Transformative Power of





           Inspirational Teachers









                                                  y teachers have a long-lasting   teacher; they are a mentor, guide, and
                                                  impact on me. They assume   inspiration. They transcend the tradi-
                                           Mthe roles of educators and     tional role of simply imparting knowl-
                                           caregivers for their students. Sometimes,   edge and instead ignite a lifelong pas-
                                           they also become our friends and help   sion for learning. A Guru shapes the
                                           us with personal problems. A teacher is   mind and soul, nurturing curiosity, fos-
                                           someone who helps you become a better   tering critical thinking, and instilling
                                           and more informed person.       values that last a lifetime. They connect
                                             As a teacher, many of my students   with students on a profound level, guid-
                                           have shared that I leave a lasting im-  ing them academically, morally, and
                                           pression on them because I always moti-  spiritually.
                                           vate them to be good human beings and   An effective and inspiring teacher
                                           to always be kind and helpful to others.   embodies several key qualities. Passion
                                             Inspirational teachers do not simply   for the subject matter is paramount, as it
                                           end their work when the class ends. In   fuels the enthusiasm that can captivate
                                           fact, they live and breathe their subject.   and motivate students. Empathy and
                                           They are passionate about their teaching   genuine care for students' well-being
                  Savita Chaudhary         and genuinely care for their students.   create a supportive learning environ-
                    Senior Teacher         You never know, but the child might   ment where students feel valued and un-
                Suratgarh, Rajasthan, India  even be lucky enough to already en-  derstood. An inspiring teacher is also
                                           counter an inspirational teacher in life.   adaptable, able to tailor their approach
                                             The influence of teacher-student rela-  to meet the diverse needs of their stu-
                                           tionships extends far beyond the con-  dents. They encourage open communi-
                                           fines of the classroom. Positive connec-  cation, making themselves approachable
           The influence of teacher-       tions, laden with empathy and respect,   and creating a classroom atmosphere
                                           are not just means of interaction but are   where questions and exploration are
               student relationships       threads that intricately weave a student’s   welcomed. Integrity and patience are
                                           life narrative. The impact of these con-  crucial, as they model the behavior and
             extends far beyond the        nections on students’ attitudes is pro-  attitudes they wish to instill in their stu-
                                           found. A cascade of changes unfolds   dents.
                       confines of the     when students perceive that their   My relationships with my own
                                           teachers genuinely care for and respect   teachers and my students have pro-
                            classroom      them. Fostering positive teacher-student   foundly shaped my perspective on edu-
                                           connections creates a seismic shift in   cation and learning. The mentors who
                                           student perceptions. With this belief as a   guided me with patience and wisdom
                                           guiding star, students navigate the aca-  taught me the importance of empathy
                                           demic realm with newfound confidence,   and the lasting impact of genuine care.
                                           taking risks that lead to unparalleled   These experiences reinforced the belief
                                           heights of learning.            that education is not just about academic
                                             The essence of a guru and the art of   achievement but also about personal
                                           teaching: A Guru is more than just a   growth and development. ■

           32                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE




           Qualities of an






           Inspiring Teacher












           A Beacon of Light



                                                   Guru is a teacher or a leader   life, and I will never forget his contrib-
                                                 with knowledge and expertise,   ution to molding my career. On Guru
                                           Alike a spiritual guide who molds   Purnima day, I pay my sincere tributes
                                           destiny. The concept of a 'Guru' tran-  to the late Dr. Zuberi. May his soul rest
                                           scends the role of a mere teacher; it em-  in peace wherever he is and continue to
                                           bodies a profound guide and mentor. A   bless me.
                                           Guru possesses not only knowledge and   Specific Memory of a Guru: While
                                           expertise but also the ability to inspire   studying at Kendriya Vidyalaya, Dogra
                                           and shape lives. They illuminate paths   Lines, Kumari Shailza, my Sanskrit
                                           of learning and personal growth, nurtur-  teacher, once explained to me how a
                                           ing not just academic understanding but   good teacher finds out errors. She said,
                                           also moral and spiritual development.    "If you have ten students standing in
                                             A Guru fosters a relationship built on   front and one is standing at the back, it
                                           trust, respect, and a shared journey to-  stands out."
                                           wards enlightenment. Their impact ex-  Memorable Experience as a Teacher:
                                           tends far beyond classrooms, leaving an   I was the officer in charge of the Promo-
                                           indelible mark on the hearts and minds   tion Cadre in 1981 in Almora for Um-
             Brigadier Pabitra Chandra Roy   of their students, guiding them towards   medwar Cadre (sepoy to Lance Naik). I
            General Officer Commanding (Retd.)   a deeper understanding of themselves   met one of my sepoys after 25 years
                A Veteran of Indian Army   and the world around them.      during the unit's Silver Jubilee; he had
                Pune, Maharashtra, India     Way back in 1975, I was studying at   become a JCO. He told me, "Sir, the
                                           D. N. College, Meerut. I had taken ad-  notes you gave during the Promotion
                                           mission in this college after completing   Cadre, I preserved them and gave them
                                           my All India Higher Secondary (last   to my son who has joined the unit to
                                           batch) from Kendriya Vidyalaya, Dogra   read, since they were worth gold."
             A Guru is a teacher or a      Lines, Meerut Cantt. During this time, I   Qualities of an Inspiring Teacher:
                                           came across Dr. F. H. Zuberi, my   Knowledge, perseverance, treating
             leader with knowledge         Physics teacher. He was an excellent   every student equally, leadership, dis-
                                           teacher who taught Physics in a most   cipline, setting an example, dedication,
                 and expertise, like a     lucid manner. He encouraged all stu-  determination, and acting as a beacon of
                                           dents to clarify their doubts and pro-  light.
                  spiritual guide who      vided solutions in a calm, cool, and dig-  Effective and inspiring teachers ex-
                                           nified manner.                  hibit qualities such as deep knowledge,
                        molds destiny        I remember he was so patient; he   patience, empathy, clear communica-
                                           never lost his cool and never rebuked   tion, and the ability to motivate.
                                           any student, which helped me to grow   They create a supportive learning en-
                                           in my life. He left an indelible impres-  vironment, encourage critical thinking,
                                           sion on my overall personality. He was a   and serve as role models of integrity and
                                           true embodiment of a real Guru in my   passion for their subject. ■

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  The True Essence of Teachers







           Mentors, Guides, and






           Second Parents








                                                   Guru or teacher holds a unique   bonded exceptionally well, or witness-
                                                 place in our lives, often becom-  ing the personal growth of a student,
                                           Aing much more than just edu-   these experiences are deeply rewarding.
                                           cators. They are mentors, guides, and   They serve as reminders of the signifi-
                                           sometimes even second parents. The re-  cance of their role and the lasting in-
                                           lationship between a Guru and their stu-  fluence they have on their students.
                                           dents is built on mutual respect, admira-  I will never forget the time when my
                                           tion, and the shared journey of learning   students organized a surprise Teacher’s
                                           and growth. This bond is unlike any   Day party for me. It was a testament to
                                           other, deeply rooted in trust and the col-  the strong bond we had built over the
                                           lective pursuit of knowledge.   years. The joy and appreciation they ex-
                                             In ancient times, Gurus were consid-  pressed were overwhelming, and it was
                                           ered fountains of knowledge and wis-  a moment of pure gratitude and connec-
                                           dom. They played a pivotal role in shap-  tion. This event was not just a celebra-
                                           ing the intellectual and spiritual lives of   tion of my role as a teacher but also a re-
                                           their disciples. The role of a Guru is   flection of the mutual respect and
                                           timeless, transcending the boundaries of   admiration we had for each other.
                    Sanya Chawla           culture and era, whether in ancient civ-  Such experiences are a reminder of
                    Senior Teacher         ilizations or the modern world, Gurus   the essence of teaching. It is not just
               Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India  continue to enlighten minds, nurture   about imparting knowledge but also
                                           spirits, and guide individuals toward a   about building relationships, fostering
                                           more fulfilling and purposeful life. Their   trust, and creating a supportive environ-
                                           teachings remain invaluable, helping us   ment where students feel valued and in-
                                           navigate the complexities of life with   spired. The impact of a Guru goes bey-
                                           clarity and confidence.         ond the classroom; it shapes the
                  The role of a Guru is      Gurus are not confined to the tradi-  students' outlook on life, instills con-
                                           tional classroom setting. They can be   fidence, and encourages them to pursue
              timeless, transcending       found in various walks of life, imparting   their dreams with determination.
                                           wisdom through their actions and words.   In conclusion, a Guru or teacher
           the boundaries of culture       They inspire us to think critically, chal-  holds an irreplaceable place in our lives.
                                           lenge our assumptions, and strive for ex-  They are beacons of knowledge, men-
                  and era, whether in      cellence in everything we do. A Guru   tors, and guides who help us navigate
                                           encourages curiosity and fosters an envi-  life's challenges. Their timeless role
              ancient civilizations or     ronment where learning is a lifelong en-  transcends cultures and eras, continu-
                                           deavor. This approach helps students be-  ously enlightening minds and nurturing
                   the modern world        come well-rounded individuals capable   spirits. The bond between a teacher and
                                           of contributing meaningfully to society.   student is a unique and powerful con-
                                             Certain moments in a teacher’s career   nection, built on mutual respect and ad-
                                           are etched in their memory forever.   miration. Moments of recognition and
                                           These moments often highlight the pro-  gratitude from students highlight the
                                           found impact they have on their stu-  profound impact teachers have, re-
                                           dents' lives. Whether it is a heartfelt   affirming the importance of their role in
                                           thank you from a student, a class that   shaping the future. ■

           34                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Enlightenment through Guidance                                                                        PERSPECTIVE



           The Profound Role of a Guru in




           Indian Tradition







                                                   hen we hear the word "Guru,"   Acharya Shri Goenka Ji, cultivates
                                                   the image of a school,   equanimity in the minds and behaviors
                                           Wteacher, and student immedi-   of practitioners. It helps in purging the
                                           ately comes to mind. This concept en-  mind of attachment and aversion, which
                                           compasses not just the worldly educa-  are the root causes of suffering. By prac-
                                           tional environment but also extends to   ticing Vipassana, individuals can experi-
                                           the spiritual and religious domains. In   ence a reduction in daily stress, achiev-
                                           Indian tradition, a Guru is not merely a   ing a state of mental calm and clarity.
                                           teacher; they are a beacon of knowledge   This mental equanimity is essential for
                                           and spirituality, guiding their disciples   living a truly religious life, free from the
                                           beyond the mundane into the realms of   shackles of sectarianism and narrow
                                           higher consciousness and self-realiza-  dogmas.
                                           tion.                              The transformative power of Vipas-
                                             In the Indian spiritual context, a Guru   sana meditation is profound. It allows
                                           is a theologian who has not only studied   practitioners to understand the universal
                                           religious texts but has deeply adopted   elements of all religions, beyond the su-
                                           and internalized their teachings. This in-  perficial differences of sects and denom-
                    Vipin Agarwal          dividual has attained a high level of pro-  inations. Through Vipassana, one can
                Trustee: Dhamma Sudha      ficiency in religious knowledge and   grasp why committing sinful acts leads
               Vipssana Centra, Hastinapur,    practices. A Guru is someone who self-  to stress and turmoil, while performing
               Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India   lessly shares this profound and accumu-  virtuous acts brings peace and tranquil-
                                           lated wisdom with seekers. This sharing   ity. This understanding arises not from
                                           is aimed at helping individuals deter-  intellectual reasoning alone but from di-
                                           mine the course of their life and the   rect experiential insight gained through
                                           journey beyond life. The role of a Guru   meditation.
                                           is akin to that of fire and light, igniting   For many, the journey of Vipassana
            The role of a Guru is akin     the fire of knowledge in the lives of   feels like a rebirth. After practicing Vi-
                                           their disciples and guiding them from
                                                                           passana, one begins to see life through a
              to that of fire and light,   darkness to light.              new lens, with a clearer understanding
                                             A true Guru serves as a guide, show-
                                                                           of ethical and moral principles. This
                    igniting the fire of   ing the path of truth to their disciples   clarity is not confined to theoretical
                                                                           knowledge but is reflected in one's ac-
                                           without creating illusions of depend-
           knowledge in the lives of       ency. They empower their disciples with   tions and interactions. The practice of
                                           the knowledge and tools needed to pro-  Vipassana thus becomes a practical tool
                   their disciples and     gress on their spiritual journey inde-  for living a life of virtue, mindfulness,
                                           pendently. One such exemplary Guru   and inner peace.
                  guiding them from        was Vishwa Vipassanacharya Shri Sa-  In conclusion, the role of a Guru in
                                           tyanarayan Goenka. Goenka Ji, in his   Indian tradition goes far beyond that of a
                    darkness to light.     humility, referred to himself as a "Ka-  conventional teacher. A Guru is a spiri-
                                           lyanmitra" (a friend in welfare) rather   tual guide, a source of wisdom, and a
                                           than a Guru. His teachings and the prac-  catalyst for personal transformation.
                                           tice of Vipassana meditation were made   Through their teachings and practices,
                                           accessible to everyone, with the doors   such as Vipassana meditation, they help
                                           always open for those seeking spiritual   individuals navigate the complexities of
                                           growth and mental equanimity.   life, achieve mental equanimity, and em-
                                             Vipassana meditation, as taught by   bark on a journey of self-realization. ■

           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                   July 16-31, 2024










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     This period brings clarity to your goals, Aries.   Social interactions will be fulfilling during this
                     Channel your energy into planning and           period. Networking can lead to new opportuni-
                     strategizing for the future. Relationships will   ties and collaborations. Creative projects will
                     benefit from your renewed focus and attention.   thrive, so let your imagination run wild. Finan-
                     Financially, unexpected gains may come your way.   cially, stay disciplined and avoid overspending.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Taurus, this is a time for creativity and innovation.   Scorpios will feel a strong drive to achieve their
                     Explore new hobbies or revisit old ones.        goals. Your determination will be your greatest
                     Professional life will be rewarding if you think   asset. Relationships might require patience and
                     outside the box. Relationships will be stable,   understanding, so communicate openly. It's a
                     offering support and encouragement.             good time to invest in long-term plans.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Communication will be key in this period. Ex-   This period is perfect for broadening your hori-
                     press your ideas clearly and listen to others.   zons. Engage in activities that stimulate your
                     Work projects will progress smoothly if you     mind and spirit. Work projects will benefit from
                     maintain a collaborative approach. Financially,   your innovative ideas. Avoid speculative invest-
                     avoid impulsive purchases.                      ments and stick to proven strategies.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Your focus will be on personal growth and self-  Focus on building strong foundations in both
                     improvement. This is a great time for learning   personal and professional life. This is a good
                     and expanding your skill set. Family matters will   time to solidify plans and strategies. Relation-
                     bring joy and satisfaction. Consider seeking ad-  ships will be supportive and nurturing. Prioritize
                     vice to manage your investments effectively.    saving and avoid unnecessary expenditures.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leos will find this period full of excitement and   Aquarius, your social life will be vibrant. Con-
                     adventure. Travel opportunities may arise, bring-  nect with new people and share your ideas. Pro-
                     ing new experiences and perspectives. Profes-   fessional life will be dynamic, with opportunities
                     sionally, your leadership skills will shine. Finan-  for growth and recognition. Health-wise, stay ac-
                     cially, be cautious and avoid unnecessary risks.   tive and maintain a balanced lifestyle.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     This is a time to focus on health and wellness.   Pisces, this is a period of introspection and re-
                     Make positive changes to your lifestyle and rou-  flection. Take time to evaluate your goals and as-
                     tine. Work matters will require attention to detail   pirations. Relationships will provide emotional
                     and perseverance. Relationships will be har-    support and understanding. Financially, be cau-
                     monious, bringing peace and contentment.        tious and avoid making hasty decisions.


           36                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | JULY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Trump assassination attempt     persists in India. In a country where mil-
             On July 14, 2024, former President   lions live in poverty, such excessive dis-
           Donald Trump survived an assassination   plays of wealth are bound to draw criti-  store essential services and evacuate
           attempt at his campaign rally in   cism and resentment from the public.   people from flooded areas.
           Pennsylvania.  The shooting left at least   This makes Anant and Radhika's   Chitra Singh, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           one attendee dead and two others injured,   wedding is a stark reminder of the grow-  India
           before the gunman, identified as 20-year-  ing divide between the haves and the
           old Thomas Matthew Crooks, was killed   have-nots.
           by Secret Service agents.         As India aspires to become a global   Gurus: Pathways to Self-
             President Joe Biden has ordered an   economic powerhouse, it must also ad-  Realization
           independent review of the security   dress the pressing issue of equitable de-  A Guru is a spiritual teacher who im-
           measures at the rally, and has called for   velopment for all its citizens.    parts wisdom, knowledge, and guidance
           calm and unity in the aftermath of the   Ravi Anand, Bhopal, Madhya Pra-  to their disciples or followers. The word
           attack.  The motive behind the shooting   desh, India           ‘Guru’ originates from Sanskrit and can
           remains unclear, but it has raised serious                      be translated as ‘dispeller of darkness.’
           questions about security lapses and the                         Gurus are highly respected figures in
           deep political divisions in the country as   Heavy monsoon wreaked havoc in   Hinduism, Buddhism, Sikhism, and
           the 2024 election approaches.  The Secret   Mumbai              other Eastern religions, as they are seen
           Service is now facing scrutiny over its   Heavy monsoon rains have wreaked   as possessing deep spiritual insight and
           handling of the rally's security.   havoc in Mumbai, causing widespread   the ability to lead others towards en-
             The shooting has raised serious   waterlogging, swelling of lakes, and   lightenment and self-realization. Their
           questions about the deep political   major traffic disruptions across the city.   role goes beyond mere teaching; they
           divisions in the country.         Several areas in Mumbai received   often serve as mentors and exemplars of
           Rajesh Sharma, New Delhi, India   over 300 mm of rainfall in just 6 hours,   spiritual values and practices.
                                           leading to inundation of roads and low-  My favorite teacher is Sanya ma’am,
                                           lying regions. Schools and educational   my English teacher. She is an amazing
           Most expensive wedding          institutes were closed due to the heavy   teacher who truly stands out. She is pas-
             The recent wedding celebrations of   downpour. Train services were sus-  sionate about literature and language,
           Anant Ambani, son of Asia's richest man   pended in parts of Mumbai and adjoin-  and her classes are always interesting
           Mukesh Ambani, have been nothing   ing areas because of waterlogging on   and fun. Sanya ma’am doesn’t just teach
           short of extravagant. Estimated to cost   tracks and stations. Over 50 flights were   us English; she also encourages us to
           over $300 million, the festivities fea-  cancelled in and out of Mumbai airport,   think deeply and be creative in how we
           tured performances by global superstars   with runway operations hit for over an   express ourselves. She is very support-
           like Rihanna, Katy Perry, and Justin   hour.                    ive and easy to talk to, which has made
           Bieber. This makes the wedding one of   The India Meteorological Depart-  a big difference for me in enjoying and
           the most expensive weddings globally.   ment (IMD) has also issued an 'orange'   understanding English better.
             While the Ambanis have every right   alert for heavy to very heavy rainfall in   The Guru is like a candle; it con-
           to celebrate their family's joyous occa-  Mumbai. The heavy monsoon showers   sumes itself to light the way for others.
           sion, the sheer scale of opulence is hard   have thrown normal life out of gear in   Sara, Class VII Student, Blossoms
           to reconcile with the stark inequality that   the city, with authorities working to re-  School, Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           JULY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>