<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 01 I JANUARY 01 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: THOMAS WOLTER










           15                               8                               24































           4-Editorial: When family travels                21-Why Sankranti is celebrated in the
           through screens                                 sky

           5-Who decides the day                           24-The many lives of Mansoor Ali Khan

           8-How the internet is redefining family         Pataudi

           11-How hypnosis is already part of ev-          27-Horoscopes
           eryday life                                     28-Letters

           15-When emotions follow rules                   31-Frame of thought

           18-Civilizations that thanked the earth












           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Boundaries Redefined
     EDITORIAL  When family travels                                                 Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           through screens                                                      Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                             or many of us, family now lives in a   Art & Culture Editor
                                             phone screen, a group chat, or a late-  Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Fnight video call that crosses time
                                        zones. A grandmother in Kochi reads bed-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        time stories to a child in Toronto. A new   Vishakha Sharma
                                        mother in Delhi finds reassurance in a What-
                                        sApp group of strangers who feel oddly fa-  Social Media Editor
                                        miliar. A young student in Berlin survives
                                        homesickness thanks to an online com-        Sushil Kumar
                                        munity that speaks the same language,
                                        cracks the same jokes and remembers the   Art & Graphics Director
                                        same festivals. On Global Family Day, it’s   Vipin Agarwal
                                        worth pausing to ask what family really
                                        means anymore.
             Traditionally, family was defined by blood, marriage, or geography. Today, it’s also   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           shaped by bandwidth. Digital platforms have quietly expanded the idea of kinship, not
           by replacing families, but by stretching their boundaries. Online communities are fill-  D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           ing emotional gaps that modern life often creates. Migration, urban isolation, single-  Editor, United News of India, New
           parent households and demanding work schedules have changed how people live.
           Technology has responded, sometimes clumsily, sometimes beautifully.   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             Virtual parenting is a good example. Parents now crowdsource advice across con-  Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           tinents. They exchange notes on sleep routines, autism support, exam stress and even   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           grief. These aren’t just message boards. They’re living networks of care. When a child   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           falls sick at midnight, someone somewhere is awake and listening. That matters more   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           than we admit.                                                    N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
             Digital support groups have also become lifelines for people who once felt invisi-  Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           ble. LGBTQ+ youth in conservative societies, caregivers of elderly parents, widows
           navigating sudden loneliness and immigrants negotiating identity find comfort in on-  SUBSCRIPTIONS
           line spaces where judgement is softer and empathy travels faster. These connections
           may begin as usernames, but they often grow into something sturdier. Trust. Belong-  Phone +91 20 40199102
           ing. A sense of being seen.
             Of course, this new kinship isn’t perfect. Screens can’t replace physical presence. A   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           hug still beats a heart emoji. Online spaces can be noisy, performative and sometimes   Baner Road,
           misleading. Not every digital bond is deep. But neither are all biological ones. Family   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           has always been complicated.                                       Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             What’s changed is choice. People today are choosing their emotional ecosystems.   Website www.revoir.in
           They’re assembling families based on shared values, shared struggles and shared time,
           even if that time is logged in different time zones. That choice can be empowering,   Legal Advisor
           especially for younger generations who are redefining identity, care and responsibility   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           on their own terms.
             As we mark Global Family Day, perhaps the point isn’t to romanticize digital life or
           mourn old definitions. It’s to acknowledge that family, like society, evolves. It adapts.   Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
           It finds new ways to hold people together. Family is no longer just where you come
           from. It’s also who shows up for you, even if they’re just a glowing rectangle away.   all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.


         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[DEEP DIVE






































           The politics of time                                            When nature was enough

                                                                              For most of human history, time was
                                                                           local and forgiving. Noon meant the sun
                                                                           was overhead. Villages kept their own
                                                                           rhythm. Farmers didn’t care if the next
                                                                           town’s midday arrived ten minutes later.
           Who decides  The Earth rotated, people adapted and
                                                                           nobody argued much about it.
                                                                              That relaxed relationship began to
           the day                                                         noon. Neither did telegraphs, shipping
                                                                           crack with speed. Trains didn’t like local
                                                                           routes, or empires stretching across con-
                                                                           tinents. When movement became faster
                                                                           than the sun’s shadow, time needed dis-
                                                                           cipline.
                                                                              That’s when clocks stopped being
           Time doesn’t just pass. It’s decided, adjusted,                 personal tools and became instruments
                                                                           of coordination and soon, of control.
           defended, and sometimes disputed. By Aarav Sharma
                                                                           Drawing invisible lines on a
                                                                           spinning planet
                  hat if the day you woke up to   and shared moments is anything but   The idea of dividing the world into
                  wasn’t purely a fact of nature,   simple. Time, as we live it, is political. It   standardized time zones sounds obvious
           Wbut a decision made in a       always has been.                today. It wasn’t always. Choosing a sin-
           meeting room, negotiated across bor-  Behind every ticking clock lies a   gle reference line from which all time
           ders, stamped with authority and quietly   long story of power, compromise,   would be measured was a deeply politi-
           enforced worldwide?             science and geopolitics. At its core is   cal act. Why one longitude and not
             We like to think of time as neutral.   Earth’s rotation, steady yet imperfect   another? Why should one country’s ob-
           The sun rises, the planet turns, shadows   and humanity’s constant attempt to tame   servatory become the world’s anchor?
           move. Simple. But the way we divide   it into something orderly enough to run   At an international gathering in the
           that turning Earth into hours, minutes   railways, markets and modern life.   late nineteenth century, delegates argued

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Who really runs

                                                                                  the world’s clock?

                                                                                There is no single authority
                                                                              that “owns” global time, yet a
                                                                              small circle of scientific bodies,
                                                                              observatories and international
                                                                              committees quietly governs it.
                                                                              These institutions coordinate
                                                                              atomic clocks; monitor Earth’s
                                                                              rotation and issue decisions that
                                                                              affect satellites, aviation, finance
                                                                              and digital networks worldwide.
                                                                              Their work is technical, but the
                                                                              implications are deeply political.
                                                                              Countries hosting major timing
                                                                              laboratories gain strategic in-
                                                                              fluence, while others depend on

                                                                              lic rarely notices these decisions
           not about astronomy, but influence. The                            standards set elsewhere. The pub-

           decision to center global time around   “                          unless something goes wrong.
           Greenwich Observatory reflected mari-                              Yet every smartphone timestamp,
           time power, trade dominance and the   We treat time as             stock trade and GPS signal relies
           practical reality that most global maps                            on this fragile consensus, proving
           already used that line.           neutral, but every               that global time is less a natural
             It wasn’t nature that crowned Green-                             constant and more a carefully
           wich. It was consensus shaped by   shared second is the            maintained agreement.
           power.
             Once that choice was made, the   result of negotiation,
           planet was effectively sliced into time                         ond affects navigation systems, financial
           zones. Invisible borders, but strict ones.   power and quiet    markets, aviation schedules and digital
           Miss your slot and you’re out of sync                           infrastructure.
           with the world.                   agreement.”                      Different countries and industries
                                                                           have different stakes. Tech companies
           Earth doesn’t rotate on schedule                                prefer uninterrupted atomic time. As-
             Here’s the quiet irony. The planet it-                        tronomers and Earth scientists argue that
           self refuses to behave like a perfect   The second that sparks debate   time should reflect the planet’s motion.
           clock.                            Those small adjustments, known to   Governments sit somewhere in between,
             Earth’s rotation slows and speeds up   specialists and barely noticed by the   balancing technical stability with sym-
           ever so slightly. Tides pull at it. Earth-  public, require international agreement.   bolic alignment to nature.
           quakes nudge it. Even melting ice shifts   Adding or removing even a single sec-  No one shouts about it in public, but
           mass and alters spin. These changes are
           tiny, but in a world ruled by satellites
           and nanoseconds, tiny matters.
             To keep modern systems running,
           scientists rely on atomic clocks, which
           are far more stable than the planet be-
           neath them. This created a problem no
           ancient civilization had to face. What
           happens when human-made time be-
           comes more precise than nature?
             The compromise was elegant and
           awkward at the same time. Atomic time
           would rule, but Earth’s rotation wouldn’t
           be ignored. Instead, occasional correc-
           tions would be added to keep clocks
           aligned with the planet’s actual move-
           ment.
             This is where science quietly meets
           diplomacy.

           6                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[When the clock


                 conflicts with the body

               Standardized time keeps econ-
             omies efficient, but human bodies
             don’t always agree with it. In
             many regions, official clock time
             drifts far from the sun’s natural
             rhythm. Mornings arrive before
             daylight. Evenings stretch unnat-
             urally long. Research links this
             mismatch to sleep disruption, re-
             duced productivity and long-term
             health concerns. Shift workers
             feel it most sharply, living in per-
             manent negotiation with fatigue.
             Cultural traditions that once fol-
             lowed seasonal and solar cues are   sleep patterns, school hours and even
                                           mental health. They tell citizens, subtly,
             gradually reshaped to fit rigid   you don’t see but live under every day.  “

             schedules. While global coordi-  whose rhythm matters most.
             nation demands uniform time, ev-  Time, in this sense, becomes a flag
             eryday life reminds us that bio-                                The Earth keeps
             logy still listens to the planet, not
             the clock on the wall.        Markets, missiles and             turning freely; it’s
                                           milliseconds
                                             In global finance, trades depend on   humans who
           behind closed doors, time is negotiated   synchronized clocks. In aviation, timing
           like a treaty.                  errors risk safety. In defense systems,   argue over how to
                                           precision is non-negotiable. The modern
           Who owns the global clock?      world runs on agreement down to frac-  count that
             There is no single world government   tions of a second.
           for time, but there are global institutions   This makes time a shared resource,   turning.”
           that act as its custodians. Their deci-  but also a contested one.
           sions ripple everywhere. When a stan-  When systems fail or drift, trust
           dard changes, every connected system   erodes. That’s why disputes over timing   deeply embedded in modern life. But
           must follow.                    standards are rarely framed as philo-  awareness matters.
             This is power of a very modern kind.   sophical questions. They’re treated as   Understanding that time is shaped by
           Not loud, not visible, but absolute.   infrastructure issues, even though they   negotiation, not destiny, changes how
             Countries that host major timing la-  shape how humanity experiences reality   we see it. It reminds us that even the
           boratories or control satellite networks   itself.              most basic structures of daily life are
           have disproportionate influence. Preci-                         built choices, not inevitabilities.
           sion timing supports military coordi-  The human cost of standardization   Earth keeps turning, patient and in-
           nation, secure communications and fi-  Lost in these debates is the individ-  different. Humans argue about how to
           nancial dominance. Losing a few   ual.                          count that turning, who gets to define it
           milliseconds can mean losing strategic   Shift workers feel the strain of im-  and whose interests it serves.
           advantage.                      posed schedules. Communities living
             So while time feels universal, its   far from their solar noon experience   A quieter way to look at the clock
           management is not evenly shared.   long mornings of darkness or late sun-  Next time you glance at your watch
                                           sets that never feel natural. Indigenous   or phone, it might feel different know-
           Time zones as political statements   concepts of time, circular and seasonal,   ing this. That moment isn’t just physics.
             Time zones also reveal how nations   struggle to survive under rigid grids.   It’s history. It’s compromise. It’s power
           see themselves.                   Standard time brought efficiency, but   translated into seconds.
             Some countries stretch a single time   it also flattened diversity. It asked bil-  Time doesn’t just pass. It’s decided,
           across vast geography to signal unity.   lions of people to live by a clock de-  adjusted, defended and sometimes dis-
           Others split time carefully to respect   signed for machines.   puted.
           local life. A few deliberately shift their   That trade-off rarely makes it into   And somewhere beneath all of it, the
           clocks away from solar logic to align   policy discussions.     planet continues its uneven spin, re-
           with political allies or economic part-                         minding us that no matter how precise
           ners.                           Can time ever be neutral again?   our clocks become, nature never fully
             These decisions shape daily routines,   Probably not. The global clock is too   hands over control. ■

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[INSIGHT
































           Digital kinship



           How the internet





           is redefining                                                   Today, distance is still hard, but it’s no

                                                                           longer final. The internet has stretched
                                                                           the idea of kinship beyond walls and
                                                                           borders, creating a new kind of close-
           family                                                          ness that is emotional rather than physi-
                                                                           cal. It’s imperfect, sometimes fragile,
                                                                           but undeniably real.
                                                                           From living rooms to login screens
           In glowing screens and late-night messages, in voices              The most visible shift is also the sim-
                                                                           plest one. Families now meet through
           that arrive from far away but feel close, people are            screens. Parents watch their children
                                                                           grow up pixel by pixel. Grandparents at-
           building families that fit the lives they’re actually living.   tend birthdays via shaky video calls.
                                                                           Siblings scattered across continents ar-
           By Siddharth Mehta                                              gue, joke and reconcile through voice
                                                                           notes and emojis.
                                                                              This isn’t a temporary fix anymore.
                  hat makes a family today. Is it   at 3 am and a group chat that never quite   For millions of migrant workers, inter-
                  blood, proximity, shared his-  sleeps, family has quietly expanded its   national students and diaspora families,
           Wtory, or simply the people     meaning.                        online connection is the primary way
           who show up when you need them most.   For centuries, family was shaped by   family life continues. Decisions are dis-
           The answer used to feel obvious. Now it   geography. You lived close, ate together,   cussed on calls. Illnesses are monitored
           feels more fluid. Somewhere between a   argued in person, made up before bed-  through daily messages. Celebrations
           late-night video call, a parenting forum   time. Distance usually meant loss.   happen with phones propped against

           8                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[When strangers


             become support


                At first, it’s just a question
             typed into a forum. A late-night
             post. A hesitant comment. Then
             replies start coming in. Advice,
             empathy, reassurance from
             people who understand without
             needing explanations. Over time,
             usernames turn familiar. Patterns
             emerge. Someone always checks
             in. Someone always listens.
             These online support groups,
             whether for parenting, grief, ill-
             ness, or mental health, often be-
             come emotional anchors. They                                                   pressures. Too
             function like extended families,                                               much advice can
             offering consistency when offline                                              feel overwhel-
             networks fall short. There’s no                                                ming. Compari-
             obligation, only presence. And                                                 son can creep in
             sometimes, that chosen presence                                                quietly. The dig-
             feels more sustaining than inher-                                              ital village
             ited ties. Digital kinship grows                                               helps, but it also
             quietly here, not loudly, but                                                  watches.
             deeply.                                                                           Still, for
                                                                                            many, these on-
                                                                                            line bonds are
           cups and books.                                                                  the reason they
             It’s easy to dismiss this as diluted to-                                       feel less alone in
           getherness. But ask anyone who relies                                            one of life’s
           on it and they’ll tell you otherwise. Pres-                                      most demanding
           ence, it turns out, is not only about being                                      roles. They may
           in the same room. It’s about availability.                                       never meet the
           About answering. About staying.                                                  people who
                                                                                            guide them
           When communities replace        Usernames turn into familiar voices.
           cousins                         Time zones become known. Absences

             Beyond blood ties, something quieter   are noticed. A kind of emotional kinship   “
           has been happening online. People are   forms, built not on obligation but on
           finding family in strangers who share   choice.                   Family is no longer
           their experiences. Parenting groups,
           grief forums, chronic illness com-  Parenting in the age of shared   defined by distance
           munities and mental health support   wisdom
           spaces have become lifelines.     Perhaps nowhere is digital kinship   or DNA alone. It’s
             A new parent struggling with exhaus-  more visible than in parenting. Advice
           tion may find more understanding in an   that once came only from elders now   shaped by who
           online group of strangers than in their   flows from across the world. Parents
           own extended family. Someone navigat-  compare notes on sleep routines, screen   shows up, even if
           ing loss might open up more easily to   time, schooling and mental health. They
           people who have walked the same path,   learn new approaches, question old ones   they arrive through a
           even if they’ve never met in person.   and sometimes unlearn what no longer
             These spaces work because they re-  fits.                       screen.”
           move some social pressure. There’s less   This shared knowledge can be em-
           performance, less expectation to appear   powering. It breaks isolation, especially
           strong. You can admit confusion. You   for single parents or those living far   through a difficult phase, but the grat-
           can say you’re tired. You can ask ques-  from family support. It also challenges   itude is real.
           tions that feel too awkward to ask at   rigid ideas of how parenting should
           home.                           look.                           Chosen families and safe spaces
             Over time, these connections deepen.   At the same time, it brings its own   For young adults, especially those

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                              9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“



            Online communities

            don’t replace family.
            They quietly become it,

            one shared story at a
            time.”






             Raising children                                                       Mistaking constant com-

                                                                                    munication for deep under-
              together, apart                                                       standing.

                                                                                       But it’s not a simple
                Modern parenting no longer                                          trade-off. Something is lost,
             happens in isolation. Parents now                                      yes. Something else is
             crowdsource wisdom across time                                         gained. Reach. Diversity.
             zones, cultures and experiences.                                       The ability to belong to
             A question about sleep routines in                                     more than one circle at
             one country finds answers from                                         once.
             another. Concerns about screen                                            Family is no longer a
             time, anxiety, or schooling spark                                      closed unit. It’s a network.
             thoughtful debates among                                               Sometimes messy. Often
             strangers united by care. This                                         overlapping. Increasingly
             shared digital village reduces                                         global.
             loneliness, especially for new or
             single parents. It challenges rigid   exist more fully everywhere.   A redefinition, not a replacement
             traditions while offering reassur-                               The internet isn’t erasing family. It’s
             ance that struggle is normal. Yet   The quiet rituals of digital   reshaping it. Expanding it. Making room
             it also demands balance, knowing   closeness                  for bonds that once had no name.
             when to listen and when to log   Every family has rituals. Dinner to-  Blood still matters. So does history.
             off. Still, for many, these online   gether. Sunday calls. Shared jokes. On-  But now, shared experience, emotional
             connections become co-parents   line families are no different. They just   availability and consistent care carry
             of sorts, shaping how children are   look different.          equal weight. Kinship has become less
             raised, even from afar.         A nightly check-in message. A   about where you come from and more
                                           weekly video call that starts late and   about how you connect.
                                           runs long. A shared playlist updated si-  This shift reflects a larger truth about
           questioning identity or navigating social   lently over months. These small acts   our times. Lives are more mobile. Iden-
           change, the internet often offers what   create rhythm and continuity.   tities are more layered. Support systems
           their immediate environment cannot.   They also require effort. Digital   need to travel with us.
           Acceptance. Language. Belonging.   closeness doesn’t happen automatically.
             Online spaces allow people to find   Someone has to initiate. Someone has to   Closing reflection
           others who understand them without ex-  remember. When it works, it’s because   At the end of the day, family has al-
           planation. These chosen families pro-  people choose to show up repeatedly.   ways been about who holds you up
           vide emotional safety, mentorship and   This effort is often invisible, but it’s   when the ground shifts. The internet did-
           solidarity. They celebrate milestones   what turns technology from a tool into a   n’t invent that need. It simply gave it
           that may go unnoticed at home. They   bridge.                   new pathways.
           offer comfort when rejection hurts.                                In glowing screens and late-night
             This kind of kinship is deeply inten-  What gets lost, what gets gained   messages, in voices that arrive from far
           tional. It’s not inherited. It’s built slowly,   Of course, digital kinship is not with-  away but feel close, people are building
           through shared stories and trust. And for   out loss. Screens can’t replace touch.   families that fit the lives they’re actually
           many, it becomes as meaningful as tradi-  Time delays matter in emergencies. Mis-  living. Not perfect. Not always easy. But
           tional family, sometimes more so.   understandings are easier when tone is   real.
             Critics worry that this weakens off-  flattened into text.       And maybe that’s what kinship has
           line relationships. But for many, it does   There’s also the risk of substitution.   always been. Not a fixed structure, but a
           the opposite. Feeling understood some-  Using online connection to avoid diffi-  living one, adapting quietly, one connec-
           where gives people the confidence to   cult but necessary offline relationships.   tion at a time. ■

           10                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[The trance within

                                                                           manship and hypnosis turns out to be far
           How hypnosis is                                                 slip into trance-like states all the time,   EXPLORATION
                                                                           more ordinary and far more intimate. We
                                                                           without noticing, without permission
                                                                           slips, without applause.
                                                                              Hypnosis, in its simplest sense, is not
           already part of                                                 rowed focus. Absorption. And if that
                                                                           about control. It is about attention. Nar-
                                                                           sounds familiar, it should.
                                                                           The everyday trance we barely
                                                                           notice
           everyday life                                                   scrolled through your phone intending to
                                                                              Think about the last time you
                                                                           spend five minutes and lost half an hour.
                                                                           Or the episode that automatically played
                                                                           after the one you planned to stop at. Or
           The trance is not something we enter from the outside.          the way time stretches and collapses
                                                                           when you are deeply lost in a book.
           It is something we carry within us, quietly shaping                These moments share a common
                                                                           quality. Your awareness narrows. The
           how we see, feel and choose. By Riya Verma                      outside world softens. Internal chatter
                                                                           quiets, at least temporarily. Psycholo-
                                                                           gists often describe this as absorption, a
                 ave you ever driven home and   That quiet, familiar state is where   key component of hypnotic states. You
                 realized you remember almost   this story begins.         are not unconscious. You are not pas-
           Hnothing about the journey? The   Most of us imagine hypnosis as   sive. You are focused, deeply and selec-
           turns were taken, the signals obeyed, the   something theatrical. A swinging watch.   tively.
           car parked safely. Yet your mind feels   A commanding voice. Someone cluck-  Driving is a classic example. On fa-
           like it was somewhere else. Not asleep.   ing like a chicken on stage. It feels dis-  miliar roads, the brain shifts into an
           Not distracted exactly. Just… elsewhere.   tant, even silly. But strip away the show-  automatic mode. Complex tasks happen









































           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[The everyday

                                                                                trance map


                                                                                We don’t slip into trance in
                                                                              dramatic ways. It happens softly,
                                                                              mid-sentence, mid-scroll, mid-
                                                                              turn. When you drive a familiar
                                                                              route and arrive without recalling
                                                                              the journey, your brain has
                                                                              shifted into automatic focus.
                                                                              When you binge-watch and lose
                                                                              track of time, narrative absorp-
                                                                              tion takes over. Even daydream-
                                                                              ing in a queue is a mild trance, at-
                                                                              tention narrowed inward. These
                                                                              states aren’t mistakes. They’re ef-
                                                                              ficient mental shortcuts, conserv-
                                                                              ing energy and reducing over-
                                                                              load. The issue isn’t entering
                                                                              them, but staying unaware of
                                                                              them. Once recognized, everyday
                                                                              trances become easier to manage,
                                                                              interrupt, or even use creatively
                                                                              rather than letting them quietly
                                                                              run the show.


                                                                           Less analytical, more experiential.
                                                                              In a way, hypnosis is not about shut-
                                                                           ting the mind down. It is about tuning it
                                                                           differently.

                                                                           Screens, stories and the modern
                                                                           trance
           down during such states. It is efficient. It  “                 tion, then modern life is a masterclass in
                                                                              If hypnosis is about focused atten-
           smoothly with little conscious effort.
           Studies using brain imaging suggest that

                                                                           inducing it.
           parts of the mind responsible for self-
           monitoring and time awareness dial
                                                                              Social media platforms are built
                                                                           and emotionally charged content. These
           is adaptive. And yes, it looks a lot like   Hypnosis isn’t about   around endless loops, variable rewards
                                             losing control. It’s
           hypnosis.                                                       features encourage a soft trance, not dra-
             This is why modern researchers in-  about where               matic, just sticky. Time passes strangely.
           creasingly describe hypnosis not as                             Awareness narrows. The outside world
           something exotic, but as a natural men-  attention quietly goes   fades.
           tal ability. Some people enter it more                             Binge-watching works similarly.
           easily than others, but everyone experi-  when no one is        Long-form storytelling pulls us into
           ences versions of it.                                           narrative trance. Our emotions sync with
                                             watching.”                    fictional characters. Heart rate changes.
           What hypnosis really is and isn’t                               Muscles relax or tense at the right mo-
             Let’s clear a few myths before going                          ments. The brain responds as if the story
           further.                        mation. Attention becomes more fo-  matters personally, because in that mo-
             Hypnosis does not make you lose   cused. Imagination becomes more vivid.   ment, it does.
           control. It does not force you to act   The mind becomes more open to sug-  This is not inherently bad. Humans
           against your values. You cannot be hyp-  gestion, especially suggestions that align   have always entered trance through
           notized into doing something you funda-  with existing goals or expectations.   stories, rituals, music and rhythm.
           mentally resist. Even in clinical settings,   Neuroscience offers clues here. Brain   Campfires and cave paintings did not
           the person remains aware and capable of   scans show altered activity in regions   come with autoplay, but they worked on
           refusing suggestions.           linked to attention, perception and self-  similar psychological mechanisms.
             What hypnosis does is temporarily   reflection during hypnotic states. The   The difference now is scale and
           change how the brain processes infor-  brain is not asleep. It is reorganized.   frequency. We enter these states re-

           12                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Every scroll, every
                                                                             familiar road, every

                                                                             late-night episode
                                                                             carries a soft trance we

                                                                             rarely question.”


                                                                              This does not mean we are helpless.
                                                                           Awareness changes the equation. Rec-
                                                                           ognizing when our attention narrows al-
                                                                           lows us to step back, even briefly. That
                                                                           pause matters.
                                                                              In some ways, learning about hypno-
                                                                           sis is less about being hypnotized and
                                                                           more about noticing when we already
                                                                           are.
                                                                           Finding conscious trance
                                                                              There is a gentler side to all this.
                                                                              Meditation, prayer, music, dance and
                                                                           even certain forms of exercise delib-
                                                                           erately invite trance-like focus. The dif-
           peatedly, often unconsciously and often   people are “highly hypnotizable” while   ference is intention. These states are en-
           without clear boundaries. The trance be-  others are not. There is some truth here,   tered with awareness and often exited
           comes background noise.         but it is more nuanced than it sounds.   with clarity.
                                             People who score higher on hyp-  Mindfulness practices, for example,
           Hypnosis in therapy and healing   notic susceptibility scales often have   train attention without hijacking it. You
             Away from screens and stages, hyp-  vivid imaginations, strong emotional re-  notice the narrowing without losing
           nosis has a quieter, more serious role.   sponsiveness and the ability to become   choice. The mind settles, but the self
             Clinical hypnosis is used alongside   deeply absorbed. Artists, writers, musi-  remains present.
           conventional treatments for pain man-  cians and avid readers often fall into   This may be the most valuable les-
           agement, anxiety, phobias, trauma, irri-  this category. Children too.   son hypnosis offers everyday life. Not
           table bowel syndrome and even habit   But susceptibility is not weakness. It   how to escape awareness, but how to
           change like smoking cessation. It is not   is flexibility. The same traits that make   work with it.
           a magic cure. It works best when com-  someone responsive to suggestion also
           bined with evidence-based therapy. But   support creativity, empathy and learn-  A quiet ending, not a dramatic one
           when it helps, it can help deeply.   ing.                          Hypnosis does not live on a stage or
             Pain is a striking example. Research   Skepticism does not make hypnosis   in a therapist’s chair alone. It lives in
           shows that hypnotic suggestion can re-  impossible either. In fact, informed   the gaps between intention and habit. In
           duce the brain’s perception of pain, not   skepticism often improves outcomes   the moments when time slips, when
           by numbing sensation, but by altering   because it replaces fear with curiosity.   focus deepens, when the mind follows a
           how the sensation is interpreted. The   Hypnosis works best when people un-  thread without checking where it leads.
           pain signal may still arrive, but it carries   derstand what it is and what it is not.   Once you notice it, you notice it ev-
           less emotional weight.                                          erywhere.
             Trauma therapy also uses trance-like   The ethics of influence   The next time you find yourself lost
           focus to safely revisit and reframe mem-  Once we accept that trance-like   in a song, a story, a road, or a screen,
           ories. Again, the person is not erased or   states are common, an uncomfortable   pause for a second. Not to judge. Just
           overwhelmed. They are guided, gently,   question follows. Who is guiding our   to observe. That softened edge of
           with consent and structure.     attention when we enter them?   awareness is not a failure of attention.
             This matters because it reframes hyp-  Advertising, political messaging and   It is a feature of being human.
           nosis as a skill rather than a spectacle. A   persuasive media all rely on repetition,   The trance is not something we enter
           way of working with the mind instead of   emotional triggers and simplified narra-  from the outside. It is something we
           fighting it.                    tives.                          carry within us, quietly shaping how we
                                             These techniques are not hypnosis in   see, feel and choose. And perhaps the
           Why some people are more        the clinical sense, but they work on   real skill is not avoiding it, but learning
           susceptible                     similar principles of attention and sug-  when to step in and when to gently step
             You may have heard that some   gestion.                       back out. ■

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE







































                                                                           knowing without knowing how. But
           The logic of love                                               psychologists will quietly tell you that
                                                                           many of these moments can be traced,
                                                                           mapped, even anticipated.
                                                                              Attraction, for instance, often follows
                                                                           proximity. We’re more likely to fall for
                                                                           people we see often, work with, or share
           When emotions  routines with. The office romance. The
                                                                           neighbor. The friend of a friend who
                                                                           keeps showing up. Familiarity softens
           follow rules                                                    us. It lowers our guard. The brain reads
                                                                           repetition as safety.
                                                                              Then there’s similarity. Shared
                                                                           values, backgrounds, humor styles, even
                                                                           speech rhythms. We say opposites at-
           Love is not a math problem to be solved. It’s closer to a       tract, but long-term bonds tend to grow
                                                                           between people who recognize them-
           language. It has grammar. Syntax. Unspoken rules that           selves in each other, at least a little. It’s
                                                                           not narcissism. It’s efficiency. Under-
           native speakers follow without thinking. By Naina Kapoor        standing takes less effort when the emo-
                                                                           tional language is already familiar.
                                                                              Romantic? Maybe not in the cine-
                  hat if love is not as chaotic as   cluded, the more repetition you notice.   matic sense. But deeply human.
                  it feels at 2 a.m.? What if, be-  Similar beginnings. Familiar conflicts.
           Wneath the butterflies, the     Predictable endings. It starts to look less   The patterns we repeat without
           mixed signals, the dramatic silences,   like magic and more like… design.   noticing
           there is a quiet structure doing its work?   Not cold design. Not mechanical.   Think about the people you’ve loved.
             That idea can feel unsettling. We like   Just human.          Not just who they were, but how those
           to think of love as spontaneous, unruly,                        relationships unfolded. Chances are,
           immune to formulas. Something that   Love feels irrational. It isn’t   there’s a theme. Maybe you’re drawn to
           happens to us, not something that fol-  When people fall in love, they rarely   emotionally distant partners. Or to care-
           lows a pattern. And yet, the more you   describe it in logical terms. They talk   takers. Or to people who need fixing.
           listen to people’s stories, your own in-  about sparks, chemistry, destiny. About   This isn’t coincidence. Early attach-

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[“



            We don’t fall
            randomly. We fall

            along emotional

            grooves already
            carved long before

            we recognize them.”


           ment experiences shape what feels like
           love later on. The brain learns its first
           emotional rules early, long before it has
           words for them. As adults, we often con-
           fuse familiarity with compatibility.

             That’s why someone can be “bad for                                   The familiarity
           us” and still feel irresistible. The emo-
           tional pattern fits. The logic, though
           painful, is consistent.                                                   effect
             We don’t fall randomly. We fall along
           grooves already carved.                                              Have you ever wondered why
                                                                              love so often begins in ordinary
           Chemistry has a timetable                                          places offices, neighborhoods,
             One of the most quietly logical as-                              shared routines? Psychologists
           pects of love is timing. Right person,                             call this the familiarity effect.
           wrong time is not just a cliché. It’s a real                       The more we see someone, the
           phenomenon.                                                        safer they begin to feel. Familiar-
             People are more likely to commit                                 ity lowers emotional defenses,
           when their lives are stable enough to                              builds trust and creates a subtle
           hold another person. Emotional band-                               sense of belonging. This is why
           width matters. So does age, ambition,                              many relationships start not with
           unresolved grief, financial stress. Two                            fireworks, but with comfort. Over
           people can feel the same connection, yet                           time, the brain associates re-
           arrive at different conclusions because                            peated presence with reliability.
           their internal clocks are out of sync.                             It’s not laziness or lack of imagi-
             Love doesn’t operate in isolation. It   mation yet.              nation. It’s emotional efficiency.
           negotiates with reality.          Over time, patterns shift. Memory   Love, in this sense, doesn’t chase
             This is why some relationships burn   softens. The brain rewrites the story to   novelty endlessly. It looks for
           bright and brief, while others grow   reduce pain. Eventually, even the sharp-  patterns it can settle into. Com-
           slowly, almost awkwardly, into some-  est heartbreak begins to make sense, not   fort becomes the foundation on
           thing lasting. Desire may be instant, but   emotionally perhaps, but narratively.   which intimacy quietly grows.
           commitment often waits for conditions   There is relief in that. Meaning is the
           to align.                       brain’s way of healing.
                                                                           That second, third, or fourth falling is
           Why heartbreak follows a script   Choice plays a bigger role than we   rarely spontaneous. It’s cultivated.
             If love has logic, heartbreak does too.   admit                  Love, it turns out, is not just a feel-
             The early days after a breakup often   Popular culture tells us love is some-  ing. It’s a practice with principles.
           feel like withdrawal. Because that’s ex-  thing that happens to us. But lasting love
           actly what they are. Romantic attach-  often comes down to something less   Predictability doesn’t make love
           ment activates the same reward circuits   glamorous. Choice.    boring
           as addiction. When the bond breaks, the   Choosing to stay curious when famil-  There’s a fear that if love follows
           brain protests. It craves the familiar   iarity dulls excitement. Choosing to   rules, it loses its mystery. But predict-
           voice, the shared routines, the chemical   communicate instead of retreat. Choos-  ability isn’t the enemy of depth. It’s
           comfort of connection.          ing repair over pride. These choices   often the condition for it.
             This is why logic rarely works in the   don’t eliminate emotion. They guide it.   When emotional safety is estab-
           first phase of heartbreak. You can know   Long-term partners often say they   lished, people take greater risks. They
           it was wrong and still want it back. The   “fell in love again” at different stages.   share more. They grow. They surprise
           mind hasn’t caught up with the infor-  After illness. After loss. After boredom.   each other. Structure creates freedom,

           16                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Why we repeat the


                                                                                  same love stories

                                                                                Many people swear they keep
                                                                              dating “the same person in a dif-
                                                                              ferent body.” There’s truth in that
                                                                              feeling. Early emotional experi-
                                                                              ences shape what love feels like
                                                                              later on. The brain seeks emo-
                                                                              tional familiarity, even when it’s
                                                                              uncomfortable. This is why some
                                                                              people are drawn to distant part-
                                                                              ners, while others lean toward
                                                                              caretakers or rescuers. These pat-
                                                                              terns aren’t conscious choices.
                                                                              They’re emotional habits. Under-
                                                              Dating apps,    standing this doesn’t instantly
                                                            for instance,     break the cycle, but it creates
                                                            have introduced   awareness. And awareness
                                                            new rules.        creates space. Space to pause, re-
                                                            Abundance over    flect and perhaps choose differ-
                                                            scarcity. Choice   ently next time. Love may follow
                                                            paralysis. The il-  rules, but recognizing them gives
                                                            lusion that       us a say in how the story un-
                                                            something better   folds.quietly run the show.
                                                            is always one
                                                            swipe away.
                                                            This changes
                                                            how people
                                                            commit, how     “
                                                            quickly they de-  Love may feel chaotic,
                                                            tach, how they
                                                            handle dis-      but beneath the
                                                            appointment.
                                                              The logic      butterflies lies a quiet
                                                            adapts. The
                                                            longing remains.   structure doing its

                                                            Knowing the      work.”
                                                            rules doesn’t
                                                            ruin the game
                                                              There’s a
                                                            temptation to be-  solved. It’s closer to a language. It has
                                                            lieve that under-  grammar. Syntax. Unspoken rules that
           not limitation.                 standing love will make it less powerful.   native speakers follow without think-
             Think of music. Notes follow rules.   That if we see the patterns, the magic   ing. We stumble when we ignore them.
           Scales, timing, harmony. Yet within   disappears. But insight doesn’t cancel   We flourish when we learn them.
           those rules, infinite variation exists.   emotion. It contextualizes it.   Perhaps the real surprise is not that
           Love works much the same way. Pat-  Knowing that attraction can be in-  love has logic, but that we resist admit-
           terns provide the framework. Emotion   fluenced by proximity doesn’t stop it   ting it. We want love to be special, un-
           fills it with color.            from happening. Knowing that heart-  repeatable, untouched by reason. And it
                                           break is chemical doesn’t make it hurt   is all of those things. Just not lawless.
           Culture shapes the rules we follow   less. But it can make us kinder to our-  Understanding love’s patterns
             Love’s logic is not universal. It’s fil-  selves while we’re inside it.   doesn’t make us less romantic. It makes
           tered through culture, class, gender and   Awareness offers choice. And choice   us more intentional.
           technology. What feels romantic in one   is where dignity enters the story.   And maybe that’s the quiet truth.
           place may feel excessive or insufficient                        Love feels wild, but it grows best when
           in another. Expectations around mar-  Where emotion and reason finally   we learn how it works.
           riage, independence, loyalty and expres-  meet                     Not to control it. Just to meet it
           sion all shape how love is interpreted.   Love is not a math problem to be   halfway. ■

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY








































           THE LOST LANGUAGE OF THANKS


           Civilizations






           that thanked


                                                                           toward nature wasn’t an abstract philos-
                                                                           ophy. It was ritualized, spoken aloud,
                                                                           acted upon. Fields were thanked before
           the earth                                                       Animals were honored even in death.
                                                                           harvest. Rivers were greeted like elders.
                                                                           Somewhere along the road to modernity,
                                                                           we learned to extract without acknowl-
                                                                           edging. The rituals faded and with them,
                                                                           a way of seeing the world.
           Reviving the lost language of thanks doesn’t                       This isn’t nostalgia. It’s anthropol-
                                                                           ogy.
           require reenacting ancient ceremonies. It requires
                                                                           When gratitude was survival, not
           attention. By Ishita Desai                                      sentiment
                                                                              Early human societies lived danger-
                                                                           ously close to uncertainty. Rain could
                  hen did we stop saying thank   us, skies that decided whether we lived   mean life or loss. A river’s generosity
                  you to the ground beneath   easily or not at all. There was a time   could change overnight. In that fragile
           Wour feet? Not the polite, auto-  when this language of thanks wasn’t po-  balance, gratitude wasn’t moral postur-
           matic kind we offer people, but a deeper,   etic. It was practical. Survival depended   ing. It was recognition of dependence.
           quieter gratitude. The kind meant for   on it.                     Among Indigenous communities in
           rivers that carried us, animals that fed   Across ancient civilizations, gratitude   the Americas, hunters offered prayers to

           18                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[When rivers had

            names, not numbers


                Before rivers became lines on
             maps or data points in climate re-
             ports, they were addressed like
             elders. Communities along the
             Nile, the Indus and the Euphrates
             spoke to water with offerings and
             prayers, aware that floods and
             droughts carried intention, not
             randomness. In India, daily rit-
             uals still thank rivers before use,
             acknowledging water as a giver,
             not a commodity. These practices
             didn’t prevent floods or famine,
             but they shaped restraint. You
             took carefully from what you re-
             spected. Today, rivers are man-
             aged, diverted and dammed, yet
             rarely acknowledged. When grat-
             itude disappears, responsibility
             often follows quietly behind it.


           the spirit of the animal before and after a
           kill. The Iroquois Thanksgiving Ad-
           dress, still spoken today, opens gath-
           erings by thanking the people, then the
           waters, plants, animals, winds, sun,
           moon, stars and finally the Creator. It’s
           not symbolic. It’s a verbal map of inter-
           dependence.
             In ancient Mesopotamia, farmers per-
           formed rituals for Tigris and Euphrates   elements, earth, water, fire, air and
           before planting season. The rivers were   space, as sacred constituents of life.
           unpredictable, sometimes destructive,   Daily prayers still thank the earth before   “
           but never treated as inert resources.   stepping on it and the food before eating   Gratitude was once
           They were addressed, negotiated with,   it.
           respected.                        Jainism takes gratitude further, ex-  a survival skill, not
             Gratitude, then, wasn’t optimism. It   tending it into radical non-violence. The
           was realism.                    practice of ahimsa isn’t just ethical re-
                                           straint; it’s acknowledgment that even   a virtue. You
           Rivers as mothers, mountains as   the smallest life forms deserve rec-
           witnesses                       ognition. Many Jain monks sweep the   thanked the river
             Civilizations around the world as-  ground before walking, a physical ex-
           signed personhood to landscapes. This   pression of thanks through care.   because your life
           wasn’t naive animism. It was a social   Buddhism teaches interdependence
           contract.                       through the idea of dependent origina-  depended on it.”
             In India, rivers have long been ad-  tion. Nothing exists independently. A
           dressed as living beings. The Ganga is   meal is the sun, the soil, the farmer, the
           not simply water but Ganga Ma, a   rain, all meeting briefly on a plate. Grat-  Thanking animals, even in death
           mother whose flow purifies and sus-  itude arises naturally from this aware-  One of the most striking features of
           tains. Long before environmental   ness.                        older gratitude systems was how they
           science articulated the value of river   Similar ideas appeared elsewhere. In   addressed animals.
           ecosystems, ritual bathing, offerings and   ancient Andean cultures, Pachamama,   The Ainu people of Japan believed
           chants reinforced a relationship of care   Mother Earth, received offerings of food   bears were divine visitors. After hunt-
           and accountability.             and drink before harvests. The Maori of   ing one, they performed the Iyomante
             This worldview is deeply rooted in   New Zealand greeted mountains and   ceremony, sending the bear’s spirit
           Indian religious traditions. Hinduism   rivers as ancestors. Nature wasn’t out-  back with gifts and apologies. To mod-
           emphasizes pancha mahabhuta, the five   side society. It was family.   ern eyes, it may seem contradictory.

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             We learned how to

                                                                             measure the earth

                                                                             precisely, but forgot
                                                                             how to speak to it

                                                                             gently.”


                                                                           Echoes in the present
           But within that worldview, killing                                 Even today, fragments of the old
           without gratitude was unthinkable.                              language surface.
             Among Arctic communities, seals      Thanking the                Farmers in parts of rural India still
           and whales were thanked through song                            thank the soil after harvest. In Japan,
           and careful use of every part of the   animal that fed you      the phrase itadakimasu, said before

           body. Waste wasn’t just inefficient. It                         meals, quietly acknowledges the lives
           was disrespectful.                   Many early societies believed   and labor behind food. Environmental
             Contrast this with contemporary in-  killing an animal without grat-  movements now speak of “rights of
           dustrial food systems, where animals   itude invited imbalance. Hunters   rivers,” a legal echo of ancient person-
           disappear behind packaging and     paused. They apologized. They   hood.
           numbers. Gratitude becomes optional   promised not to waste what was   Interestingly, many urban, educated
           when visibility vanishes.          given. From Arctic seal hunts to   people are rediscovering these ideas
                                              forest-based tribal cultures, every   not through religion, but through ecol-
           How the language faded             part of the animal was used, not   ogy. Climate science has forced a re-
             So how did we lose this way of   out of efficiency alone, but re-  turn to interdependence. Suddenly,
           speaking to the earth?             spect. Contrast that with modern   what ancient rituals knew intuitively
             Part of the answer lies in scale. As   food systems, where meat arrives   feels urgent again.
           societies grew, personal relationships   stripped of story, struggle, or sac-  But something is missing.
           with land and water became abstract. A   rifice. Gratitude becomes abstract   Ritual created pause. It slowed con-
           river managed by a state no longer   when distance grows. The old rit-  sumption with acknowledgment. Our
           needed appeasement. It needed regula-  uals weren’t sentimental. They   current systems move too fast for
           tion.                              were grounding. They reminded   thanks.
             Colonial systems also played a role.   humans that life feeds on life and
           Indigenous gratitude rituals were often   that acknowledgment, not guilt,   Learning to speak again
           dismissed as superstition, replaced by   was the ethical response to sur-  Reviving the lost language of thanks
           resource-based thinking. Land became   vival.                   doesn’t require reenacting ancient cere-
           property. Forests became timber re-                             monies. It requires attention.
           serves.                                                            It might begin with recognizing that
             Modern science, for all its benefits,   lational. You protect what you love.   food is not just calories. That water is
           unintentionally widened the gap. When   It’s harder to love what you only cal-  not just supply. That land is not merely
           nature is explained entirely through   culate.                  real estate. Gratitude doesn’t need in-
           data, it becomes measurable but not re-  And yet, traces remain.   cense or chants, though it can include
                                                                           them. Sometimes it’s restraint. Some-
                                                                           times it’s repair.
                                                                              There’s humility in saying thank
                                                                           you to something that can survive
                                                                           without you. That humility once kept
                                                                           civilizations grounded.
                                                                              We don’t need to romanticize the
                                                                           past. Ancient societies had flaws, hier-
                                                                           archies and violence. But they under-
                                                                           stood one thing clearly: you don’t
                                                                           dominate what you depend on.
                                                                              Perhaps the earth hasn’t stopped lis-
                                                                           tening. Perhaps we’ve just stopped
                                                                           speaking.
                                                                              And maybe, quietly, it’s waiting for
                                                                           us to remember how. ■

           20                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT












































           The vertical festival                                                   hen was the last time a festi-
                                                                                   val asked you to look up in-
                                                                           Wstead of down? Not at an idol,
           Why Sankranti                                                   pattern on the floor, but straight into the
                                                                           not at a lamp, not at a carefully drawn
                                                                           open sky. There are celebrations that fill
                                                                           our streets, our courtyards, our temples
                                                                           and our homes. And then there is Sank-
                                                                           ranti, which quietly insists that the real
                                                                           stage is above our heads.
                                                                              Every year on January 14 (sometimes
           is celebrated in  January 15, depending on the solar cal-
                                                                           endar), Makar Sankranti arrives without
                                                                           fireworks or processions. It doesn’t an-
           the sky                                                         nounce itself with loudspeakers. Instead,
                                                                           it lifts its voice gently, carried on the
                                                                           string of a kite, asking people to tilt their
                                                                           faces upward and notice the sky again.
                                                                           A festival that refuses to stay
           Most festivals in India are horizontal experiences. We          grounded
                                                                              Most festivals in India are horizontal
           walk, bow, circle, sit, eat, touch the earth. Sankranti         experiences. We walk, bow, circle, sit,
           breaks that rhythm. It pulls the celebration off the            eat, touch the earth. Sankranti breaks
                                                                           that rhythm. It pulls the celebration off
           ground. By Aditya Joshi                                         the ground. The action happens in the
                                                                           air, the competition unfolds in mid-flight

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Why this festival

                      rises

                Most celebrations expand out-
             ward. Streets fill, courtyards
             glow, crowds move horizontally.
             Sankranti does the opposite. It
             compresses people into rooftops
             and releases the celebration up-
             ward. The focus shifts from
             where we stand to where we
             look. This verticality is not acci-
             dental. It mirrors the sun’s north-
             ward movement and humanity’s
             instinctive response to seasonal
             change. By flying kites, people
             physically engage with wind,
             light and altitude. The body be-  Sankranti doesn’t need to explain as-
             comes aware of direction. Unlike   tronomy to make this point. It lets the

             processions or rituals tied to fixed   body understand it first.   “
             spaces, Sankranti unfolds in an
             open, shared sky. It’s one of the   Why the sky matters here    Most festivals ask us
             few festivals where participation   Unlike many religious observances
             depends less on proximity and   tied to lunar cycles, Sankranti follows   to bow, walk, or
             more on perspective.          the sun. That alone sets it apart. It marks
                                           a clear astronomical shift, when the sun   gather. Sankranti
                                           moves into Capricorn, or Makara, in the
                                                                             asks something
                                                                             rarer: to look up and

                                                                             let the sky
                                                                             participate.



                                                                           For a few hours, social boundaries blur,
                                                                           replaced by shared laughter and collec-
                                                                           tive attention upward.
                                                                           India’s many skies, one impulse
                                                                              Travel across India during Sankranti
                                                                           and you’ll notice how the festival
                                                                           changes form while keeping its vertical
                                                                           soul intact.
           and the joy travels vertically, from roof-  zodiac. For agrarian societies, this   In Gujarat, especially in Ahmedabad,
           tops to clouds and back.        movement signalled longer days, gentler   rooftops turn into packed arenas during
             Kites become more than toys. They   cold and the promise of harvest.   Uttarayan. Families gather early, music
           turn into messengers. Each one carries   But what’s fascinating is how this   plays, snacks circulate and the sky be-
           intention, playfulness, pride, even quiet   scientific transition found expression not   comes so crowded with kites that it feels
           rivalry. The sky fills with colour, motion   in textbooks or rituals alone, but in play.   almost textured. The competition is
           and sound. Strings hum. Paper flutters.   Kite flying became a way to engage   fierce, but the mood remains festive.
           Someone shouts in triumph. Someone   with the sky physically. You don’t just   Strangers cheer for each other. Children
           else laughs it off and reaches for another   acknowledge the sun’s movement. You   learn the art of balance and timing, les-
           spool.                          respond to it.                  sons disguised as fun.
             There’s something deeply symbolic   There’s also a subtle equality in this.   In Rajasthan, the skies over Jaipur
           about this upward movement. At a time   The sky doesn’t belong to anyone. Roof-  glow with kites of all sizes. Against the
           when days begin to lengthen and the sun   tops may differ in height, neighbour-  backdrop of forts and old city walls, the
           starts its northward journey, people in-  hoods in wealth, but once the kite is air-  contrast is striking. History below, free-
           stinctively respond by lifting their gaze.   borne, everyone plays in the same space.   dom above. In parts of Telangana and

           22                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[a  Learning science

                                                                                  without naming it

                                                                                Long before aerodynamics en-
                                                                              tered classrooms, Sankranti
                                                                              brought it to rooftops. Kite flying
                                                                              quietly teaches physics through
                                                                              touch and trial. Which angle
                                                                              holds best? How much tension is
                                                                              too much? Why does one kite
                                                                              climb while another dips? Chil-
                                                                              dren learn by doing, adjusting in-
                                                                              stinctively to wind speed and di-
                                                                              rection. Even adults read the sky,
            “                              A festival of rooftops and pauses   festival turns abstract science into
                                                                              sensing invisible air currents. The

                                             Urban India has changed the way we
                                                                              lived experience. There are no
                                           celebrate many festivals. Space has
                                                                              formulas, only feedback. Success
            For a few hours,
                                                                              comes from attention, not instruc-
                                           shrunk. Schedules are tighter. Attention
                                                                              often feels distant, Sankranti re-
                                           adapted with surprising grace.
            rooftops disappear,            spans are shorter. Yet Sankranti has   tion. In a world where science
                                             Rooftops have become precious.   minds us that understanding once
            borders blur and the           They are no longer just utility spaces but   came from observation, play and
                                           social platforms. On Sankranti, they host   patience, guided by curiosity
            sky becomes a                  conversations that don’t usually happen.   rather than curriculum.
                                           Neighbours who rarely speak exchange
            shared playground.”            smiles. Teenagers negotiate strings. Eld-
                                           ers point at the sky and tell stories about   what was once a simple joy. These is-
                                           how it used to be.              sues deserve attention and responsibility,
           Andhra Pradesh, kite flying is quieter,   There’s also permission to pause. To   not dismissal.
           more communal, woven into the larger   stand still and watch. To let your phone   Yet it would be a loss if the vertical
           Sankranti celebrations that include ran-  slip into your pocket while your eyes   spirit of Sankranti were reduced to nos-
           goli, cattle worship and shared meals.   track a tiny moving dot far above. In a   talgia alone. The festival isn’t just about
             Even where kites are not central, the   culture increasingly dominated by   kites. It’s about direction. About lifting
           idea of looking upward remains. Bon-  screens, Sankranti insists on a different   the head, if only briefly, from the
           fires, sugarcane stalks, tilgul sweets, all   kind of gaze.     ground-level noise of life.
           serve as reminders of transition and                               Even if the form changes, the essence
           gratitude. The sky may not always be   The diaspora’s sky       can remain. Looking up. Marking transi-
           filled with paper wings, but it is ac-  For Indians living abroad, Sankranti   tion. Sharing space without ownership.
           knowledged.                     often becomes a festival of memory. The
                                           sky may look different. Regulations may   Ending where the sky begins
           The science hiding in plain sight   restrict kite flying. Weather may not co-  There’s a quiet humility in celebrat-
             There’s an understated brilliance in   operate. Still, the impulse survives.   ing something that cannot be controlled.
           how Sankranti brings science into every-  Community parks host small gath-  You can guide a kite, but you can’t com-
           day life without naming it as such. Kite   erings. Children fly plastic kites be-  mand the wind. You can plan your day,
           flying teaches aerodynamics intuitively.   tween buildings. Someone explains why   but the sky always has the final say.
           Wind direction, tension, angle, balance.   this day mattered back home. Food   Maybe that’s why Sankranti feels dif-
           Children learn these concepts long be-  bridges the distance. So does the shared   ferent. It doesn’t ask for perfection. It
           fore they encounter them in classrooms.   act of looking up.In these moments,   asks for participation. It reminds us that
             It also sharpens awareness. You look   Sankranti becomes less about precision   some of the most meaningful celebra-
           at clouds differently. You feel the breeze   and more about connection. It reminds   tions don’t happen at eye level. They
           on your face and read it. You notice how   people that culture isn’t fixed to geogra-  happen when we tilt our heads back,
           sunlight shifts as the day progresses.   phy. It travels, adapts and waits patiently   squint a little against the sun and allow
           Sankranti turns passive observation into   for recognition.     ourselves to be small under a vast, wel-
           active engagement.                                              coming sky.
             In an age where science often feels   What we might be forgetting   For a few hours each year, the festi-
           abstract or intimidating, this festival   As cities grow denser and safety con-  val doesn’t sit in our hands or at our
           offers a reminder. Knowledge doesn’t   cerns rise, kite flying faces challenges.   feet. It floats. And in following it up-
           always arrive through equations. Some-  Glass-coated strings, power lines and   ward, we remember something quietly
           times, it comes on a spool of string.   environmental concerns complicate   important about ourselves too. ■

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[PROFILE
































           Not just Tiger

                                                                           moved comfortably between tradition
                                                                           and change, between old India and the
           The many lives                                                  remember him only for his cricket
                                                                           one learning to speak in a new voice. To
                                                                           would be to miss the fuller story.

                                                                           Born into privilege, raised by
                                                                           expectation
           of Mansoor Ali                                                  into the princely family of Pataudi, a lin-
                                                                              Mansoor Ali Khan was born in 1941
                                                                           eage steeped in diplomacy, power and
                                                                           ceremony. His father, Iftikhar Ali Khan
                                                                           Pataudi, had captained India before him.
           Khan Pataudi                                                    education at Winchester and Oxford all
                                                                           The palace, the etiquette, the English
                                                                           suggested a life mapped out in advance.
                                                                              Yet privilege can be a burden. For a
                                                                           young man with a famous surname,
                                                                           every step is watched, every success
           Mansoor Ali Khan Pataudi was also a thinker, a                  questioned. Was it talent, or was it ac-
                                                                           cess? Pataudi seemed aware of this
           husband, a father, a reformer in his own understated            shadow early on and perhaps that is why
                                                                           he worked so hard to step beyond it.
           way. By Siddharth Mehta
                                                                           Cricket, interrupted and
                                                                           reinvented
                  hat does it mean to inherit a   fidence. Mansoor Ali Khan Pataudi,   At 21, Pataudi lost vision in his right
                  crown at birth, lose an eye in   forever nicknamed Tiger, lived several   eye following a car accident in England.
           Wyouth, captain a nation in     lives at once and none of them felt bor-  For most athletes, it would have ended
           your twenties, marry into cinema royalty   rowed.               everything. Depth perception is not op-
           and still be remembered most for your   Every year, on January 5, his birth   tional in cricket. It is survival.
           grace? Few lives carry so many inter-  anniversary invites reflection, not only   What followed was not a dramatic
           secting identities with such quiet con-  on a sporting legend but on a man who   comeback story full of noise, but a qui-

           24                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Leadership, for

                                                                             Pataudi, was never

                                                                             about dominance. It
                                                                             was about belief;

                                                                             belief that Indian

                                                                             cricket could walk
                                                                             into any country

                                                                             without apology.”






                  The one-eyed

                   captain

                When Mansoor Ali Khan Pa-
             taudi returned to cricket after los-
             ing vision in one eye, he didn’t
             attempt to reclaim what he had
             lost. He rebuilt instead. Adjusting
             his stance, relying on instinct and
             trusting muscle memory over
             sight, he reshaped his game
             quietly. As captain, that same ap-
             proach defined his leadership. He
             didn’t shout. He didn’t dramatize.
             But he expected his players to
             compete, especially overseas,
             where Indian teams had long
             been tentative. Wins were rare,   The captain who changed the tone   with wit, often self-deprecating. There
             yes, but belief took root. Under   Indian cricket before Pataudi often   was an ease about him, a sense that he
             Pataudi, Indian cricket learned   carried a faint apologetic air abroad.   did not need to prove anything.
             something subtle yet vital: it did-  Under him, that changed. His teams   Despite holding a royal title in post-
             n’t need permission to belong on   competed, not just participated. He   Independence India, he never clung to it.
             the world stage.              backed young players, encouraged fast   When privy purses were abolished, he
                                           bowlers and refused to accept that In-  adapted. When palaces became expen-
                                           dian teams were destined to struggle   sive to maintain, he opened them to the
           eter, more impressive act of reinvention.   outside the subcontinent.   world. Tradition, for him, was some-
           Pataudi relearned his game, adjusted his   He was not perfect. His batting aver-  thing to carry lightly, not cling to des-
           stance, trusted instinct over sight. He re-  ages were modest, his captaincy some-  perately.
           turned to international cricket and soon   times conservative. But leadership is not
           after, became India’s youngest Test cap-  arithmetic. It is mood, confidence, the   A marriage that bridged worlds
           tain.                           subtle sense that someone is in charge.   His marriage to Sharmila Tagore in
             Those who played under him often   In many ways, Pataudi laid the emo-  1969 was more than a personal mile-
           spoke less about tactics and more about   tional groundwork for the assertive In-  stone. It symbolized a meeting of two
           temperament. He led without bluster. In   dian teams that came decades later.   Indias. One rooted in aristocratic her-
           an era when Indian cricket was still find-                      itage, the other in the glamour and reach
           ing its spine, he offered belief. Overseas   The Nawab in everyday life   of popular cinema.
           wins were rare then. Standards were   Off the field, the Nawab of Pataudi   Their relationship was notable for its
           lower. Pataudi pushed them higher,   lived with understated elegance. He   normalcy. No public theatrics, no culti-
           sometimes simply by expecting more.   dressed well but never loudly. He spoke   vated mystique. Friends recall warmth,

           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[A private man in

                                                                               public worlds


                                                                                 Despite royalty, sporting
                                                                              fame and a high-profile marriage,
                                                                              Pataudi guarded his personal life
                                                                              with care. His relationship with
                                                                              Sharmila Tagore was marked not
                                                                              by spectacle but by steadiness.
                                                                              Together, they navigated two de-
                                                                              manding public worlds without
                                                                              turning their private life into per-
                                                                              formance. As a father, he resisted
                                                                              scripting futures, allowing his
                                                                              children space to find their own
                                                                              paths. Fame, he believed, was not
                                                                              inheritance but effort. Those
                                                                              close to him recall humor, hon-
                                                                              esty and an absence of preten-
            “                              sal to be impressed by celebrity. Suc-  shaped by visibility, Pataudi’s re-
                                                                              sion. In an age increasingly
                                           cess, Pataudi believed, was about show-
                                                                              straint feels almost radical. He

                                                                              understood something many for-
                                           ing up and doing the work, whether on a
                                           cricket pitch or a film set.
                                                                              get: dignity doesn’t need an au-
            He didn’t cling to
                                           Reinvention after retirement       dience.
            royalty, cricket, or             After cricket, Pataudi did not fade
            celebrity. He carried          into ceremonial appearances. He became   tributes came from cricketers, actors, ad-
                                                                           ministrators and fans who had never
                                           a respected commentator, selector and
            each lightly, as if            administrator. His analysis was crisp,   seen him play live. That in itself says
                                           sometimes blunt, always informed by
                                                                           something. His influence was not con-
            identity was                   experience. He understood the modern   fined to statistics or highlight reels. It
                                           game without romanticizing his own   lived in tone, in example, in the idea that
            something to be                era.                            leadership could be gentle without being
                                             There was also the quieter reinven-  weak.
            worn comfortably,              tion of domestic life. The Pataudi Pal-  Today’s India, louder and faster, may
                                           ace, once a private royal residence,   seem far removed from his world. Yet
            not announced.”                transformed into a heritage hotel. It was   the need for figures who bridge eras,
                                           a practical decision, but also a symbolic   who show that tradition and progress are
                                           one. The past was not locked away. It   not enemies, feels more urgent than
           mutual respect and shared curiosity.   was shared, adapted, made relevant.   ever.
           Sharmila Tagore continued her work in
           cinema with distinction, while Pataudi   A man comfortable with   Remembering Tiger, beyond the
           remained firmly grounded in sport and   contradiction           roar
           public life. Together, they modeled a   What made Mansoor Ali Khan Pa-  To remember Mansoor Ali Khan Pa-
           partnership that allowed individuality to   taudi compelling was not perfection but   taudi only as Tiger is tempting. The
           breathe.                        balance. He was aristocratic yet acces-  nickname is catchy, heroic. But it is in-
                                           sible. Traditional yet adaptable. Compet-  complete. He was also a thinker, a hus-
           Fatherhood and a new kind of    itive yet calm. He belonged to institu-  band, a father, a reformer in his own un-
           legacy                          tions, cricket boards, royal houses, but   derstated way.
             As a father, Pataudi entered yet   never allowed them to define him en-  Perhaps that is his enduring lesson.
           another role. His children, especially   tirely.                You can live many lives without losing
           Saif Ali Khan, would grow up in a very   He accepted loss with dignity,   yourself. You can carry history without
           different India. Fame came from   whether it was a Test series or political   being trapped by it.
           screens, not scorecards. The public gaze   relevance. He accepted change without   And you can lead, not by raising your
           was sharper, more intrusive.    bitterness. That, perhaps, is the hardest   voice, but by standing steady when
             Pataudi never tried to script their   skill of all.           others are unsure.
           lives. He offered guidance, not direction.                         On Mansoor Ali Khan Pataudi’s birth
           Saif Ali Khan has often spoken about his   The quiet imprint he left behind   anniversary, that feels like a legacy
           father’s honesty, his dry humor, his refu-  When Pataudi passed away in 2011,   worth pausing for. ■

           26                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                 January 01-15, 2026







           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     The year opens with career focus and            Libra, home and emotional grounding matter
                     responsibility. You may feel the weight of      more than external approval. Family conver-
                     expectations, but this is also your chance to lead   sations or domestic decisions may arise. Career
                     with purpose. Avoid rushing personal decisions.   can wait briefly, inner balance cannot. Be care-
                     Patience now brings long-term respect.          ful.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     A broader outlook inspires you. Travel plans,   Scorpio, communication sharpens. Important
                     learning, or spiritual interests call your attention.   messages, meetings, or negotiations move for-
                     Emotionally, you feel steadier than before. Trust   ward. Choose words carefully, they carry lasting
                     that growth doesn’t always need urgency,        impact now. A short journey or reconnection
                     sometimes it needs trust.                       brings insight.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Shared matters, emotional or financial, require   Sagittarius, money and self-worth come into
                     clarity. This is a good time to resolve old misun-  focus. Don’t worry, budgeting and long-term
                     derstandings or reassess commitments. Honest    planning help reduce anxiety. Emotionally,
                     conversations may feel intense, but they        you’re learning to value stability as much as
                     strengthen bonds.                               freedom.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Relationships take the spotlight. You’re learning   Capricorn, this is your season and your reset.
                     the art of balance, between giving and protecting   Personal goals feel clearer and confidence builds
                     your emotional space. A partnership deepens     steadily. Lead with integrity rather than pressure.
                     through empathy and mutual respect. Choose      The year begins on your terms but carelessness
                     calm over reaction.                             can create problem.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Daily routines and work-life balance need atten-  Aquarius, a quiet, introspective phase invites rest
                     tion. You’re building momentum quietly. Health   and emotional housekeeping. Release what no
                     improvements come through small, consistent     longer fits. Solitude now strengthens you for the
                     changes. Recognition follows discipline, not    social momentum ahead. Release all your ten-
                     drama.                                          sions and focus on future plans.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, creativity and emotional warmth return.   Pisces, friends, networks and shared dreams up-
                     Love feels lighter, more genuine. This is a good   lift you shortly. A meaningful connection re-
                     time to reconnect with hobbies, art, or joy     minds you that you’re not alone. Don’t worry, as
                     you’ve postponed. Let pleasure be productive    the year closes, hope feels realistic, not fragile.
                     too.                                            The year ahead begins with self-trust..


           JANUARY 01 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Supreme Court upholds justice
                                           rakhand, India
             The recent order of the Supreme Court

           of India, setting aside the bail granted to
                                                                           remains above commercial interests.

           former legislator Kuldeep Singh Sengar   Suman Srivastava, DehraDun, Utta-  move ensures that the game’s integrity
           by the Allahabad High Court, has been   Questions over uncontested wins   Such decisions strengthen ties between
           widely welcomed across the country.   in BMC polls              cricketing nations and set an inspiring
             The apex court’s intervention has   The recent controversy surrounding   example for all cricket boards. The
           reaffirmed public faith in the justice   the Brihanmumbai Municipal Corpora-  people everywhere have welcomed this
           system, especially in sensitive cases   tion elections has triggered widespread   step as a reflection of fairness and re-
           involving serious crimes and abuse of   concern. Reports suggesting that nearly   spect in global cricket.
           power. Many citizens felt disheartened   70 candidates linked to the National   Ravindra Kumar Sharma, New Delhi,
           when bail was granted despite the gravity   Democratic Alliance were declared   India
           of the offence and its wider social   elected unopposed, allegedly after rival
           implications. The Supreme Court’s firm   candidates withdrew, have raised serious
           stance sends a clear message that   questions about the health of our demo-  Algorithms can’t measure
           influence and political stature cannot   cratic process. Even more troubling are   affection
           dilute accountability.          allegations that hefty sums, reportedly   I read the editorial “When Numbers
             At a time when public trust in   as high as ₹5 crore, were offered to in-  Knock on the Heart’s Door” with inter-
           institutions is often tested, this decision   duce withdrawals.   est and appreciation. The author rightly
           stands as a reminder that justice, though   Democracy thrives on competition,   captures how technology has entered
           sometimes delayed, is not denied.   choice and transparency. When victories   even the most personal spaces of our
           Rajeev Agarwal, Delhi, India    are secured without a contest under a   lives and I agree that it can sometimes
                                           cloud of allegations, public trust inevita-  help people find one another.
                                           bly erodes. Citizens across the country   Yet, I cannot fully agree with the idea
           Supreme Court steps in to protect   have welcomed the demand for a thor-  that numbers can meaningfully guide
           Aravalis                        ough probe, as accountability is essen-  matters of the heart. Coming from a cul-
             The recent order of the Supreme   tial to preserve the sanctity of elections.   ture where relationships are shaped by
           Court of India concerning the protection   It is imperative that authorities inves-  values, patience and emotional respon-
           of the Aravalli Hills has been widely   tigate these claims swiftly and transpar-  sibility, I believe love grows less through
           welcomed by people across the country.   ently, ensuring that electoral processes   calculation and more through lived ex-
           For long, environmentalists and local   remain free, fair and beyond reproach.   perience. Silence, adjustment and shared
           communities have raised concerns over   Vivek Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,   struggle cannot be predicted by data.
           illegal mining, construction and ecologi-  India                   Technology may introduce people,
           cal degradation in this fragile region.                         but commitment and affection still be-
             By reaffirming the need to strictly                           long to the human soul. In other words
           enforce environmental laws, the apex   BCCI’s decision to release   while algorithms may open doors, the
           court has underlined that development   Bangladesh player       heart, guided by culture and conscience,
           cannot come at the cost of irreversible   The decision of the BCCI to release   still decides whom to welcome and why.
           ecological damage. The Aravalis are not   Bangladesh pacer Mustafizur Rahman   Shahid Ali Siddiqui I.R.S. (Retd.) New
           just an ancient mountain range; they act   from his IPL contract so that he may rep-  Delhi, India
           as a natural barrier against desertifica-  resent his national team has been widely
           tion and play a crucial role in maintain-  appreciated by cricket lovers. This ges-
           ing groundwater levels.         ture reflects the BCCI’s respect for inter-  Letters (limited to one hundred
             This timely intervention has restored   national commitments and the true spirit   words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           public faith and sent a strong message   of sportsmanship. Mustafizur is an ex-  Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           that environmental protection is a na-  ceptional talent whose contribution to
           tional priority, not an option.   Bangladesh cricket is immense and this


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           28                                                 www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | JANUARY 01 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Xain Sheikh


                                                        Happy New Year 2026]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>