<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents






                       VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 08  I  APRIL 16 2024      ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             12




                                                            26













                                                            22                                       18















           4-Editorial-The Indian marriage                 22-The clash of values in Indian

           dilemma                                         marriages

           5-The heatwaves may persist longer              26-The enchanting beauty of Thailand
           this time                                       29-Horoscopes

           9-How it shapes India's economy                 30-Letters

           12-The truth about body shaming
           15-Finding balance in the digital age

           18-The return of an analog treasure











           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Tradition vs. Modernity
     EDITORIAL  The Indian                                                         Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           marriage dilemma                                                       Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n the kaleidoscope of Indian culture,   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           marriages stand as a vibrant tapestry
                                        Iwoven with threads of tradition and        Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        modernity. It's a delicate dance between the
                                        values handed down through generations   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        and the evolving dynamics of contemporary    Sushil Kumar
                                        life. As we delve into the heart of Indian
                                        marriages, we find ourselves at the       Social Media Editor
                                        intersection of tradition and modernity,   Vishakha Sharma
                                        where conflicts arise, but so do
                                        opportunities for growth and understanding.   Art & Graphics Director
                                           In traditional Indian marriages, customs   Vipin Agarwal
                                        and rituals hold immense significance,
                                        serving as the cornerstone of familial bonds
           and societal cohesion. From elaborate ceremonies steeped in age-old traditions to
           intricate matchmaking processes guided by familial elders, the essence of tradition   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           permeates every aspect of marital union. However, in the backdrop of this rich
           tapestry, the winds of change blow steadily, ushering in a new era characterized by   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           individualism, autonomy, and the pursuit of personal fulfillment.   Editor, United News of India, New
             The clash of values inherent in Indian marriages reflects the broader societal   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           transition from tradition to modernity. The tension between honoring familial   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           expectations and embracing personal aspirations often manifests in conflicts   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           regarding career choices, gender roles, and lifestyle preferences. Young couples find   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           themselves torn between the reverence for tradition instilled in them since childhood   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           and the desire to chart their own paths in a rapidly changing world.
             Communication becomes the bridge that spans the gap between tradition and   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
           modernity in Indian marriages. Open dialogue, characterized by active listening and   Jamali (Architect)
           empathy, fosters understanding and cultivates mutual respect. Couples learn to
           navigate cultural nuances and negotiate differences with grace and compassion.   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           Moreover, seeking professional guidance through marriage counseling or therapy
           offers couples the tools and insights needed to navigate conflicts effectively and   Phone +91 20 40199102
           strengthen their bonds.                                           Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             Financial considerations add another layer of complexity to the dynamics of   Baner Road,
           tradition and modernity in Indian marriages. While traditional norms may dictate   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           communal financial management and adherence to established roles, modern couples   Email revoir@post.com
           often prioritize financial independence and equitable decision-making. Balancing   Website www.revoir.in
           these contrasting perspectives requires transparency, compromise, and a shared
           commitment to financial well-being.
             Ultimately, the essence of Indian marriages lies in embracing the intersection of   Legal Advisor
           tradition and modernity with grace and resilience. It's about honoring the wisdom of   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           the past while embracing the opportunities of the present. As we navigate the
           complexities of marital life, let us remember that it is in the synthesis of tradition and   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           modernity that we find the true beauty and richness of Indian marriages. It's a journey   all rights reserved. This publication
           of growth, adaptation, and above all, love.                      may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[CLIMATE TECHNOLOGY














































           Alarming Trends


          The heatwaves may







          persist longer this time







           By Aarav Sharma

                 s the world grapples with the   Zhang and his team at Utah State Uni-  moving more slowly, allowing them to
                 consequences of climate   versity, the average duration of heat-  affect larger geographic areas. While
           Achange, a recent analysis span-  waves has increased from eight days to   heatwaves were traditionally associated
           ning over four decades sheds light on   12 days during the specified period.   with specific regions, their impact now
           the alarming intensification of heat-  Moreover, as temperatures continue to   transcends borders as weather systems
           waves globally. Conducted between   rise, projections suggest that by 2060,   responsible for their occurrence shift at
           1979 and 2020, the study reveals a sig-  these heatwaves could endure for as   a reduced pace. The team observed a de-
           nificant and concerning trend: heat-  long as 16 days on average. This prolon-  crease in the speed of heatwave move-
           waves are not only becoming more   gation poses dire consequences for both   ment from about 340 kilometers per day
           frequent but also persisting for longer   human societies and the natural world.   in the 1980s to approximately 280 kilo-
           durations.                        The study indicates that alongside   meters per day presently, with this de-
             According to the findings by Wei   prolonged durations, heatwaves are also   celeration accelerating over time.

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Interestingly, the research also high-  crucial for understanding the spatial dy-  fatalities, but they also exacerbate pre-
           lights regional variations in the move-  namics of heatwaves and formulating ef-  existing social and environmental chal-
           ment of heatwaves. For instance, in Aus-  fective mitigation strategies.   lenges. Studies have shown a correlation
           tralia, these phenomena tend to gravitate   The implications of prolonged and   between prolonged exposure to extreme
           towards the southeast, whereas in South   intensifying heatwaves are profound.   heat and increased hospitalization rates
           America, they exhibit a tendency to   Not only do they pose immediate health   and mortality.
           move northeastward. Such insights are   risks, such as heat-related illnesses and   Furthermore, the impact of rising
                                                                           temperatures extends beyond heatwaves.
                                                                           The article also underscores the link be-
                                                                           tween climate change and other extreme
                                                                           weather events, such as hurricanes,
         Street thermometer displaying the peak temperature
                                                                           which are exhibiting similar patterns of
                                                                           reduced speed and increased duration.
                                                                           This trend amplifies the devastation
                                                                           wrought by these events, leading to pro-
                                                                           longed periods of destruction and recov-
                                                                           ery for affected communities.
                                                                              In light of these findings, urgent ac-
                                                                           tion is imperative to mitigate the effects
                                                                           of climate change and curb further
                                                                           warming. While the study refrains from
                                                                           delving into the causes of these trends,
                                                                           the message is clear: without concerted
                                                                           efforts to address climate change, the
                                                                           frequency and intensity of heatwaves,
                                                                           along with other extreme weather
                                                                           events, will continue to escalate, posing
                                                                           existential threats to human civilization

                                                                             Global city
         Shielding from the scorching sun with an umbrella                   temperatures





                                                                             peak

                                                                             Death Valley (USA): 56.7 degrees
                                                                             Celsius (134 degrees Fahrenheit) on
                                                                             July 10, 1913
                                                                             Ahvaz (Iran): 53.0 degrees Celsius
                                                                             (127.4 degrees Fahrenheit) on June
                                                                             29, 2017
                                                                             Kuwait City (Kuwait): 53.1 de-
                                                                             grees Celsius (127.6 degrees
                                                                             Fahrenheit) on July 31, 2012
                                                                             Tirat Tsvi (Israel): 54.0 degrees
                                                                             Celsius (129.2 degrees Fahrenheit)
                                                                             on June 21, 1942
                                                                             Basra (Iraq): 53.9 degrees Celsius
         Refreshing with a splash to beat the heat                           Celsius (128.3 degrees Fahrenheit)
                                                                             (129.0 degrees Fahrenheit) on Au-
                                                                             gust 14, 2020
                                                                             Turbat (Pakistan): 53.5 degrees
                                                                             on May 28, 2017
                                                                             Mitribah (Kuwait): 54.0 degrees
                                                                             Celsius (129.2 degrees Fahrenheit)
                                                                             on July 21, 2016
                                                                             Bandar-e Mahshahr (Iran): 53.0
                                                                             degrees Celsius (127.4 degrees
                                                                             Fahrenheit) on June 29, 2017



           6                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[India's city

            temperature

            peaks


            New Delhi: 48.4 degrees Celsius
            (119.1 degrees Fahrenheit) on June
            10, 2021                                                                                       Global heatwaves map
            Amritsar: 48.1 degrees Celsius
            (118.6 degrees Fahrenheit) on May
            25, 2018
            Churu: 50.8 degrees Celsius (123.4
            degrees Fahrenheit) on May 19, 2016   and the natural world.   reminder of the extremes to which tem-
            Ganganagar: 50.0 degrees Celsius   Record-Breaking Temperatures and   peratures can soar. From Death Valley in
            (122.0 degrees Fahrenheit) on May   Wildfires: A Global Perspective   the United States to Kuwait City in Ku-
            19, 2016                         The intensification of heatwaves isn't   wait, these records highlight the vulner-
            Jaipur: 48.0 degrees Celsius (118.4   merely a statistical phenomenon—it   ability of diverse ecosystems and human
            degrees Fahrenheit) on May 26, 2016   manifests in record-breaking tempera-  populations to the impacts of rising tem-
            Jaisalmer: 50.0 degrees Celsius   tures across the globe. Major cities and   peratures.
            (122.0 degrees Fahrenheit) on May   regions have witnessed unprecedented   In India, where heatwaves are an an-
            19, 1966                       spikes in mercury levels, underscoring   nual occurrence, recent years have seen
            Phalodi: 51.0 degrees Celsius (123.8   the urgency of addressing climate   temperatures reach alarming heights.
            degrees Fahrenheit) on May 19, 2016   change.                  Cities like New Delhi and Jaipur have
                                             The list of highest recorded tempera-  experienced record-breaking heatwaves,
                                           tures in various cities serves as a stark   resulting in adverse effects on public
                                                                           health and agriculture. The scorching
                                                                           temperatures in regions like Churu and
                                                                           Ganganagar underscore the urgent need
                                                                           for adaptive measures to protect vulner-
                                                                           able communities.
                                                                              The year 2023 witnessed several In-
                                                                           dian cities experiencing exceptionally
         A sweltering summer day in Delhi                                  and Sri Ganganagar topping the list.
                                                                           high temperatures, with Delhi, Churu,
                                                                           These soaring temperatures not only
                                                                           pose immediate health risks but also ex-
                                                                           acerbate challenges such as water scar-
                                                                           city and agricultural stress.
                                                                              The ramifications of rising tempera-
                                                                           tures extend beyond human settlements,
                                                                           contributing to the exacerbation of wild-
                                                                           fires worldwide. From California to
                                                                           Australia, the Mediterranean region to
                                                                           Siberia, these infernos ravage vast ex-
                                                                           panses of land, decimating ecosystems
                                                                           and displacing wildlife. The increasing
                                                                           frequency and intensity of wildfires un-
                                                                           derscore the urgent need for proactive
                                                                           measures to mitigate their impacts and
         Europe is also gripped by heatwaves                               ing temperatures, prolonged heatwaves,
                                                                           address the root causes of climate
                                                                           change.
                                                                              In conclusion, the nexus between ris-

                                                                           and escalating wildfires underscores the
                                                                           urgent need for decisive action to com-
                                                                           bat climate change. As the world grap-
                                                                           ples with the consequences of environ-
                                                                           mental degradation, concerted efforts

                                                                           emissions, enhance resilience, and safe-

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            are required to mitigate greenhouse gas  7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[guard the planet for future generations.   to power outages and increased electric-  resilience to heatwaves.
             Impacts on Human Health and Well-  ity costs.                    Additionally, community-based ini-
           being                             In urban areas, the urban heat island   tiatives, such as heatwave shelters and
             The prolonged duration and in-  effect exacerbates the intensity of heat-  outreach programs, can provide support
           creased frequency of heatwaves have   waves, as built-up environments trap   and resources to those most at risk. Col-
           profound implications for human health   heat and exacerbate temperature ex-  laboration between governments, health-
           and well-being. As temperatures soar to   tremes. Lack of access to cooling infras-  care providers, and community organi-
           record-breaking levels, individuals face   tructure, such as air conditioning, further   zations is essential to develop and
           heightened risks of heat-related illnesses   exacerbates the risks faced by vulner-  implement effective heatwave response
           and fatalities.                 able populations, particularly those liv-  strategies.
             Heatwaves can lead to a range of   ing in low-income neighborhoods.   Ultimately, addressing the root
           health issues, from heat exhaustion and   Furthermore, the psychological toll   causes of climate change is paramount
           heatstroke to cardiovascular and respira-  of heatwaves cannot be overlooked. Ex-  to reducing the frequency and intensity
           tory problems. Vulnerable populations,   treme heat can contribute to stress, anx-  of heatwaves and safeguarding human
           including the elderly, children, and indi-  iety, and mental health issues, particu-  health and well-being. By transitioning
           viduals with pre-existing medical con-  larly among individuals experiencing   to clean energy sources, reducing green-
           ditions, are particularly at risk. Pro-  social isolation or economic hardship.   house gas emissions, and promoting sus-
           longed exposure to extreme heat can   Heatwaves can also disrupt daily life,   tainable development practices, we can
           exacerbate underlying health issues and   limiting outdoor activities and exacer-  mitigate the impacts of climate change
           strain healthcare systems, leading to in-  bating social disparities.   and create a more resilient and equitable
           creased hospitalization rates and mortal-  In light of these impacts, adaptive   future for all. ■
           ity.                            measures are crucial to mitigate the risks
             Moreover, the socio-economic im-  posed by heatwaves. Public health inter-
           pacts of heatwaves are far-reaching. Ag-  ventions, such as heatwave early warn-
           riculture, livestock, and infrastructure   ing systems and heat health action plans,   Areas of
           are vulnerable to the adverse effects of   can help raise awareness and protect
           extreme heat, leading to crop failures,   vulnerable populations. Investments in
                                           green infrastructure, such as urban green
           livestock losses, and disruptions in   spaces and cool roofs, can help mitigate  wildfire
           supply chains. Additionally, heatwaves
           can exacerbate energy demand, leading   the urban heat island effect and enhance
                                                                             incidence

         Street fans provide relief from extreme heat                        fires, especially during hot and dry

                                                                               California, United States: Cali-
                                                                             fornia experiences frequent wild-
                                                                             conditions. Regions like the Sierra
                                                                             Nevada foothills and Southern Cali-
                                                                             fornia are particularly prone to
                                                                             wildfires.
                                                                               Australia: Australia is known
                                                                             for its bushfires, which often occur
                                                                             during hot and dry conditions.
                                                                             Some of the worst bushfire seasons
                                                                             in recent years have affected states
                                                                             like New South Wales and Victoria.
                                                                               Mediterranean Region: Coun-
                                                                             tries like Greece, Spain, Portugal,
                                                                             and Italy often face wildfires during
                                                                             hot summer months due to dry
                                                                             vegetation and strong winds.
                                                                               Amazon Rainforest, Brazil:
         A girl worn out by the hot weather                                  the past, primarily due to deforesta-
                                                                             The Amazon rainforest in Brazil has
                                                                             experienced significant wildfires in
                                                                             tion and dry weather conditions.
                                                                               Siberia, Russia: In recent years,
                                                                             Siberia has seen an increase in wild-
                                                                             fires during hot summer months, at-
                                                                             tributed to rising temperatures and
                                                                             dry conditions.


           8                                                             www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[CLIMATE ECONOMY







































           Climate Crisis



           How it shapes








           India's economy









            By Karan Malhotra

                limate change is a global issue   ploys almost 60% of the workforce. Cli-  cluding Mumbai, Chennai, and Kolkata.
                that has severe consequences for   mate change is expected to have a sig-  Sea-level rise, coastal flooding, and in-
           Cthe economy, environment, and   nificant impact on India’s agricultural   creased storm surges are likely to lead to
           society. It has been certified by the sci-  sector, primarily due to changes in rain-  widespread damage to infrastructure and
           entific community that global warming   fall patterns and increased frequency   properties. This could lead to enormous
           and climate change are real. India is par-  and intensity of extreme weather events,   economic losses and increased eco-
           ticularly vulnerable to the impacts of cli-  including floods and droughts. These   nomic burden on the country.
           mate change, due to its vast and diverse   impacts are likely to result in reduced   Moreover, the health of the Indian
           geography, and its reliance on agricul-  crop yields and increased food insecu-  population is also expected to take a sig-
           ture, which is heavily influenced by   rity in the country, thereby affecting the   nificant hit due to the impacts of climate
           rainfall patterns.              Indian economy as a whole.      change. Climate change is likely to in-
             Agriculture in India accounts for   Climate change is also expected to   crease the incidence of vector-borne dis-
           more than a quarter of the country’s   impact India’s coastal regions, which are   eases, such as dengue fever, chikung-
           gross domestic product (GDP), and em-  home to major cities and industries, in-  unya, and malaria. These diseases, along

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Enhancing public transportation sys-
         Patients hospitalized due to heat-related illnesses               hicles, and improving infrastructure for
                                                                           Sustainable transport
                                                                           tems, promoting electric and hybrid ve-

                                                                           walking and cycling can reduce emis-
                                                                           sions from the transportation sector. Im-
                                                                           plementing policies such as vehicle
                                                                           emission standards, promoting the use
                                                                           of biofuels, and expanding public trans-
                                                                           portation networks can contribute to
                                                                           emission reductions without severely
                                                                           impacting mobility or livelihoods.

                                                                           Sustainable agriculture practices:
                                                                               Promoting sustainable agricultural
                                                                           practices, including organic farming,
           with other heat-related ailments, could   mitigate to make strides in addressing   precision irrigation techniques, and use
           lead to increased burdens on the health-  the issue.            of climate-resilient crop varieties, can
           care system and increased healthcare                            help reduce emissions from the agricul-
           costs, thereby negatively impacting the   Transition to renewable energy   tural sector. Additionally, adopting prac-
           Indian economy.                   India has made significant progress   tices such as agroforestry and efficient
             The impacts of climate change on In-  in renewable energy deployment, par-  livestock management can contribute to
           dia’s economy are significant and far-  ticularly in solar and wind power. Con-  emissions reduction and enhance the re-
           reaching. Reducing emissions and   tinuing to invest in renewable energy in-  silience of farming communities.
           adapting to the unavoidable impacts of   frastructure and promoting their
           climate change are necessary steps to   adoption can significantly reduce emis-  Waste management
           help India mitigate the worst effects of   sions without adversely affecting the   Implementing effective waste man-
           climate change. The Indian government   economy. This transition can create new   agement strategies, including waste seg-
           has recognized the urgency and impor-  job opportunities and foster economic   regation, recycling, composting, and
           tance of addressing climate change, as   growth in the clean energy sector.   waste-to-energy conversion, can miti-
           demonstrated by its commitment to                               gate emissions from landfills. This ap-
           meeting international climate change   Energy efficiency        proach can help address the issue of pol-
           regulations, such as the Paris Agree-  Improving energy efficiency across   lution while also creating employment
           ment. It has also initiated several pro-  industries, buildings, and transportation   opportunities in the waste management
           grams and policies aimed at strengthen-  sectors can lead to substantial emission   sector.
           ing the country’s resilience to climate   reductions. Encouraging the use of
           change impacts, such as promoting re-  energy-efficient technologies, imple-  Green building and urban planning
           newable energy uptake and promoting   menting energy efficiency standards,   Encouraging green building practices
           sustainable agricultural practices.   and providing incentives or subsidies to   and sustainable urban planning can lead
             In conclusion, the effect of climate   promote energy-efficient practices can   to energy-efficient buildings, reduced
           change on the Indian economy is signifi-  help achieve this goal. Energy-efficient   energy consumption, and lower emis-
           cant and should be taken seriously. India   measures can also result in cost savings   sions. Implementing building codes,
           would need to continue to adapt and   for businesses and households.   providing incentives for green building
                                                                           certifications, and incorporating sustain-
                                                                           able design principles in urban planning
                                                                           can facilitate emission reductions with-
                                                                           out negatively impacting construction or
                                                                           urban development.
                                                                                Increasing awareness about the im-
                                                                           Public awareness and
         Urban area flooded during heavy rainfall                          portance of emissions reduction and the
                                                                           engagement

                                                                           benefits of sustainable practices can
                                                                           foster a positive mindset towards cli-
                                                                           mate action. Promoting public participa-
                                                                           tion, engaging communities, and provid-
                                                                           ing education and training programs can
                                                                           empower individuals to adopt sustain-
                                                                           able lifestyles and support emission re-
                                                                           duction efforts.
                                                                              It is crucial to prioritize a just transi-

           10                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[India's climate
                                                                            resilience initiatives
         Waste management techniques                                        ience against climate change through
                                                                               India has embarked on a multi-
                                                                            faceted approach to bolster its resil-

                                                                            various initiatives. At the core of this
                                                                            strategy lies the National Action Plan
                                                                            on Climate Change (NAPCC), which
                                                                            delineates eight missions targeting
                                                                            specific areas like solar energy,

                                                                            ture, water conservation, and bio-
           tion approach, ensuring that vulnerable   nities for farmers to access new markets,   energy efficiency, sustainable agricul-
                                                                            diversity.
           communities and sectors are supported   increase their income, and improve their   In collaboration with France, India
           in the process. Policy measures, finan-  livelihoods. Government agencies can   spearheaded the International Solar
           cial incentives, and support mechanisms   support such initiatives by providing ac-  Alliance (ISA) to propagate solar
           can help mitigate any negative impacts   cess to reliable market data, facilitating   energy adoption worldwide, aiming
           on livelihoods, ensuring a fair and inclu-  connections with potential buyers, and   to mobilize investment, curtail solar
           sive transition to a low-carbon economy.   creating value chains for sustainable ag-  power costs, and facilitate its deploy-
           By adopting a holistic approach and in-  ricultural products.    ment in developing nations.
           tegrating sustainability into various sec-                          The Pradhan Mantri Kisan Sam-
           tors, India can reduce emissions while   Stable agri-prices      pada Yojana (PMKSY) serves as a
           promoting economic growth and en-  The government can ensure stable   cornerstone program, endeavoring to
           hancing people's well-being.    and fair prices for sustainable agricul-  modernize India's food processing
                                           ture products to promote their adoption   sector while promoting sustainable
           Balancing sustainable agriculture   without negatively impacting the   agricultural practices, minimizing
           and farmer livelihoods          farmers. The introduction of Minimum   food wastage, and augmenting
             The transition to sustainable agricul-  Support Price(MSP) is one such initia-  farmers' income through value ad-
           tural practices in India can contribute to   tive by the government but it needs to be   dition and market connectivity.
           reducing greenhouse gas (GHG) emis-  implemented effectively to ensure its ef-  For adaptation endeavors, the Na-
           sions and enhancing the resilience of   fectiveness.             tional Adaptation Fund for Climate
           farming communities. While this transi-                          Change (NAFCC) channels dedicated
           tion is essential, it is crucial to ensure   Risk mitigation     resources to vulnerable sectors and
           that it does not have any negative im-  Climate variability and extreme   regions, fostering initiatives like
           pacts on farmers' livelihoods and income   weather events can adversely impact   water resource management, agricul-
           stability. Here are some ways the gov-  farmers' livelihoods. The government   ture resilience, and coastal safeguard-
           ernment can address these concerns:   can consider implementing crop and   ing.
                                           weather insurance schemes to mitigate   Addressing deforestation and eco-
           Supporting capacity building and   the risks associated with such events.   system restoration, the Green India
           technical assistance            Additionally, disaster management plans   Mission (GIM) endeavors to expand
             The government can provide adequ-  and early warning systems can be imple-  forest cover, rejuvenate degraded
           ate technical and financial support to   mented to reduce the impact of extreme   ecosystems, and enhance biodiversity
           farmers through capacity building pro-  weather events.          conservation and ecosystem services.
           grams, training, and education pro-                                 Efforts towards energy efficiency
           grams. Such initiatives can equip   Farmer participation and     are consolidated under the National
           farmers with knowledge and skills to   involvement               Mission for Enhanced Energy Effi-
           adopt sustainable practices and enhance   It is essential to involve farmers in   ciency (NMEEE), which targets in-
           their productivity and profitability.   the policymaking process related to the   dustries, buildings, and agriculture
                                           transition to sustainable agriculture   through schemes like the Perform,
           Financial incentives            practices. Farmers should be made   Achieve, and Trade (PAT) initiative.
             Providing financial incentives and   aware of the benefits of sustainable   To combat air pollution, the Na-
           subsidies for sustainable farming prac-  practices and should be provided with a   tional Clean Air Programme (NCAP)
           tices can encourage farmers to adopt   platform to share their experiences and   undertakes a comprehensive ap-
           them. For example, the government can   challenges. Their feedback and input   proach, encompassing emission re-
           consider offering incentives for adopting   should be considered in policy formula-  duction measures across transporta-
           organic farming or climate-resilient crop   tion.                tion, industry, and households,
           varieties.                        These measures can help promote the   alongside intensified monitoring and
                                           transition to sustainable agriculture   awareness campaigns, all aimed at
           Market support                  practices without negatively impacting   ameliorating air quality in Indian
             Creating a market for sustainable ag-  farmers' livelihoods and income stabil-  cities.
           ricultural products can provide opportu-  ity. ■

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[PERSONAL DEVELOPMENT














































           Breaking the Chains




           The truth







           about body shaming








           By Naina Kapoor


             n today's image-centric society, the   their physical appearance, perpetuating   Understanding Body Shaming: Body
             pervasive issue of body shaming   harmful beauty standards and unrealis-  shaming encompasses a wide spectrum
           Ihas become a deeply ingrained cul-  tic ideals. In this comprehensive explo-  of behaviors and attitudes aimed at crit-
           tural phenomenon, permeating various   ration, we delve deeper into the multi-  icizing or belittling individuals based
           facets of life and leaving a trail of emo-  faceted nature of body shaming, its   on their physical attributes. Weight-
           tional turmoil and societal pressure in   profound impact on mental and physi-  based shaming is perhaps the most
           its wake. From subtle remarks to overt   cal health, and the imperative need to   prevalent manifestation, with individ-
           discrimination, individuals continually   foster a culture of acceptance and body   uals subjected to ridicule and discrim-
           face scrutiny and judgment based on   positivity.               ination for being perceived as too thin

           12                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[or too heavy. This weight-centric focus   color, facial features, and physical dis-  to relentless scrutiny and pressure to
           perpetuates harmful stereotypes and   abilities. These aspects of appearance   conform to unattainable beauty stan-
           fosters a culture of diet culture obses-  are often subject to societal scrutiny   dards perpetuated by the media's ide-
           sion, leading to the normalization of   and discrimination, further exacerbating   alization of thinness and flawless fea-
           disordered eating behaviors and un-  feelings of inadequacy, self-doubt, and   tures. On the other hand, men face a
           healthy body image perceptions. Fur-  alienation.               distinct set of expectations, often pres-
           thermore, appearance-based shaming   Gender also plays a significant role   sured to achieve muscular ideals that
           extends beyond weight to encompass   in body shaming, albeit in different   reinforce toxic masculinity and contrib-
           various aspects such as height, skin   ways. Women are frequently subjected   ute to body dysmorphia. These gender-
                                                                           specific expectations fuel a culture of
                                                                           comparison and competition, where in-
                                                                           dividuals strive to attain an unrealistic
                                                                           and often unattainable physical ideal,
                                                                           perpetuating feelings of inadequacy and
                                                                           worthlessness.
                                                                              The Impact of Body Shaming: The
                                                                           consequences of body shaming extend
         A confident girl gazing into the mirror                           ing undermines self-esteem, eroding
                                                                           far beyond superficial critiques, deeply
                                                                           impacting individuals' mental and phys-
                                                                           ical well-being. At its core, body sham-

                                                                           one's sense of self-worth and perpetu-
                                                                           ating feelings of inadequacy, shame,
                                                                           and unworthiness. This constant barrage
                                                                           of criticism can lead to body dys-
                                                                           morphic disorder, a debilitating mental
                                                                           health condition characterized by obses-
                                                                           sive thoughts about perceived flaws in
                                                                           appearance and compulsive behaviors
                                                                           aimed at altering one's body to meet so-
                                                                           cietal standards.
                                                                              Moreover, body shaming is a signifi-
                                                                           cant contributing factor to the devel-
                                                                           opment of eating disorders, such as an-
                                                                           orexia nervosa, bulimia nervosa, and
         A girl contemplating her weight                                   individuals to extreme measures, risk-
                                                                           binge-eating disorder. The pressure to
                                                                           attain an idealized body image drives
                                                                           ing their health and well-being in pur-
                                                                           suit of an unattainable goal. Beyond the
                                                                           physical consequences, body shaming
                                                                           also takes a profound toll on mental
                                                                           health, contributing to depression, anx-
                                                                           iety, and other mood disorders. The
                                                                           emotional distress caused by constant
                                                                           criticism and judgment can lead to feel-
                                                                           ings of isolation, despair, and even sui-
                                                                           cidal ideation, further perpetuating a vi-
                                                                           cious cycle of self-loathing and
                                                                           self-destructive behaviors.
                                                                              Combatting Body Shaming: Ad-
                                                                           dressing the pervasive issue of body
                                                                           shaming requires a multifaceted ap-
                                                                           proach, involving individuals, com-
                                                                           munities, and society at large. Promot-
                                                                           ing body positivity is paramount,
                                                                           celebrating diversity and challenging
                                                                           narrow beauty standards. By embracing
                                                                           the inherent beauty of all body types
         A girl jogging                                                    tion, we can create a more inclusive
                                                                           and rejecting harmful notions of perfec-
                                                                           and accepting environment where every
                                                                           individual feels valued, accepted, and

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[respected for who they are, regardless   struggling with body image issues. By   programs that emphasize body positiv-
           of their physical appearance.   promoting media literacy and critical   ity and self-acceptance can empower
             Education and awareness are essen-  thinking skills, individuals can chal-  individuals to cultivate healthy relation-
           tial tools in the fight against body   lenge unrealistic beauty ideals and de-  ships with their bodies and reject harm-
           shaming, dispelling myths and miscon-  mand more diverse representation in   ful societal norms that perpetuate body
           ceptions and fostering empathy and   advertising, entertainment, and fashion.   shaming and discrimination.
           compassion towards those who may be   Moreover, comprehensive sex education   Self-care is also crucial in combat-
                                                                           ting body shaming, empowering indi-
                                                                           viduals to prioritize their mental and
                                                                           physical well-being. Practicing self-
                                                                           compassion, mindfulness, and healthy
                                                                           habits can help individuals cultivate re-
                                                                           silience and self-confidence in the face
                                                                           of societal pressure and criticism. Sur-
                                                                           rounding oneself with supportive
                                                                           friends, family, and communities can
                                                                           also provide valuable validation and af-
                                                                           firmation in times of doubt and insecu-
                                                                           rity, fostering a sense of belonging and
                                                                           acceptance that is essential for mental
         Ageism                                                            and emotional well-being.
                                                                              Seeking professional help is impera-
                                                                           tive for those struggling with body
                                                                           image issues or eating disorders. Ther-
                                                                           apy, support groups, and online re-
                                                                           sources can provide invaluable support
                                                                           and guidance, helping individuals navi-
                                                                           gate the complex emotions and chal-
                                                                           lenges associated with body shaming.
         Body shaming for being exceptionally thin                         receives the support and care they need
                                                                           By destigmatizing mental health treat-
                                                                           ment and promoting access to re-
                                                                           sources, we can ensure that everyone

                                                                           to heal and thrive, breaking free from
                                                                           the shackles of self-doubt and self-ha-
                                                                           tred and embracing their inherent worth
                                                                           and beauty.
                                                                              In conclusion, body shaming is a
                                                                           pervasive societal issue that undermines
                                                                           individual dignity and perpetuates
                                                                           harmful beauty standards and unrealis-
                                                                           tic ideals. By fostering a culture of ac-
                                                                           ceptance, empathy, and body positivity,
                                                                           we can dismantle the toxic norms that
                                                                           fuel body shaming and create a world
                                                                           where every body is valued and re-
                                                                           spected. Let us celebrate the beauty of
                                                                           diversity and embrace the inherent
                                                                           worth of all individuals, free from the
                                                                           shackles of judgment and comparison.
                                                                           Together, we can build a more inclusive
                                                                           and compassionate society where every
                                                                           body is free to shine, empowered to
                                                                           embrace their uniqueness and live au-
         Engagement in physical activity                                   body shaming by promoting accept-
                                                                           thentically and unapologetically.
                                                                              Finally, it's imperative to combat
                                                                           ance, empathy, and body positivity. By
                                                                           challenging harmful beauty standards
                                                                           and embracing diversity, we empower
                                                                           individuals to thrive authentically and
                                                                           unapologetically in a more inclusive so-
                                                                           ciety. ■

           14                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[HEALTH & SCIENCE













































           Tech Addiction




           Finding balance in the







           digital age







           By Siddharth Mehta


             n today's rapidly evolving digital   tential strategies for managing and over-  of addictive behaviors, such as exces-
             age, technology has become an inte-  coming it.               sive smartphone use, social media add-
           Igral part of our daily lives, offering                         iction, online gaming addiction, and in-
           convenience, connectivity, and enter-  Understanding technology   ternet addiction.
           tainment. However, with its pervasive   addiction
           presence, the dark side of excessive   Technology addiction refers to the   Causes of technology addiction
           technology usage, commonly known as   compulsive and excessive usage of digi-  Several factors contribute to the de-
           technology addiction, has emerged as a   tal devices and online platforms that in-  velopment of technology addiction:
           concerning issue. This article delves   terferes with an individual's daily activ-  Instant Gratification: The instant ac-
           into the concept of technology add-  ities, relationships, and overall   cess to information, entertainment, and
           iction, its causes, consequences, and po-  well-being. It encompasses a wide range   social connections provided by technol-

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Common signs

                                                                            or symptoms
         Every member engrossed in their mobile phones                      Constantly thinking about using digi-
                                                                               Preoccupation with technology:

                                                                            tal devices, social media, or online
                                                                            entertainment instead of focusing on
                                                                            daily activities.
                                                                               Losing track of time while using
                                                                            technology: Spending hours on a de-
                                                                            vice, online platform, or social media
                                                                            without realizing how much time has
                                                                            passed.
                                                                               Neglecting responsibilities: Fail-
                                                                            ing to meet academic, professional,
                                                                            or personal obligations due to exces-
                                                                            sive technology use.
                                                                               Withdrawal symptoms: Experi-
         Repetitive daily routines may indicate technology addiction
                                                                            encing anxiety, irritability, or depres-
                                                                            sion when not using technology.
                                                                               Physical symptoms: Experienc-
                                                                            ing fatigue, eye strain, back pain, or
                                                                            other physical discomforts due to
                                                                            prolonged screen time.
                                                                               Difficulty concentrating: Experi-
                                                                            encing difficulty concentrating or re-
                                                                            maining focused due to constant in-
                                                                            terruptions from technology.
                                                                               Social isolation or relationship
                                                                            problems: Neglecting real-life rela-
                                                                            tionships, social interactions, or ac-
                                                                            tivities due to excessive technology
                                                                            use.
                                                                               Denial or defensiveness: Becom-
                                                                            ing defensive or denying excessive
                                                                            technology use when confronted by
                                                                            family, friends, or loved ones.
           ogy fuels the desire for immediate satis-  pression, sleep disturbances, and de-  It's important to note that experi-
           faction, making it easy to develop add-  creased attention spans. It can also exac-  encing one or two of these symptoms
           ictive habits.                  erbate existing mental health conditions.   doesn't necessarily indicate technol-
             Dopamine Response: The brain's re-  Impaired Relationships: Long   ogy addiction. However, if someone
           ward system is stimulated by technol-  hours spent on devices can strain per-  exhibits multiple signs and finds it
           ogy, triggering the release of dopamine,   sonal relationships, leading to communi-  challenging to control their technol-
           a neurotransmitter associated with   cation gaps, emotional disconnection,   ogy usage, it may be worth seeking
           pleasure and reinforcement. This re-  and neglect of real-life interactions.   help to address the issue.
           inforces the addictive behavior, leading   Academic and Professional Chal-
           to a continuous craving for more.   lenges: Technology addiction can ad-
             Escapism and Loneliness: Technol-  versely affect academic and professional   help individuals regain control over their
           ogy can provide an escape from daily   performance, compromising productiv-  technology usage
           stress, loneliness, and boredom. This   ity, focus, and time management skills.   Establish Healthy Boundaries: Set
           makes individuals more susceptible to   Physical Health Problems: Sedentary   limits on screen time and create des-
           seeking solace in the digital world,   lifestyles resulting from excessive   ignated device-free zones or hours.
           eventually leading to addiction.   screen time can contribute to obesity,   Gradually reduce usage to find a health-
                                           musculoskeletal issues, eye strain, and   ier balance.
           Consequences of technology      other physical health complications.   Practice Mindfulness: Engage in
           addiction                                                       mindful activities such as meditation,
             Technology addiction can have sig-                            exercise, hobbies, or spending time in
           nificant negative impacts on various as-  Managing and Overcoming   nature to develop a more balanced ap-
           pects of life:                  Technology Addiction            proach to technology.
             Mental Health Issues: Excessive   Recognizing the signs of technology   Seek Social Support: Connect with
           technology use can lead to anxiety, de-  addiction and taking proactive steps can   friends, family, or support groups to dis-

           16                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[cuss concerns and share strategies for
           managing technology use.
             Digital Detox: Take intentional
           breaks from technology, dedicating spe-
           cific periods for offline activities and
           building face-to-face relationships.
             Seek Professional Help: If addiction
           symptoms persist, consider seeking sup-
           port from mental health professionals                                                           Becoming enslaved to technology happens quickly
           specializing in technology addiction.

           Technology addiction in kids
             Excessive Preoccupation: If a child
           consistently talks, thinks, or expresses a
           strong desire about using digital de-
           vices, video games, or online platforms,
           to the point where it interferes with their
           daily routine and activities, it could be a   addiction issue.   changes in mood, irritability, or emo-
           sign of technology addiction.     Social Isolation: If a child with-  tional disturbances when the child is un-
             Neglected Responsibilities: Ne-  draws from real-life social interactions,   able to access technology or if you try
           glecting schoolwork, chores, or other re-  preferring to spend excessive amounts   to limit their usage can be signs of add-
           sponsibilities due to excessive technol-  of time alone with digital devices rather   iction.
           ogy use is a red flag. If a child   than engaging in activities or connecting   Physical and Health Changes: Ex-
           consistently prioritizes screen time over   with peers, it may indicate a problem.   cessive screen time can lead to physical
           other essential tasks, it may indicate an   Emotional Distress: Noticeable   symptoms such as poor posture, fatigue,
                                                                           sleep disturbances, and decreased physi-
                                                                           cal activity. If you observe these
                                                                           changes in a child, it is important to ad-
                                                                           dress their technology use.
         Limiting technology can help overcome addiction                   technology use, it may suggest an un-
                                                                              Loss of Interest in Other Activ-
                                                                           ities: If a child loses interest in pre-
                                                                           viously enjoyed hobbies, outdoor activ-
                                                                           ities, or social engagements in favor of
                                                                           healthy attachment to digital devices.
                                                                              Resistance to Limits: Persistent re-
                                                                           sistance, defiance, or agitation when at-
                                                                           tempts are made to set boundaries or
                                                                           limit technology use may indicate an
                                                                           addiction issue.
                                                                              It's important to approach the issue
                                                                           with empathy and open communication
                                                                           with children. If you suspect technology
                                                                           addiction in a child, it may be helpful to
                                                                           consult with a healthcare professional or
                                                                           a mental health specialist who special-
                                                                           izes in child psychology to evaluate and
                                                                           address the problem effectively.
                                                                              While technology addiction is a
                                                                           growing concern in today's society, it is
                                                                           crucial to acknowledge its impact and
         Technology addiction in today's society                           ing balance, and prioritizing real-life in-
                                                                           take proactive steps to prevent and man-
                                                                           age it. By consciously establishing
                                                                           healthier technology usage habits, seek-

                                                                           teractions, individuals can regain control
                                                                           over their lives and create a healthier re-
                                                                           lationship with technology.
                                                                              Let us embrace the benefits of tech-
                                                                           nology while being mindful of its poten-
                                                                           tial addictive nature, ensuring a well-

                                                                           digital age. ■

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            rounded and fulfilling existence in the  17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[ENTERTAINMENT












































           Vinyl Records Resurgence



           The return of an








           analog treasure









            By Anaya Gupta

             n an era dominated by digital   has had on the music industry, highlight-  have attracted a growing number of au-
             streaming and music downloads, the   ing its connection to the Bollywood in-  diophiles and music collectors. The
           Ihumble vinyl record is experiencing   dustry in India.         crackling sound and imperfections that
           a remarkable resurgence. The warm, rich                         often accompany vinyl playback only
           sound of vinyl, coupled with its tangible   The analog charm:   add to its charm, creating an immersive
           and nostalgic appeal, has captured the   Vinyl records offer a unique audio   and authentic listening experience.
           hearts of music enthusiasts around the   experience that cannot be replicated by
           world. This article explores the resur-  digital formats. The warmth and depth   The vinyl comeback:
           gence of vinyl records and the impact it   of the sound produced by vinyl records   The resurgence of vinyl can be attrib-

           18                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[A vinyl record enthusiast in a store














                                                                           uted to various factors. One major rea-
                                                                           son is the nostalgic appeal it holds for
                                                                           older generations who grew up with
                                                                           vinyl records as their primary medium
                                                                           for music consumption. The tangible na-
                                                                           ture of vinyl records, with their large
                                                                           album covers and physical presence,
                                                                           connects listeners to the music in a way
                                                                           that digital files cannot.
                                                                              Additionally, younger generations
                                                                           have also been drawn to vinyl records,
                                                                           attracted by the unique experience they
                                                                           offer. The rise of vinyl gifting and the
                                                                           aesthetic appeal of vinyl collections
                                                                           have contributed to its renewed popular-
                                                                           ity among millennials and Gen Z.

                                                                           The Bollywood connection:
                                                                              India, with its vibrant and culturally
                                                                           diverse film industry known as Bolly-
                                                                           wood, has not been left untouched by
                                                                           the resurgence of vinyl records. Bolly-
                                                                           wood music, with its wide range of gen-
         Indulging in the music of vinyl records                           music lovers.
                                                                           res and iconic film soundtracks, has a
                                                                           nostalgic connection to many Indian

                                                                              Vinyl records have become a collec-
                                                                           tor's item for Bollywood enthusiasts,
                                                                           who treasure the original soundtracks of
                                                                           classic films. The vinyl format provides
                                                                           a sense of authenticity and nostalgia, al-
                                                                           lowing listeners to connect with the

                                                                           not replicate. The unique album art and

                                                                                                       19
           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            music in a way that digital formats can-]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Iconic Bollywood

            soundtracks
            reissued on vinyl


              "Aashiqui" (1990) - The sound-
            track of this romantic drama, com-
            posed by Nadeem-Shravan, became                                                                Youngsters show interest in purchasing new vinyl records
            a sensation. The vinyl reissue of
            "Aashiqui" includes evergreen
            tracks like "Dheere Dheere Se" and
            "Nazar Ke Samne."
              "Dilwale Dulhania Le Jay-
            enge" (1995) - This iconic film's
            soundtrack, composed by Jatin-
            Lalit, captured the hearts of mil-
            lions. The vinyl reissue features be-
            loved songs like "Tujhe Dekha Toh"
            and "Mere Khwabon Mein."
              "Hum Aapke Hain Koun..!"
            (1994) - The musical extravaganza
            of this family drama, composed by
            Raamlaxman, is still cherished by
            fans. The vinyl reissue includes
            chart-toppers like "Didi Tera Devar
            Deewana" and "Joote Do Paise Lo."
              "Kabhi Kabhie" (1976) - This
            romantic drama's soundtrack, com-
            posed by Khayyam, is considered a                                                              Limited edition vinyl releases are highly sought after
            classic. The vinyl reissue features
            melodies like "Kabhi Kabhie Mere
            Dil Mein" and "Main Pal Do Pal Ka
            Shayar Hoon."
              "Guide" (1965) - The sound-
            track of this drama film, composed
            by S.D. Burman, is renowned for its
            soulful melodies. The vinyl reissue
            includes iconic tracks like "Aaj Phir   ing classic Bollywood soundtracks on   where they reissue classic Bollywood
            Jeene Ki Tamanna Hai" and "Tere   vinyl, tapping into the growing demand   soundtracks on vinyl, ensuring that the
            Mere Sapne."                   from collectors and enthusiasts. This has   magic of these songs lives on.
              "Rangeela" (1995) - This in-  not only generated revenue for the in-  HMV Saregama: HMV Saregama, a
            fluential film's soundtrack, com-  dustry but also rekindled interest in   collaboration between Saregama and the
            posed by A.R. Rahman, revolution-  older music.                HMV record label, has been instrumen-
            ized Bollywood music. The vinyl   Independent artists and niche genres   tal in releasing vinyl reissues of Bolly-
            reissue includes peppy tracks like   have also benefited from the vinyl re-  wood classics. They have an extensive
            "Tanha Tanha" and "Hai Rama."   vival. With the ability to produce lim-  collection of vinyl records, including
              These are just a few examples   ited-edition runs of vinyl records, artists   iconic soundtracks from the golden era
            among many Bollywood sound-    have found a new way to connect with   of Hindi cinema.
            tracks that have been reissued on   their audience and monetize their music.   Odeon Records: Odeon Records has
            vinyl.                         This has led to a diverse and thriving   gained prominence as a vinyl record
                                           vinyl ecosystem, encompassing both   label specializing in reissues of Bolly-
                                           mainstream and niche genres in the Bol-  wood music. Their releases often in-
           liner notes of Bollywood vinyl records   lywood industry.       clude sought-after soundtracks from dif-
           add to the overall experience, making it                        ferent eras, allowing collectors and
           a cherished possession for fans.   Bollywood vinyl reissue      enthusiasts to add these gems to their
                                           specialists                     vinyl collections.
           Impact on the music industry:     Saregama: Saregama is a well-known   Bombay Connection: Bombay Con-
             The resurgence of vinyl records has   Indian music label that has been at the   nection is a Netherlands-based record
           had a significant impact on the music in-  forefront of preserving and promoting   label that focuses on releasing vintage
           dustry as a whole, including Bollywood.   Bollywood music. They have a ded-  Bollywood music on vinyl. They have
           Major record labels have started reissu-  icated section called "Music on Vinyl"   preserved and reissued rare soundtracks,

           20                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Enhanced
         Needle delicately touching the grooves of a vinyl record
                                                                             Bollywood vinyl

                                                                             reissues

                                                                               Remastered sound quality:
                                                                             Many vinyl reissues of Bollywood
                                                                             soundtracks offer remastered sound
                                                                             quality to enhance the listening ex-
                                                                             perience, especially for old and rare
                                                                             compositions. These reissues often
                                                                             come with new pressings, with su-
                                                                             perior mastering technology, which
                                                                             result in better sound clarity and
                                                                             overall listening pleasure.
                                                                               Limited edition and collectibil-
                                                                             ity: Vinyl reissues of Bollywood
                                                                             soundtracks may come in limited-
                                                                             edition pressings that increase their
                                                                             collectibility. Limited edition re-
                                                                             leases are often pressed in relatively
                                                                             small numbers, making them more
                                                                             unique and valuable for collectors.
                                                                               Album art and design: The art-
                                                                             work and design of a vinyl release
                                                                             are an important aspect for many
                                                                             collectors. Reissues of Bollywood
                                                                             soundtracks often come with beauti-
                                                                             fully-designed album art and pack-
                                                                             aging, which make them attractive
                                                                             to collectors as pieces of visual art.
                                                                               Inserts and booklets: Vinyl reis-
         An old-style gramophone, now a memory                               booklets that offer additional infor-
                                                                             sues of Bollywood soundtracks may
                                                                             come with additional inserts and
                                                                             mation and insights into the music
                                                                             and artists. These may include inter-
                                                                             views, rare photographs, behind-
                                                                             the-scenes insights, and other his-
                                                                             torical context that provides a
                                                                             deeper appreciation of the music.
                                                                               Bonus tracks and alternate
                                                                             takes: Some vinyl reissues of Bol-
                                                                             lywood soundtracks may feature
                                                                             previously unreleased bonus tracks
           offering a glimpse into the diverse musi-  dulge in the nostalgia and relive the   or alternate takes, which provide a
           cal heritage of Hindi cinema.   magic of Bollywood music.         new and unique listening experience
             Vinyl India: Vinyl India is a record   The resurrection of vinyl records in   for fans. Collectors often seek these
           label based in India that predominantly   the digital age is a testament to the en-  rare and exclusive tracks to add to
           focuses on reissuing Bollywood sound-  during power of analog and nostalgia.   their collections.
           tracks on vinyl. They have a wide selec-  The unique audio experience, coupled   Overall, vinyl record reissues of
           tion of vintage and contemporary Bolly-  with the tangible nature of vinyl, has   Bollywood soundtracks offer many
           wood albums, appealing to both   won the hearts of music lovers world-  additional features and bonuses that
           seasoned vinyl collectors and new en-  wide. In India, the Bollywood industry   appeal to collectors and enthusiasts
           thusiasts.                      has embraced the vinyl revival, reissu-  beyond just sound quality. From
             These are just a few examples of   ing classic soundtracks and tapping into   limited editions to stunning album
           vinyl record labels and companies that   the growing interest from collectors. As   art, inserts, and bonus tracks, these
           specialize in reissuing Bollywood   vinyl continues to captivate old and new   reissues are highly valued and
           soundtracks. Each label has its own   generations alike, it is clear that this an-  sought after by passionate collec-
           unique catalog, offering a treasure trove   alog treasure has found its place in the   tors.
           of vinyl records that allow fans to in-  modern music landscape. ■

           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[MARITAL ISSUES












































           BRIDGING TRADITION AND MODERNITY



           The clash of values in







           Indian marriages






           By Rajeev Khanna



                  arriage, an institution revered   of sources. Understanding these con-  modernity. While traditional values em-
                  in Indian society, is often per-  flicts and learning how to navigate them   phasize familial harmony and duty to-
           Mceived as a union of souls     is crucial for fostering healthy and en-  wards elders, modern lifestyles often
           bound by love, respect, and understand-  during relationships.   prioritize individual freedom and per-
           ing. However, beneath the surface of   Understanding the Dynamics: Con-  sonal aspirations. This clash of values
           these blissful unions lie the complexities   flicts in Indian marriages can be attrib-  can lead to conflicts, especially in
           of human relationships, including con-  uted to various factors, ranging from   matters concerning career choices,
           flicts. In the diverse landscape of India,   cultural differences and societal expecta-  family planning, and gender roles.
           where cultural, social, and economic dy-  tions to financial pressures and com-  Communication breakdowns also
           namics vary significantly, conflicts in   munication gaps. One significant aspect   contribute significantly to marital con-
           married couples can stem from a myriad   is the interplay between tradition and   flicts. In many Indian households, open

           22                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[discussions about emotions and personal
           issues are often discouraged, leading to
           pent-up frustrations and misunderstand-
           ings. Moreover, cultural norms regard-
           ing gender roles may hinder effective
           communication, with women sometimes
           feeling unheard or marginalized in deci-
           sion-making processes.
             Financial stress is another common
           source of conflict in Indian marriages.
           Economic instability, debt, and disparity
           in financial goals can strain relationships
           and lead to disagreements about spend-
           ing habits, savings, and long-term finan-                                                       A contemporary Indian couple
           cial planning. Moreover, the pressure to
           conform to societal expectations, such
           as extravagant wedding expenses and
           dowry customs, can exacerbate financial
           tensions within families.
             Cultural and societal expectations   compatibility, resulting in marital dis-  may feel torn between traditional roles
           also play a significant role in shaping   cord. Moreover, societal pressures to   and personal aspirations. Navigating
           marital conflicts. Arranged marriages,   conform to gender norms and fulfill   Conflict:
           still prevalent in many parts of India,   familial obligations can create internal
           can sometimes lead to mismatches in   conflicts, especially for women who   Effective communication
                                                                              Addressing conflicts in Indian mar-
                                                                           riages requires a holistic approach that
                                                                           acknowledges cultural nuances while
                                                                           promoting individual autonomy and mu-
                                                                           tual respect. Effective communication is
         Conflicts escalate with decreased communication                   ment for expressing emotions, concerns,
                                                                           paramount in resolving conflicts and
                                                                           strengthening marital bonds. Couples
                                                                           should create a safe and open environ-

                                                                           and needs without fear of judgment or
                                                                           reprisal. Active listening and empathy
                                                                           are essential skills that can foster under-
                                                                           standing and promote compromise.

                                                                           Seeking professional guidance
                                                                              Couples can also benefit from seek-
                                                                           ing professional guidance through coun-
                                                                           seling or therapy. Marriage counseling
                                                                           provides a neutral space for couples to
                                                                           explore underlying issues, improve com-
                                                                           munication skills, and develop strategies
                                                                           for conflict resolution. Additionally,
                                                                           couples can participate in workshops or
                                                                           support groups that focus on relationship
         Gratitude and appreciation can mitigate conflicts                 boundaries is crucial for managing con-
                                                                           building and personal growth.

                                                                           Setting realistic expectations and
                                                                           boundaries
                                                                              Setting realistic expectations and
                                                                           flicts and maintaining healthy bound-
                                                                           aries. Couples should openly discuss
                                                                           their values, goals, and priorities, and
                                                                           work towards finding common ground.
                                                                           Flexibility and compromise are essential
                                                                           in navigating cultural differences and

                                                                           context of marriage.


                                                                                                       23
           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            negotiating individual needs within the]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Practicing stress management and self-care can be beneficial.
                                                                           care are essential for maintaining emo-
                                                                           tional well-being and resilience in mar-
                                                                           riage. Couples should support each other
                                                                           in coping with external stressors and
                                                                           find healthy outlets for relaxation and
                                                                           rejuvenation. Taking time for self-reflec-
                                                                           tion and self-care can strengthen indi-
                                                                           vidual mental health and enhance mari-
                                                                           tal satisfaction.

                                                                           Continuous learning and growth
                                                                              Finally, fostering a growth mindset
                                                                           and a willingness to learn and adapt is
                                                                           crucial for the long-term success of a
                                                                           marriage. Couples should approach con-
                                                                           flicts as opportunities for growth and
                                                                           self-discovery, rather than as obstacles
                                                                           to be avoided or ignored. By committing
                                                                           to continuous learning and personal de-
                                                                           velopment, couples can deepen their
           Financial transparency and joint   Embracing cultural sensitivity and   emotional connection and build a resil-
           decision-making                 adaptation is key to navigating conflicts   ient foundation for their relationship.
           Furthermore, financial transparency and   arising from cultural differences. Couples
           joint decision-making can help alleviate   should strive to understand and respect   Strategies for managing
           tensions related to money matters.   each other's cultural backgrounds,   expectations in marriage
           Couples should establish shared financial   traditions, and values. By acknowledging   Communication: Open and honest
           goals, create a budget, and regularly   and celebrating diversity within their   communication is crucial in managing
           review their financial situation to ensure   relationship, couples can forge stronger   expectations in marriage. Couples
           alignment and accountability.   bonds and overcome cultural barriers.   should have regular conversations
                                                                           about their expectations, goals, and
                                           Stress management and self-care   needs. This can help them understand
           Cultural sensitivity and adaptation   Managing stress and prioritizing self-  each other better and avoid misunder-


              Enhancing Marital Communication: Practical Tips


                   ctive listening: Practice active   municating. Maintain eye contact, use   Seek clarification: If you are un-
                   listening by giving your full   affirmative gestures, and avoid defen-  sure about something your partner said
             Aattention to your partner when   sive or confrontational postures. Non-  or meant, ask for clarification instead
             they are speaking. Avoid interrupting   verbal communication can convey un-  of making assumptions. This helps to
             or formulating your response while   derstanding, empathy, and openness.   resolve any misunderstandings and
             they are talking. Show genuine interest   Set aside dedicated quality time:   promotes effective communication.
             and try to understand their perspective.   Carve out regular quality time for the   Practice empathy: Put yourself in
               Express emotions openly: Create   two of you to connect and communi-  your partner's shoes and try to under-
             a safe space where both partners can   cate without distractions. It could be a   stand their point of view. Empathy
             freely express their emotions without   weekly date night or a simple walk to-  helps to foster understanding and re-
             judgment or criticism. Encourage open   gether. Use this time to talk, share ex-  solve conflicts by acknowledging each
             and honest communication by being   periences, and strengthen your bond.   other's emotions and experiences.
             understanding and empathetic towards   Use technology mindfully: In to-  Seek professional help if needed:
             each other's feelings.         day's digital age, it is important to be   If communication problems persist or
               Use "I" statements: When discus-  mindful of the impact of technology   escalate, consider seeking the assis-
             sing issues or conflicts, use "I" state-  on communication. Set boundaries for   tance of a professional couples thera-
             ments instead of "you" statements. For   device usage during specific times to   pist. They can provide guidance, tools,
             example, say "I feel hurt when..." in-  ensure uninterrupted quality time and   and techniques to improve communi-
             stead of "You always make me feel..."   conversation.         cation and resolve conflicts.
             This helps to express your feelings   Avoid sarcasm and contempt:   Remember, improving communica-
             without blaming or attacking the other   Sarcasm and contempt can be toxic to   tion takes time and effort from both
             person.                        communication and can lead to con-  partners. By implementing these prac-
               Practice non-verbal communica-  flicts. Strive to communicate with re-  tical tips, you can enhance your com-
             tion: Pay attention to your body lan-  spect and kindness, even when discus-  munication skills, reduce conflicts,
             guage and non-verbal cues when com-  sing challenging topics.   and strengthen your marital bond.


           24                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[standings.
             Realistic expectations: Unrealistic
           expectations can lead to disappoint-
           ment and frustration, so it's essential to
           set realistic expectations. Couples
           should have a clear understanding of
           what they can expect from each other
           and the marriage. They should discuss
           their priorities and work together to
           make a plan that meets their needs and
           goals.
             Respect: Mutual respect is crucial
           in a healthy marriage. Couples should
           respect each other's differences, opin-
           ions, and values. They should avoid
           criticizing or judging each other and                                                           Professional guidance for conflict resolution
           focus on understanding and supporting
           each other.
              Compromise: Compromise is an
           essential aspect of marriage. Couples
           should be willing to compromise and
           make adjustments to meet each other's
                                                                           needs. They should look for common
                                                                           ground and work together to find solu-
                                                                           tions that work for both parties.
                                                                              Gratitude: Showing gratitude and
         A marriage counseling session can offer assistance                efforts and contributions and express
                                                                           appreciation for each other can help
                                                                           manage expectations in marriage. Cou-
                                                                           ples should acknowledge each other's
                                                                           their appreciation regularly.
                                                                              Seek professional help: If couples
                                                                           are struggling to manage their expecta-
                                                                           tions and avoid conflicts, they should
                                                                           seek help from a professional coun-
                                                                           selor or therapist. A therapist can pro-
                                                                           vide tools and techniques to help re-
                                                                           solve conflicts and improve
                                                                           communication skills.
                                                                              In conclusion, managing expecta-
                                                                           tions in a marriage is a continuous
                                                                           process that requires effort and pa-
                                                                           tience from both partners. By follow-
                                                                           ing these strategies, couples can avoid
                                                                           conflicts and create a healthy and ful-
                                                                           filling relationship.
                                                                              Conflicts are an inevitable aspect of
                                                                           any relationship, including marriage. In
         Seek guidance from a professional counselor                       perceptions and behaviors. However,
                                                                           the context of Indian marriages, con-
                                                                           flicts often stem from cultural, societal,
                                                                           and economic factors that influence

                                                                           by fostering open communication, mu-
                                                                           tual respect, and a willingness to com-
                                                                           promise, couples can navigate conflicts
                                                                           effectively and cultivate enduring rela-
                                                                           tionships built on trust, understanding,
                                                                           and love. Embracing diversity and
                                                                           celebrating individuality within the

                                                                           for harmonious unions that withstand
                                                                           the test of time. ■

                                                                                                       25
           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            context of marriage can pave the way]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[TRAVEL































           A Journey of Wonders



           The enchanting beauty






           of Thailand







           By Ishita Desai



                 estled in the heart of Southeast   tament to Mother Nature’s creativity, of-  simply basking in the tropical sun. Trav-
                 Asia lies a land of captivating   fering a plethora of landscapes to ex-  elers seeking a quieter escape can ven-
           Nbeauty, rich culture, and a tapes-  plore and admire. The southern region   ture to the lesser-known islands of Koh
           try of flavors that awaken the senses—  boasts some of the world's most pictur-  Lanta and Koh Tao, where pristine
           Thailand. With its azure beaches, lush   esque beaches, drawing visitors with   beaches and laid-back atmospheres
           jungles, and ancient temples, Thailand   their powdery white sands, swaying   await.
           offers a kaleidoscope of experiences that   palm trees, and crystal-clear waters.   In the north, the province of Chiang
           allure travelers from across the globe.   Among the most renowned are Phuket,   Mai beckons with its verdant hills, mist-
           Let us embark on an immersive journey   the largest island in Thailand, and Koh   shrouded mountains, and rich cultural
           through the Land of Smiles, exploring   Samui, famous for its luxury resorts and   heritage. Explore the lush jungles of Doi
           its diverse landscapes, vibrant traditions,   vibrant nightlife.   Inthanon National Park, home to Thai-
           and the warm hospitality of its people.   Further south, the Phi Phi Islands,   land's highest peak and a myriad of ex-
                                           with their towering limestone cliffs and   otic flora and fauna. Trekking enthusi-
           Discovering Nature's Splendor   emerald lagoons, provide a postcard-  asts can embark on guided expeditions
             Thailand’s natural wonders are a tes-  perfect setting for snorkeling, diving, or   to remote hill tribe villages, immersing

           26                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[themselves in the traditional lifestyles of
           the Karen, Hmong, and Lisu com-
           munities.
             For an unforgettable aquatic adven-
           ture, head to Khao Sok National Park,
           where towering limestone cliffs rise
           from the turquoise waters of Cheow Lan
           Lake. Kayak through hidden caves, hike
           to cascading waterfalls, and spend the
           night in a floating bungalow, surrounded
           by the tranquil beauty of the rainforest.

           Immersing in Cultural Marvels                                                                   Scenic view of Khao Sok National Park
             Beyond its natural splendor, Thailand
           boasts a rich cultural heritage that dates
           back centuries, reflected in its ancient
           ruins, ornate temples, and vibrant festi-
           vals. Begin your cultural journey in the
           ancient city of Ayutthaya, a UNESCO
           World Heritage Site that was once the   (spires) that still stand today.   pedal through the sprawling archae-
           thriving capital of the Kingdom of Siam.   Continue your exploration in Sukho-  ological park, stopping to admire the
           Explore the impressive ruins of temples   thai, another UNESCO-listed site re-  graceful Buddha statues and tranquil
           and palaces, marveling at the intricate   nowned for its well-preserved ruins and   lotus ponds that dot the landscape.
           stucco carvings and towering prang   serene atmosphere. Rent a bicycle and   In Bangkok, the bustling capital city,
                                                                           modernity seamlessly blends with tradi-
                                                                           tion, offering a fascinating glimpse into
                                                                           Thai culture past and present. Visit the
                                                                           iconic Grand Palace, home to the re-
         Chaweng Beach, Koh Samui: A Tropical Paradise                     alongside bustling markets and aromatic
                                                                           vered Emerald Buddha, and wander
                                                                           through the labyrinthine streets of Chi-
                                                                           natown, where ancient temples stand

                                                                           street food stalls.
                                                                              No visit to Thailand is complete
                                                                           without experiencing the grandeur of its
                                                                           religious monuments. The majestic Wat
                                                                           Phra Kaew, nestled within the grounds
                                                                           of the Grand Palace, dazzles visitors
                                                                           with its intricate architecture and daz-
                                                                           zling mosaics, while the gleaming spires
                                                                           of Wat Arun illuminate the skyline dur-
                                                                           ing sunset, casting a magical glow over
                                                                           the Chao Phraya River.

                                                                           Savoring Gastronomic Delights
                                                                              Thai cuisine is a culinary journey that
                                                                           tantalizes the taste buds with its har-
                                                                           monious blend of flavors—sweet, sour,
                                                                           salty, and spicy. Indulge in fragrant
                                                                           dishes like Pad Thai, a stir-fried noodle
         Phi Phi Islands: Spectacular tropical beauty                      soup brimming with succulent shrimp
                                                                           dish infused with tamarind and peanuts,
                                                                           or Tom Yum Goong, a spicy and tangy

                                                                           and aromatic herbs.
                                                                              Street food vendors offer a gastro-
                                                                           nomic adventure around every corner,
                                                                           serving up an array of delectable treats,
                                                                           from crispy spring rolls and savory satay
                                                                           skewers to creamy coconut curries and
                                                                           mango sticky rice—a sweet finale to any
                                                                           meal.
                                                                              For those seeking a deeper under-


                                                                                                       27
           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            standing of Thai cuisine, cooking classes]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Popular

                                                                             destinations

                                                                               Koh Samui: Koh Samui is one of
                                                                             Thailand's largest islands, known for
                                                                             its stunning beaches, coral reefs, and
                                                                             coconut groves. Its crystal-clear
                                                                             waters offer opportunities for snor-
         Phuket: Paradise in Thailand                                        also explore the ancient Wat Plai
                                                                             keling and diving, and visitors can

                                                                             Laem temple.
                                                                               Pattaya: Pattaya is a bustling
                                                                             coastal city loved by tourists who
                                                                             come to enjoy its vibrant nightlife,
                                                                             beaches, and many shopping malls.
                                                                             The city is also known for its vibrant
                                                                             events and festivals, including the
           offer a hands-on experience, where you   backdrop that offers visitors a serene   Pattaya International Music Festival
           can learn the art of crafting traditional   and peaceful atmosphere.   and the Pattaya Grand Sale.
           dishes using fresh ingredients sourced   Prasat Muang Singh Historical   Kanchanaburi: Kanchanaburi is
           from local markets. Join a guided food   Park: The Prasat Muang Singh Histori-  a province in western Thailand that
           tour to sample regional specialties and   cal Park is a collection of Khmer-style   offers outdoor activities such as
           hidden culinary gems, or simply follow   ruins of ancient temples. Located in a   camping and hiking, as well as his-
           your nose to the nearest street vendor   forest, the site has a mysterious feel and   torical sites like the Kanchanaburi
           and let your taste buds be your guide.   is a peaceful reflection of Thailand's rich   War Cemetery and the Bridge on the
                                           history.                          River Kwai.
           Historical sites of great         Chong Kai War Cemetery: The       Koh Tao: Koh Tao is a popular
           significance                    Chong Kai War Cemetery is a historic   diving destination famous for its
             The Bridge on the River Kwai: The   site that honors 1,740 Allied prisoners of   coral reefs and colorful marine life.
           Bridge on the River Kwai is a famous   war who died in Kanchanaburi during   The island also offers stunning views
           landmark in Kanchanaburi that was built   World War II. The beautifully main-  and opportunities for hiking and rock
           during World War II. The bridge is the   tained cemetery features rose gardens   climbing.
           subject of both a book and a movie and   and tall trees and offers a tranquil and   Sukhothai: An ancient city of
           is an important reminder of Thailand's   serene atmosphere.       Thailand, Sukhothai was the first
           history during the Second World War.   These are just a few of the many his-  capital of the Kingdom of Siam. It is
             Hellfire Pass Museum: The Hellfire   torical sites and landmarks in Kanchana-  now a UNESCO World Heritage Site
           Pass Museum offers a poignant account   buri that are worth exploring. They pro-  known for its impressive temples,
           of the building of the infamous wartime   vide visitors with a unique opportunity   parks, and historical landmarks. It is
           railway in Kanchanaburi. It provides an   to learn more about Thailand's history   a must-visit destination for tourists
           extensive and well-presented exhibition   and the significant role it played during   who love history and archeology.
           of archival footage, stories, photographs   World War II.
           and interactive displays.                                       the art of Muay Thai, or simply sharing
             Kanchanaburi War Cemetery: The   Embracing the Thai Way of Life   stories over a cup of steaming Thai tea,
           Kanchanaburi War Cemetery is the final   But perhaps the most enduring charm   every moment spent in Thailand is an
           resting place for over 6,000 Allied pris-  of Thailand lies in the warmth and hos-  invitation to embrace the joys of life.
           oners of war who died during the con-  pitality of its people, whose genuine   As the sun sets on another day in the
           struction of the Thai-Burma railway dur-  smiles and gracious demeanor welcome   Land of Smiles, one cannot help but be
           ing World War II. It is a beautifully   visitors with open arms. Whether savor-  captivated by the magic of Thailand—a
           maintained site set against a mountain   ing a traditional Thai massage, learning   land where ancient traditions meet mod-
                                                                           ern luxuries, and every corner reveals a
                                                                           new adventure waiting to unfold. So
                                                                           pack your bags, embark on a journey of
                                                                           discovery, and let Thailand enchant you
         Doi Inthanon National Park                                        tine beaches and lush jungles, immers-
                                                                           with its timeless allure. Whether you're
                                                                           exploring the natural wonders of its pris-

                                                                           ing yourself in its rich cultural heritage,
                                                                           or savoring the tantalizing flavors of its
                                                                           cuisine, Thailand offers a treasure trove
                                                                           of experiences that will leave you long-
                                                                           ing to return again and again. ■

           28                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY
             HOROSCOPES                                     April 16-30, 2024






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     During this bi-weekly period, Aries, focus on   During this bi-weekly period, Libra, the spot-
                     relationships and partnerships. Finding balance   light is on personal growth and self-improve-
                     and harmony in your connections with others is   ment. Embrace new challenges and take action
                     key. Embrace compromise, communication, and     towards your goals. Trust your instincts and be
                     empathy to create strong bonds.                 bold in your pursuits.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     The spotlight for Taurus is on self-expression and   The focus for Scorpio during this bi-weekly
                     creativity during this period. Embrace your unique   period is on communication and networking.
                     ideas and share them with others. You have the   Embrace social interactions and connect with
                     confidence and charisma to connect with new     others. Your ability to persuade and influence
                     people and build new partnerships.              others will be particularly strong.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     This bi-weekly period highlights practicality and   This period highlights finance and material
                     productivity for Gemini. Focus on organization   wealth for Sagittarius. Embrace practicality and
                     and planning to maximize your results. Take     organization to maximize your earning potential.
                     care of your health and well-being, and avoid   Be cautious with spending, and focus on build-
                     overcommitting yourself.                        ing long-term stability.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     During this period, Cancer, take time for self-re-  During this bi-weekly period, the focus is on
                     flection and spiritual growth. Embrace your intu-  personal relationships and partnerships. Nurture
                     ition and inner guidance to bring clarity and di-  your connections with loved ones and seek bal-
                     rection to your life. Reach out to trusted loved   ance and harmony in your interactions. Be open
                     ones for support.                               to compromise and collaboration.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     The focus for Leo during this bi-weekly period   This period encourages Aquarius to embrace ad-
                     is on home life and family. Nurture your rela-  venture and explore new experiences. Expand
                     tionships with loved ones and seek comfort in   your horizons through travel, learning, and cul-
                     familiar surroundings. Focus on creating a      tural exploration. Channel your passion and cre-
                     peaceful and harmonious living space.           ativity into new projects.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     This period highlights relationships and partner-  During this bi-weekly period, Pisces, focus on
                     ships for Virgo. Seek balance and harmony in    practicality and productivity. Organize your
                     your interactions with others. Take advantage of   schedule and take care of your physical well-
                     opportunities for collaboration and compromise   being. Take advantage of new opportunities for
                     to create strong connections.                   growth and advancement.





           APRIL 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Gratitude for comprehensive
           coverage of didi
                                           I am writing to share the remarkable
                                           discovery of a preserved Bronze Age
           It is to our delight and pure happiness that
                                           settlement in England. The excavation at
           Dr. Kamran have created and holistically   Remarkable discovery   women's safety in India. While it com-
           covered a 360-degree point of view of our   Must Farm offers unprecedented insights   prehensively addresses the challenges, I
           beloved didi, which is indeed beyond our   into ancient lifestyles, culinary practices,   believe it could benefit from highlight-
           imagination. As an erudite yourself, you   and craftsmanship. This significant find   ing grassroots initiatives and success
           have done perfect justice in showcasing   sheds light on our shared human history   stories. Additionally, exploring intersec-
           all elements of her character and covering   and deserves wider recognition. I urge you   tional perspectives, such as the experi-
           all essential details integral to her, such as   to feature this story, as it enriches our   ences of marginalized communities,
           focus, rigor, and discipline fueled by her   understanding of the past and underscores   would enrich the narrative. Overall, am-
           love of music, lifelong learning, and   the importance of archaeological   plifying voices from diverse back-
           teaching music. Your writing is indeed   preservation efforts.   grounds can foster a more inclusive dia-
           praiseworthy, as you are an amazing and   Ravi Kumar Anand, Bruchsal,   logue on this crucial issue.
           seasoned professional; your article will be   Germany           Ruchi Sharma, Delhi, India
           remembered for ages and has become
           timeless in existence. We again thank you
           and shower blessings and love upon you   A balanced approach    India's unique democratic spirit
           and your family for being there as a strong   While the article on intuition offers   As India braces for the upcoming
           anchor and support for didi and us.   valuable insights into its spiritual and   parliamentary elections, it's a moment to
           Wishing you great success always.   philosophical dimensions, it lacks depth   reflect on the nation's vibrant democ-
           Dr. Beena Saxena, Mr. Rajendra Pal,   in exploring its modern applications and   racy. With its diverse electorate, multi-
           Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India    scientific underpinnings. Integrating re-  phase voting, and the influence of re-
                                           search on cognitive psychology and neu-  gional parties, Indian elections stand as
                                           roscience could enhance its credibility   a testament to the country's commitment
           Tribute to Dr. Sunita Saxena    and relevance to a broader audience. Ad-  to democratic principles. From the use
             I was deeply moved by the heartfelt   ditionally, including real-life examples   of technology to the role of identity pol-
           tribute to the late Dr. Sunita Saxena, a   and practical tips for honing intuition   itics, each aspect adds to the richness of
           cherished mentor and musician, featured   would engage readers seeking actionable   the electoral process. As citizens exer-
           in your magazine. The article beautifully   advice. Overall, a more balanced ap-  cise their right to vote, let us celebrate
           captured her unwavering dedication to   proach that bridges ancient wisdom with   the essence of democracy and uphold
           music and the profound impact she had   contemporary understanding would en-  the values that define our nation.  As cit-
           on her students' lives. It serves as a poig-  rich the discourse on this fascinating   izens exercise their fundamental right to
           nant reminder of the enduring power of   topic.                 vote, it's crucial to uphold the demo-
           music and the legacy of those who ded-  Ramesh Sehgal, Delhi, India   cratic principles that define our nation,
           icate their lives to its pursuit. Thank you                     ensuring that every voice resonates in
           for honoring Dr. Sunita's memory in                             the corridors of power.
           such a meaningful way.          Enhancing women's safety        Rakesh Rastogi, Kanpur, Uttar
           Rashmi Singh, Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh,   discourse                Pradesh, India
           India                             I recently read your article on



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | APRIL 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>