<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="34"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                      VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 06  I  MARCH 16 2024       ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             18



                                                            24













                                                            9                                        27
















           4-Editorial: The unvoiced agony of              21-The artistic evolution of dental
           parents                                         jewellery

           5-A surge in heart attack threat                24-Easter's historical tapestry

           9-Health Hazards of Blue Light                  27-Journey through Turkey’s Rich

           12-The painful reality for struggling           Heritage
           parents                                         31-Horoscopes

           15-From necessity to style                      32-Letters

           18-The vibrant festival of colors












           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Generation Gap
     EDITORIAL  The unvoiced                                                        Editor-in-Chief




                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           agony of parents                                                       Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n an era defined by rapid change and the   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           omnipresence of social media, the
                                        Ichasm between generations poses a          Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        significant challenge for parents. Struggling
                                        parents feel the pain as traditional values   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        clash with the autonomy sought by the        Sushil Kumar
                                        younger generation.
                                           The generational divide intensifies in the   Social Media Editor
                                        age of individualism, where the younger    Vishakha Sharma
                                        generation embraces change with
                                        enthusiasm. Parents grapple with preserving   Art & Graphics Director
                                        tradition while allowing room for            Vipin Agarwal
                                        independence, especially evident in matters
                                        like marriage, where rituals are discarded
           for live-in relationships. This rebellion, fueled by social media, adds complexity to
           the intergenerational struggle.                                   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             Parents seek solutions to reconnect the younger generation with their roots and
           regain authority over significant decisions. The pain is acute as they yearn for a   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           return to a time when filial piety and respect were paramount.    Editor, United News of India, New
             However, the editorial landscape offers hope through open communication and   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           mutual understanding. Struggling parents can bridge the gap by listening to their   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           children's aspirations without dismissing tradition. There's room for compromise,   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           marrying old and new while respecting cultural heritage and the evolving identity of   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           the youth.                                                        Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
             Education is crucial in this journey. Parents and children must engage in
           conversations elucidating the historical and cultural significance of traditions,   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
           fostering a deeper appreciation and shared identity.                    Jamali (Architect)
             In this poignant struggle for understanding and autonomy, it is crucial to reflect on
           the sacrifices made by the previous generation. Those parents who taught them to   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           walk by holding their fingers, stayed awake all night to put their children to sleep,
           fulfilled every small and big wish of theirs, even though they themselves lived on   Phone +91 20 40199102
           little food but fed their children to their heart's content. After growing up, how can it   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           be acceptable to ignore parents and play with their feelings?             Baner Road,
             Navigating the challenges of tradition in modern parenthood requires recognizing   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           parental sacrifices as a catalyst for open communication and mutual understanding.   Email revoir@post.com
           The pain of struggling parents is a plea for a harmonious blend of tradition and   Website www.revoir.in
           modernity. The editorial's appeal for empathy and compromise gains resonance when
           considering the emotional investment parents have made in their children's lives.
             In conclusion, the editorial landscape, marked by the clash between tradition and   Legal Advisor
           autonomy, demands a nuanced perspective. By acknowledging and appreciating   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           parental sacrifices, we pave the way for a compassionate dialogue bridging the
           generational gap. Understanding requires acceptance of change and recognition of   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           enduring love that shapes the family dynamic, creating a future where tradition is   all rights reserved. This publication
           respected, and the youth find autonomy within cultural heritage.   may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[HEALTH AND SCIENCE






































           Microplastics
           A surge in








           heart attack threat







           A groundbreaking study has shed light on a concerning connection between
           microplastics and heart disease |  By Karan Malhotra


             n recent years, the issue of plastic   walls of our blood vessels. The research-  ronment, particularly in water bodies
             pollution has garnered increasing at-  ers found that individuals with artery   such as oceans, rivers, and lakes. These
           Itention. We are all aware of the sig-  plaques containing microplastics were   microplastics can originate from various
           nificant environmental impact that plas-  approximately four times more likely to   sources, including the breakdown of
           tic waste has on our planet, but what   suffer from heart attacks or strokes com-  larger plastic objects, microbeads in per-
           about the potential health risks it poses   pared to those with plastic-free plaques.   sonal care products, and fibers from syn-
           to humans? A groundbreaking study has   These findings have raised significant   thetic clothing. The ability of these par-
           shed light on a concerning connection   questions about the role of microplastics   ticles to accumulate in our bodies and
           between microplastics and heart disease.   in the development and progression of   their potential health effects have be-
           This article explores the findings of this   heart disease.     come a growing concern.
           study and its implications for our health.
             A recent study conducted by a team   Understanding microplastics   The plausible mechanism
           of scientists examined the presence of   Microplastics are tiny particles of   While the exact mechanism through
           microplastics in artery plaques, which   plastic less than five millimeters in size.   which microplastics contribute to heart
           are the fatty deposits that build up on the   They are commonly found in the envi-  disease is still not fully understood, re-

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Identifying

         Microplastics linked to elevated risk of heart attacks             Identifying if a cleaning product or de-
                                                                            microplastics in
                                                                            cleaning products



                                                                            tergent contains microplastics can be
                                                                            challenging as they are not always ex-
                                                                            plicitly listed on the label. However,
                                                                            there are certain ingredients that are
                                                                            commonly used in these products and
                                                                            can indicate the presence of micro-
                                                                            plastics. Here are a few ingredients to
                                                                            look out for:
                                                                              1. Polyethylene (PE): This is a
                                                                            common plastic polymer used in var-
                                                                            ious products and can be an indicator
           searchers propose several possible ex-  tently. These microplastics can then   of microplastic presence. If you see
           planations. One theory is that microplas-  travel through our digestive system and   "polyethylene" listed on the label, it
           tics may trigger chronic inflammation in   potentially enter the bloodstream.   means the product may contain micro-
           arterial walls, leading to the formation   Inhalation: Microplastics can also   plastics.
           of plaques and the narrowing of blood   be inhaled, primarily through the air we   2. Polypropylene (PP): Another
           vessels. Additionally, these particles   breathe. These particles may be released   plastic polymer often used in products,
           may disrupt the normal function of cells   into the atmosphere from various   including cleaning solutions and deter-
           lining the blood vessels, impacting their   sources such as industrial activities, ve-  gents. Look for "polypropylene" on
           ability to regulate blood flow and pro-  hicle emissions, and the breakdown of   the label as an indication of potential
           mote healthy cardiovascular function.   larger plastic objects. Once inhaled, they   microplastic content.
                                           can potentially reach the bloodstream   3. Polyethylene terephthalate
           Microplastics Pathway to Artery   and circulate throughout the body.   (PET): This plastic polymer is com-
           Plaques                           Absorption through the skin:   monly used in bottles, but it can also
             The exact pathway by which micro-  While less is known about this particular   be found in cleaning product packag-
           plastics find their way into artery   pathway, there is some evidence to sug-  ing. While it might not directly indi-
           plaques is still an area of ongoing re-  gest that microplastics can be absorbed   cate microplastic presence in the pro-
           search and study. While the specific   through the skin. This could occur when   duct itself, it highlights the use of
           mechanism has not been fully elu-  microplastics are present in cosmetic   plastic materials.
           cidated, scientists have put forward sev-  and personal care products or when indi-  4. Ingredients with "microbeads"
           eral plausible explanations     viduals come into direct contact with   or "microspheres": Some products
             Ingestion: Microplastics can enter   plastic-contaminated surfaces.   may explicitly mention the use of mi-
           our bodies through ingestion. When we   Once microplastics enter the blood-  crobeads or microspheres on the label.
           consume food and drink, it is possible   stream, they can potentially be trans-  These tiny particles are often made of
           for microplastics present in the environ-  ported to different parts of the body, in-  plastic and can act as exfoliants or
           ment, such as in contaminated water or   cluding the arteries. The exact   abrasives in cleaning products.
           food packaging, to be ingested inadver-  mechanisms through which microplas-  Keep in mind that the absence of
                                                                            these specific ingredients does not
                                                                            guarantee that a product is free of mi-
                                                                            croplastics. Manufacturers might use
                                                                            other types of microplastics or varia-
                                                                            tions in naming conventions. When in
                                                                            doubt, you can contact the manufac-
         Medical scientific study on microplastics                          products that are labeled "microplas-
                                                                            turer directly to inquire about the pres-
                                                                            ence of microplastics in their products.
                                                                              Additionally, seeking out cleaning

                                                                            tic-free" or specifically state that they
                                                                            do not contain microplastics can be a
                                                                            viable alternative. Supporting brands
                                                                            that are committed to sustainable and
                                                                            environmentally friendly practices can
                                                                            help in reducing exposure to micro-
                                                                            plastics.


           6                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Food and beverages: Microplastics
                                                                           have been found in various food and
                                                                           beverage products, including bottled
                                                                           water, seafood, and salt. Plastic packag-
                                                                           ing, contamination during processing,
                                                                           and environmental pollution can con-
                                                                           tribute to the presence of microplastics
                                                                           in these items. Choosing fresh, unpack-
                                                                           aged foods and tap water whenever pos-
         Plastic pollution in nature                                       with a type of plastic called polypropy-
                                                                           sible can help reduce exposure.
                                                                              Teabags: Many tea bags are made

                                                                           lene to help seal the bags. When these
                                                                           tea bags are steeped in hot water, micro-
                                                                           plastics can be released into the bever-

                                                                           brands that use plastic-free or biode-
           tics interact with arterial plaques and   into the water, which eventually end up   age. Opt for loose leaf teas or look for
                                                                           gradable tea bags.
           contribute to their formation is an active   in aquatic environments. To minimize   Cosmetics and makeup: Besides
           area of research. It is hypothesized that   microfiber release, wash synthetic cloth-  personal care items like face washes and
           microplastics may trigger inflammation,   ing in colder water, use a washing ma-  scrubs, microplastics can also be found
           disrupt normal cellular functions, and   chine filter or laundry bag designed to   in cosmetics and makeup products, in-
           contribute to the development of arterial   collect microfibers, or opt for natural   cluding foundations, lipsticks, and eye-
           plaque buildup. It is important to note   fiber clothing.       shadows. Read product labels andchoose
           that further research is needed to fully
           understand the processes by which mi-
           croplastics reach artery plaques and their
           precise role in the progression of heart
           disease. Scientists are working diligently
           to uncover these details and expand our
           understanding of this complex issue.

           Implications for public health
             The implications of this study are
           profound and warrant further investiga-
           tion. If microplastics are indeed a signif-
           icant contributor to heart disease, it
           raises concerns about the widespread ex-
           posure we face on a daily basis. At pres-
           ent, there are limited regulations and                                                          Global plastic recycling
           guidelines regarding microplastic pollu-
           tion, and this research underscores the
           need for urgent action to mitigate the
           risks posed by these particles.

           Microplastics in Various Everyday
           Products
             Cleaning products and detergents:
           Some cleaning products, such as liquid
           soaps, dishwashing liquids, and laundry
           detergents, can contain microplastics.
           These microplastics are often used as
           abrasives or thickeners in these pro-
           ducts. To reduce exposure, choose envi-
           ronmentally friendly and microplastic-
           free alternatives, or consider making                                                           Healthy artery alongside an artery with plaques
           your own cleaning solutions using natu-
           ral ingredients.
             Synthetic clothing and textiles:
           Synthetic fabrics like polyester, acrylic,
           and nylon are made from plastic
           polymers. When these fabrics are
           washed, they can release microfibers

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Eco-friendly

           cleaning products


              1. Vinegar: Vinegar is a natural
           cleaning agent that can be used to
           clean surfaces, floors, and even win-
           dows. Its acidic properties help cut                                                            Medical research on cardiovascular health
           through grease and grime, making it a
           powerful cleaning tool. Mix equal
           parts water and vinegar in a spray bot-
           tle for an easy-to-use cleaning solution.
              2. Baking soda: Baking soda is a
           versatile cleaning agent that can be
           used in various ways, such as to re-
           move stains and odors from carpets,   brands that are committed to using mi-  microplastics entering our environment.
           scrub away grime from sinks and tubs,   croplastic-free formulations.   Filter drinking water: Investing in a
           and freshen up laundry. Create a paste   Chewing gum: Some chewing gums   high-quality water filter can help re-
           by mixing baking soda with water and   contain synthetic rubber or plastic   move microplastics from our drinking
           apply it to the surface you want to   polymers to give them their chewy tex-  water, reducing our exposure.
           clean.                          ture. These additives can contribute to   Choose natural fibers: Opt for cloth-
              3. Castile soap: Castile soap is a   microplastic consumption when chew-  ing and textiles made from natural fibers
           natural soap made from vegetable oil,   ing gum. Consider switching to natural   such as cotton or wool, as synthetic fab-
           such as olive oil or coconut oil. It is a   chewing gum alternatives, or reduce   rics are more likely to shed microplastic
           versatile cleaning agent that can be   your overall consumption.   fibers during washing.
           used for everything from body wash to   It's important to stay informed and   Support research and regulations:
           laundry detergent. Dilute castile soap   read product labels to identify potential   Advocating for increased research into
           with water to create a cleaning solution   sources of microplastics. By making   the impacts of microplastics and sup-
           for surfaces and floors.        conscious choices and seeking out mi-  porting policies that regulate their usage
              4. Lemon juice: Lemon juice is a   croplastic-free alternatives, we can mini-  and disposal can help address this issue
           natural bleach that can be used to re-  mize our exposure to these particles and   on a larger scale.
           move stains and brighten whites. Its   contribute to a healthier environment.   The association between microplas-
           acidic properties make it a powerful                            tics and heart disease revealed by this
           cleaning agent that can cut through   Prevention and mitigation   study serves as a wake-up call, high-
           grease and grime. Mix lemon juice   While it may be challenging to com-  lighting the potential health risks posed
           with water to clean surfaces and appli-  pletely avoid exposure to microplastics,   by plastic pollution. As individuals and
           ances.                          there are steps we can take to minimize   as a society, it is crucial that we take im-
              5. Essential oils: Essential oils,   their presence in our lives:   mediate action to mitigate plastic pollu-
           such as tea tree oil, lavender oil, and   Reduce single-use plastic consump-  tion and reduce our exposure to micro-
           peppermint oil, have natural antibac-  tion: Replacing single-use plastics with   plastics. By doing so, we can safeguard
           terial, antifungal and antiviral proper-  sustainable alternatives can help reduce   not only our planet but also our health
           ties that make them useful for cleaning.   plastic waste and lessen the chances of   and well-being for future generations. ■
           Add a few drops of essential oil to a
           water and vinegar solution for an
           added scent boost and disinfectant
           properties.
              6. Eco-friendly cleaning pro-
           ducts: Look for eco-friendly cleaning
           products that use natural ingredients,
           such as plant-based surfactants and
           enzymes, to clean surfaces without the
           use of harsh chemicals or microplas-
           tics.
              These are just a few examples of
           environmentally friendly and micro-
           plastic-free cleaning products avail-
           able. Remember to always read the
           label and ingredient list to ensure that                                                        Plastic waste recycling process
           the product you choose is free of mi-
           croplastics and environmentally
           friendly.


           8                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[HEALTH AND WELLNESS















































           Digital Progress
           Health Hazards of








           Blue Light







           By Pooja Mehta

             n the age preceding the digital rev-  tended exposure to blue light on our   proliferation of LED lights has ushered
             olution, the world was bathed in the   eyes, sleep patterns, and general health.   in a new era characterized by an abun-
           Iwarm, yellow glow of tungsten fila-                            dance of blue light.
           ment bulbs, and health issues related to   The Digital Culprit Explored   Blue light, with its high energy and
           eyes, sleep, and overall well-being were   Before the advent of LED technol-  short wavelength on the visible spec-
           less pervasive. Fast forward to today,   ogy, the predominant artificial lighting   trum, offers benefits such as enhanced
           and our lives are dominated by digital   source was tungsten filament bulbs,   alertness and mood during the day. Yet,
           devices—smartphones, tablets, com-  emitting a comforting yellow light that   concerns arise when considering pro-
           puters, and LED lights—exposing us to   closely mimicked natural sunlight. This   longed exposure, particularly during the
           unprecedented levels of blue light. This   type of lighting had minimal impact on   evening hours, as it can disrupt our natu-
           transformation has given rise to concerns   circadian rhythms, fostering a healthier   ral circadian rhythm and exert various
           about the potential repercussions of ex-  balance in our daily lives. However, the   effects on our health.

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Unraveling the Ocular Conundrum   idence suggesting a connection between   awake and alert, disrupting the natural
             One of the most debated concerns   excessive blue light exposure and an in-  process of winding down before bed-
           surrounding blue light exposure is its   creased risk of age-related macular de-  time.
           potential impact on eye health. Blue   generation (AMD). As our reliance on   The prevalence of smartphones, tab-
           light penetrates the eyes more deeply   digital devices grows, the long-term   lets, and computers in our evening rou-
           than other visible light, reaching the ret-  consequences of blue light on ocular   tines has ushered in a new challenge to
           ina and prompting worries about digital   health become an increasingly pressing   our sleep hygiene. The use of such de-
           eye strain. Symptoms such as dry eyes,   issue.                 vices before bedtime can delay the onset
           blurred vision, and headaches have been   The frequent use of screens often re-  of sleep, reduce total sleep duration, and
           linked to extended screen time.   sults in decreased blink rates, contrib-  compromise sleep quality. Chronic sleep
             The implications extend beyond im-  uting to the prevalence of dry eyes. This   deprivation, a potential consequence of
           mediate discomfort, with emerging ev-  cumulative effect raises concerns about   our modern lifestyles, has been linked to
                                           the potential for lasting damage to eye   a myriad of health issues, including
            Minimizing blue light          health.                         obesity, diabetes, and cardiovascular dis-
                                                                           eases.

            exposure effects               Blue Light's Twilight Challenge    The overall health implications of
                                             One of the most pronounced effects   disrupted sleep patterns are significant,
              Aside from using filters or   of blue light is its impact on sleep. Me-  as adequate and restful sleep is vital for
            glasses, there are other ways to re-  latonin, a hormone crucial for regulating   various physiological processes. Disrup-
            duce the negative effects of blue   sleep-wake cycles, sees its production   tions to circadian rhythms can affect
            light exposure. Here are some tips:   suppressed when exposed to blue light,   hormone regulation, immune function,
              1. Take frequent breaks: Taking   especially in the evening. The body in-  and mood, opening the door to a spec-
            frequent breaks from digital screens   terprets this light as a signal to stay   trum of potential health concerns.
            can help reduce eye strain and also
            give your eyes a chance to rest and
            recover.
              2. Increase distance from
            screens: Maintaining a distance of at
            least 20-30 inches from devices can
            help reduce the amount of blue light
            exposure.
              3. Use proper lighting: Adequate
            lighting can help reduce eye strain
            and make working with digital
            screens easier on the eyes. Using
            natural daylight, softer light bulbs or
            desk lamps with correct positioning                                                            A person using a laptop in a dark room
            can help reduce the amount of blue
            light exposure.
              4. Adjust device settings: Ad-
            justing device settings such as
            brightness, contrast, and text size can
            help reduce eye strain and make
            working on digital screens more
            comfortable.
              5. Limit screen time: Limiting
            overall screen time is a simple yet
            effective way to reduce exposure to
            blue light and other potential neg-
            ative effects associated with exces-
            sive screen usage.
              6. Establish a sleep routine: Es-
            tablishing a regular sleep routine can
            help improve sleep quality and quan-
            tity, which in turn can minimize the
            negative effects of blue light expo-
            sure on sleep.
              In general, taking steps to reduce                                                           Special filters can remove blue light
            blue light exposure can help improve
            eye health, reduce the risk of sleep
            disturbances, and promote better
            overall health in the long run.


           10                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Warm yellow light provides comfort to the eyes                                                    Modern LED bulb with warm yellow light


















                                                                             Helpful eye
           Connecting the Dots             screen use.
             Beyond the realms of eyes and sleep,   Opt for Warm Lighting: Choose
           the impact of blue light on overall health is   warm-colored LED bulbs with lower   exercises
           a topic under constant scrutiny.   color temperatures for indoor lighting,
           Disruptions to circadian rhythms may   mimicking the natural warmth of tung-  While there is no direct scientific
           influence various physiological processes,   sten filament bulbs. Consider using   evidence suggesting that specific eye
           including hormone regulation, immune   dimmer switches to adjust the brightness   exercises or techniques can specifi-
           function, and mood. Some studies suggest   levels based on the time of day.   cally reduce the negative effects of
           a potential correlation between prolonged   Establish a Sleep Routine: Create a   blue light exposure, there are some
           exposure to artificial blue light and an   consistent sleep routine by avoiding   general practices that may help alle-
           increased risk of conditions such as   electronic devices at least an hour before   viate eye strain and promote overall
           depression and obesity.         bedtime. Create a relaxing pre-sleep en-  eye health. Here are a few sugges-
                                           vironment with dim, warm lighting, and   tions:
             Researchers are delving into the intri-  consider incorporating activities that   1. Blinking exercises: Remind
           cate ways in which our bodies respond to   promote relaxation, such as reading or   yourself to blink frequently, espe-
           artificial lighting, seeking to understand   gentle stretching.   cially when using digital screens for
           the intricate web of connections between   Encourage Outdoor Time: Expo-  extended periods. Blinking helps to
           light exposure and health outcomes. As   sure to natural sunlight during the day   lubricate the eyes and prevent dry-
           our daily lives become increasingly in-  helps regulate circadian rhythms and   ness and discomfort.
           tertwined with technology, the need for a   supports overall well-being. Aim for reg-  2. Palming: Close your eyes and
           comprehensive understanding of these   ular outdoor activities to balance the ef-  place your palms over them, creating
           interactions becomes paramount.   fects of artificial lighting.   a gentle pressure without applying
                                                                             too much force. This technique can
           Strategies for a Balanced Digital   Striking a Balance in the Digital Age   help relax the eyes and provide a
           Lifestyle                         In the digital age, where blue light is   brief period of darkness.
             While it may be challenging to avoid   omnipresent, understanding its impact on   3. Eye focusing exercises: Prac-
           blue light entirely in today's digital   our eyes, sleep, and health is crucial for   tice shifting your focus between near
           world, there are strategies to mitigate its   maintaining a balanced and healthy life-  and far objects. This can help reduce
           impact on our health. Consider the fol-  style. While technology has undoubtedly   eye strain caused by prolonged near-
           lowing recommendations:         enriched our lives, being mindful of our   vision tasks such as staring at a
             Limit Screen Time: Take regular   exposure to artificial lighting and adop-  screen.
           breaks from screens, especially during   ting strategies to mitigate potential risks   4. Eye breaks: Take regular
           extended periods of use. Implement the   is essential.            breaks from staring at screens by fol-
           20-20-20 rule, where every 20 minutes,   As technology continues to advance,   lowing the 20-20-20 rule: Every 20
           look at something 20 feet away for at   ongoing research will provide further in-  minutes, look at an object at least 20
           least 20 seconds to reduce eye strain.   sights into the long-term effects of blue   feet away for 20 seconds. This helps
             Use Blue Light Filters: Many de-  light, guiding us in making informed   reduce eye fatigue and strain.
           vices now offer built-in blue light filters   choices for a healthier and more har-  5. Eye massages: Gently massag-
           or applications that adjust the color tem-  monious future.       ing the area around your eyes with
           perature of the screen, reducing the   In the future, such technology is also   your fingertips can help alleviate
           amount of blue light emitted. Ad-  expected by which digital devices will   tension and increase blood circula-
           ditionally, consider investing in blue   not emit blue light at all and we will get   tion to the eye area.
           light blocking glasses for extended   rid of it completely. ■

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[FAMILY DYNAMICS









































           Clash of Generations




           The painful reality for






           struggling parents










                   Parents find themselves    n the rapidly evolving landscape of   The rebellion against tradition
                                              the 21st century, parents find them-  Parents, who once guided their chil-
                  grappling with a growing   Iselves grappling with a growing dis-  dren through their first steps and self-
             disconnect between them and   connect between them and their chil-  lessly catered to their every need, are
                                           dren. The angst deepens when    now confronted with a perplexing real-
                             their children  traditional values and customs, once   ity. The current scenario reflects an on-
                                           considered sacrosanct, are discarded by   going narrative where children openly
                        By Naina Kapoor    the younger generation in favor of indi-  defy their parents, labeling them as old-
                                           vidualistic choices, particularly evident   fashioned. This rebellious streak is not a
                                           in matters like marriage. This shift has   novel phenomenon, as history has wit-
                                           given rise to a surge in live-in relation-  nessed generations challenging the
                                           ships, a trend that challenges the age-old   status quo. However, the contemporary
                                           rituals and customs that have endured   era, fueled by the omnipresence of so-
                                           for centuries.                  cial media, has amplified the youth's as-

           12                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[ideologies. While this interconnect-
         Children openly defy parents, labeling them old-fashioned
                                                                           edness has broadened horizons and fa-
                                                                           cilitated cross-cultural understanding, it
                                                                           has also led to a dilution of traditional
                                                                           values. The allure of Western ideals,
                                                                           often portrayed in the media and on so-
                                                                           cial platforms, has become irresistible to
                                                                           many young individuals, prompting
                                                                           them to question and, at times, reject the
                                                                           values upheld by their parents.

                                                                           Parental dilemmas: Seeking
                                                                           solutions
                                                                              As parents grapple with the evolving
                                                                           dynamics, they find themselves ponder-
                                                                           ing solutions to this widening chasm.
                                                                           Can the younger generation be recon-
                                                                           nected with their values? Will parents
                                                                           regain the authority to make decisions
           sertiveness, making the clash between   suggestion of an alliance with an Indian   regarding their children's marriages?
           generations more palpable.      settled in America was proposed, the   These questions loom large, leaving par-
                                           daughter nonchalantly gave her approval   ents yearning for answers and hoping
           Live-in relationships as a symbol   without considering the cultural implica-  for a future where mutual respect and
           of rebellion                    tions. Such instances reveal a growing   understanding between generations can
             A poignant manifestation of this re-  trend where the youth dismisses age-old   be restored.
           bellion is the increasing acceptance of   customs without regard for their parents'
           live-in relationships. Instances abound   sentiments.           Communication as the bedrock of
           where parents, adhering to cultural                             understanding
           norms, have urged their children to   The role of social media     To bridge the gap between parents
           marry within the confines of traditional   Social media's pervasive influence   and their children, effective communica-
           rituals. Astonishingly, children often   plays a pivotal role in shaping the atti-  tion is paramount. Parents need to create
           adamantly refuse, choosing instead to   tudes of the new generation. The con-  an environment where open dialogue is
           continue their live-in arrangements. This   stant exposure to diverse perspectives   encouraged, allowing for the exchange
           defiance underscores a broader shift to-  and lifestyles fosters an environment   of perspectives without judgment. By
           wards a rejection of traditional values in   where individualism is championed,   fostering a space for honest conver-
           favor of adopting a more Westernized   often at the expense of traditional   sations, both parties can gain insights
           lifestyle.                      values. This phenomenon accelerates the   into each other's values and concerns,
                                           generational divide, making it even   laying the foundation for understanding.
           Case studies highlighting the   more challenging for parents to bridge   Parents must be willing to listen ac-
           chasm                           the gap.                        tively to their children's viewpoints, ac-
             Several cases underscore the wide-                            knowledging the challenges posed by
           ning gap between parents and the   The impact of globalization on   the rapidly changing world. Simulta-
           younger generation. One such example   traditions               neously, children should recognize the
           involves a mother who implored her   Globalization has ushered in an era   wisdom embedded in their parents' ex-
           daughter to marry her live-in partner,   of interconnectedness, exposing younger   periences, appreciating the cultural and
           only to be met with resistance. When the   generations to a myriad of cultures and   familial context that shapes their values.
                                                                           Through mutual understanding, a middle
                                                                           ground can be established that respects
                                                                           tradition while accommodating the
                                                                           evolving aspirations of the younger gen-
                                                                           eration.

                                                                           Education and cultural sensitivity
                                                                              Education plays a pivotal role in
                                                                           shaping perspectives. Both parents and
                                                                           children need to invest time in under-
                                                                           standing the historical and cultural sig-
         A parent in struggle                                              seminars, or family discussions centered
                                                                           nificance of traditions. Workshops,
                                                                           around cultural heritage can provide a
                                                                           platform for learning and appreciation.
                                                                              Moreover, cultural sensitivity should


           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            be emphasized, fostering an awareness  13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Promoting responsible social media
                                                                           use involves fostering a discerning ap-
                                                                           proach to online content. Parents can
                                                                           guide their children in distinguishing be-
                                                                           tween constructive dialogue and harmful
                                                                           influences, empowering them to use so-
         A young lady engrossed in work                                    lion.
                                                                           cial media as a platform for positive en-
                                                                           gagement rather than a source of rebel-

                                                                           Empowering tradition through
                                                                           adaptation
                                                                              Tradition is not static; it evolves over
                                                                           Parents and children can collaborate to
                                                                           reinterpret traditions in a way that res-
                                                                           time to accommodate societal changes.
                                                                           onates with contemporary values. This
                                                                           adaptive approach allows for the preser-
                                                                           vation of cultural heritage while ac-
                                                                           knowledging the need for flexibility in a
                                                                           dynamic world.
                                                                              For instance, in matters of marriage,
                                                                           parents can explore ways to incorporate
         Children disregard parents' wishes                                provide a compromise that satisfies both
                                                                           traditional ceremonies into modern cele-
                                                                           brations. This fusion of old and new can

                                                                           generations, fostering a sense of conti-
                                                                           nuity while embracing change.
                                                                              The clash between tradition and
                                                                           modernity is a perennial challenge faced
                                                                           by every generation. In the age of social

                                                                           gap between parents and children has
                                                                           widened, especially in matters of mar-
                                                                           riage. Navigating this complex terrain
           of the diversity within traditions. Rec-  Media literacy and responsible   media and heightened individualism, the
           ognizing that interpretations of customs   social media use     requires open communication, empathy,
           can vary, even within the same culture,                         and a willingness to find common
           promotes tolerance and a willingness to   While social media has contributed   ground. Only through understanding and
           adapt. Parents can share the importance   to the generation gap, it can also serve   compromise can both generations hope
           of certain rituals, helping children ap-  as a tool for bridging it. Media literacy   to bridge the gap and foster a society
           preciate the richness of their heritage   programs should be implemented to help   that respects both tradition and individ-
           while maintaining an openness to new   both parents and children critically eval-  ual autonomy.
           ideas.                          uate the content they consume. Under-  The road to reconciliation is paved
                                           standing that social media often presents   with mutual respect, education, and a
           Mentorship and role models      an idealized version of reality can miti-  shared commitment to preserving the
             Mentorship programs and exposure   gate the unrealistic expectations that   rich tapestry of cultural heritage in an
           to positive role models can play a piv-  contribute to generational conflicts.   ever-changing world. ■
           otal role in guiding the younger genera-
           tion towards a more balanced perspec-
           tive. Elders within the community, who
           have successfully navigated the chal-
           lenges of modernity while upholding tra-
           ditions, can serve as inspirational fig-
           ures.
             By witnessing individuals who have
           found harmony between tradition and
           contemporary values, young people may                                                           A parent and young adult in conversation
           be more inclined to explore a similar
           path. Creating opportunities for inter-
           generational interactions can facilitate
           the transfer of wisdom and provide a
           roadmap for navigating the complexities
           of cultural identity in a globalized world.

           14                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[EYEWEAR TECHNOLOGY














































           Spectacle Revolution



           From necessity








           to style









           By Dr. Uzma Naaz

                he rich history of spectacles is a   nings to intricate designs, spectacles   cutting-edge innovations, and the prom-
                mesmerizing journey through the   have played a pivotal role in enhancing   ising future of eyewear.
           Tannals of time, offering insights   the quality of life for countless individ-
           into the relentless human pursuit of   uals. In this detailed examination, we   Ancient origins
           clearer vision. This exploration spans   will delve into the historical intricacies   The origins of spectacles can be
           centuries, weaving through the fabric of   of spectacles, exploring their ancient   traced back to ancient times, with ev-
           human ingenuity, tracing the origins,   origins, the Renaissance period, techno-  idence suggesting that the Romans
           evolution, and profound impact of spec-  logical advancements in the 18th and   crafted rudimentary lenses as early as
           tacles on society. From humble begin-  19th centuries, the modern era with its   the 1st century. These initial lenses,

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[made from glass or rock crystal, prima-  convex lenses set in frames that could be   The renaissance and the spread of
           rily served the purpose of magnification,   balanced on the nose. This invention   spectacles
           facilitating reading for individuals with   marked a revolutionary step forward in   The Renaissance, a period from the
           vision impairments. However, the trans-  vision correction, especially for those   14th to the 17th century, witnessed a
           formative leap in the history of spec-  suffering from presbyopia. The ability to   convergence of intellectual, artistic, and
           tacles occurred in the 13th century.   enhance near vision brought about a sig-  scientific advancements. Spectacles,
             Around 1286, Venetian craftsmen   nificant improvement in the quality of   during this era, became emblematic of
           fashioned the first wearable spectacles.   life for individuals grappling with age-  progress and enlightenment, embodying
           These groundbreaking creations featured   related vision challenges.   the spirit of discovery. As the demand
                                                                           for these vision aids surged, skilled arti-
                                                                           sans refined their designs, and the man-
                                                                           ufacturing process underwent significant
                                                                           improvements.
                                                                              In this period, frames made from ma-
                                                                           terials like wood, horn, and leather
                                                                           emerged, reflecting a departure from the
                                                                           simpler designs of earlier times. The de-
                                                                           velopment of concave and convex lenses
         Custom-made Bespoke Frames                                        specific vision problems. Spectacles
                                                                           allowed for more tailored solutions to
                                                                           evolved from being purely functional to
                                                                           becoming fashionable accessories, re-
                                                                           flecting not just the wearer's need for
                                                                           clear vision but also their social status
                                                                           and intellectual prowess.

                                                                           The 18th and 19th centuries:
                                                                           Technological advancements
                                                                              The 18th century brought about sub-
                                                                           stantial advancements in lens grinding
                                                                           and polishing techniques, enhancing the
                                                                           precision of lens crafting. This refine-
                                                                           ment translated into more accurate pre-
                                                                           scriptions, catering to a broader spec-
                                                                           trum of vision impairments. Notably,
                                                                           Benjamin Franklin, a polymath of the
                                                                           era, is often credited with the invention
                                                                           of bifocals in the 1780s. Bifocals com-
                                                                           bined two different prescriptions in a
                                                                           single lens, offering a seamless solution
                                                                           for both near and distant vision.
         Gold Pince-nez                                                    era with the onset of the industrial rev-
                                                                              The 19th century marked a pivotal
                                                                           olution. This transformative period had a
                                                                           profound impact on the manufacturing
                                                                           of spectacles. Mass production tech-
                                                                           niques were introduced, making spec-
                                                                           tacles more accessible to a broader range
                                                                           of people. The introduction of steel and
                                                                           other metals in frame construction re-
                                                                           placed traditional materials, resulting in
                                                                           more durable and lightweight designs.
                                                                              During this time, the role of opticians
                                                                           became increasingly prominent. The
                                                                           profession evolved, and opticians be-
                                                                           came skilled in crafting lenses to address
                                                                           various vision issues.
                                                                              The collaboration between opticians
         Medieval-glasses                                                  finement of spectacles, making them not
                                                                           and manufacturers further fueled the re-
                                                                           only functional but also aesthetically
                                                                           pleasing.


           16                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[future  of  eyewear  promises  even  more
                                                                           innovations,  ensuring  that  the  journey
                                                                           of  improving  vision  remains  an  ongo-
                                                                           ing  and  captivating  saga.
                                                                              The  story  of  spectacles  is  not
                                                                           merely  a  chronicle  of  optical  advance-
                                                                           ments;  it  is  a  reflection  of  the  deep
         Expensive Bentley glasses                                         world  with  greater  clarity.  As  we  gaze
                                                                           connection  between  science,  culture,
                                                                           and  the  human  desire  to  perceive  the
                                                                           into  the  future,  the  continued  fusion
                                                                           of  technology  and  eyewear  opens  new
                                                                           frontiers,  holding  the  promise  of
                                                                           further  enhancing  the  way  we  see  and

                                                                              The  evolution  of  spectacles  con-
                                                                           experience  the  world.
           Modern era and technological    the  cutting-edge  designs  of  the  21st   tinues  to  be  an  enthralling  narrative,
           innovations                     century,  spectacles  have  evolved  into   echoing  the  human  spirit's  ceaseless
                                           a  critical  aspect  of  our  daily  lives.  As   quest  for  knowledge  and  improve-
             The  20th  century  ushered  in  a  new   technology  continues  to  advance,  the   ment. ■
           era  of  technological  innovations  that
           revolutionized  the  field  of  optometry.
           Plastic  frames  gained  popularity  due   World's most expensive
           to  their  affordability  and  a  broader
           20th  century  saw  the  introduction  of  frames and lenses
           range  of  design  possibilities.  The  mid-

           contact  lenses,  providing  an  alternative
           solution  for  vision  correction.  Laser   n the world of eyewear, there are   The Icon III frames are known for
           eye  surgery  emerged  as  a  ground-  Iseveral frames and lenses that are   their exceptional craftsmanship and
           breaking  procedure  that  could  reshape   known for their exceptionally high   limited production, with prices ranging
           the  cornea,  offering  a  more  permanent   prices due to factors such as luxury   from tens to hundreds of thousands of
           vision  correction  option.      materials, intricate designs, and brand   dollars.
             The  latter  half  of  the  20th  century   prestige. Here are a few examples of   4. Gold and Diamond frames by
           and  the  early  21st  century  witnessed   some of the costliest frames and   Dolce & Gabbana: Dolce & Gabbana
           the  development  of  progressive  lenses,   lenses:            offers luxurious eyewear options, in-
           photochromic  coatings,  and  anti-reflec-  1. Cartier Panthère Precious Eyes   cluding frames adorned with gold and
           tive  coatings.  Progressive  lenses,  with   Sunglasses: Cartier is renowned for its   diamonds. These limited-edition
           their  gradual  transition  from  near  to   luxury eyewear, and the Panthère Pre-  frames showcase intricate detailing,
           distant  vision,  addressed  the  limita-  cious Eyes Sunglasses are among the   with frames and temples crafted from
           tions  of  bifocals  and  trifocals.  Photo-  most expensive eyewear pieces in the   gold and embellished with diamonds.
           chromic  coatings  enabled  lenses  to   world. These sunglasses feature an ex-  The prices for these frames can vary
           darken  in  response  to  UV  light,   quisite design, encrusted with dia-  but often reach high five-figure or six-
           adapting  to  changing  lighting  con-  monds, emeralds, and other precious   figure amounts.
           ditions.  Anti-reflective  coatings  re-  gemstones. A pair of these sunglasses   5. Custom-made Bespoke
           duced  glare  and  improved  clarity,   can cost several hundred thousand dol-  Frames: Some eyewear brands or op-
           especially  in  low-light  situations.   lars.                  tical boutiques offer bespoke eyewear
             The  integration  of  technology  into   2. Bentley Eyewear EXP 100 GT:   services that allow customers to have
           eyewear  represents  the  latest  frontier   This collaboration between Bentley   frames completely tailored to their
           in  the  ongoing  evolution  of  spectacles.   and Estede combines the craftsman-  preferences and measurements. These
           Smart  glasses,  equipped  with  features   ship of luxury cars with high-end eye-  custom-made frames can be crafted
           such  as  augmented  reality  displays,   wear. The EXP 100 GT frames are   from high-end materials like buffalo
           activity  tracking,  and  even  prescription   made from solid white gold or plati-  horn, exotic woods, or precious
           monitoring,  are  pushing  the  bound-  num, featuring unique designs and in-  metals. The prices for such frames can
           aries  of  traditional  eyewear.  These  in-  tricate details. The lenses are often   vary greatly, depending on the materi-
           novations  not  only  cater  to  vision  cor-  customized to the individual's pre-  als, design, and level of customization.
           rection  but  also  integrate  seamlessly   scription. These frames can reach   It's important to note that the prices
           into  the  digital  age,  providing  wearers   prices exceeding $200,000.   mentioned here represent some of the
           with  enhanced  functionality.     3. Maybach-The Icon III: Inspired   most exceptional and extravagant eye-
             In  conclusion,  the  history  of  spec-  by Maybach automobiles, these frames   wear options available. Most eyewear
           tacles  is  a  testament  to  human  curios-  feature exquisite handcrafted designs,   on the market falls within a wide range
           ity,  ingenuity,  and  the  relentless  pur-  often incorporating precious materials   of prices that cater to various budgets
           suit  of  clearer  vision.  From  their   like gold, diamonds, and buffalo horn.   and preferences.
           modest  beginnings  in  ancient  Rome  to

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[FESTIVALS
































           Holi




           The vibrant








           festival of colors








           By Aditya Joshi

                 oli, also known as the Festival   To truly understand the essence of   ied by the ritualistic Holika Dahan ob-
                 of Colors, stands as a testament   Holi, one must delve into the historical   served the night before Holi.
           Hto the vibrant and dynamic cul-  and mythological narratives that have
           tural tapestry of Hindu traditions. This   shaped this colorful celebration. One of   Celebrations
           ancient celebration, marked on March   the most revered legends associated with   Holika Dahan: The Holi celebra-
           25, 2024, transcends its religious origins   Holi is that of Holika and Prahlada.   tions commence with the ceremonial
           to become a global symbol of diversity,   King Hiranyakashipu, granted a boon of   lighting of bonfires during the Holika
           unity, and the triumph of good over evil.   near invincibility, sought to eliminate his   Dahan ritual. People gather around these
           Rooted in historical and mythological   son Prahlada's devotion to Lord Vishnu.   fires, symbolizing the triumph of good
           narratives, Holi has evolved into a festi-  Holika, the king's sister immune to fire,   over evil. The ritual involves prayers,
           val that not only resonates with the   attempted to kill Prahlada by sitting with   chanting, and the burning of effigies,
           Hindu community but also attracts par-  him in a blazing fire. However, in a turn   creating a sense of community and spiri-
           ticipants from diverse backgrounds   of events, Holika perished, and Prahlada   tual connection. The flames of the bon-
           worldwide.                      emerged unscathed. Holi commemorates   fire are believed to purify the surround-
             Historical and mythological roots   this triumph of good over evil, embod-  ings and ward off negative energies.

           18                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Rangwali Holi: The main event,   parks, and open spaces come alive with   of togetherness.
           Rangwali Holi, takes place on the day   a kaleidoscope of colors as people of all   Traditional Music and Dance: Holi
           following Holika Dahan. This part of the   ages and backgrounds participate in the   is synonymous with traditional music
           celebration involves the playful throw-  festivities. It is a time of unbridled joy,   and dance, which adds to the festive at-
           ing of vibrant colored powders, known   laughter, and camaraderie, transcending   mosphere. The beats of dhols resonate
           as gulal, and water balloons. Streets,   social boundaries and fostering a sense   through the air as people dance and sing
                                                                           folk songs, celebrating the spirit of Holi.
                                                                           These cultural expressions contribute to
                                                                           the festival's unique charm, providing a
                                                                           platform for artistic and creative en-
                                                                           deavors.
                                                                              Delicious Holi Specialties: The gas-
                                                                           tronomic delights of Holi play a crucial
                                                                           role in enhancing the festive experience.
                                                                           Specialties like gujiya, a sweet dum-
                                                                           pling filled with khoya, and other savory
         Girls enjoying colors during Holi                                 food during Holi further strengthens the
                                                                           snacks are prepared and shared among
                                                                           friends and family. The act of sharing
                                                                           bonds of togetherness and underscores
                                                                           the communal nature of the festival.

                                                                           Global Impact
                                                                              In recent years, Holi has transcended
                                                                           its cultural and religious boundaries,
                                                                           making its mark on the global stage.
                                                                           Many non-Hindu communities and indi-
                                                                           viduals from diverse cultural back-
                                                                           grounds actively participate in Holi cele-
                                                                           brations. The festival's inclusive nature
                                                                           and universal themes of joy, love, and
                                                                           unity resonate with people worldwide,
         Heart's desire: To color everyone                                 India; it has become a celebrated event
                                                                           turning it into a symbol of cultural ex-
                                                                           change and understanding.
                                                                              Holi's global impact is not limited to
                                                                           in various parts of the world. Cities
                                                                           around the globe organize Holi festivals,
                                                                           attracting participants from different cul-
                                                                           tural backgrounds. These events often
                                                                           feature live music, dance performances,
                                                                           and, of course, the iconic throwing of
                                                                           colored powders, creating an at-
                                                                           mosphere reminiscent of the authentic
                                                                           Indian celebration.

                                                                           Celebrations across India
                                                                              Holi is celebrated with great enthusi-
                                                                           asm in different parts of India. In Ma-
                                                                           thura and Vrindavan, the birthplace of
                                                                           Lord Krishna, Holi is celebrated in a
                                                                           grand manner. The festivities include
                                                                           'Lathmar Holi' where women playfully
                                                                           beat men with sticks, symbolizing the
         Separated friends reconnect                                       town of Barsana hosts the famous 'Lath-
                                                                           playful aspect of Lord Krishna's love for
                                                                           Radha. In the state of Uttar Pradesh, the
                                                                           mar Holi.'
                                                                              Moreover, social media platforms
                                                                           play a crucial role in spreading the joy
                                                                           of Holi globally. Photos and videos cap-
                                                                           turing the exuberance of the festival are


           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            shared widely, fostering a sense of con- 19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[colors. These alternatives, made from
                                                                           natural ingredients, reduce the environ-
                                                                           mental impact of Holi celebrations. Ad-
                                                                           ditionally, promoting water conservation
                                                                           and responsible disposal of waste during
                                                                           the festivities can contribute to a more
                                                                           sustainable approach to celebrating Holi.
                                                                              As Holi 2024 approaches, it is a time
                                                                           to reflect on the rich tapestry of cultural,
                                                                           religious, and historical elements that
                                                                           define this vibrant festival.
                                                                              As we celebrate Holi on March 25,
                                                                           2024, let the spirit of this festival inspire
                                                                           us to embrace diversity, foster unity, and
                                                                           spread happiness in our lives and com-
                                                                           munities. Whether through traditional
                                                                           rituals, festive gatherings, or global cele-
                                                                           brations, Holi continues to be a beacon
                                                                           of joy, reminding us of the beauty that
                                                                           comes from shared celebrations and the
                                                                           bonds that connect us all. ■

                                                                             Safe and
                                                                             eco-friendly Holi


                                                                               Use natural colors: Synthetic
         Few embrace safe, Eco-friendly Holi                                 fruits, and vegetables.
                                                                             colors can be harmful to the skin and
                                                                             the environment. It's best to use nat-
                                                                             ural colors made from flowers,
                                                                               Stay hydrated: Holi can be tir-
                                                                             ing, especially if you're out in the
                                                                             sun playing with colors. It's essential
                                                                             to stay hydrated by drinking plenty
                                                                             of water and fluids.
                                                                               Protect your skin and hair: Be-
                                                                             fore playing with colors, it's a good
                                                                             idea to apply coconut or olive oil on
                                           cal roots, Holi holds deep cultural sig-  your skin and hair. This will protect
            Holi Unaffected by             nificance in the Hindu community. It is a   your skin and hair from the harsh
            Lunar Eclipse                  time when people come together to cele-  colors and make them easier to wash
                                                                             off later.
                                           brate the arrival of spring, marking the
                                           end of winter and the beginning of a   Wear protective clothing: Holi
              This year, the lunar eclipse is coin-  season characterized by vibrancy and re-  can get messy, so it's best to wear old
            ciding with Holi celebrations, ho-  newal. The use of colors during Holi   clothes and shoes that you don't
            wever, many people are concerned   symbolizes the various hues of life and   mind getting dirty. Consider wearing
            about whether the ‘sutak period’ will   the diversity that defines the human ex-  sunglasses to protect your eyes from
            impact the rituals. Fortunately, this   perience.                color.
            wouldn't be the case. The lunar   Holi also serves as a reminder of the   Respect others: Holi is a festival
            eclipse wouldn't be visible in India as   importance of forgiveness and reconcili-  of love and unity. It's important to
            there is no need to observe the ‘sutak   ation. During the festivities, people   respect others' boundaries and not
            period’. There is no issue with con-  often extend gestures of goodwill and   force anyone to participate if they
            ducting Holi rituals and puja in this   bury past grievances. The festival pro-  don't want to play with colors.
            auspicious muhurta.            vides an opportunity for individuals to   Avoid littering: Dispose of waste
                                           let go of negativity and embrace a fresh   responsibly. Avoid littering the
           nection and shared celebration among   start, promoting harmony and unity   streets and instead, use a bin or a
           people of diverse cultures. This digital   within communities.    trash bag.
           exchange further contributes to the                                 By following these tips, you can
           global unity promoted by the festival.   Environmental considerations   enjoy Holi while ensuring your
                                             To address environmental concerns,   safety and being eco-friendly. Have a
           Cultural significance           there is a growing movement advocating   happy and colorful Holi!
             Beyond its historical and mythologi-  for the use of eco-friendly and organic

           20                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[MODERN TRENDS






































           Smiles as Canvases



           The artistic evolution of






           dental jewellery







           By Anaya Gupta

             n an era where the pursuit of beauty   invites individuals to express their   was prevalent among certain indigenous
             has taken unprecedented turns, the   unique style through the most unex-  tribes as a symbol of beauty and cultural
           Iconventional standards of attractive-  pected canvas—their smiles. Embarking   identity.
           ness have undergone a radical transfor-  on a journey that transcends the bound-  In ancient Egypt, where beauty held
           mation. Traditionally, white and well-  aries of traditional beauty, dental jew-  immense cultural significance, both men
           shaped teeth were deemed to be an   ellery has emerged as a dazzling and un-  and women adorned their teeth with
           essential component of beauty, symbol-  conventional form of self-expression.   semi-precious stones and metals. Fast
           izing health and vitality. However, the                         forward to the Renaissance period in Eu-
           contemporary fashion landscape has in-  Origins of dental jewellery   rope, where dental jewellery experienced
           troduced a captivating twist to this age-  The origins of dental jewellery can be   a resurgence among the elite. Aristocrats
           old notion. Enter the enchanting world of   traced back to ancient cultures that em-  would often decorate their teeth with
           dental jewellery, where the art of adorn-  braced body modification and ornamen-  gold, pearls, or gemstones, not only as a
           ing teeth with small gemstones and dec-  tation. Historically, various civilizations   symbol of wealth but also as an expres-
           orative accessories has become the latest   viewed dental adornments as symbols of   sion of their unique status in society.
           trend in lifestyle aesthetics.   status, wealth, or spiritual significance.   However, the modern resurgence of
             This avant-garde trend not only chal-  In Southeast Asia, for instance, the prac-  dental jewellery can be attributed to the
           lenges the conventional norms but also   tice of embedding gemstones into teeth   convergence of fashion, pop culture, and

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[sive, allowing for easy removal without
                                                                           causing damage.
                                                                              Beyond tooth gems, dental jewellery
                                                                           encompasses a wide range of acces-
                                                                           sories, including tooth piercings, tooth
         Sparkling white teeth: A beauty essential                         more than just fashion accessories; they
                                                                           tattoos, and even tooth-shaped charms.
                                                                           The artistry involved in creating these
                                                                           dental adornments has elevated them to
                                                                           are miniature masterpieces that reflect
                                                                           the craftsmanship and creativity of both
                                                                           the wearer and the designer.

                                                                             Materials used for





                                           tal norms and express their non-confor-  dental jewellery
                                                                               Dental jewellery can be made
                                           mity. In the Western world, dental jew-  from a variety of materials, depend-
                                           ellery has become synonymous with   ing on the desired look and durabil-
                                           self-expression and a way to enhance   ity. Here are some common materi-
                                           one's personal style.             als used for dental jewellery:
                                             Moreover, the trend has found a place   rovski crystals and other types of
                                                                               1. Crystals and Gems: Swa-
         Smiling with a tooth gem          Influential figures in the music and fash-  dental jewellery. These crystals are
                                           in various subcultures, including the vi-
                                           brant hip-hop and street fashion scenes.
                                                                             gemstones are popular choices for
                                           ion industries have proudly showcased
                                                                             known for their sparkling appear-
                                           their bedazzled smiles, further fueling
                                                                             ance and come in various colors and
                                                                             sizes. They are typically attached to
                                           the popularity of dental jewellery among
                                           the youth.
                                             From New York to Tokyo, the allure
                                                                               2. Enamel Designs: Some dental
                                                                             jewellery is made using enamel,
                                           of dental jewellery has captured the   the tooth using dental adhesives.
                                           imagination of individuals seeking to   which is a colored glass-like mate-
                                           make a statement beyond traditional   rial that is applied to the tooth's sur-
                                           fashion accessories. The trend has be-  face. Enamel designs can be custom-
                                           come a visual language that transcends   ized to create unique patterns or
                                           linguistic barriers, allowing people from   symbols, adding a pop of color to
                                           different walks of life to communicate   the teeth.
                                           their personality, creativity, and rebel-  3. Gold and Silver: For a more
                                           lious spirit through the gleam of their   luxurious look, dental jewellery can
                                           adorned teeth.                    be made from gold or silver. Thin,
                                                                             decorative metal pieces or patterns
         A modern trend                    forms, ranging from subtle and elegant   tooth, creating a subtle yet elegant
                                           The art of smile enhancement
                                                                             can be bonded to the surface of the
                                             Dental jewellery comes in various
                                                                             effect.
                                           to bold and extravagant. Tooth gems,
                                                                               4. Tooth-Colored Composites:
                                           crystals, or gold, are meticulously ap-
           a growing desire for individuality. The   made from materials such as diamonds,   Another popular option for dental
                                                                             jewellery is using tooth-colored
           trend gained momentum in the early   plied to the tooth surface using safe and   composites. These materials blend in
           2000s when celebrities began flaunting   non-invasive techniques. Some enthusi-  naturally with the tooth, making the
           tooth gems and accessories, transform-  asts opt for small, understated gems that   jewellery discreet and less notice-
           ing what was once an obscure practice   add a touch of sparkle to their smiles,   able. They can be used to create var-
           into a mainstream fashion statement.   while others embrace elaborate designs,   ious designs and shapes.
                                           turning their teeth into miniature works   It's important to note that the ma-
           Cultural implications and global   of art.                        terials used for dental jewellery
           appeal                            Dentists and dental professionals   should be safe for oral use and
             Dental jewellery transcends cultural   skilled in cosmetic dentistry are at the   should not cause any harm to the
           boundaries, resonating with people   forefront of this trend, ensuring that the   teeth or gums. Dental professionals
           around the globe. In Japan, tooth gems   application of dental jewellery is not   typically use materials that are bio-
           are embraced as a form of rebellion   only aesthetically pleasing but also safe   compatible and non-toxic to ensure
           against conventional beauty standards,   for oral health. The gems are typically   the safety and comfort of the patient.
           allowing individuals to challenge socie-  attached to the tooth using dental adhe-

           22                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Impact on Oral

                                                                            Health

                                                                               Dental jewellery, when applied
         Various types of tooth gems                                        cause any harm to the natural teeth or
                                                                            and maintained properly, should not
                                                                            gums over a period of time. Ho-
                                                                            wever, it's essential to follow good
                                                                            oral hygiene practices and seek regu-
                                                                            lar dental check-ups to ensure the
                                                                            jewellery is not causing any issues.
                                                                            Here are a few considerations regard-
                                                                            ing the potential impact of dental
                                                                            jewellery on oral health:
                                                                               1. Tooth Damage: If the dental
                                                                            jewellery is not applied correctly or
         Young lady prepared for dental jewellery placement                 the dental jewellery applied by a
                                                                            if it becomes loose or damaged, there
                                                                            is a risk of it scratching or damaging
                                                                            the tooth enamel. It's crucial to have

                                                                            qualified dental professional who can
                                                                            ensure proper placement and secure
                                                                            bonding.
                                                                               2. Gum Irritation: Poorly placed
                                                                            dental jewellery or rough edges can
                                                                            irritate the gums, leading to discom-
                                                                            fort, inflammation, or gingivitis.
                                                                            Regular brushing, flossing, and gen-
                                                                            risk of gum irritation.
                                                                               3. Increased Plaque and Tartar
                                                                            Buildup: Dental jewellery, espe-
                                                                            cially when placed on the front sur-
                                           remain exciting, with advancements in   tle oral care can help minimize the
           Navigating trends and future    dental technology and materials contin-  face of the tooth, can create small
           projections                     ually pushing the boundaries of what is   areas for plaque and tartar to accu-
             As with any fashion trend, the pop-  possible. From innovative materials that   mulate. Regular and thorough oral
           ularity of dental jewellery is ever-  enhance durability to personalized de-  hygiene practices, including brush-
           evolving. What was once considered   signs that reflect individual stories, the   ing, flossing, and professional clean-
           edgy and unconventional may become   world of dental jewellery is poised to   ings, can help prevent plaque and tar-
           mainstream, or vice versa. However,   evolve into a realm where creativity   tar buildup.
           the allure of dental jewellery lies in its   knows no bounds.       4. Allergic Reactions: In rare
           ability to adapt and cater to a diverse   In conclusion, dental jewellery has   cases, individuals may have allergies
           range of styles. Whether it's a discreet   transformed the conventional percep-  or sensitivities to the materials used
           gem accentuating a canine tooth or a   tion of beauty and self-expression.   in dental jewellery. It's important to
           dazzling display of intricate designs,   What was once an overlooked aspect of   inform your dental professional
           dental jewellery continues to captivate   personal adornment has emerged as a   about any known allergies or sensi-
           individuals seeking to make a bold   canvas for creativity, allowing individ-  tivities to ensure that suitable materi-
           statement through their smiles.   uals to showcase their uniqueness with   als are used.
             The trend has not only infiltrated the   a simple smile.          Overall, if dental jewellery is ap-
           world of fashion and pop culture but   As the trend continues to gain mo-  plied correctly and maintained prop-
           has also become a means of expressing   mentum, one thing is certain—the   erly, it should not cause any long-
           individual stories and experiences. Cus-  world of dental jewellery is not merely   term harm to the natural teeth or
           tom-designed dental jewellery allows   about enhancing teeth; it's about cele-  gums. However, it's essential to prac-
           wearers to showcase their passions, in-  brating the art of individuality in the   tice good oral hygiene and seek pro-
           terests, or personal milestones through   most unexpected and dazzling way pos-  fessional dental care to ensure the
           unique and bespoke pieces. From musi-  sible. Whether it's a subtle gem or an   health and integrity of the teeth and
           cal notes to miniature landscapes, den-  intricate design, dental jewellery is a   gums. Regular check-ups with a den-
           tal jewellery has evolved into a dy-  testament to the limitless possibilities   tist will help detect and address any
           namic form of self-expression that   of self-expression, where the beauty of   potential issues associated with den-
           transcends mere aesthetics.     a smile becomes a captivating work of   tal jewellery.
             The future projections of this trend   art. ■

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[RELIGIOUS HERITAGE











































           Roots of Renewal


           Easter's historical






           tapestry







            By Aarav Sharma

                aster, a time-honored celebration   brations, and diverse global traditions.   inclusion of elements from pre-existing
                deeply rooted in Christian tradi-                          cultural traditions has contributed to its
           Etions, serves as a beacon of hope   Historical background      universality.
           and renewal, marking the resurrection   The origins of the term "Easter" can
           of Jesus Christ from the dead. As this   be traced back to the Old English word   Religious significance
           religious observance transcends its spir-  "ēastre," associated with the spring sea-  At its core, Easter holds profound
           itual roots, it has evolved into a globally   son and the pagan festival of the vernal   significance for Christians worldwide. It
           embraced cultural and festive occasion,   equinox. The early Christians, recogniz-  commemorates the pivotal event of the
           weaving together a rich tapestry of cus-  ing an opportunity to integrate their   Christian faith – the resurrection of
           toms, symbolism, and historical signifi-  faith with existing cultural practices,   Jesus Christ. According to the New Tes-
           cance. This comprehensive exploration   strategically aligned the celebration of   tament, Jesus was crucified on Good
           of Easter will delve into its historical   Christ's resurrection with the season of   Friday, and on the third day, Easter Sun-
           background, religious significance, the   renewal and rebirth. While Easter is   day, he rose from the dead, symbolizing
           observance of Holy Week, secular cele-  firmly rooted in Christian beliefs, the   victory over sin and death. This trium-

           24                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[tradition can be traced back to German
                                                                           folklore, where the hare symbolized fer-
                                                                           tility and new life.
                                                                              Easter Parades: Many communities
                                                                           organize colorful parades on Easter
                                                                           Sunday. These parades feature floats,
                                                                           religious processions, music, and festive
                                                                           attire. They provide an opportunity for
                                                                           people to come together, celebrate, and
                                                                           showcase their Easter spirit.
                                                                              The Cross: The cross, a significant
                                                                           Christian symbol, holds particular im-
                                                                           portance during the Easter season. It
                                                                           serves as a reminder of the crucifixion
         Maundy Thursday rituals                                           sizing the core beliefs of the Christian
                                                                           and resurrection of Jesus Christ, empha-
                                                                           faith.

                                                                           Easter traditions
                                                                              The diversity of Easter traditions
                                                                           around the world reflects the rich tapes-
                                                                           try of global cultures and historical in-
           phant moment offers believers the   sents the interlude between his death   fluences. In Greece, the midnight Res-
           promise of eternal life and redemption,   and resurrection, leading to the joyous   urrection Service is a central part of the
           making Easter a cornerstone of Chris-  culmination of the Easter celebration on   celebration, with people lighting can-
           tian theology. The journey towards   Sunday.                    dles and sharing the "Holy Light."
           Easter begins with Lent, a period of in-                        Spain's Holy Week is marked by elabo-
           trospection, fasting, and prayer, culmi-  Traditions and symbols   rate processions depicting the Passion
           nating in the joyous celebration of   Easter is accompanied by a multi-  of Christ, showcasing a unique blend of
           Christ's victory over death.    tude of customs and symbols that vary   religious fervor and artistic expression.
                                           from one culture to another. Some of   In the United States and other Western
           Holy week                       the most common traditions include:   countries, Easter Sunday often involves
             The week leading up to Easter,   Easter Eggs: Eggs have long been   attending church services, sharing fes-
           known as Holy Week, unfolds as a   associated with new beginnings and re-  tive meals with family and friends, and
           series of events that reflect the profound   birth. The custom of decorating eggs   engaging in various egg-related activ-
           narrative of Christian salvation. Palm   has evolved to become an integral part   ities. Each culture contributes its dis-
           Sunday marks the beginning of Holy   of Easter celebrations. People often   tinctive flavor to the celebration, cre-
           Week, commemorating Jesus' trium-  paint, dye, or decorate eggs with vibrant   ating a mosaic of traditions that
           phant entry into Jerusalem, where   colors and intricate designs. It is also   collectively embody the spirit of Easter.
           crowds greeted him with palm    common to organize Easter egg hunts,
           branches. Maundy Thursday focuses on   where children search for hidden eggs.   Easter in different cultures
           the Last Supper, during which Jesus in-  Easter Bunny: The Easter Bunny,   Greece: In Greece, Easter is a grand
           stituted the sacrament of Holy Com-  often depicted as a friendly rabbit, is a   and elaborate affair, deeply rooted in
           munion. Good Friday, a day of solemn   popular symbol of Easter. It is believed   Orthodox Christian traditions. The mid-
           reflection, recalls the crucifixion and   to bring baskets filled with eggs and   night Resurrection Service, also known
           death of Jesus. Holy Saturday repre-  treats for children. The origins of this   as the Anastasi, takes place on Holy
                                                                           Saturday night. As the clock strikes
                                                                           midnight, the priest declares, "Christos
                                                                           Anesti" (Christ is Risen), and the con-
                                                                           gregation responds with "Alithos
                                                                           Anesti" (Truly He is Risen). Candles
                                                                           are lit from the "Holy Light," symboliz-
                                                                           ing the Resurrection, and the flame is
         Spain's Semana Santa Procession                                   nificant moment, symbolizing the tri-
                                                                           shared among the faithful. This cere-
                                                                           mony is a poignant and spiritually sig-
                                                                           umph of light over darkness.
                                                                              Spain: Spain's Holy Week, or Se-
                                                                           mana Santa, is renowned for its dra-
                                                                           matic processions depicting the Passion
                                                                           of Christ. Cities and towns across the

                                                                           as elaborate floats, called pasos, are car-

                                                                                                       25
           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            country come alive with religious fervor]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Modern-day



                                                                             additions


                                                                               The celebration of Easter has in-
                                                                             deed evolved over time, adapting to
                                                                             the changing cultural and social dy-
                                                                             namics. While the core religious sig-
                                                                             nificance remains intact, there have
         Easter eggs decorating                                              with Easter.
                                                                             been several modern-day additions
                                                                             to the traditional customs associated

                                                                               1. Commercialization: In recent
                                                                             times, the commercial aspect of
                                                                             Easter has gained prominence. The
                                                                             sale of Easter-themed merchandise,
                                                                             including chocolates, candies, and
           ried through the streets. These proces-  Easter is celebrated by Christians across   decorations, has become a wide-
           sions often involve hooded penitents,   the country. Churches are adorned with   spread practice. Retailers often
           adding an air of mystery to the events.   flowers and lights, and special Easter   create marketing campaigns centered
           The atmosphere is charged with emo-  services are held. In the state of Goa,   around Easter, promoting gift-giving
           tion, as the faithful reenact and reflect   which has a significant Christian pop-  and festive products.
           upon the events leading to Jesus' cru-  ulation, Easter is marked by proces-  2. Easter Egg Hunts: Easter egg
           cifixion. Semana Santa is a unique   sions, feasts, and cultural events. The   hunts have become a widely prac-
           blend of solemnity, artistic expression,   celebration reflects the cultural diversity   ticed tradition in many countries.
           and communal devotion.          of the country, showcasing how Easter   These events involve hiding and
             United States: In the United States,   is embraced within the broader tapestry   searching for eggs, often filled with
           Easter is celebrated with a mix of reli-  of Indian traditions.   chocolates or small gifts, in outdoor
           gious observance and secular traditions.   Easter, with its deep religious roots   or indoor spaces. While the concept
           Many people attend church services on   and inclusive cultural celebrations,   of egg hunts dates back centuries, it
           Easter Sunday, participating in special   stands as a testament to the universality   has gained popularity in recent times
           liturgies and hymns that emphasize the   of hope, renewal, and the enduring   as a fun activity for families and
           resurrection. Families come together for   cycle of life. From its historical origins   communities.
           festive meals, often featuring lamb or   to the rich symbolism of Holy Week,   3. Easter Bunny and Gift-giv-
           ham as the centerpiece. Easter egg   the secular festivities involving eggs   ing: The association of the Easter
           hunts, a beloved tradition for children,   and bunnies, and the diverse global tra-  Bunny with gift-giving has become
           involve hiding and searching for color-  ditions, Easter weaves together a narra-  more prevalent in modern times.
           ful eggs, sometimes filled with candies   tive that resonates across different cul-  4. Easter Parades and Festivals:
           or small toys. The White House hosts   tures and beliefs. Whether celebrated in   While parades have been part of
           an annual Easter Egg Roll on its lawn, a   a grand religious service, a quiet family   Easter traditions for centuries, the
           tradition dating back to 1878, attracting   gathering, or a vibrant community   modern-day parades have taken on a
           families from across the country.   event, Easter remains a time for reflec-  more elaborate and festive nature.
             India: In India, where diverse reli-  tion, joy, and the shared embrace of the   People participate in processions,
           gious and cultural practices coexist,   promise of new beginnings. ■   wearing colorful outfits, floats are
                                                                             decorated, music is played, and com-
                                                                             munity celebrations are organized.
                                                                               5. Social Media Celebrations:
                                                                             With the rise of social media plat-
                                                                             forms, Easter celebrations have
                                                                             taken on a new dimension.
                                                                               6. Easter-themed Events and
                                                                             Activities: In recent years, there has
                                                                             been an increase in Easter-themed
         Easter eggs decorating                                              Easter brunches, egg dyeing work-
                                                                             events and activities. These include
                                                                             shops, charity fundraisers, com-
                                                                             munity fairs, and theatrical perform-
                                                                             ances centered around the Easter
                                                                             story.


           26                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[TRAVEL





























           A Traveler's Tale


           Journey through Turkey’s






           Rich Heritage






           By Shahid A. Siddiqui*


                 mid the monotony induced by   paved the way for a Turkey expedition   One brisk morning, the charismatic
                 the pandemic, a chance en-  post-Eid festivities.         Goksu Pamir materialized, summoning
           Acounter with the series "Dirilis   Armed with an e-visa and a curated   us to the hotel lobby within 20 minutes.
           Ertugrul" catapulted me into an unex-  itinerary from Fez Travels, I set forth to   Fueled by anticipation, we hurriedly
           pected journey. Initially resistant, a mal-  Anatolia. Istanbul's minarets and vibrant   gathered, arriving in just 5 minutes. To
           functioning laptop led me to the capti-  markets resonated with on-screen tales.   our delight, Turkish tea, a taste only
           vating landscapes of ancient Anatolia   Despite a minor airport hiccup, an unex-  heard of until then, patiently awaited our
           via YouTube. The characters and their   pected act of kindness from a road main-  arrival.
           tales became companions, transporting   tenance worker set the tone for unparal-  With poised elegance, Goksu intro-
           me to an era where honor and camarade-  leled warmth throughout Turkey.   duced himself. Recognizing the tongue-
           rie thrived.                      This journey wasn't just through   twisting potential of his name, he gra-
             As the episodes unfolded, a burning   landscapes; it was a profound explora-  ciously suggested we call him Goksu –
           desire emerged—to explore the very   tion of the gracious hearts that wel-  an elegant moniker. As he detailed our
           landscapes that breathed life into the   comed me. The initial encounter's sim-  journey, the promise of an unforgettable
           epic tale. With lockdown easing, I dived   ple yet powerful act of generosity   adventure hung in the air. Amidst the
           into books and documentaries, turning   became a poignant reminder—true   aromatic notes of Turkish tea, Goksu's
           newfound knowledge into a tapestry of   beauty in travel lies not just in places but   words painted a vivid picture of the ex-
           dreams. Retirement on the horizon, my   in the hearts of those who embrace us   traordinary days ahead.
           wife's advice and strategic planning   along the way.              Seated comfortably in a luxurious

           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Mercedes 16-seater, our diverse group,   left open for personal exploration. The   ing the waters connecting Europe and
           representing eight nationalities, em-  following day marked the commence-  Asia, unveiling mesmerizing views of a
           barked on a ten-day odyssey guided by   ment of our adventure, venturing to the   nation that once held dominion over
           the charismatic Mr. Goksu. The anticipa-  Blue Mosque, St. Sophia Museum, Top-  three continents.
           tion of remarkable experiences lingered   kapi Palace, Hagia Irene, the Harem, and   In a world full of narratives about
           in the air like the aroma of that first cup   the Hippodrome. In the afternoon, a   Turkey, my journey wasn't just about
           of Turkish tea.                 spellbinding experience awaited us with   visiting a country; it was a quest to wit-
             The first afternoon in Istanbul was   a 'Half-day Bosphorus cruise,' navigat-  ness living history etched in the glow of
                                                                           the Holy Quran. I longed to tread upon
                                                                           grounds where civilizations once
                                                                           thrived, vanished into obscurity, and re-
                                                                           surfaced miraculously during excava-
                                                                           tions—a testament to the wonders of
                                                                           time and archaeology.
                                                                              Turkey unfolded before me not as a
                                                                           mere destination but as a vibrant narra-
                                                                           tive waiting to reveal chapters of awe
                                                                           and wonder. In Islamic history, this en-
                                                                           chanting region, referred to as "Shaam,"
                                                                           resonates with the echoes of numerous
                                                                           prophets whose stories are immortalized
         Sultanahmet Blue Mosque                                           "Kahf" weaves a tale of individuals tak-
                                                                           in the Holy Quran. The sacred Surah
                                                                           ing refuge in a cave with their faithful
                                                                           animal, their existence veiled in the
                                                                           mystery of passing years.
                                                                              Embarking on a chronological adven-
                                                                           ture, the subsequent morning greeted us
                                                                           with a mild contact of Indian iciness as
                                                                           we set our attractions at the Blue
                                                                           Mosque, constructed between 1609 and
                                                                           1616, by the architect Mehmet Ağa, in-
                                                                           structed by Sultan Ahmed- I. It was de-
                                                                           signed as an imperial show of strength to
                                                                           complement the imposing Hagia Sophia,
                                                                           which faces it across Sultan Ahmet
                                                                           Square. Adorned with thousands of
                                                                           Iznik tiles and intricate floral motifs in
                                                                           varying shades of blue, the mosque
         Hagia Sophia Mosque                                               fronted by a spacious courtyard and dis-
                                                                           stands as an iconic symbol of Istanbul,
                                                                           tinguished by six minarets.
                                                                              Our exploration continued to the Hip-
                                                                           podrome of Constantinople, once the vi-
                                                                           brant epicenter of sports and social life
                                                                           in the Byzantine capital. The first Hip-












         Topkapi Palace, Istanbul










           28                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[podrome was built In AD 203 by the
           Emperor Septimius Severus. A witness
           to thrilling horse races and chariot com-
           petitions, the Hippodrome reflected the
           popular pastimes of the ancient world.
           Despite succumbing to ruin by the end
           of the Byzantine Empire in 1453, it left
           behind echoes of ancient sporting glory
           and political intrigue.
             In the vicinity of the Hippodrome,
           our attention turned to the Serpent Col-
           umn, erected to commemorate the
           Greeks' victory over the Persians in the
           5th century BC. As part of the city's em-
           bellishment initiative, the relocation of
           the Tripod from the Temple of Apollo at                                                         Hot air balloons in Cappadocia
           Delphi to the center of the Hippodrome
           underscored the fusion of historical sig-
           nificance and artistic expression, shap-
           ing the city's architectural identity.
             Hagia Sophia, a significant Byzantine
           creation, emerged as a global monument   chestrated our exploration of the St. So-  the main residence of its sultans.
           with diverse historical layers within its   phia Museum and Topkapi Palace. The   A cruise was waiting to navigate us
           magnificent walls. Constructed between   Topkapı Palace is a large museum and li-  the waters that naturally divide Europe
           532 and 537 CE, it initially served as a   brary in the east of the Fatih district of   and Asia. The breathtaking separation of
           Christian church, later transforming into   Istanbul in Turkey. From the 1460s to   two continents unfolded as an extraordi-
           a mosque before becoming a museum   the completion of Dolmabahçe Palace in   nary experience, capturing the enchant-
           and, once again, reverting to a mosque.   1856, it served as the administrative   ing spectacle as the sun gracefully began
             Our guide with keen precision or-  center of the Ottoman Empire and was   its descent.
                                                                              Following a satisfying day of sight-
                                                                           seeing, a restful night was interrupted by
                                                                           an early morning alarm and persistent
                                                                           knocks on the door, signaling the reluc-
                                                                           tant departure from our cozy beds for the
                                                                           next destination—Çanakkale. Along the
                                                                           way, our journey took an emotional flip
                                                                           as we visited the Gallipoli Battlefields.
                                                                           The Gallipoli Campaign, orchestrated by
                                                                           way of the Entente powers, aimed to
         Cave Hotel Cappadocia                                             huge losses, it serves as a pivotal Otto-
                                                                           weaken the Ottoman Empire. Despite
                                                                           man victory, shaping Turkey's future and
                                                                           laying the foundation for the Republic of
                                                                           Turkey.
                                                                              Journeying to Kuşadası, with stops at
                                                                           Troy and Bergama, we explored ancient
                                                                           ruins of BC and a magnificent acropolis.
                                                                           Troy&Torzen Horse, with its UNESCO-
                                                                           listed archaeological site, invites the
                                                                           public to explore its 4000-year history
                                                                           marked by cycles of destruction and re-
                                                                           building.
                                                                              Pergamon, a prosperous ancient
                                                                           Greek city, showcased monumental tem-
                                                                           ples and a library. The well-planned
         Sultanahmet Hippodrome                                            grand theatre and Temple of Artemis,
                                                                           acropolis serves as a testament to suc-
                                                                           cessful urban planning. Ephesus, with its

                                                                           immersed me in the mystical aura of an
                                                                           ancient city. Pamukkale, renowned for
                                                                           its thermal waters, provided a stunning
                                                                           backdrop to Hierapolis' Greco-Roman


           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            town.                       29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Gallipoli battlefields and grave yard of Martyrs                    Pilgrimage Through

                                                                             Turkey's Rich History


                                                                               Turkey, the Republic of Türkiye,
                                                                             shines brightly as a bastion of secu-
                                                                             larism. Exploring Central Türkiye
                                                                             ignited a yearning for more, yet the
                                                                             prospect of migration remained dis-
                                                                             tant. Then came Cengiz Kellekci,
                                                                             our guide-turned-comrade, who el-
                                                                             evated our journey to unprece-
                                                                             dented heights. Tracing the foot-
                                                                             steps of revered figures like Hazrat
                                           A two-day stay, featuring hot air bal-  Ayub Ansari and Hazrat Abu Darda,
                                           loon sports, added excitement before   we embarked on a pilgrimage
                                           heading to Ankara.                steeped in historical significance.
                                             Ankara Turkey's captivating capital,   Among these esteemed figures
                                           mesmerized with well-preserved    lies Abu Şeybe al-Hudri, sharing a
                                           Roman and Ottoman architecture. The   unique bond with Prophet Muham-
                                           city's history weaved through civiliza-  mad (PBUH). Nearby, the tombs of
                                           tions, leaving an indelible mark. A   companions Hamdullah al-Ansari
         The Trojan Horse                  grul lived, unfolded the hero's tale.   significance rooted in Medina. The
                                                                             and Ahmet al-Ansari awaited, their
                                           visit to Söğüt, the place where Ertu-
                                                                             revelation of Abu Dhar al-Ghifari's
                                           Returning from Sogut, I visited the
                                           tomb of Hazrat Ayyub Ansari, a close
                                                                             tomb, foretold in Grand Vizier Ali
                                           companion of Prophet Muhammad.
                                             My journey captured Turkey's es-  Pasha's dream, added depth to our
                                                                             expedition.
             Our journey led us to the Silk   sence—a rich tapestry of religions, an-  Continuing onward, we encoun-
           Road in Konya, exploring Sultanhani   cient civilizations, and modern in-  tered Haceti Hafir's tomb near
           Caravansary and the Mevlana Mu-  fluences. From diverse cuisine to   Edirnekapı's ancient walls, believed
           seum. A night in Cappadocia, marked   breathtaking natural beauty, Turkey   to tie to Abu Ayyub al-Ansari's
           by a traditional Turkish folklore even-  stands as a testament to our shared   campaign in Istanbul. These brave
           ing, unfolded tales of the Seljuk,   human heritage.              souls, immortalized in prophetic ha-
           Marco Polo, and Ottoman Silk Routes.   As limitless as Turkey's stories may   diths, exemplify the valor that
           Embarking on the Silk Route at dawn,   be, the constraints of words compel   marked the sieges of Constantino-
           surrounded by lush landscapes, felt   me to pause this tale, leaving the   ple, echoing the prophecy of its
           like a slice of heaven. Cappadocia,   beauty of this remarkable journey lin-  eventual conquest.
           with its volcanic rock formations, By-  gering in the heart. ■      The valor displayed by these
           zantine wonders, and underground   *The writer, I.R.S. (Retd.), crafted this   martyrs finds resonance in the Pro-
           cities, created an atmosphere of magic.   article after his visit.   phet's (PBUH) renowned hadith on
                                                                             Istanbul, reflecting the determina-
                                                                             tion of Muslim armies. With Mu-
                                                                             hammad's companions and the 'ta-
                                                                             bi'eens' in their ranks, their resolve
                                                                             remained steadfast amidst the trials
                                                                             of battle.
                                                                               Our odyssey reached its apex at
                                                                             the revered Sufi Saint Rumi's tomb,
                                                                             enriching our understanding. Rumi,
                                                                             a beacon of mysticism and love,
         Tomb of Ertugrul Ghazi: Interior view                               order's ethos. Immersed in Rumi's
                                                                             birthed the mesmerizing 'Whirling
                                                                             Dervishes,' embodying the Mevlevi

                                                                             timeless works, such as "Fihi ma
                                                                             Fihi" and "The Makatib," Turkey's
                                                                             essence unfolded before us. This
                                                                             voyage seamlessly intertwines his-
                                                                             tory, prophecy, and Rumi's wisdom,
                                                                             revealing Turkey's vibrant cultural
                                                                             tapestry and rich heritage.


           30                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY
             HOROSCOPES                                     March 16-31, 2024






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     During this bi-weekly period, Aries, you may find   This bi-weekly period highlights relationships
                     yourself focused on personal growth and self-   and partnerships for Libra. Seek harmony and
                     improvement. This is a great time to set goals and   balance in your interactions with others. Focus
                     take action towards achieving them. Embrace new   on compromise and finding win-win solutions
                     challenges and trust in your abilities.         for any conflicts that may arise.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     The focus for Taurus during this period is on   During this period, Scorpio, you may feel a de-
                     relationships and partnerships. Nurture your    sire for transformation and growth. Embrace
                     connections with loved ones and collaborate with   change and let go of what no longer serves you.
                     others to achieve shared goals. Communication   Trust your intuition and follow your passions
                     and compromise are key to maintaining harmony.   fearlessly.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Highlights self-expression and creativity for   Adventure awaits you, Sagittarius, during this
                     Gemini. Embrace your unique ideas and share     bi-weekly period. It's a favorable time for travel,
                     them with others. Your communication skills     exploration, and broadening your horizons. Em-
                     will be on point, making it a great time for net-  brace new experiences that expand your knowl-
                     working and building new connections.           edge and perspectives.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Cancer, this period encourages you to take care   Focus on your long-term goals and ambitions,
                     of your emotional well-being. Prioritize self-care   Capricorn. This bi-weekly period provides op-
                     and find ways to recharge. Nurture your relation-  portunities for career advancement and profes-
                     ships with loved ones and seek comfort in famil-  sional growth. Embrace responsibility and take
                     iar surroundings.                               calculated risks.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     During this bi-weekly period, Leo, your focus is   This period emphasizes social connections and
                     on career and ambition. Set ambitious goals and   community involvement for Aquarius. Engage
                     go after them with confidence. Your hard work   with your social circle and contribute to collec-
                     and determination will be recognized, leading to   tive initiatives. Embrace your unique ideas and
                     opportunities for growth.                       inspire others.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Attention to detail and practicality are important   During this bi-weekly period, Pisces, you may
                     for Virgo during this period. Focus on organiza-  feel a stronger connection to your intuition and
                     tional tasks and productivity. Take care of your   spiritual side. Take time for self-reflection and
                     physical well-being and maintain a balanced     embrace your creativity. Trust in the universe's
                     lifestyle.                                      guidance.





           MARCH 16 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Remembering Legend
                                             The magazine’s current issue (1-15
             We lost two legends in February this
                                           March 2024) is commendable for its
           year - Ameen Sayani & Pankaj Udhas -   Rich Content             Tribute to Janab Aziz Qureshi
           and Revoir has aesthetically sketched   rich content, especially the captivating   The late Janab Aziz Qureshi, former
           their inimitable personas in its latest   features titled “The Glamour of   governor, was an outspoken, fearless,
           issue. Starting with Sayani, his magical   Women’s Mind” and my all-time favou-  and honest individual dedicated to serv-
           voice broke like the dawn, dispelling the   rite ‘Horoscope.’ The editorial for Inter-  ing the community. His deep love for the
           darkness of ignorance. His opening   national Women’s Day is a thoughtful   country was evident in his actions. He
           phrase – "beheno aur bhaiyon" –   reflection on the role women play in so-  was also a sympathetic figure and well-
           touched human hearts deeply, and the   ciety.                   regarded within the community. He
           connection that developed was forever.   It is an open reminder that Western   made significant sacrifices, including
             The velvety voice that arrived on the   influence has caused women to find   stepping down from his post as gov-
           scene when radio penetration was still in   themselves in situations which widen   ernor, to advocate for the minority role
           the nascent stage and accessible only to   the gap between them and the inherited   of Jauhar University. He held great ap-
           the rich, kept pace with the evolution of   values for many generations. In this   preciation for the freedom fighters who
           the radio waves through the decades. A   sense, utmost respect should be ac-  fought for the country's independence.
           time came when it reverberated in every   corded to women and they should be   May Allah grant him the highest posi-
           corner of the country, and the voice got   given positions as their own people   tion in Jannat ul Firdaus.
           etched in the annals of history. Today,   rather than being treated as objects.   Dr. Yusuf Qureshi (Advocate) Meerut,
           every radio program has a reflection of   Shahid Ali Siddiqui I.R.S (Retd.),   Uttar Pradesh, India
           Ameen Sayani’s style. He may have ex-  Hamdard Education Society, New
           ited the stage, but the world will always   Delhi, India
           remember him the way it reveres the                             Exceptional Edition!
           early man who invented the wheel, and
           subsequent generations followed.   Highlighting Excellence         I would like to express my admira-
             Pankaj Udhas is yet another phenom-                           tion for the latest edition of Revoir mag-
           enon whose soft demeanour and inno-  In the latest issue of Revoir Maga-  azine. The editorial on the upcoming In-
           cent smile captured the hearts of all age   zine, while the special issue for Inter-  ternational Women’s Day, along with the
           groups. Even today, ‘Chhitthi Aayi Hai’   national Women's Day was detailed ex-  articles discussing the rise of green fash-
           churns the conscience of the diaspora,   tensively, it was commendable to see   ion and the essence of Vietnam, are truly
           whose heart weeps for the motherland   in-depth coverage on two great music   captivating and easily accessible to
           and invokes the longing to be with their   personalities who are no longer with us,   readers. The engaging content reflects
           loved ones they left on the soil of their   Ameen Sayani and Pankaj Udhas. Ad-  the dedication and hard work of the en-
           origin long ago. The song in Udhas’s   ditionally, the magazine introduced the   tire team, and I want to extend my con-
           voice gave words to that emotion like   natural beauty of Vietnam and discussed   gratulations on yet another successful
           never before. May the souls of these   'The Hidden Drawback of School Uni-  edition. Each piece contributes to the
           greats rest in peace as the mortals on   forms' along with shedding light on   overall quality and appeal of the maga-
           Earth continue to bask in the magical   other topics including 'Bidding Farewell   zine, making it a pleasure to read. Keep
           glow of their gifted voices.    to Baldness', which is praiseworthy.   up the excellent work!
           Sandeep Rai, Bureau Chief, West UP,   J.P. Tyagi (Senior Journalist) Lucknow,   Novormi Vats, Meerut, Uttar Pradesh,
           The Times of India              Uttar Pradesh, India            India


            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at

            Email: revoir@post.com



             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           32                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 16 2024]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>