<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="34"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[24




                                                                            18













                                                                            5

            12









                                                                            21






            30



                                                                            9












           IN THIS ISSUE




                     VOLUME: 01, ISSUE: 3, DECEMBER 01 2023

           4. Editorial: Unlocking the sunlight   17. Whispers of devotion
           conundrum                       18. The fading shadow of AIDS
           5. Unveiling the digital tapestry   21. Flaunt your natural canvas
           9. Evolving skies               24. Beyond skyscrapers
                                                                            17
           12. From 9 to 6                 30. Decoding the defeat




           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[EDITORIAL  Unlocking the sunlight conundrum                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           Vitamin D deﬁciency among

           Indian oﬃce workers                                                    Art & Culture Editor
                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel
                                           n the heart of India's bustling office
                                           spaces, a silent health crisis is unfur-  Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                        Iling  Vitamin D deficiency among of-
                                        fice workers. The Sunlight Conundrum, as    Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        we aptly term it, is casting shadows over
                                        the well-being of countless professionals   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        confined within office walls from 9 to 6,    Sushil Kumar
                                        shielded from the life-sustaining embrace
                                        of sunlight.                              Social Media Editor
                                           As office routines in India often mirror   Vishakha Sharma
                                        a relentless cycle of indoor confinement,
                                        the consequence is an alarming lack of   Art & Graphics Director
                                        exposure to natural sunlight. Many profes-   Vipin Agarwal
                                        sionals, like Nilesh Dhamanekar, a sea-
           soned Principal Software Development Engineer in Test, navigate their workdays
           without the luxury of basking in the sun's rays. The predicament is exacerbated
           by the pervasive use of cars for daily commutes, creating a dual barrier to sun-  EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           light—office walls and enclosed transportation.
             India's diverse climate adds another layer to the challenge. The sweltering heat   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           in some regions and prolonged monsoons in others limit the opportunities for out-  Editor, United News of India, New
           door activities. For those who do step outside, the looming specter of air pollu-  Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           tion further diminishes the efficacy of the sun's natural vitamin D production.   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
             Nilesh's narrative serves as a poignant microcosm of a broader issue affecting   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           office workers nationwide. The National Family Health Survey in India has   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           sounded the alarm on widespread vitamin D deficiency across age groups and re-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           gions. This deficiency extends beyond bone health concerns, infiltrating the   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
           realms of immune system compromise, mental health challenges, and heightened   Jamali (Architect)
           susceptibility to chronic diseases.
             In the midst of this health conundrum, awareness becomes the beacon of hope.
           The editorial spotlight turns towards employers and healthcare professionals to   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           champion initiatives that address the root of the problem. Flexible work hours,
           encouragement of outdoor breaks, and fostering a workplace culture that priori-  Phone +91 20 40199102
           tizes health are essential steps in mitigating the sunlight conundrum.   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             The office itself, often designed with minimal natural light, must become a   Baner Road,
           partner in the quest for employee well-being. Incorporating elements such as sun-  Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           lit spaces, encouraging physical activity, and even integrating Vitamin D checks   Email revoir@post.com
           into regular health screenings can pave the way for a healthier workforce.   Website www.revoir.in
             The Sunlight Conundrum is a challenge, but it's also an opportunity for trans-
           formation. It beckons employers to rethink traditional office structures and em-
           brace a holistic approach to employee health. For the office workers of India, it's   Legal Advisor
           a call to step out of the shadows, both figuratively and literally, and reclaim the   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           vitality that sunlight bestows.
             As we navigate the Sunlight Conundrum, let Nilesh's story be a catalyst for   Copyright © 2023 REVOIR (eZine),
           change. The remedy lies not just in supplements or dietary adjustments but in the   all rights reserved. This publication
           fundamental reimagining of our relationship with sunlight and its profound impact   may not be reproduced in any form
           on our well-being. It's time to illuminate the path to a healthier, sun-kissed tomor-  without permission.
           row for every office worker in India.


                         Dr. Kamran Zuberi
                         Editor in Chief


       4                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Unveiling the digital tapestry                                                                        TECHNOLOGY AND INNOVATION



           How computers paint empowerment



           for the visually impaired




             n the tapestry of existence, where                            and vocalizing the content displayed on
             shadows dance and sunbeams paint                              the screen. They provide auditory feed-
           Ithe canvas of life, the challenge of                           back for every action taken, allowing
           visual impairment casts a unique silhou-                        users to navigate through applications,
           ette. Within this intricate mosaic, ho-                         read documents, and interact with web-
           wever, emerges a tale of transformation                         sites. This technology has revolutionized
           — a narrative woven by the delicate                             the way visually impaired individuals
           hands of technology. In the grand atelier                       engage with digital content, making it
           of progress, computers stand as virtuoso                        more accessible and user-friendly.
           artisans, sketching vibrant pathways of                            Braille Displays and Braille Em-
           accessibility and independence for those                        bossers: Braille is a tactile writing sys-
           traversing the realm of sightless vistas.   the delicate threads of touch and sound.   tem that uses raised dots to represent
             Our journey embarks upon the lumi-                            letters and numbers. Computers have fa-
           nous intersection of human ingenuity    Screen Reader Technology:   cilitated the integration of Braille into
           and the ethereal glow of computerized   One of the ground-breaking advance-  the digital realm through the devel-
           enchantment, exploring how these digi-  ments in aiding the visually impaired is   opment of Braille displays and Braille
           tal maestros orchestrate symphonies of   the development of screen reader tech-  embossers. A Braille display is a device
           assistance for the visually impaired. Let   nology. Screen readers are software pro-  that connects to a computer or mobile
           us navigate the corridors of innovation   grams that convert digital text into syn-  device and translates on-screen text into
           where screen readers whisper tales,   thesized speech. These tools enable   Braille, allowing users to read digital
           Braille displays sculpt narratives in   individuals with visual impairments to   content through touch.
           touch, and the dance of artificial intelli-  access information on computers, smart-  Braille embossers, on the other hand,
           gence choreographs a ballet of new-  phones, and other digital devices. Pop-  are printers that produce hard-copy
           found possibilities. In this enchanted   ular screen reader software includes   Braille documents by embossing dots
           forest of binary wonders, we shall un-  JAWS (Job Access with Speech), NVDA   onto paper. This technology is instru-
           cover the magical artifacts and spells   (NonVisual Desktop Access), and Voi-  mental in educational settings, enabling
           that computers conjure to empower   ceOver.                     visually impaired students to access
           those who navigate the world through   Screen readers work by interpreting   textbooks, worksheets, and other learn-

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[accessibility features and specialized ap-
                                                                           plications. Navigation apps, such as
                                                                           BlindSquare and Soundscape, use GPS
                                                                           and augmented reality to provide audio-
                                                                           based guidance, helping users navigate
                                                                           unfamiliar environments independently.
                                                                              Additionally, object recognition apps,
         A girl using low vision Portable Magnifier                        faces. These applications leverage the
                                                                           like Seeing AI, leverage the smart-
                                                                           phone's camera to identify and describe
                                                                           objects, read text, and even recognize
                                                                           computational power of smartphones to
                                                                           enhance the daily lives of visually im-
                                                                           paired individuals.

                                                                           Electronic Braille Notetakers:
                                                                              Electronic Braille notetakers are port-
                                                                           able devices designed to assist visually
                                                                           impaired individuals in taking notes,
                                                                           reading, and managing information.
                                                                           These devices typically feature a Braille
           ing materials in Braille format.                                keyboard and display, allowing users to
                                           Accessible Operating Systems and   input and read Braille text. Notetakers
           Speech Recognition Software:    Applications:                   often support connectivity to computers
             Speech recognition software has   Major operating systems, such as Mi-  and other devices, facilitating the trans-
           emerged as a valuable tool for individ-  crosoft Windows, macOS, and various   fer of data and documents.
           uals with visual impairments. These pro-  Linux distributions, prioritize accessibil-  These devices are particularly valu-
           grams convert spoken words into text,   ity features. These features encompass   able in educational and professional set-
           allowing users to dictate and control   screen readers, magnifiers, voice con-  tings, providing an efficient and portable
           their devices through voice commands.   trol, and high contrast themes. More-  solution for visually impaired individ-
           Popular examples include Dragon Natu-  over, many applications, including web   uals to engage with written information.
           rallySpeaking and Microsoft's Speech   browsers and productivity suites, have
           Recognition.                    integrated accessibility standards, ensur-  Accessible Gaming for
             Speech recognition technology en-  ing that their interfaces are compatible   Entertainment and Social
           hances the efficiency and accessibility   with assistive technologies.   Inclusion:
           of tasks such as writing emails, creating   Accessible operating systems and ap-  The world of computer gaming has
           documents, and browsing the internet.   plications play a crucial role in fostering   not been left untouched by efforts to en-
           By providing an alternative input   inclusivity, enabling visually impaired   hance accessibility. Developers are in-
           method, it reduces reliance on tradi-  individuals to seamlessly navigate and   creasingly incorporating features such as
           tional keyboard and mouse interactions,   utilize digital resources.   audio cues, screen readers, and custom-
           offering a more inclusive computing ex-                         izable controls to make video games
           perience.                       Mobile Applications for Navigation   more inclusive for individuals with vi-
                                           and Identification:             sual impairments. Platforms like Xbox
           Magnification and Contrast        Smartphones have become indispen-  and PlayStation include accessibility
           Adjustment:                     sable tools for individuals with visual   settings that cater to a diverse range of
             Computers assist individuals with vi-  impairments, thanks to the plethora of   needs, ensuring that everyone can enjoy
           sual impairments through features that
           enhance visual content. Magnification
           tools enlarge on-screen text and
           graphics, catering to individuals with
           low vision. Moreover, contrast adjust-
           ment features enable users to modify the
           color schemes, making content more
           readable for those with specific visual
           conditions.
             Operating systems and software ap-
           plications often include built-in acces-
           sibility features that allow users to cus-
           tomize their display settings according
           to their preferences. These adjustments
           empower visually impaired individuals
           to tailor their computing environment
           for optimal visibility.

       6                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[the immersive experience of gaming.
             Accessible gaming not only provides
           entertainment but also contributes to so-
           cial inclusion by allowing visually im-
           paired individuals to participate in the
           broader gaming community.

           Online Resources and
           Communities:
             The internet has become a vast re-
           source for individuals with visual im-
           pairments, offering a multitude of acces-                                                       A visually impaired child is sensing Braille through touch
           sible content and online communities.
           Websites and platforms are designed
           with accessibility in mind, ensuring that
           screen readers can effectively interpret
           the content. Additionally, online forums
           and social media communities provide a
           platform for individuals with visual im-
           pairments to share experiences, seek ad-
           vice, and build a supportive network.
             The interconnected nature of the in-  gence (AI) and computer vision has   people.
           ternet has facilitated the creation of a   opened up new frontiers in assisting in-  Computer vision applications, such
           global community where visually im-  dividuals with visual impairments. AI-  as the Microsoft Seeing AI mentioned
           paired individuals can access infor-  powered systems can analyze images   earlier, leverage machine learning algo-
           mation, connect with peers, and partici-  and describe the visual content to users   rithms to recognize and provide detailed
                                                                           descriptions of objects captured by a de-
                                                                           vice's camera. These innovations har-
                                                                           ness the capabilities of AI to enhance the
                                                                           independence and understanding of
                                                                           visually impaired individuals in various
                                                                           contexts, from shopping to exploring
                                                                           outdoor environments.

                                                                           Tactile Graphics and 3D Printing:
                                                                              While Braille is an essential tool for
                                                                           conveying textual information, it has
                                                                           limitations when it comes to represent-
                                                                           ing graphical content. Tactile graphics
                                                                           and 3D printing technologies address
                                                                           this challenge by converting visual in-
           pate in discussions regardless of   through text-to-speech technology. This   formation into tactile formats. Tactile
           geographical location.          functionality is particularly beneficial   graphics use embossed lines, textures,
                                           for understanding the visual aspects of   and shapes to represent visual elements
             The integration of artificial intelli-  the world, including scenes, objects, and   such as graphs, maps, and diagrams. On






                                                                                                           Virtual assistant through voice commands

















           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[the other hand, 3D printing can create
           physical representations of objects, al-
           lowing individuals to explore and under-
           stand them through touch.
             These technologies enhance educa-
           tional experiences by providing access
           to visual information in a tactile form,
           promoting a more inclusive learning en-                                                         E-book reader with text-to-speech features
           vironment for students with visual im-
           pairments.

           Wearable Devices and Haptic
           Feedback:
             Advancements in wearable technol-
           ogy have introduced innovative solu-
           tions for assisting the visually impaired.   mation and managing daily activities.   The progress made in assisting indi-
           Wearable devices, such as smart glasses,   Moreover, cognitive assistance ex-  viduals with visual impairments through
           can utilize cameras and sensors to pro-  tends beyond basic tasks, with some sys-  computer technology is a result of col-
           vide real-time feedback about the user's   tems capable of understanding and re-  laborative efforts between tech devel-
           surroundings. Some smart glasses are   sponding to more complex requests.   opers, accessibility advocates, and the
           equipped with haptic feedback, using   This evolution in virtual assistant tech-  visually impaired community. Continu-
           vibrations or other tactile sensations to   nology holds great promise for further   ous dialogue and feedback loops are es-
           convey information about obstacles or   empowering individuals with visual im-  sential for refining existing technologies
           important points of interest.   pairments in both personal and profes-  and developing new solutions that ad-
             These wearable devices enhance mo-  sional settings.          dress evolving needs.
           bility and situational awareness, allow-                           Advocacy plays a crucial role in pro-
           ing users to navigate public spaces more   E-books and Digital Accessibility:   moting the importance of accessibility in
           confidently. As technology continues to   The transition from traditional print   technology design and implementation.
           evolve, we can expect further refine-  to digital media has significantly im-  Organizations and individuals dedicated
           ments and integration of these wearable   pacted the accessibility of literature for   to accessibility advocacy contribute to
           solutions into the daily lives of individ-  individuals with visual impairments. E-  raising awareness, influencing policy
           uals with visual impairments.   books, equipped with text-to-speech ca-  changes, and fostering a culture of inclu-
                                           pabilities and adjustable fonts, provide a   sivity in the tech industry.
           Cognitive Assistance and Virtual   flexible and customizable reading ex-
           Assistants:                     perience. Additionally, digital formats   Ongoing development of assistive
             Cognitive assistance technologies   allow for seamless integration with   tools:
           leverage AI and natural language pro-  Braille displays and other assistive tech-  In the rapidly evolving landscape of
           cessing to provide context-aware sup-  nologies.                technology, the ongoing development of
           port for individuals with visual impair-  Furthermore, initiatives like the Mar-  assistive tools and features for individ-
           ments. Virtual assistants, such as   rakesh Treaty facilitate the cross-border   uals with visual impairments continues
           Amazon's Alexa and Apple's Siri, can   exchange of accessible format copies of   to broaden the possibilities for a more
           assist users in various tasks, from setting   books, ensuring that individuals with   inclusive and accessible future. From
           reminders to answering questions and   print disabilities have access to an ex-  the early days of screen readers to the
           controlling smart home devices. These   tensive and diverse range of literature.   integration of AI, wearable devices, and
           virtual assistants contribute to increased                      haptic feedback, the journey has been
           independence by offering a voice-acti-  Collaborative Efforts and   marked by innovation and a commit-
           vated interface for accessing infor-  Advocacy:                 ment to breaking down barriers.
                                                                              As we move forward, it is imperative
                                                                           to maintain a focus on user experience,
                                                                           inclusivity, and collaboration. The syn-
         Online community dedicated to accessibility                       themselves is key to ensuring that ad-
                                                                           ergy between technology developers, ac-
                                                                           cessibility advocates, and the end-users

                                                                           vancements in computer-assisted tech-
                                                                           nologies truly meet the diverse needs of
                                                                           the visually impaired community.
                                                                              By fostering this collaboration, we
                                                                           can look forward to an era where indi-
                                                                           viduals with visual impairments not only
                                                                           navigate the digital world with ease but
                                                                           actively contribute to shaping the tech-
                                                                           nologies that empower them.


       8                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[SOCIAL ISSUES



































           Evolving skies



           The rise of male flight attendants in



           India and its implications




           The article explores the increasing presence of male flight attendants in India, challenging

           traditional gender norms in response to rising in-flight misbehaviour.

                he aviation industry in India has   lating incidents of unruly behaviour on   professionalism in the aviation industry.
                undergone a noteworthy transfor-  flights, airlines in India are increasingly   It is essential to recognize that pro-
           Tmation in recent years, marked   opting for a more diverse flight crew, in-  fessionalism and the ability to provide
           by a surge in the number of male flight   cluding a growing number of male flight   excellent customer service are not inher-
           attendants on local flights. This shift is   attendants. This shift challenges tradi-  ently gender-specific traits. Male flight
           not merely a change in personnel but   tional gender norms and stereotypes,   attendants are just as capable of ensur-
           represents a response to the increasing   emphasizing the need for a broader per-  ing the safety and comfort of passengers
           commotion and misbehaviour experi-  spective on the role of flight attendants.   as their female counterparts. However,
           enced on flights. As we explore the im-                         societal expectations and preconceived
           plications of this trend, we must address   Gender and Professionalism:   notions may influence perceptions of
           various questions surrounding the role   One fundamental question that arises   their suitability for the role.
           of flight attendants, societal expecta-  in this context is whether a male flight
           tions, and the responsibility of air serv-  attendant can effectively take on the role   Air Service Provider
           ice providers.                  traditionally associated with an air hos-  Responsibility:
                                           tess. The term "air hostess" itself carries   The question of whether it is the sole
           The Changing Dynamics:          connotations of a woman as a respectful   responsibility of the air service provider
             Traditionally, the role of a flight at-  host and caretaker, raising concerns   to take care of its passengers adds
           tendant was largely associated with   about the acceptability of men in this   another layer to the debate. While air-
           women, often referred to as air hos-  position. This leads to a broader discus-  lines are undoubtedly accountable for
           tesses. However, in response to the esca-  sion on the intersection of gender and   passenger safety and well-being, the in-

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                          9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[creasing incidents of misbehaviour on
           flights suggest a need for a more com-
           prehensive approach. This includes ad-
           dressing societal attitudes, enhancing se-
           curity measures, and promoting a
           culture of respect among passengers.

           The Role of Male Flight Attendants:
             Male flight attendants bring a unique                                                         Flight attendants wearing Indian traditional dress
           perspective to the profession, challeng-
           ing stereotypes and contributing to a
           more inclusive work environment. The
           ability of men to fulfil the role of a care-
           taker and host is not determined by their


                                           gender but by their training, skills, and
                                           dedication to their job. It is crucial to   Challenges and Opportunities:
                                           recognize and appreciate the diversity   The evolution of the aviation indus-
                                           within the profession, as it ultimately   try towards a more inclusive workforce
                                           benefits both the airline industry and   is not without its challenges. Cultural
                                           passengers.                     norms and societal expectations, deeply
                                                                           ingrained over decades, can resist
                                           Impact on Women in the Industry:   change. The acceptance of male flight
                                             As the number of male flight atten-  attendants might be met with skepticism
                                           dants rises, concerns may arise about the   or resistance from some passengers who
                                           potential reduction in opportunities for
                                           women in the field. Critics argue that the
                                           entry of men into traditionally female-
                                           dominated professions may limit career
                                           prospects for women who aspire to be-
                                           come air hostesses. This issue is particu-
                                           larly significant for those who have nur-
                                           tured dreams of working in the skies
                                           since childhood.
                                             However, it is essential to address
                                           these concerns while emphasizing that
                                           diversity within the aviation industry   are accustomed to the traditional image
                                           should not be viewed as a zero-sum   of an air hostess.
                                           game. The goal is not to replace women   Moreover, within the industry itself,
                                           with men but to create a workforce that   there may be resistance to change, with
                                           reflects the rich tapestry of society. Ini-  stereotypes persisting about the roles
                                           tiatives to encourage more women to   that men and women should play. This
                                           pursue careers in aviation, including   necessitates a concerted effort by air-
                                           flight attendant roles, must be strength-  lines and aviation authorities to not only
                                           ened to ensure equal opportunities for   hire a diverse workforce but also to ac-
                                           all.                            tively promote and celebrate this diver-
         International flights employ female flight attendant                                              Male attendant in a flight crew





















       10                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[ship programs, scholarships, and out-
                                                                           reach efforts to schools and colleges to
                                                                           inspire young women to consider ca-
         Career prospects to become an air hostess                         tributions of all employees, irrespective
                                                                           reers in the aviation industry.
                                                                              Furthermore, creating a workplace
                                                                           culture that values and respects the con-

                                                                           of their gender, is vital. This extends
                                                                           beyond recruitment to include policies
                                                                           that support work-life balance, career
                                                                           advancement, and a safe and inclusive
                                                                           working environment.
                                                                              The increasing presence of male
                                                                           flight attendants on local flights in India
                                                                           is a positive step toward breaking
                                                                           gender stereotypes and promoting inclu-
                                                                           sivity within the aviation industry. While
           sity. Initiatives such as awareness cam-  it is equally important to strike a balance   questions about their ability to replace
           paigns, training programs, and fostering   that ensures equal opportunities for all   air hostesses persist, it is crucial to rec-
           a culture of inclusivity can help over-  genders. Initiatives that encourage   ognize that professionalism knows no
           come these challenges.
             The positive side of this transfor-
           mation lies in the opportunities it pres-
           ents for both men and women. Breaking
           away from gender stereotypes opens up
           new career paths for individuals who
           may have been discouraged from pursu-
           ing certain professions based on societal
           expectations. It sends a powerful mes-
           sage that anyone, regardless of gender,
           can excel in roles traditionally associ-
           ated with the opposite sex.
             Moreover, the inclusion of male                                                               Flight attendants working together harmoniously
           flight attendants brings a fresh perspec-
           tive to the profession. Different life ex-
           periences and viewpoints contribute to a
           more dynamic and adaptable workforce.
           This diversity can enhance the overall
           customer experience, as flight attendants
           bring a range of skills and perspectives
           to their interactions with passengers.
                                           women to pursue careers in aviation, ad-  gender boundaries. The responsibility of
           Striking a Balance:             dressing any existing barriers or biases,   air service providers extends beyond the
             While embracing diversity is crucial,   are essential. This may include mentor-  confines of the aircraft, requiring a col-
                                                                           laborative effort to address societal is-
                                                                           sues contributing to in-flight misbehav-
                                                                           iour.
                                                                              The rise of male flight attendants
                                                                           should not be seen as a threat to the as-
                                                                           pirations of women in the industry but
                                                                           as an opportunity to create a more di-
                                                                           verse and dynamic workforce. Through
                                                                           thoughtful initiatives and continued dia-
                                                                           logue, the aviation industry in India can
                                                                           pave the way for a future where gender
                                                                           does not determine one's suitability for
                                                                           any role within the skies. Challenges
         A Vistara flight crew                                             with a commitment to equality and in-
                                                                           and opportunities must be navigated
                                                                           clusivity, ensuring that the skies remain
                                                                           open and welcoming to all.




           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[COVER STORY





























           From nine to six



           How office life is robbing





           you of vital Vitamin D







           Vitamin D deficiency among office workers in India is a significant concern that
           can lead to a range of health issues, from weakened bones to compromised

           immune function


                 itamin D is a vital nutrient that   exposed to ultraviolet B (UVB) radia-  Immune System Support: Vitamin D
                 plays a crucial role in maintain-  tion from sunlight. There are two main   plays a vital role in the functioning of
           Ving overall health. It is primarily   forms of vitamin D: vitamin D2 (ergo-  the immune system. It helps the body to
           known for its role in calcium absorption   calciferol) and vitamin D3 (cholecalcife-  defend against infections and illnesses.
           and bone health, but it also has a signifi-  rol). Vitamin D3 is the more potent form   A deficiency in vitamin D can lead to a
           cant impact on various bodily functions,   and is the type produced by the skin in   compromised immune system, making
           including the immune system, cardio-  response to sunlight.     individuals more susceptible to infec-
           vascular health, and mental well-being.                         tions.
           Unfortunately, a growing number of of-  The primary roles of vitamin D in   Mood and Mental Health: There is
           fice workers in India are experiencing a   the body include:    evidence to suggest that vitamin D may
           deficiency in this essential vitamin due   Calcium Absorption: Vitamin D en-  influence mood and mental health. It is
           to limited exposure to sunlight. The Im-  hances the absorption of calcium from   thought to play a role in the synthesis of
           portance of Vitamin D           the intestines, which is crucial for main-  neurotransmitters like serotonin, which
             Vitamin D, often referred to as the   taining strong bones and teeth. Without   can impact mood. Deficiencies in vita-
           "sunshine vitamin," is a fat-soluble vita-  sufficient vitamin D, the body struggles   min D have been linked to conditions
           min that is essential for the body's   to absorb enough calcium, leading to   like depression and Seasonal Affective
           proper functioning. It is unique because   weak bones and an increased risk of os-  Disorder (SAD).
           the body can produce it when the skin is   teoporosis.             Cardiovascular Health: Some re-

       12                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[search has indicated that vitamin D may   workers in India who work from 9 to 6   air pollution is a significant problem.  A corporate office environment in India is commonly seen
           have a role in maintaining cardiovascu-  and travel by car are particularly suscep-  Poor air quality can reduce the effective-
           lar health by regulating blood pressure   tible to this deficiency for several rea-  ness of UVB rays in producing vitamin
           and reducing inflammation. A lack of vi-  sons:                 D in the skin. Additionally, air pollution
           tamin D may increase the risk of heart   Limited Sun Exposure: Office   can make outdoor activities less appeal-
           disease and related issues.     workers typically spend most of their   ing, further limiting exposure to sun-
             Muscle Function: Vitamin D is essen-  daylight hours indoors, which signifi-  light.
           tial for muscle strength and function. In-  cantly reduces their exposure to natural   Mode of Transportation: Many office
           dividuals with a deficiency in this vita-  sunlight. In India, many office buildings   workers in India rely on cars for their
           min may experience muscle weakness   are designed with minimal natural light,   daily commute. Traveling in enclosed
           and pain.                       and employees often have limited op-  vehicles further restricts exposure to
             Given its multifaceted importance,   portunities to go outside during the   sunlight, making it difficult for individ-
           maintaining adequate levels of vitamin   workday.               uals to benefit from the sun's natural vi-
           D is crucial for overall health and well-  Climate: India's diverse climate   tamin D production.
           being.                          means that some regions experience pro-  Sunscreen Use: When individuals do
                                           longed periods of heat and intense sun,   have the opportunity to spend time out-
           Vitamin D Deficiency: A Global   while others face extended monsoon   doors, many use sunscreen to protect
           Concern                         seasons or cool temperatures. This varia-  their skin from the harmful effects of
             Vitamin D deficiency is not limited   tion can affect the amount of sunlight in-  UV radiation, including the risk of skin
           to India but is a global concern. Factors   dividuals are exposed to, potentially   cancer. While sunscreen is essential for
           contributing to this issue include life-  leading to seasonal fluctuations in vita-  skin protection, it can also limit the
           style changes, dietary choices, and envi-  min D levels.        body's ability to produce vitamin D.
           ronmental factors. However, office   Air Pollution: In many Indian cities,
                                                                           The Prevalence of Vitamin D
                                                                           Deficiency
                                                                              Vitamin D deficiency is more com-
         A woman working in an office deprived of sunlight                 surveys have highlighted this issue:
                                                                           mon than one might expect, and its
                                                                           prevalence is growing among office
                                                                           workers in India. Several studies and

                                                                              National Family Health Survey
                                                                           (NFHS): The National Family Health
                                                                           Survey conducted in India reported that
                                                                           a significant portion of the population,
                                                                           including office workers, has low levels
                                                                           of vitamin D. The survey revealed that
                                                                           vitamin D deficiency is a concern across
                                                                           all age groups and regions, indicating

                                                                           tional one.
                                                                              Work-Related Studies: Various work-

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         that this is not a localized issue but a na-  13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[place-based studies have shown a high
           prevalence of vitamin D deficiency
           among office workers in India. These
           studies often consider factors like re-
           duced sun exposure and sedentary work
           routines as contributing to the problem.
             Bone Health Concerns: India has also
           seen an increase in the number of indi-
           viduals, including office-goers, experi-
           encing bone health issues, such as osteo-
           porosis and fractures. This is directly                                                         Office workers depend on cars for their daily commute
           linked to insufficient vitamin D levels,
           as it is essential for calcium absorption
           and bone health.

           The Health Consequences of
           Vitamin D Deficiency
             The consequences of vitamin D defi-
           ciency can have far-reaching implica-
           tions for an individual's health and well-  Mental Health Issues: Emerging re-  ployers can play a role in educating their
           being. Among office workers in India,   search suggests a connection between   employees about the risks of deficiency
           these consequences are not uncommon   low vitamin D levels and mental health   and encouraging them to take preventive
           and may include:                problems, including depression and anx-  measures.
             Weak Bones: Vitamin D deficiency   iety. Given the already high-stress levels   Dietary Supplements: When natural
           can lead to brittle bones and a higher   experienced by office workers, this can   sources of vitamin D are limited, dietary
           risk of fractures. This is a significant   compound the issue.   supplements can help maintain optimal
           concern for individuals, as bone health   Chronic Diseases: Vitamin D defi-  levels. Individuals, especially those at
           is crucial for daily activities and overall   ciency has been linked to an increased   higher risk, should consider consulting a
           quality of life.                risk of chronic diseases, including car-  healthcare professional and taking sup-
             Immune System Compromise: A   diovascular diseases, diabetes, and cer-  plements as recommended.
           weakened immune system due to low
           vitamin D levels can make individuals
           more susceptible to infections and ill-
           nesses, which can result in frequent sick
           days and reduced productivity at work.
                                                                                                           Limited sun exposure can exhaust the worker
             Muscle Weakness and Pain: Many
           office workers who are deficient in vita-
           min D report muscle weakness and pain.
           This can negatively impact their ability
           to exercise and maintain a healthy life-
           style.










                                                                              Regular Screenings: Employers can
                                           tain types of cancer. The long-term   consider offering regular health screen-
         An employee taking a short outdoor break  Addressing the Vitamin D   tify deficiencies and provide early inter-
                                           health implications are a cause for con-
                                                                           ings to their employees, including tests
                                           cern.

                                                                           for vitamin D levels. This can help iden-
                                                                           vention.
                                           Deficiency Issue
                                             It is clear that vitamin D deficiency
                                                                              Sunlight Breaks: Encourage employ-
                                           among office workers in India is a grow-
                                                                           ees to take short breaks and spend time
                                                                           outdoors during the day, especially in
                                           ing problem with significant health im-
                                                                           sunny weather. Design office spaces to
                                           plications. To address this issue, a multi-
                                                                           maximize natural light exposure.
                                           faceted approach is needed:
                                             Education and Awareness: Raising
                                                                              Flexible Work Hours: Some em-
                                           min D and its sources is essential. Em-
                                                                           hours or remote work policies, which
       14                                  awareness about the importance of vita-  ployers have adopted flexible work
                                                                    www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[A Vitamin D supplement bottle                                     balanced lifestyle are all steps that can





                                                                           help combat vitamin D deficiency
                                                                           among office workers. Ultimately, a
                                                                           healthier, more vitamin D-aware work-
                                                                           reduced healthcare costs, and, most im-
           can give employees more control over                            force can lead to improved productivity,
           their daily routines and potentially in-
           crease their exposure to sunlight.
             Encourage Physical Activity: Physi-
           cal activity, including outdoor exercise,
           is essential for overall health. Encourage
           employees to engage in outdoor activ-
           ities, and provide facilities like company
           gyms or outdoor recreational areas.
             Balanced Diet: A diet rich in vitamin
           D-rich foods, such as fatty fish, fortified
           dairy products, and egg yolks, can help
                                                                                                           Vitamin D-rich foods







                                           style choices like traveling by car. Em-  portantly, better overall health and well-
                                           ployers, healthcare professionals, and   being for all.
                                           individuals themselves all have a role to   As our understanding of the impor-
                                           play in addressing this growing prob-  tance of vitamin D continues to grow, it
         Outdoor exercise for overall health  ments when necessary, and promoting a   vulnerable to this health concern.
                                                                           is essential that we prioritize addressing
                                           lem.
                                                                           the issue of deficiency, especially among
                                             Raising awareness, encouraging out-
                                           door breaks, providing dietary supple-
                                                                           office workers who may be particularly







           maintain adequate levels of the vitamin.
           Promote healthy eating habits among
           employees.
             Vitamin D deficiency among office                                                             Employees engage in outdoor recreational areas
           workers in India is a significant concern
           that can lead to a range of health issues,
           from weakened bones to compromised
           immune function. The issue is complex,
           with various factors contributing to the
           problem, including limited sunlight ex-
           posure, climate, air pollution, and life-

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[COVER STORY  Illuminating the hidden effects



           A tale of Vitamin D deficiency in the office




                  eet Nilesh Dhamanekar, a 40-
                  year-old Principal Software
           MDevelopment Engineer in Test
           with a remarkable 16 years of experi-
                                                                                                           An ideal office filled with natural light
           ence working in an office environment,
           except for the challenging pandemic













                                           When working from home, flexibility   Recently, Nilesh experienced minor
                                           reigns supreme, allowing him to snatch   pain around the cuboid bone near the
                                           moments outdoors during a 5-6 hour   heel, a potential symptom of vitamin D
                                           workday.                        deficiency. Planning a blood test during
                                             However, a stark reality emerges as   his next annual health checkup, he is
                                           Nilesh estimates spending a mere 20 mi-  taking steps towards understanding and
                 Nilesh Dhamanekar         nutes in daylight daily, with most work   addressing his health concerns.
           years, based in Pune, Maharashtra. Ni-  hours confined indoors. His mode of   Coping strategies, however, remain
           lesh graciously shared insights into his   transportation, an office cab that whisks   on the horizon for Nilesh. Amidst the
           daily routine, shedding light on the   him directly from his society parking to   demands of setting up a new home and
           often-overlooked impact of office life on   the office parking, ensures negligible ex-  caring for a 10-month-old baby, lifestyle
           vitamin D levels.               posure to sunlight.             changes are a high-priority task yet to be
             Nilesh's typical workday is a meticu-  As we delve into the realm of health   undertaken.
           lous dance between the office and home.   awareness, Nilesh admits to a lack of   In discussing the role of the work-
           When working from the office, he em-  detailed knowledge about vitamin D de-  place, Nilesh suggests initiatives like en-
           barks on a cab journey at 8 AM, squeez-  ficiency. Though he acknowledges his   couraging walks during free time and in-
           ing in a quick breakfast at 9 AM before   employer's well-being programs and en-  corporating outdoor activities. While his
           immersing himself in work until 3 PM.   couragement for daily workouts, the   workplace currently lacks specific pol-
           The return cab ride brings him home   connection between his work environ-  icies for addressing vitamin D defi-
           around 4 PM, where he juggles family   ment and overall health hasn't been a   ciency, Nilesh expresses a willingness to
           time, relaxation, and household duties.   focal point.          enhance awareness and take initiative in
                                                                           this regard.
                                                                              Looking ahead, Nilesh emphasizes
                                                                           the need for increased awareness about
                                                                           vitamin D deficiency in office settings.
                                                                           He recommends potential changes such
                                                                           as rewarding employees for taking the
                                                                           most steps outside each month and add-
                                                                           ing the 25-hydroxy vitamin D test to an-
                                                                           nual check-ups.
                                                                              In a poignant personal message, Ni-
                                                                           lesh urges fellow office workers to step
                                                                           into the sunlight occasionally, take a
                                                                           walk, and avoid severe health issues.
          Work from home                                                   deficiency, Nilesh's story serves as a
                                                                           With a global prevalence of vitamin D
                                                                           timely reminder for office workers to
                                                                           bring this essential health consideration
                                                                           into the light.

       16                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[WHISPERS OF DEVOTION                                                                                 BOOK REVIEW






           'Neelmani Kesav' and the art of spiritual Haiku





                                              n the enchanting world of "Neelmani   themes such as Bal-lila, the endearing
                                              Kesav," Pramodini Sharma takes   Ma Yashoda, the mischievous Makhan
                                           Ireaders on a poetic pilgrimage, ex-  Chori, the significance of Krishna's or-
                                           ploring the diverse and intricate tapestry   naments, and the celebration of festivals
                                           of Haiku, Tanka, Choka, Sedoka, Renga,   like Basant and Holi. The author's ex-
                                           and Haibun—short forms of poetry that   ploration of Radha and Meera adds a
                                           have become cherished elements of In-  layer of emotional depth, while the Flute
                                           dia's literary landscape. With grace and   and the Cow become symbolic elements
                                           depth, Sharma invites readers into a   in Krishna's life, each carrying its own
                                           realm where spirituality, devotion, and   resonance.
                                           the timeless allure of Haiku converge,   As Pramodini Sharma reflects on her
                                           crafting a debut work that transcends its   creative journey, she provides readers
                                           pages.                          with a glimpse into the inspiration and
                                             The opening chapters serve as a po-  acknowledgment that fueled the book's
                                           etic primer, offering a comprehensive   creation. Her early exposure to devo-
              Pramodini Sharma, Author     exploration of the essence of Haiku.   tional stories from her mother, Mrs.
                                           Originating in Japan, Haiku is character-  Gayatri Devi, laid the foundation for a
                                           ized by three lines composed of 17 pho-  lifelong devotion to Lord Krishna. Long
                                           netic units arranged in a 5-7-5 syllable   poems became a passion during her col-
            This is more than a book;      count. Delving deeper, the author intro-  lege days, inspired by travel experiences
                                           duces readers to Katauta, a specific form
                                                                           documented in a diary.
                    it's an invitation to   of Haiku, and unravels its intricate struc-  The author acknowledges the pivotal
                                           ture—17 or 19 syllables arranged in   role played by her daughters-in-law,
            embark on a literary and       three lines of either 5-7-5 or 5-7-7 syl-  Vertika and Manaswee, who gifted her a
                      spiritual journey    lables.                         diary and encouraged her to articulate
                                             What emerges is a vivid understand-
                                                                           her thoughts sequentially. Mrs. Neeta
                                           ing of the artistry involved in crafting   Sharma, her sister-in-law, was the cata-
                                           these condensed poetic expressions. Ka-  lyst behind the decision to share her po-
                                           tauta, initially designed as an address to   etic thoughts on Instagram and compile
                                           a lover, takes on various forms within   them into a book.
                                           the book. A single Katauta is considered   The journey into Haiku was sparked
                                           a half-poem, while a set of two, with the   by a friend, Mrs. Bhupinder Kaur, lead-
                                           type 5-7-7, transforms into Sedoka. This   ing Pramodini Sharma to join the Haiku
                                           sequential form of poems, resembling a   group 'Haiku Manjusha' founded by Mr.
                                           conversation through question-and-an-  Pradeep Kumar Dash 'Deepak.' Initially
                                           swer, adds a layer of complexity and   daunting, the task of writing Haiku be-
         The book 'Neelmani Kesav' is available on Amazon  Hued Krishna," reflects the author's rev-  ality through the introduction to the pub-
                                                                           came a testament to the author's ded-
                                           depth to the narrative.
                                             The heart of "Neelmani Kesav" lies
                                                                           ication, fueled by the blessings of Lord
                                                                           Krishna and the unwavering support of
                                           in its dedication to Lord Krishna. The
                                                                           her family and friends.
                                           title itself, translating to "The Blue-
                                                                              The book's publication became a re-
                                           erence for the divine. With 72 pages in
                                           the paperback edition, the book falls
                                                                           lisher, M/s Nikhil Publishers and Dis-
                                           within the religious and spiritual fiction
                                                                           tributors, by Mrs. Sunita Dixit, a friend.
                                           genre, serving as a poetic hymn to Lord
                                                                           The collaborative effort is evident, with
                                           Krishna's childhood and various life
                                                                           a nod to the tireless work put in by all
                                                                           involved to bring "Neelmani Kesav" to
                                           stages, his divine 'Lilas,' and the poig-
                                           nant theme of separation (viyoga) when
                                                                           print, a testament to the author's com-
                                                                           mitment to her spiritual endeavor.
                                           Krishna moves from Vrindavan to Ma-
                                           thura.
                                             The narrative unfolds like a lyrical
                                                                              ...Continured on page 29
                                           tapestry, intricately weaving together
           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            The cover photograph, meticulously    17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[GLOBAL HEALTH







































           The fading shadow of AIDS



           Understanding the eclipsed threat in the wake


           of the COVID-19



                he COVID-19 pandemic, caused   from a death sentence to a manageable   with improved treatment options, public
                by the novel coronavirus SARS-  chronic condition for many individuals.   attention began to shift to emerging
           TCoV-2, has dominated global at-  Global efforts, including awareness   health threats, such as the H1N1 in-
           tention since its emergence in late 2019.   campaigns and increased funding for   fluenza pandemic in 2009 and, more re-
           The unprecedented scale and impact of   HIV prevention and treatment, contrib-  cently, the COVID-19 pandemic.
           this viral outbreak have understandably   uted to a reduction in new infections and
           diverted public focus from many other   AIDS-related deaths.    Overlapping Crises: COVID-19
           health issues, including the long-stand-  The success in controlling the spread   Takes Center Stage
           ing and still-prevalent HIV/AIDS epi-  of HIV, however, may have inadver-  The emergence of the COVID-19
           demic. In recent years, there has been a   tently led to a sense of complacency. As   pandemic in late 2019 captured the
           noticeable decline in public awareness   the urgency of the AIDS crisis lessened   world's attention like never before. The
           and discourse surrounding AIDS, raising                         rapid spread of the virus, the overwhel-
           concerns about the potential con-                               ming impact on healthcare systems, and
           sequences of neglecting a disease that                          the unprecedented global response, in-
           has been a persistent global health threat                      cluding lockdowns and mass vaccina-
           for decades.                                                    tion campaigns, pushed other health
                                                                           concerns to the sidelines. Governments,
           Initial Success and Subsequent                                  health organizations, and the media were
           Complacency                                                     forced to redirect their resources and ef-
             The late 20th century and early 21st                          forts to address the immediate threat
           century witnessed significant progress in                       posed by the novel coronavirus.
           the understanding and management of                                The similarities between the two pan-
           HIV/AIDS. The development of antiret-                           demics, including the respiratory nature
           roviral therapy (ART) transformed HIV                           of both viruses and the societal disrup-

       18                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[tions caused by their spread, led to a nat-
           ural focus on COVID-19. As a result,
           HIV/AIDS, once a headline-making
           global health crisis, found itself over-
           shadowed by the more imminent threat
           of the coronavirus.

           Pandemic Fatigue and Information
           Overload
             The continuous and prolonged nature
           of the COVID-19 pandemic has resulted                                                           Testing for HIV/AIDS with a self-testing kit
           in pandemic fatigue among the general
           population. People are overwhelmed by
           the constant stream of pandemic-related
           news, updates, and guidelines. In the
           face of this fatigue, attention spans have
           shortened, and interest in health issues
           beyond COVID-19 has waned.      other healthcare services, including   lockdowns and travel restrictions have
             Furthermore, the public's attention is   those related to HIV/AIDS. Many   disrupted supply chains, potentially
           highly influenced by the media, which   clinics and healthcare facilities have   leading to shortages of antiretroviral
           tends to prioritize current and sensa-  faced disruptions in their operations,   drugs in some regions. The combined
           tional topics. As a result, the steady and   leading to challenges in providing essen-  impact of these factors has contributed
           on-going nature of the HIV/AIDS epi-  tial HIV testing, counseling, and treat-  to a sense of neglect and vulnerability
                                                                           among individuals living with
                                                                           HIV/AIDS.
                                                                              The disruptions in healthcare services
                                                                           have also had ripple effects on HIV pre-
                                                                           vention efforts. Outreach programs,
                                                                           community education initiatives, and
                                                                           condom distribution activities have
         A healthcare worker wearing PPE                                   gains made in reducing transmission
                                                                           faced setbacks, potentially leading to an
                                                                           increase in new HIV infections. The
                                                                           rates are at risk of being eroded if the
                                                                           focus on HIV/AIDS prevention is not
                                                                           reinstated and strengthened.

                                                                           Stigmatization and Discrimination:
                                                                              Stigmatization and discrimination
                                                                           HIV/AIDS, and the COVID-19 pan-
           demic has struggled to compete for   ment services.             have long been associated with
                                                                           demic has unfortunately exacerbated
           media coverage with the dynamic and   The diversion of resources to combat   these issues. The fear and uncertainty
           evolving narrative of the COVID-19   the COVID-19 pandemic has strained   surrounding COVID-19 have sometimes
           pandemic.                       healthcare systems, affecting the deliv-  fueled discrimination against individuals
             The overwhelming volume of infor-  ery of routine HIV care. Additionally,   perceived as potential carriers of the
           mation on COVID-19 has created a sce-
           nario where essential health issues, such
           as HIV/AIDS, are at risk of being
           drowned out. Educational campaigns
           that were once successful in raising
           awareness about HIV transmission, pre-
           vention, and stigma reduction are find-
           ing it challenging to capture public at-
           tention amid the noise of
           pandemic-related news.
                                                                                                           A HIV/AIDS patient admitted in a hospital
           Impact of Lockdowns and
           Disruptions on HIV/AIDS Services:
             The widespread implementation of
           lockdowns and social distancing meas-
           ures to curb the spread of COVID-19
           has had unintended consequences for

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Procession against the stigma associated with AIDS
                                                                           the epidemic.
                                                                              Forgetting the lessons of the past and
                                                                           neglecting on-going health challenges,
                                                                           such as HIV/AIDS, poses the risk of un-
                                                                           dermining the progress achieved in re-
                                                                           cent decades. It is essential to recognize
                                                                           the interconnectedness of health issues
                                                                           and to adopt a comprehensive and inclu-
                                                                           sive approach that addresses both imme-
                                                                           diate threats and longstanding epi-
                                                                           demics.

                                                                           The Role of Communities
                                                                              Communities have always been at
                                                                           the forefront of the fight against
                                                                           HIV/AIDS. They have played a vital
                                                                           role in providing prevention education,
           virus. This has created an environment   their programs and services in the wake   supporting people living with HIV, and
           where people living with HIV/AIDS   of diminished financial support.   advocating for policies that protect the
           may be hesitant to disclose their status   International collaboration and finan-  rights of those affected by the disease.
           or seek support due to the added stigma   cial support are essential in addressing   The theme of World AIDS Day 2023,
           associated with respiratory illnesses dur-  both the immediate challenges of the   "Let Communities Lead", emphasizes
           ing the pandemic.               COVID-19 pandemic and the enduring   the crucial role of communities in
             The intersectionality of stigma re-  threat of HIV/AIDS. Global health ini-  achieving the goal of ending AIDS.
           lated to both HIV/AIDS and COVID-19   tiatives need to adopt a balanced ap-  Communities have the knowledge, ex-
           has created a complex web of challenges   proach that recognizes the intercon-  pertise, and passion to drive progress to-
           for those living with HIV. As the broader   nected nature of health challenges and   wards a world free from HIV/AIDS.
           public focuses on COVID-19, the nu-  allocates resources to address both acute   While the COVID-19 pandemic
           anced struggles of individuals with   and chronic health issues.
           HIV/AIDS may be overlooked, further
           marginalizing this population.   Lessons from the Past: The Danger
             Efforts to combat stigma and dis-  of Forgetting:
           crimination associated with HIV/AIDS   The history of public health is
           must be reinvigorated, emphasizing the   marked by instances where one health
           importance of empathy, understanding,   crisis eclipsed another, leading to dire
           and education. Addressing the dual   consequences. The disregard for on-  rightly commands attention and re-
           stigma of respiratory illnesses and HIV   going health threats can result in set-  sources, it is crucial not to lose sight of
           is essential for creating a supportive en-  backs, reversals of progress, and the   other persistent health challenges, par-
           vironment for individuals to access test-  emergence of new challenges.   ticularly HIV/AIDS. The progress made
           ing, treatment, and support services   The early years of the HIV/AIDS   in the fight against HIV/AIDS should
           without fear of judgment or discrim-  epidemic serve as a poignant reminder   not be undermined by the shifting prior-
           ination.                        of the consequences of neglect. Initial   ities and distractions brought about by
                                           indifference and delayed responses al-  the current global health crisis.
           Funding Shifts and Global       lowed HIV to spread rapidly, leading to   As the world navigates the complex-
           Priorities:                     widespread suffering and loss of life. It   ities of the COVID-19 pandemic, it is
             The allocation of financial resources   was only through sustained efforts, ad-  imperative to maintain a holistic per-
           plays a crucial role in addressing public   vocacy, and international collaboration   spective on public health, ensuring that
           health challenges. The overwhelming   that progress was made in controlling   no one is left.
           demand for funds to combat the
           COVID-19 pandemic has led to a shift
           in global health priorities. Many coun-
           tries and international organizations
           have redirected their budgets to respond
           to the immediate needs of the COVID-
           19 crisis, potentially at the expense of
           on-going HIV/AIDS programs.
             The shift in funding priorities can
           have cascading effects, impacting pre-                                                          HIV/AIDS awareness campaigns
           vention, treatment, and support services
           for individuals affected by HIV/AIDS.
           Organizations that were once at the fore-
           front of the fight against HIV/AIDS may
           find themselves struggling to maintain

       20                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[LIFESTYLE
































                     Flaunt your natural canvas


             The art of makeup-free






                                   confidence






             n a world inundated with beauty stan-                            Sun Protection: Shielding your skin
             dards and makeup trends, the notion                           from harmful UV rays is paramount. Use
           Iof embracing one's natural beauty has                          a broad-spectrum sunscreen with at least
           gained remarkable prominence. While                             SPF 30 to prevent premature aging, sun-
           makeup undoubtedly serves as a transfor-                        spots, and protect against skin cancer.
           mative tool, there's a growing movement
           towards appreciating and enhancing                              Natural Remedies for Glowing Skin
           one's features without relying on cos-                             Hydration: Drinking an adequate
           metics. This article is designed to provide                     amount of water is fundamental for
           an extensive guide on how to radiate                            healthy, hydrated skin. Water helps flush
           beauty naturally, focusing on skincare,   Exfoliation: Regular exfoliation is   out toxins, leaving your skin looking
           lifestyle choices, and the cultivation of   crucial to slough off dead skin cells, pro-  fresh and radiant. Consider infusing
           self-confidence.                moting a smoother and brighter complex-  water with fruits and herbs for added
                                           ion. Opt for natural exfoliants like sugar   benefits.
           Establishing a Consistent Skincare   or coffee grounds, avoiding harsh chemi-  Healthy Diet: The saying "you are
           Routine                         cals that can irritate the skin.   what you eat" holds true for your skin.
             Cleansing: Begin your skincare rou-  Moisturizing: Hydration is the key to   Incorporate fruits, vegetables, and foods
           tine with a gentle cleanser to remove im-  radiant skin. Choose a moisturizer that   rich in antioxidants into your diet. These
           purities and excess oil from your face.   suits your skin type to keep it nourished   nutrients promote skin health and combat
           Cleansing is the foundational step that   and supple. Well-moisturized skin is less   oxidative stress.
           prepares your skin for subsequent treat-  prone to dryness, flakiness, and prema-  DIY Face Masks: Natural ingredients
           ments.                          ture aging.                     like honey, yogurt, and avocado can be

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Balanced Diet:
                                                                              Omega-3 Fatty Acids: Incorporate
                                                                           foods rich in omega-3 fatty acids, such as
                                                                           salmon and flaxseeds. These promote
         Fresh-faced morning routine                                       uting to a naturally vibrant complexion.
                                                                           skin elasticity and hydration, contrib-
                                                                              Limit Sugar and Processed Foods:
                                                                           High sugar intake and processed foods
                                                                           can contribute to inflammation and skin
                                                                           issues. Opt for a diet rich in whole, nu-
                                                                           trient-dense foods to nourish your skin
                                                                           from the inside out.

           used to create DIY face masks. These
           masks can address specific skin con-
           cerns, providing a natural glow without
           the need for makeup.

           Embrace a Healthy Lifestyle:
             Improved Circulation: Exercise in-
           creases blood flow, delivering oxygen
           and nutrients to the skin, resulting in a
           natural, healthy glow. Aim for at least 30                                                      Elegance without excessive adornment
           minutes of moderate exercise most days
           of the week.
             Stress Reduction: Physical activity
           helps reduce stress levels, which can con-
           tribute to clearer skin and a more relaxed
           appearance. Activities like yoga and pi-
                                                                             Cultivate Self-Confidence:
         Confident body language displays self-confidence                  tures and embrace imperfections as part
                                                                              Challenge Negative Thoughts: Re-
                                                                           place self-critical thoughts with positive
                                                                           affirmations. Celebrate your unique fea-

                                                                           of your individual beauty. Remember,
                                                                           confidence is a key component of attrac-
                                                                           tiveness.
                                                                              Confidence Building Exercises: En-
                                                                           gage in activities that boost confidence,
                                                                           whether it's public speaking, joining a
                                                                           dance class, or participating in a hobby

                                                                           shines through and enhances your overall
                                                                           allure.

           lates combine physical exertion with                            you're passionate about. Confidence
           mindfulness, offering a double benefit.

           Adequate Sleep:
             Skin Repair: Quality sleep is essential
           for the body's repair processes, including
           the regeneration of skin cells. Lack of
           sleep can lead to dull, tired-looking skin.
           Aim for 7-9 hours of quality sleep each
           night.
             Silk Pillowcases: Switching to silk
           pillowcases can reduce friction and pre-                                                        Engaging in outdoor exercise
           vent skin creases, minimizing the risk of
           morning puffiness. This small change
           can have a significant impact on the over-
           all health and appearance of your skin.

       22                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Natural portrait showcasing beauty















         Sun protection for maintaining youthful and healthy skin

                                                                                                           Healthy Omega-3 Foods









                                                                           styles that accentuate your natural fea-
                                                                           tures.
                                                                              Minimalist Accessories: Sometimes,
                                                                           less is more. Opt for simple accessories
                                                                           that complement your natural features
                                                                           without overpowering your look. Let
                                                                           your individuality shine through without
                                                                           relying on heavy adornment.
                                           pearance. These practices also encourage   In a world where the beauty industry
                                           self-awareness and acceptance.   often emphasizes external enhance-
                                             Breathing Exercises: Deep, conscious
                                                                           ments, embracing your natural beauty
         Sleep Sanctuary                   breathing helps oxygenate the skin and   becomes a powerful act of self-love. By
                                           promotes relaxation, reducing the ap-
                                                                           prioritizing skincare, adopting a healthy
                                           pearance of stress-related skin issues. In-
                                                                           lifestyle, and cultivating self-confidence,
                                                                           you can achieve a gorgeous appearance
                                           corporate simple breathing exercises into
                                                                           true beauty is diverse, and each person's
                                           boost.
           Mindfulness and Stress          your daily routine for a quick confidence   without the need for makeup. Remember,
           Management:                                                     natural features are unique and worthy of
                                           Dressing for Confidence:        celebration. By following the tips out-
             Meditation and Yoga: Practicing   Wear What Makes You Feel Good:   lined in this comprehensive guide, you
           mindfulness through meditation and   Choose clothing that makes you feel   can enhance your natural beauty and ra-
           yoga can reduce stress levels, contrib-  comfortable and confident. When you   diate confidence from within, embracing
           uting to a calmer and more radiant ap-  feel good on the inside, it radiates on the   the beauty that is authentically and
                                           outside. Experiment with colors and   uniquely yours.

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[TRAVEL



























           Beyond skyscrapers






           Uncovering Singapore's






           hidden gems






           As the Lion City continues to evolve, it remains a beacon of innovation, cultural

           diversity, and unparalleled hospitality, inviting travelers to immerse themselves

           in a tapestry of experiences that leave an indelible mark.


                 estled at the crossroads of Asia,   Singapore is separated from Malaysia by   blend is reflected in the city's rich tapes-
                 Singapore stands as a vibrant   the Straits of Johor to the north and from   try of traditions, festivals, and cuisines.
           Nand dynamic city-state that    Indonesia by the Singapore Strait to the   Top Tourist Attractions:
           seamlessly blends tradition and modern-  south. This strategic location has played   Marina Bay Sands: Dominating the
           ity. From its iconic skyline to its rich   a pivotal role in shaping Singapore into   skyline, the Marina Bay Sands resort is
           cultural tapestry, this island nation has   a global hub for trade, finance, and tour-  an architectural marvel that combines
           evolved into a premier tourist destina-  ism.                   luxury accommodations, a world-class
           tion.                             Cultural Diversity: One of Singa-  casino, and the breathtaking SkyPark.
             Geography and Overview: Singa-  pore's most distinctive features is its cul-  The SkyPark offers panoramic views of
           pore, often referred to as the "Lion   tural diversity, with a population that   the city, creating a visual spectacle dur-
           City," is a sovereign city-state and island   comprises a melting pot of ethnicities,   ing both day and night.
           country in Southeast Asia. Situated at   including Chinese, Malay, Indian, and   Gardens by the Bay: A testament to
           the southern tip of the Malay Peninsula,   Eurasian communities. This harmonious   Singapore's commitment to sustainable

       24                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Singapore often referred to as the "Lion City"


















           urban development, Gardens by the Bay
           is a futuristic garden that showcases the
           city's dedication to green spaces. The
           Supertree Grove, Cloud Forest, and
           Flower Dome are must-visit attractions
           that seamlessly blend nature and tech-
           nology.
             Sentosa Island: For a dose of fun and
           relaxation, Sentosa Island is a haven for
           tourists. With pristine beaches, theme
           parks like Universal Studios Singapore,
           and the iconic Merlion statue, Sentosa                                                          Futuristic Supertrees at Gardens by the Bay
           offers a perfect escape from the urban
           bustle.
             Singapore Zoo and Night Safari: The
           Singapore Zoo is renowned for its open-
           concept enclosures, allowing visitors to
           experience close encounters with a di-
           verse range of wildlife. The Night Sa-
                                                                           fari, situated adjacent to the zoo, offers a
                                                                           unique nocturnal experience, allowing
         Supertrees at Gardens by the Bay in the daytime                   pong Glam: These cultural enclaves
                                                                           guests to observe animals in their natu-
                                                                           ral habitats after dark.
                                                                              Chinatown, Little India, and Kam-

                                                                           showcase the diversity of Singapore's
                                                                           heritage. Chinatown is a bustling district
                                                                           with vibrant markets and authentic Chi-
                                                                           nese cuisine. Little India immerses vis-
                                                                           itors in the sights, sounds, and flavors of
                                                                           Indian culture, while Kampong Glam,
                                                                           with the majestic Sultan Mosque, repre-
                                                                           sents the Malay and Arab influence.
                                                                              Singapore Botanic Gardens: Estab-

                                                                           Gardens is a UNESCO World Heritage

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         lished in 1859, the Singapore Botanic   25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Vibrant reflections of buildings, flowers, and the beauty of a sunrise




























           Site and a haven of tranquility in the   city-state caters to every palate.   and Laksa reflect the vibrant flavors of
           heart of the city. The National Orchid   Hawker Centers: Maxwell Food Cen-  this heritage, and restaurants in Katong
           Garden within the premises is a high-  tre, Lau Pa Sat, and Chinatown Com-  and Joo Chiat are ideal places to savor
           light, featuring an extensive collection   plex Food Centre are just a few exam-  these delicacies.
           of orchid species.              ples of Singapore's iconic hawker   Fine Dining: For those seeking a
             Culinary Delights:            centers. These bustling food hubs offer a   more upscale dining experience, Singa-
             Singapore is a food lover's paradise,   plethora of affordable and delicious   pore boasts a myriad of Michelin-starred
           offering a culinary adventure that re-  local dishes, providing a true taste of   restaurants. From celebrity chef-helmed
           flects its diverse cultural influences.   Singaporean cuisine.   establishments to avant-garde gastro-
           From hawker centers serving local de-  Peranakan Cuisine: The Peranakan   nomic experiences, the city's fine-dining
           lights like Hainanese Chicken Rice and   culture, a fusion of Chinese and Malay   scene is a testament to its culinary pro-
           Laksa to fine-dining establishments   influences, has given rise to a unique cu-  wess.
           showcasing international cuisines, the   linary tradition. Dishes like Nasi Lemak   Shopping Paradise:




































       26 The National Gallery is housed in the former Supreme Court  www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Singapore's reputation as a shopper's
                                                                           paradise is well-earned, with a diverse
                                                                           range of shopping districts that cater to
                                                                           every taste and budget.
                                                                              Orchard Road: A world-renowned
                                                                           shopping belt, Orchard Road is lined
                                                                           with high-end boutiques, department
                                                                           stores, and luxury brands. It's a haven
                                                                           for fashion enthusiasts and a prime loca-
                                                                           tion for indulging in retail therapy.
                                                                              Bugis Street: For a more eclectic
                                                                           shopping experience, Bugis Street offers
                                                                           a mix of trendy boutiques, street stalls,
                                                                           and vibrant markets. It's a great place to
                                                                           discover unique fashion finds and
                                                                           souvenirs.
                                                                              Chinatown and Little India Markets:
                                                                           Immerse yourself in the cultural ambi-
                                                                           ance of Chinatown and Little India,
                                                                           where markets brim with traditional
                                                                           crafts, textiles, and trinkets. These areas
                                                                           offer an authentic shopping experience
                                                                           that reflects the cultural diversity of Sin-
                                                                           gapore.
                                                                              City of Festivals:
                                                                              Throughout the year, Singapore hosts
                                                                           a myriad of festivals and events that
                                                                           showcase its cultural richness and vi-
                                                                           brant spirit.
                                                                              Chinese New Year: Celebrated with
                                                                           grandeur and festive fervor, Chinese
                                                                           New Year transforms the city with daz-
                                                                           zling decorations, vibrant parades, and
         A beautiful aerial view of Singapore                              during the Hindu festival of lights,
                                                                           traditional lion and dragon dances.
                                                                              Deepavali: Little India comes alive
                                                                           Deepavali. The streets are adorned with
                                                                           colorful lights, and cultural perform-
                                                                           ances add to the celebratory atmosphere.
                                                                              Hari Raya Puasa: The end of Rama-
                                                                           dan is marked by Hari Raya Puasa, a
                                                                           Muslim festival celebrated with feasts,
                                                                           prayers, and a sense of communal har-
                                                                           mony. The Kampong Glam district is a
                                                                           focal point for these celebrations.
                                                                              Hidden Gems:
                                                                              Beyond the well-trodden tourist paths
                                                                           lie hidden gems that showcase the local
                                                                           flavor and charm of Singapore.
                                                                              Haji Lane: Tucked away in the heart
                                                                           of Kampong Glam, Haji Lane is a nar-
                                                                           row street adorned with vibrant murals
                                                                           and lined with eclectic boutiques.
                                                                           Known for its independent fashion
                                                                           stores, quirky cafes, and street art, Haji
         Singapore Botanic Gardens                                         bohemian and offbeat side of Singapore.
                                                                           Lane is a haven for those seeking a more
                                                                              Bukit Timah Nature Reserve: Nature
                                                                           enthusiasts will find solace in the Bukit
                                                                           Timah Nature Reserve, home to one of
                                                                           the richest and most diverse ecological
                                                                           systems in the world. It's a perfect es-


           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         cape from the urban bustle, offering hik-  27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Lanterns adorning Chinatown during the Chinese New Year celebrations






























           ing trails that lead to the summit of   forming into a trendy enclave that pre-  masterpiece. The museum hosts a rotat-
           Bukit Timah Hill, the highest point in   serves its Art Deco architecture. Tiong   ing selection of exhibitions that seam-
           Singapore.                      Bahru is a treasure trove of independent   lessly blend art, science, and technology,
             Pulau Ubin: For a trip back in time,   bookstores, hip cafes, and local bak-  providing a thought-provoking and im-
           Pulau Ubin, an offshore island, provides   eries, offering a nostalgic yet contempo-  mersive experience.
           a glimpse into Singapore's rural past.   rary ambiance.            National Gallery Singapore: Housed
           Rent a bicycle to explore the island's   Art and Culture:       in two national monuments, the former
           rustic villages, mangrove swamps, and   Singapore's commitment to fostering   Supreme Court and City Hall, the Na-
           abandoned quarries. The Chek Jawa   creativity and artistic expression is ev-  tional Gallery Singapore is a treasure
           Wetlands, known for its rich biodiver-  ident in its vibrant arts scene.   trove of Southeast Asian art. It features
           sity, is a must-visit for nature lovers.   ArtScience Museum: Shaped like an   an extensive collection of paintings,
             Tiong Bahru: This historic neighbor-  open lotus flower, the ArtScience Mu-  sculptures, and installations, offering in-
           hood has undergone a revival, trans-  seum at Marina Bay Sands is a visual   sight into the region's diverse cultural
                                                                           heritage.
                                                                              Street Art in Tiong Bahru: Tiong
                                                                           Bahru is not only a culinary and archi-
                                                                           tectural delight but also a canvas for
                                                                           street artists. Take a leisurely stroll
                                                                           through the neighborhood to discover
                                                                           colorful murals and street art that add a
                                                                           contemporary touch to this historic dis-
                                                                           trict.
         Thermal Spa relaxation                                            Ordinary:
                                                                              Festivals and Events Beyond the
                                                                              While the major festivals add vi-
                                                                           brancy to Singapore's calendar, there are
                                                                           several unique events that showcase the
                                                                           city's creativity and innovation.
                                                                              Singapore International Film Festi-

       28                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Southern Ridges Trail: The Southern
                                                                           Ridges Trail is a nature lover's paradise,
                                                                           connecting several parks and nature re-
                                                                           serves through a network of trails and
                                                                           walkways. Highlights include Hender-
                                                                           son Waves, a pedestrian bridge with
                                                                           stunning architectural design, and
                                                                           Mount Faber Park, offering panoramic
                                                                           views of the city.
                                                                              Health and Wellness:
                                                                              In recent years, Singapore has
         Hawker Center Delights                                            treats, wellness centers, and healthy din-
                                                                           emerged as a hub for health and well-
                                                                           ness tourism, offering a range of spa re-
                                                                           ing options.
                                                                              Thermal Spas: Singapore boasts
                                                                           world-class thermal spas, where visitors

                                                                           using mineral-rich waters. These spas
           val: Film enthusiasts should plan their   gapore Cocktail Festival is a celebration   can indulge in rejuvenating treatments
                                                                           provide a perfect escape from the
           visit during the Singapore International   of the city's burgeoning cocktail scene.   stresses of everyday life.
           Film Festival, a prestigious event that   Featuring world-class bartenders and in-  Wellness Retreats: Several luxury re-
           showcases a diverse range of inter-  novative concoctions, this festival is a   sorts in Singapore offer wellness retreats
           national and Asian films. It provides a   must-attend for cocktail connoisseurs.   that focus on holistic health, combining
           platform for emerging filmmakers and   Singapore Night Festival: The Singa-  fitness programs, nutritious cuisine, and
           fosters a deeper appreciation for the art   pore Night Festival transforms the Bras   relaxation therapies to promote overall
           of cinema.                      Basah and Bugis precinct into a mes-  well-being.
             Singapore Cocktail Festival: For   merizing spectacle of light installations,   Healthy Dining Options: The city's
           those who appreciate mixology, the Sin-  art performances, and cultural activities.   culinary scene has evolved to include an
                                           This annual event showcases the city's   array of healthy dining options. From or-
                                           creative spirit, bringing the streets to life   ganic cafes to restaurants with plant-
                                           after dark.                     based menus, health-conscious travelers
                                             Day Trips and Nearby Attractions:   can easily find nutritious and delicious
                                             Beyond the city limits, Singapore   meals.
                                           offers easy access to captivating day trip   Singapore, with its timeless wonders
                                           destinations.                   and hidden charms, stands as a testa-
                                             Singapore Cable Car to Sentosa: For
                                                                           ment to the coexistence of tradition and
         Singapore's world-class thermal spa  Faber. Enjoy breathtaking views of the   tion, cultural diversity, and unparalleled
                                                                           modernity. As the Lion City continues to
                                           a scenic journey to Sentosa Island, take
                                                                           evolve, it remains a beacon of innova-
                                           the Singapore Cable Car from Mount
                                           city skyline and Sentosa's attractions as
                                                                           hospitality, inviting travelers to immerse
                                                                           themselves in a tapestry of experiences
                                           you soar above the harbor.
                                                                           that leave an indelible mark. Whether
                                             Jurong Bird Park: Nature lovers
                                           should consider a visit to Jurong Bird
                                                                           exploring iconic landmarks, savoring di-
                                                                           verse cuisines, or uncovering hidden
                                           Park, Asia's largest bird park. Home to
                                                                           gems, Singapore promises a journey that
                                           over 5,000 birds across 400 species, the
                                           park offers immersive experiences such
                                                                           to discover the extraordinary.
                                           as feeding sessions and bird shows.
           ...Continured from page 17   “WHISPERS OF DEVOTION”             transcends the ordinary and invites you
                                           woven with threads of spirituality, art-  and grading her poems adds a layer of
           selected by the author's sons, Anurag and   istry, and familial bonds. The author's   authenticity to the creative process.
           Chirag, serves as a visual prelude to the   commitment to the spiritual path, cou-  In conclusion, "Neelmani Kesav" is
           poetic journey within. Mr. Atul Sharma,   pled with her poetic prowess, transforms   more than a book; it's an invitation to
           the author's husband, emerges as a stead-  this collection into a resonant experience   embark on a literary and spiritual jour-
           fast supporter, offering invaluable in-  for readers.           ney. Available on Amazon, this debut
           sights during the manuscript's proofread-  In a promising hint at the future, Pra-  work by Pramodini Sharma is a testa-
           ing process.                    modini Sharma speaks of a second vol-  ment to the enduring power of Haiku and
             As readers delve into "Neelmani   ume, already in the works, exploring a   its ability to evoke profound emotions
           Kesav," they find not just a book but a   different theme. Her humility in ac-  while seamlessly intertwining with the
           labor of love and devotion, a tapestry   knowledging the difficulty of selecting   spiritual realm.


           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[WORLD CUP                                                                                             PM Narendra Modi and Australia's Deputy PM R. Marles presenting the trophy

































           DECODING THE DEFEAT






           A comprehensive analysis of India's



           fall in the 2023 World Cup final





                he echoes of India's heartbreak-                           tent, making it less challenging for their
                ing defeat in the 2023 World Cup                           batsmen.
           Tfinal against Australia at the Na-                                Australia's Clinical Bowling Per-
           rendra Modi Stadium in Ahmedabad still                          formance: Stifling India's Run Rate
           reverberate through the cricket world.                             Australia's bowling attack, spear-
           The Men in Blue, who had stormed                                headed by the experienced Mitchell
           through the tournament with an un-                              Starc and Pat Cummins, exploited the
           beaten record, faltered on the grandest                         pitch conditions to perfection. They
           stage, leaving their fans in a state of be-                     maintained accurate line and length, re-
           wilderment and despair. While Aus-  ing on flat and high-scoring wickets.   stricting India's batsmen to a cautious
           tralia's victory was well-deserved, it is   The slowness of the pitch made it diffi-  approach. The slower bowling of Glenn
           crucial to delve into the factors that con-  cult for batsmen to find boundaries and   Maxwell and Adam Zampa further sti-
           tributed to India's downfall in that fate-  rotate the strike, leading to a below-par   fled India's scoring rate, keeping the
           ful match.                      total of 239 runs.              pressure on the hosts throughout the in-
             Pitch Conditions: A Tale of Two   The pitch conditions changed further   nings.
           Halves                          under the floodlights, becoming slightly   Starc, with his fiery pace and relent-
             The Narendra Modi Stadium in Ah-  more conducive to batting. However,   less attack, led the way with two
           medabad, the venue for the final, pre-  Australia, having won the toss and   wickets, while Cummins, with his con-
           sented a pitch that was slower and drier   elected to bowl first, had already seized   sistent line and length, picked up one.
           than anticipated. This unexpected sur-  the advantage of the early pitch con-  Maxwell and Zampa, bowling spin in
           face posed a significant challenge for In-  ditions. By the time India came out to   the middle overs, slowed down the run
           dia's batting lineup, accustomed to play-  bat, the pitch had dried out to some ex-  rate and made it difficult for India to

       30                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[find quick runs. Their economical spells   keeping the pressure on the Indian bats-  Head's scintillating century was the cor- An exciting and cheering moment for the victorious Australian team
           put enormous pressure on India's bats-  men.                    nerstone of their chase, while David
           men, forcing them to take unnecessary   Cummins' decision to start with   Warner and Marnus Labuschagne pro-
           risks.                          Glenn Maxwell, a spinner, was a sur-  vided valuable contributions.
             India's Middle-Order Failure: A   prise move, but it proved to be a master-  Head, who had been in the runs
           Key Area of Concern             stroke. Maxwell's tight bowling re-  throughout the tournament, was at his
             India's middle order, a crucial com-  stricted India's scoring rate and forced   best, playing some elegant and powerful
           ponent of their success throughout the   them to take risks. Cummins' astute field   shots. His century, laced with thirteen
           tournament, faltered under the pressure   placements, with extra fielders in the   fours and a six, gave Australia the plat-
           of the final. Shreyas Iyer, Suryakumar   deep, further limited India's boundary   form for victory. Warner and Labus-
           Yadav, and Rishabh Pant, all of whom   options.                 chagne, the experienced opening pair,
           had played significant roles in India's   Australia's Composed Chace: A   provided a solid foundation for the
           victories, failed to fire on the day. Their   Masterclass in Patience   chase, with their half-century stands set-
           dismissals exposed India's tail, putting   Australia's chase of 240 runs was a   ting the stage for Head's heroics.
           an end to any hopes of posting a for-  masterclass in controlled aggression.   Missed Opportunities in the Field:
           midable total.                  They started cautiously, ensuring they   Costly Lapses
             Iyer, who had been in excellent form   didn't lose early wickets. As the innings   India's fielding, usually sharp and
           throughout the tournament, was dis-  progressed, they began to accelerate,   consistent, was below par in the final.
           missed after a promising start, falling to   finding boundaries with regularity but   They dropped crucial catches, particu-
           a sharp caught-and-bowled by Adam   without taking unnecessary risks. Travis   larly in the early stages of Australia's
           Zampa. Yadav, known for his explosive
           batting, was unable to get going, finding
           himself trapped lbw by Mitchell Starc.
           Pant, a hard-hitting wicketkeeper-bats-
           man, threw away his wicket with a reck-
           less shot, giving Australia a crucial
           breakthrough.
             Australia's Strategic Captaincy:
           Outsmarting the Opposition
             Australian skipper Pat Cummins                                                                Excited Pat Cummins holds the World Cup trophy
           played a crucial role in his team's vic-
           tory with his astute leadership. He made
           bold tactical decisions, such as introduc-
           ing spin from an early stage, which put
           India's batsmen under immediate pres-
           sure. His field placements were also
           spot-on, cutting off boundaries and

           DECEMBER 01 2023 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[chase, which could have turned the tide
           of the match. These missed opportuni-
           ties allowed Australia's batsmen to settle
           into their innings and build partnerships,
           increasing the pressure on India's
           bowlers.
             One of the most costly drops came in
           the ninth over of Australia's chase, when
           Glenn Maxwell was put down at mid-                                                              PM Narendra Modi consoling Mohammed Shami
           wicket by Shikhar Dhawan. Maxwell,
           who went on to score a crucial 89 runs,
           was still a relative newcomer to the in-
           ternational stage at the time, and his dis-
           missal at that stage could have derailed
           Australia's chase.
             Another missed opportunity came in
           the 16th over, when Steve Smith was put
           down at point by Shreyas Iyer. Smith,   The missed opportunities in the field   with each passing over.
           already well-established in international   had a significant impact on India's   The missed opportunities also put
           cricket, went on to score a half-century   chances of winning the World Cup final.   extra pressure on India's bowlers, who
           and form a crucial partnership with   Had they held on to those catches, Aus-  were already struggling to contain Aus-
           Maxwell.                        tralia would have been under signifi-  tralia's batsmen. When you drop catches,
             These misses, and others, proved to   cantly more pressure, and the match   it can be demoralizing for the bowlers,
           be costly for India, as they allowed Aus-  could have taken a different course.   and it can make them more likely to err
                                                                           in their line and length.
         Indian Captain Rohit Sharma in a somber mood                      their fielding, especially in high-pres-
                                                                              Lessons Learned
                                                                              The missed opportunities in the field
                                                                           should serve as a valuable lesson for
                                                                           India. They need to focus on improving

                                                                           sure situations. They can do this by
                                                                           practicing regularly and by making sure
                                                                           that their fielders are well-aware of their
                                                                           positions and responsibilities.
                                                                              India also needs to work on their
                                                                           catching technique. They need to make
                                                                           sure that they are catching the ball with
                                                                           their hands close to their chest and that
                                                                           they are keeping their hands firm. They
                                                                           also need to practice catching balls in
                                                                           different weather conditions and under
           tralia to chase down the target with rel-  The drops cost India not only runs   different lighting conditions.
           ative ease. A more disciplined and fo-  but also momentum. When a batsman   If India can improve their fielding,
           cused fielding performance could have   gets a life early in their innings, it can   they will be a much more dangerous
           put Australia under much more pressure   boost their confidence and make them   team in the future. They will be able to
           and potentially changed the outcome of   more difficult to dislodge. Australia's   put more pressure on the opposition, and
           the match.                      batsmen capitalized on these missed op-  they will be less likely to give away cru-
             Impact of Missed Opportunities   portunities, and their confidence grew   cial runs.





         …eagerly awaiting the World Cup














       32                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | DECEMBER 01 2023]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>