<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                     VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 04  I  FEBRUARY 16 2024  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL PHOTO: ROHIT SHARMA




               5




                                                            11













                                                            24                                       14















           4-Editorial: The rise of online rendezvous  18-The changing face of time

           5-Secret online rendezvous in                   21-Uniting for Hope

           extramarital affairs                            24-Bollywood's eerie farewell to horror
           8-The invisible enemy and how to                cinema

           defend yourself                                 27-Urban discoveries and

           11-Architect of empires and champion of  neighbourhood whispers
           justice                                         30-Letters

           14-The Sahara's silent threat











           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Pixelated Passion
     EDITORIAL  The rise of online                                                 Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           rendezvous                                                             Art & Culture Editor

                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n the age of technological advancement,   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           our relationships have undergone a
                                        Isignificant transformation, giving rise to   Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        new dynamics that were once
                                        unimaginable. One such intriguing facet is   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        the surge in extramarital affairs facilitated   Sushil Kumar
                                        by the cloak of secrecy offered by the
                                        digital realm. As we delve into the complex   Social Media Editor
                                        web of modern relationships, it becomes    Vishakha Sharma
                                        imperative to dissect the phenomenon of
                                        digital infidelity and the allure of secret   Art & Graphics Director
                                        online rendezvous.                           Vipin Agarwal
                                           In the realm of traditional relationships,
                                        the landscape has shifted dramatically. No
           longer confined to the physical world, connections are forged, and secrets are shared
           in the vast expanse of cyberspace. The discreet allure of secret online rendezvous has   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           become a prevalent theme, rewriting the rules of engagement in extramarital affairs.
             Digital infidelity, a term once alien, now looms large in our societal narrative. The   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           ease with which individuals can navigate various online platforms has opened   Editor, United News of India, New
           avenues for connections beyond the boundaries of matrimony. Social media, dating   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           apps, and discreet online forums have become the modern-day clandestine meeting   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           spots, fostering connections that were previously unthinkable.   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             The allure lies in the anonymity and accessibility that the digital world affords.   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           Secret online rendezvous offer individuals the thrill of exploration without the fear of   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           societal judgment. The virtual space allows for the creation of alternate personas,
           providing a veil of secrecy that emboldens individuals to seek connections outside   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
           the bounds of their marital commitments.                                Jamali (Architect)
             The digital landscape's impact on extramarital affairs is not solely confined to
           discreet interactions but extends to the emotional and psychological realms.   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           Conversations that would once have transpired behind closed doors are now
           exchanged through screens, blurring the lines between the real and the virtual. The   Phone +91 20 40199102
           emotional intimacy forged in secret online rendezvous poses a unique challenge to   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           the traditional definitions of fidelity.                                  Baner Road,
             This editorial does not intend to pass judgment on the choices individuals make in   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           their personal lives but rather seeks to unravel the complexities of the evolving   Email revoir@post.com
           dynamics in modern relationships. The digital age has ushered in unprecedented   Website www.revoir.in
           freedoms, challenging established norms and pushing the boundaries of what is
           deemed acceptable in matters of the heart.
             As we grapple with the implications of digital infidelity and secret online   Legal Advisor
           rendezvous, it is crucial to foster open conversations around these evolving   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           dynamics. Acknowledging the changing landscape of relationships allows us to
           navigate this brave new world with empathy and understanding. In doing so, we can   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           strive towards building relationships that withstand the tests of time, technology, and   all rights reserved. This publication
           the intricate dance between tradition and progress.              may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.





           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[TECHNOLOGY & SOCIETY










































           Digital Infidelity



           Secret online rendezvous in





           extramarital affairs






             n recent years, the occurrence of ex-                         behind the growing prevalence of extra-
             tramarital affairs has experienced a                          marital affairs is the evolving paradigm
           Inotable surge, prompting a compel-                             of relationships, especially within the
           ling exploration of the intricate factors                       context of parental influence. As parents
           that contribute to this societal phenome-                       observe their children engaging in love,
           non. This article seeks to delve deeper                         infatuation, and live-in relationships, a
           into the complex web of social dy-                              latent desire may emerge within them to
           namics fueling the rise in extramarital                         experience the unbridled passion and
           relationships, examining changing atti-                         spontaneity they may have missed dur-
           tudes towards relationships, the evolving                       ing their own youth. The societal norms
           parent-child dynamic, and the role of so-                       that once served as stringent constraints,
           cial media in facilitating clandestine                          restricting individuals from exploring
           connections. By unraveling these inter-                         their romantic desires, are gradually
           connected threads, we aim to shed light                         eroding, making it more socially accept-
           on the multifaceted nature of this socie-                       able for people to pursue relationships
           tal shift.                                                      outside the confines of matrimony.
             Changing attitudes towards rela-                                 This shift in attitudes towards rela-
           tionships: One of the primary catalysts                         tionships is not merely a generational di-

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Observing extra-pair
                                                                             copulations amongst
                                                                             animals
                                                                               Extra-marital relationships, or
                                                                             extra-pair copulations, have been
                                                                             observed in various animal species.
                                                                               Birds: Many bird species, such
         Manifestation of affection                                          terfowl, and raptors, have been
                                                                             as certain species of songbirds, wa-

                                                                             found to engage in extra-pair copu-
                                                                             lations. This behavior is often asso-
                                                                             ciated with high levels of social mo-
                                                                             nogamy, where individuals form
                                                                             long-term pair bonds but also seek
                                                                             additional mates outside of their
                                                                             pair bond.
         Extramarital affairs and polygamous relationships                   such as chimpanzees and bonobos,
                                                                               Primates: Primates, including
                                                                             humans, have been extensively
                                                                             studied for their social and mating
                                                                             behaviors. In some primate species,

                                                                             extra-pair copulations are common
                                                                             and can play a role in social dy-
                                                                             namics, genetic diversity, and repro-
                                                                             ductive success.
                                                                               Insects: Insects, such as bees,
                                                                             ants, and butterflies, also exhibit
                                                                             extra-pair mating behaviors. These

                                                                             tors such as genetic compatibility,
                                                                             resource availability, or the pres-
                                                                             ence of rival males.
           vide; it reflects a broader societal trans-  the satisfaction parents derive from wit-  behaviors can be influenced by fac-
                                                                               The study of extra-marital rela-
           formation. The traditional constraints   nessing their children's relationships.   tionships in animals has evolved
           that once defined the boundaries of ro-  Having experienced societal constraints   over time through various research
           mantic involvement are giving way to a   in their own time, parents may feel a   methods and techniques. Research-
           more open and permissive outlook. Con-  sense of liberation vicariously through   ers have used a combination of field
           sequently, individuals find themselves   their children's pursuits. Paradoxically,   observations, genetic analyses, and
           more inclined to explore the vast spec-  this satisfaction may foster an unspoken   experimental manipulations to un-
           trum of romantic experiences, contrib-  agreement between parents and children,   derstand the prevalence, con-
           uting significantly to the increasing inci-  creating an environment where each   sequences, and evolutionary drivers
           dence of extramarital affairs.   party agrees not to interfere in the   of this behavior.
             The changing landscape of relation-  other's romantic escapades.
           ships is also influenced by a reevalu-  This implicit agreement is founded
           ation of societal expectations and the ac-  on the understanding that parents will   in extramarital affairs without facing
           knowledgment that one size does not fit   not impede their children's choices, be it   significant consequences or moral con-
           all. As individuals witness diverse forms   love, infatuation, or live-in relationships.   demnation, it may normalize such be-
           of relationships, including open mar-  In return, children are expected to recip-  havior. This normalization, in turn, con-
           riages and polyamory, gaining accept-  rocate this non-interference when it   tributes to a generational shift where
           ance, the boundaries of what is consid-  comes to their parents' decisions regard-  extramarital affairs are viewed with
           ered socially acceptable are expanding.   ing extramarital affairs or other personal   greater leniency.
           This broader spectrum of acceptable re-  matters. While seemingly harmonious,   The era of social media
           lationship dynamics creates an environ-  this mutual tolerance can contribute to a   The advent of social media has unde-
           ment where extramarital affairs may be   broader societal acceptance of non-tradi-  niably revolutionized the way individ-
           perceived as an extension of this evolv-  tional relationships, including extramari-  uals interact, creating new avenues for
           ing landscape, rather than a deviation   tal affairs.           connection and communication. In the
           from societal norms.              Moreover, the evolving parent-child   context of extramarital affairs, social
             Parental satisfaction and implicit   dynamic may play a crucial role in shap-  media platforms provide a convenient
           agreements: Parallelly, another dimen-  ing perceptions of marital fidelity. If   and discreet space for individuals seek-
           sion to this phenomenon emerges from   children witness their parents engaging   ing connections beyond the confines of

           6                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Smartphones: Making love anywhere a miracle                                                       Digital platforms facilitating interconnectedness
















                                                                           for self-discovery. Extramarital affairs
                                                                           may be seen as an avenue to rediscover
                                                                           passion and excitement, offering a tem-
                                                                           porary respite from the mundane real-
                                                                           ities of marital life.
                                                                              Furthermore, societal expectations
                                                                           and pressures can contribute to the ap-
                                                                           peal of extramarital affairs as a form of
                                                                           rebellion or self-assertion. Individuals
                                                                           may feel constrained by societal norms
                                                                           and expectations related to marriage,
                                                                           and engaging in extramarital affairs can
                                                                           be perceived as a way to reclaim auton-
                                                                           omy and assert one's individuality.
                                                                              The increasing prevalence of extra-
                                                                           marital affairs can be attributed to a
         A real rendezvous                                                 ing from changing societal attitudes to-
                                                                           myriad of interconnected factors, rang-
                                                                           wards relationships to the influence of
                                                                           social media. The evolving dynamics
                                                                           between parents and children, character-
                                                                           ized by implicit agreements and mutual
           their marriages. The ability to connect   actions. The ease of connecting with po-  tolerance, further contribute to the ac-
           with like-minded individuals and ex-  tential partners, coupled with the ability   ceptance of non-traditional relation-
           plore relationships covertly has signifi-  to maintain a certain level of anonymity,   ships. As we navigate this complex land-
           cantly contributed to the surge in extra-  creates an environment conducive to the   scape, it is essential to recognize the
           marital affairs.                flourishing of extramarital relationships.   need for open communication, empathy,
             Moreover, the virtual nature of social   Escaping the world   and a reevaluation of societal norms to
           media enables individuals to create per-  In the fast-paced and interconnected   address the underlying issues fueling the
           sonas distinct from their real-life iden-  world of today, individuals are con-  rise in extramarital affairs.
           tities, fostering a level of anonymity that   stantly seeking ways to escape the   Only through a comprehensive un-
           emboldens them to pursue relationships   stresses and monotony of daily life. Ex-  derstanding of these factors can society
           without fear of societal judgment. The   tramarital affairs, in this context, may be   hope to foster healthier relationships and
           allure of a secret online rendezvous,   perceived as a means of escapism, al-  reduce the incidence of extramarital af-
           coupled with the ease of communication   lowing individuals to experience excite-  fairs in the future. By promoting open
           and coordination, further contributes to   ment, passion, and emotional fulfillment   dialogue about relationship dynamics,
           the growing prevalence of extramarital   outside the constraints of their marital   encouraging emotional transparency,
           affairs in the digital age.     relationships. The ability to maintain a   and adapting societal norms to reflect
             The availability of various platforms   dual life, shielded from the scrutiny of   the diverse ways individuals experience
           designed specifically for facilitating ex-  friends, family, and society at large, pro-  and express love, we can work towards
           tramarital connections adds another   vides a sense of liberation for those in-  creating an environment where extra-
           layer to the role of social media in this   volved.             marital affairs are less prevalent, and
           trend. These platforms provide a discrete   The desire for escapism can be   couples are empowered to navigate the
           space for individuals seeking extramari-  rooted in various factors, including dis-  complexities of modern relationships
           tal affairs, offering a level of secrecy   satisfaction with the routine of everyday   with greater understanding and resil-
           that is hard to achieve in offline inter-  life, unmet emotional needs, or a quest   ience.

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SCIENCE & HEALTH








































           EMF radiation




           The invisible enemy and





           how to defend yourself







                echnology has revolutionized our                           constant exposure to EMF can have det-
                lives in countless ways, making                            rimental effects on our health. Studies
           Tour daily tasks easier and more                                have shown that prolonged exposure to
           efficient. From smartphones to smart                            EMF can lead to a range of health prob-
           homes, we are surrounded by technol-                            lems, including headaches, fatigue, in-
           ogy that has made our lives more con-                           somnia, and even cancer.
           venient and connected than ever before.                            The World Health Organization
           However, with all the benefits that tech-                       (WHO) has classified EMF as a possible
           nology brings, there are also some                              carcinogen, meaning that it has the po-
           downsides that we need to be aware of.                          tential to cause cancer. While the ev-
           One of the most significant concerns is                         idence is not yet conclusive, there is
           the impact of electromagnetic                                   growing concern among scientists and
           frequencies (EMF) on our health.                                health experts about the long-term ef-
             EMF is a type of radiation that is                            fects of EMF exposure. In addition to
           emitted by electronic devices such as                           cancer, EMF has also been linked to
           power lines, Wi-Fi routers, appliances,                         other health problems such as infertility,
           computers, smartphones, and smart                               neurological disorders, and immune sys-
           meters. While these devices have be-                            tem dysfunction.
           come an integral part of our lives, the                            Despite the potential risks, many of

           8                                                         www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[phone away from your head.
                                                                              Turn off Wi-Fi at night: When you're
                                                                           not using the internet, turn off your Wi-
                                                                           Fi router, especially at night when you're
                                                                           sleeping. This reduces the constant ex-
                                                                           posure to Wi-Fi signals.
                                                                              Use wired connections: Whenever
                                                                           possible, use wired connections for your
                                                                           devices instead of relying on Wi-Fi. This
                                                                           includes using an Ethernet cable for
                                                                           your computer and connecting your TV
                                                                           or gaming console directly to the router.
                                                                              Keep devices away from your body:
                                                                           Avoid carrying electronic devices, such
                                                                           as smartphones, in your pockets or close
         WIFI: A source of EMF radiation                                   bag or purse.
                                                                           to your body. Instead, keep them in a
                                                                              Create EMF-free zones: Designate
                                                                           certain areas in your home as EMF-free
                                                                           zones, such as your bedroom. Keep
                                                                           electronic devices out of these areas to
                                                                           minimize exposure while you sleep or
                                                                              Use EMF shielding products: Con-
                                                                           sider using EMF shielding products,
                                                                           such as phone cases or laptop shields,
           us continue to use electronic devices   tronic devices to reduce the amount of   relax.
           without taking any precautions to reduce   radiation that is absorbed by the body.   which can help reduce the amount of ra-
           our exposure to EMF. However, there                             diation emitted by these devices.
           are several steps that we can take to   Some practical ways to limit our   Limit exposure to power lines: Avoid
           minimize our exposure and protect our                           spending extended periods of time near
           health. One of the most effective ways   exposure to EMF in our daily lives   power lines or electrical substations. If
           to reduce EMF exposure is to limit our   There are several practical ways to   you live close to these sources, consider
           use of electronic devices. This can be   limit our exposure to EMF in our daily   rearranging your living space to mini-
           done by turning off devices when they   lives. Here are some suggestions:   mize exposure.
           are not in use, using wired connections   Reduce cell phone usage: Limit the   Spend time in nature: Take breaks
           instead of Wi-Fi, and avoiding the use of   time you spend on your cell phone and   from technology and spend time out-
           electronic devices in the bedroom.   use it only when necessary. Keep your   doors in nature. This not only reduces
             Another way to reduce EMF expo-  phone away from your body when not in   your exposure to EMF but also provides
           sure is to use protective devices such as   use, and avoid sleeping with it next to   other health benefits.
           EMF shielding products. These products   your bed.
           are designed to block or reduce the   Use speakerphone or wired headsets:
           amount of EMF that is emitted by elec-  Instead of holding your cell phone di-
           tronic devices. They can be used on   rectly to your ear, use the speakerphone
           smartphones, laptops, and other elec-  function or wired headsets to keep the












         Devices emitting EMF radiation                                                                    Cell phone towers emit significant EMF levels













           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                      9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Stay informed: Stay updated on the   EMF shielding laptop pads: These   instead of wireless options. For exam-
           latest research and guidelines regarding   pads are placed underneath laptops to   ple, connect your computer to the in-
           EMF exposure. This will help you make   create a barrier between the device and   ternet using an Ethernet cable instead
           informed decisions about your technol-  the user, reducing the amount of radia-  of relying on Wi-Fi.
           ogy usage and take necessary precau-  tion absorbed by the body.   Disable unnecessary wireless fea-
           tions.                            EMF shielding fabrics: Some fabrics   tures: Turn off Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, and
             Remember, while it may not be pos-  are specifically designed to block or re-  cellular data when you're not actively
           sible to completely eliminate EMF ex-  duce EMF radiation. These fabrics can   using them. This reduces the amount
           posure, taking these practical steps can   be used to make curtains, bed canopies,   of EMF radiation emitted by your de-
           significantly reduce your overall expo-  or clothing to create a shielded environ-  vice.
           sure and help protect your health.   ment.                         Use speakerphone or wired head-
                                             EMF shielding paint: This special   sets: Instead of holding your cell phone
           EMF shielding products that you   paint contains metallic particles that can   directly to your ear, use the speaker-
           would recommend for reducing    help block or reduce the penetration of   phone function or wired headsets. This
                                           EMF radiation. It can be applied to   keeps the device away from your head
           exposure to radiation from      walls, ceilings, or other surfaces to   and reduces exposure.
           electronic devices              create a shielded area.            7. Keep devices away from your
                                             When considering EMF shielding   body while sleeping: Avoid placing
                                           products, it's important to do thorough   electronic devices, such as cell phones,
                                           research, read reviews, and consult with   near your head or body while sleeping.
                                           experts or professionals in the field.   Keep them at a distance, such as on a
                                           Look for products that have been inde-  nightstand or in another room.
                                                                              Create technology-free zones: Des-
                                           pendently tested and certified for their   ignate certain areas in your home as
                                           effectiveness in reducing EMF radiation.
         EMF-protected laptop pad          the effectiveness of these products may   room or dining area. This allows you
                                                                           technology-free zones, such as the bed-
                                           Additionally, it's important to note that
                                                                           to have dedicated EMF-free spaces for
                                           vary, and it's always a good idea to com-
                                                                           relaxation and sleep.
                                           bine their use with other practical meas-
                                           ures to minimize EMF exposure.
                                                                              Use timers or alarms: If you use
                                                                           electronic devices for alarm clocks or
                                             Remember, it's essential to make in-
                                                                           your bed. Consider using battery-oper-
                                           that align with your specific needs and
                                                                           ated alternatives or traditional analog
             EMF shielding phone cases: These   formed decisions and choose products   timers, place them at a distance from
                                           preferences.
           cases are designed to block or reduce the                       devices.
           amount of radiation emitted by smart-  General tips or guidelines for   Educate yourself: Stay informed
           phones. They typically have a layer of   reducing EMF exposure    about the latest research and guidelines
           shielding material integrated into the                          regarding EMF exposure. This knowl-
           case.                             Here are some general tips and   edge will help you make informed
                                           guidelines for reducing EMF exposure   decisions and take appropriate meas-
                                           from electronic devices, aside from   ures to reduce exposure.
                                                                              Remember, these tips are meant to
                                           using shielding products:       complement the use of EMF shielding
         EMF-protected mobile cover        Keep a safe distance between yourself   to reducing EMF exposure. It's impor-
                                             Increase distance: The intensity of
                                                                           products and create a holistic approach
                                           EMF radiation decreases with distance.
                                           and electronic devices whenever pos-
                                                                           tant to find a balance that works for
                                           sible. For example, hold your cell
                                                                           you and aligns with your lifestyle and
                                           phone away from your body when
                                                                           needs.
                                                                              While technology has undoubtedly
                                           making calls.
                                             Limit device usage: Minimize the
                                           time spent using electronic devices,
                                                                           acknowledge the potential risks associ-
                                                                           ated with EMF radiation. By adopting
                                           especially those that emit high levels   enriched our lives, it is imperative to
                                           of EMF radiation, such as cell phones,   these practical tips and incorporating
                                           laptops, and tablets. Take regular   protective measures, individuals can
                                           breaks and engage in activities that   actively reduce their exposure to EMF
                                           don't involve technology.       and continue to enjoy the benefits of
         EMF-protected shield paint        your device, switch it to airplane   ary steps, and navigate the invisible
                                             Use airplane mode: When you don't
                                                                           technology without compromising their
                                                                           health. Stay informed, take precaution-
                                           need to use the wireless functions of
                                                                           threat of EMF radiation in the modern
                                           mode. This disables the cellular, Wi-Fi,
                                                                           age. Remember, your well-being is in
                                           and Bluetooth connections, reducing
                                           EMF exposure.
                                                                           your hands—make informed choices
                                             Opt for wired connections: Whe-
                                                                           and prioritize your health in our tech-
                                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024
           10                              never possible, use wired connections   driven world.]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[HISTORY & HERITAGE







































           Shivaji Maharaj






           Architect of empires and





           champion of justice







                 n the 19th of February 1630, in                           From a young age, Shivaji exhibited
                 the illustrious Bhonsle dynasty,                          qualities that hinted at his future great-
           Oa legendary figure was born in                                 ness. His mother, Jijabai, played a piv-
           the hill fort of Shivneri near Pune –                           otal role in instilling a sense of patriot-
           Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj. As we                              ism and valor in him.
           commemorate his birth anniversary in                               Despite being surrounded by the opu-
           2024, it is crucial to delve deeper into                        lence of the royal court, Shivaji's early
           the life and legacy of this visionary                           years were marked by the turbulent po-
           leader who not only laid the foundation                         litical landscape of the Deccan region.
           for the Maratha Empire but also left an                         Witnessing the injustices inflicted upon
           indelible mark on the tapestry of Indian                        the common people by the oppressive
           history.                                                        regimes, Shivaji developed a deep sense
           Early Life and Education                                        of empathy and a strong desire to protect
             Shivaji, born as Shivaji Bhonsle, was                         his people.
           raised in the turbulent times of medieval                          His early education, though informal,
           India. His father, Shahaji Bhonsle,                             was comprehensive. He was well-versed
           served as a prominent military officer                          in the art of warfare, statecraft, and ad-
           under the Adil Shahi sultans of Bijapur.                        ministration. His exposure to the mili-

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[His strategic forts along the coastline,
                                                                           including the famous sea fort of Sindhu-
                                                                           durg, were a testament to his far-sighted
                                                                           military tactics.
                                                                           Military Prowess and Guerrilla
                                                                           Warfare
                                                                              Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj was not
                                                                           only a visionary leader but also a bril-
                                                                           liant military strategist. He pioneered
                                                                           the concept of guerrilla warfare, a tactic
                                                                           that proved to be highly effective against
                                                                           the more significant and well-estab-
                                                                           lished forces of the time. His guerilla
                                                                           tactics, known as "Ganimi Kava" or
                                                                           "Mountain Warfare," involved swift and
                                                                           unexpected attacks, disrupting the larger
                                                                           armies.
                                                                              Fortifications played a crucial role in
                                                                           Shivaji's military strategy. He meticu-
                                                                           lously constructed and strategically lo-
                                                                           cated forts across his kingdom, making
                                                                           it challenging for invaders to penetrate
                                                                           his defenses. The iconic Raigad Fort
                                                                           stands as a symbol of his military
                                                                           acumen and strategic foresight.
                                                                           Religious Tolerance and Administrative
                                                                           Reforms
                                                                              Shivaji's reign was characterized by a
                                                                           remarkable sense of religious tolerance.
                                                                           In an era marked by religious strife, he
         Map of the Maratha Kingdom                                        istration was known for its inclusive
                                                                           embraced diversity and promoted har-
                                                                           mony among his subjects. His admin-
                                                                           policies, ensuring that people of differ-
                                                                           ent faiths lived together peacefully.
                                                                              Administratively, Shivaji imple-
                                                                           mented several reforms that aimed at
                                                                           creating a just and efficient governance
                                                                           system. He established a council of eight
                                                                           ministers, known as the "Ashta Prad-
           tary strategies of his father and the   erance, and prosperity. In 1674, he   han," each overseeing specific aspects of
           teachings of his mother set the stage for   crowned himself as the Chhatrapati, es-  the administration. This system ensured
           the remarkable journey that lay ahead.   tablishing the Maratha Empire with Rai-  a balanced and effective governance
           Establishment of the Maratha Empire   gad as its capital.       structure.
             Shivaji's vision extended beyond the   One of Shivaji's notable achieve-  Shivaji's administrative reforms were
           confines of his own kingdom. He as-  ments was the development of a navy,   not limited to military and political
           pired to create a sovereign Maratha state   which significantly expanded the Mara-  spheres. He was a forward-thinking
           that would be a beacon of justice, tol-  tha influence along the western coast.   ruler who paid attention to the welfare
                                                                           of his subjects. He encouraged agricul-
                                                                           ture and trade, promoting economic
                                                                           prosperity. The system of 'Ryotwari' –
                                                                           direct collection of revenue from peas-
                                                                           ants – was introduced, providing a more
         Pratapgad: The Fortress of Valor                                  extends far beyond the borders of his
                                                                           equitable distribution of resources.
                                                                           Legacy and Impact
                                                                              Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj's legacy
                                                                           empire. His vision for a strong, united,
                                                                           and prosperous Maratha state inspired
                                                                           future generations of leaders. The Mara-
                                                                           tha Empire continued to flourish under
                                                                           the leadership of his descendants, leav-
                                                                           ing an enduring impact on the course of

           12                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Indian history.                 rich history of medieval India. The im-
             Shivaji's ideals of justice, religious   portance of integrating these historical
           tolerance, and social welfare laid the   lessons into the curriculum cannot be
           foundation for a just and inclusive soci-  overstated, as they offer valuable in-
           ety. His legacy is celebrated not only in   sights into leadership, governance, and
           Maharashtra but resonates throughout   nation-building.
           India as a symbol of resistance against   Shivaji's legacy lives on in the nu-
           oppression and the pursuit of a just and   merous festivals, plays, and literature
           equitable society.              dedicated to him. The depiction of his
           Commemorating the Birth         life in Marathi literature and the wide-
           Anniversary                     spread celebration of Shivaji Jayanti
             As we mark the 394th birth anniver-  showcase the enduring impact he has                      Shivaji showed great respect and honor towards women
           sary of Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj on   had on the cultural fabric of Maharash-
           the 19th of February 2024, it is an op-  tra.
           portune moment to reflect on the values   The 394th birth anniversary serves as
           he stood for and the challenges he over-  an occasion not just for celebration but
           came. Various events and celebrations   also for introspection. It prompts us to
           are planned across the country, including   reflect on how Shivaji's principles of
           processions, cultural programs, and edu-  justice, equality, and unity can be ap-
           cational seminars, to honor the memory   plied in contemporary society. The chal-
           of this iconic leader.          lenges faced by Shivaji in his time may
             Educational institutions are encour-  differ from the challenges we face today,   Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj's life is a
           aged to organize lectures and discus-  but the spirit of resilience and deter-  testament to the power of resilience,
           sions on Shivaji's life and legacy, pro-  mination he embodied remains a source   leadership, and a vision for a just soci-
           viding students with insights into the   of inspiration.        ety. As we celebrate his birth anniver-
                                                                           sary in 2024, let us remember and honor
                                                                           the legacy of this legendary ruler who
                                                                           defied the odds and established a legacy
                                                                           that continues to inspire generations.
                                                                           May his ideals of justice, tolerance, and
                                                                           unity continue to guide us on the path to
                                                                           a brighter and more equitable future. As
                                                                           we reflect on Shivaji's life, let us also
                                                                           acknowledge the importance of preserv-
                                                                           ing and sharing these historical narra-
                                                                           tives to inspire future generations and
                                                                           instill a sense of pride in our rich cul-
                                                                           tural heritage.
         Guerrilla Warfare




















         Navy of Chhatrapati Shivaji                                                                       Shivaji maharaj on warfare











           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[ENVIRONMENT




































           Tackling the desert's relentless expansion



           The Sahara's silent







           threat










                he Sahara Desert, known as the   communities.              sion of the Sahara.
                largest hot desert in the world, is   Causes of Expansion: Several factors   Additionally, human activities such
           Ta vast expanse of arid land    contribute to the expansion of the Sa-  as deforestation, overgrazing, and unsus-
           stretching across northern Africa. It   hara Desert. One of the primary drivers   tainable agricultural practices have ex-
           covers an area of approximately 9.2 mil-  is climate change, which has led to in-  acerbated the desertification process,
           lion square kilometers, making it larger   creased temperatures and altered precip-  further contributing to the expansion of
           than the entire United States. One of the   itation patterns in the region. As a result,   the Sahara. Deforestation, particularly in
           most intriguing aspects of the Sahara   the desert's boundaries have been grad-  the Sahel region, has resulted in the loss
           Desert is its on-going expansion, with   ually encroaching upon neighboring   of vegetation cover, leaving the soil ex-
           studies indicating that it is growing at a   areas, transforming once habitable lands   posed to erosion and reducing its ability
           rate of about 0.8 kilometers per month   into arid desert landscapes. The rise in   to retain moisture. Overgrazing by live-
           (9.6 km per year). In this article, we will   global temperatures intensifies evapora-  stock has also played a significant role
           delve into the causes and consequences   tion rates, leading to drier conditions   in desertification, as it leads to the remo-
           of this expansion, as well as its potential   and reduced soil moisture. This, in turn,   val of vegetation and the degradation of
           impact on the environment and local   promotes desertification and the expan-  soil quality. Unsustainable agricultural


           14                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[shade, thereby creating a more favorable
                                                                           environment for other plant and animal
                                                                           species. Sustainable land management
                                                                           practices, such as terracing, contour
                                                                           plowing, and the use of organic fertil-
                                                                           izers, can help conserve soil moisture
                                                                           and improve soil fertility.
                                                                              Additionally, the promotion of alter-
                                                                           native livelihoods can reduce the pres-
                                                                           sure on agricultural activities and pro-
                                                                           vide economic opportunities for local
                                                                           communities. Diversifying income
         Map of the Sahara Desert                                          production, and renewable energy proj-
                                                                           sources through ecotourism, handicraft
                                                                           ects can help alleviate poverty and re-
                                                                           duce dependence on natural resources
                                                                           that contribute to desertification.
                                                                              Furthermore, advancements in tech-

                                                                           played a vital role in understanding the
           practices, such as improper irrigation   diversity not only disrupts the delicate   nology and scientific research have
                                                                           causes and effects of desertification. Re-
           techniques and the overuse of water re-  ecological balance but also diminishes   mote sensing techniques, for example,
           sources, have further strained the fragile   the cultural and scientific value of the   enable scientists to monitor changes in
           ecosystems of the region.       region. Indigenous communities that   the desert's boundaries and assess the ef-
           Consequences and Impact         rely on the desert's resources for their   fectiveness of mitigation measures. Such
             The expansion of the Sahara Desert   traditional practices and medicinal   knowledge is essential for developing
           has far-reaching consequences for both   knowledge are also adversely affected.   targeted interventions and policies to
           the environment and local communities.   Mitigation and Adaptation   combat desertification effectively.
           One of the most significant impacts is   Efforts to mitigate and adapt to the   Specific measures are being taken to
           the loss of fertile land, which poses a   expansion of the Sahara Desert are cru-  combat desertification in the Sahara re-
           threat to agricultural activities and food   cial in addressing the challenges posed   gion, with various organizations, gov-
           security in the affected regions. As the   by desertification. International organi-  ernments, and local communities imple-
           desert expands, it engulfs arable land,   zations, governments, and local com-  menting strategies to address this
           making it increasingly challenging for   munities have implemented various   pressing issue. These measures aim to
           communities to sustain their livelihoods   strategies to combat desertification and   mitigate the expansion of the Sahara De-
           through farming and grazing. This loss   restore degraded lands. These include   sert and restore degraded lands. While
           of productive land not only affects the   reforestation initiatives, sustainable land   the effectiveness of these measures can
           local economy but also exacerbates pov-  management practices, and the promo-  vary, they have shown promising results
           erty and food insecurity.       tion of alternative livelihoods that are   in certain areas. Let's explore some of
             Furthermore, the expansion of the   less dependent on agriculture.   the specific measures being taken:
           Sahara has implications for biodiversity.   Reforestation plays a vital role in   Reforestation and Afforestation:
           The desert is home to a unique array of   combating desertification by restoring   Planting trees and establishing forests in
           plant and animal species that have   vegetation cover and preventing soil   desertified areas is a key strategy to
           adapted to its harsh conditions. Ho-  erosion. Planting drought-resistant tree   combat desertification. Drought-resis-
           wever, as the desert expands, these   species and implementing agroforestry   tant tree species are being planted to sta-
           species face the risk of habitat loss and   practices can help stabilize the soil, in-  bilize the soil, increase water retention,
           potential extinction. The loss of bio-  crease water retention, and provide   and provide shade. Agroforestry prac-
                                                                           tices, such as combining tree planting
                                                                           with agricultural activities, are also
                                                                           being implemented to improve soil fer-
                                                                           tility and create more sustainable land
                                                                           use systems.
         A Vast Stretch of the Sahara Desert                               ment practices is crucial to prevent soil
                                                                              Sustainable Land Management: Im-
                                                                           plementing sustainable land manage-

                                                                           erosion and degradation. Techniques
                                                                           such as terracing, contour plowing, and
                                                                           the use of organic fertilizers help con-
                                                                           serve soil moisture, improve soil struc-
                                                                           ture, and enhance agricultural productiv-
                                                                           ity. These practices aim to promote soil

                                                                           ity of land to desertification.

                                                                                                       15
           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         conservation and reduce the vulnerabil-]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Water Management: Efficient water
           management is essential in combating
           desertification. Measures such as the
           construction of small-scale dams, reser-
           voirs, and water harvesting systems help
           capture and store water for agricultural
           and domestic use. Proper irrigation tech-
           niques, such as drip irrigation and preci-
           sion farming, are also being promoted to
           minimize water wastage and maximize
           crop yield.
             Community-Based Initiatives: En-
           gaging local communities in the fight
           against desertification is crucial for                                                          A drought-resistant tree species in full bloom
           long-term success. Community-based
           initiatives involve raising awareness,
           providing training on sustainable land
           management practices, and empowering
           local communities to take ownership of
           their natural resources. These initiatives
           encourage sustainable livelihoods and
           promote the conservation of ecosystems.   ing techniques, such as satellite imagery   tem resilience. However, the long-term
             Policy Interventions: Governments   and Geographic Information Systems   success of these measures requires sus-
           and international organizations are im-  (GIS), help monitor changes in land   tained commitment, adequate resources,
           plementing policies and regulations to   cover and assess the effectiveness of   and collaboration among stakeholders.
           address desertification. These policies   mitigation measures. Research institu-  It is important to note that combating
           focus on land use planning, sustainable   tions are also studying the impacts of   desertification is a complex and multi-
           agriculture, and the protection of natural   climate change and developing innova-  faceted challenge that requires a holistic
           resources. They aim to create an en-  tive solutions to combat desertification.   approach. Addressing the root causes of
           abling environment for sustainable de-  The effectiveness of these measures   desertification, such as climate change
           velopment and provide incentives for   can vary depending on various factors,   and unsustainable land use practices, is
           adopting practices that combat desertifi-  including local conditions, community   crucial for long-term success. Continued
           cation.                         involvement, and the scale of implemen-  research, monitoring, and evaluation of
             Research and Technology: Advances   tation. In some areas, reforestation and   the implemented measures are essential
           in technology and scientific research   sustainable land management practices   to refine strategies and ensure their ef-
           play a vital role in understanding and   have shown positive results in restoring   fectiveness in combating desertification
           combating desertification. Remote sens-  degraded lands and improving ecosys-  in the Sahara region.
                                                                              The expansion of the Sahara Desert
                                                                           at a rate of about 0.8 kilometers per
                                                                           month is a concerning phenomenon with
                                                                           significant implications for the environ-
                                                                           ment and local communities. Climate
                                                                           change, coupled with human activities,
                                                                           has accelerated the desertification pro-
                                                                           cess, leading to the loss of fertile land
                                                                           and biodiversity. However, through col-
                                                                           lective efforts and sustainable practices,
                                                                           it is possible to mitigate the expansion
                                                                           of the Sahara and restore degraded
                                                                           areas. By prioritizing conservation, re-
                                                                           forestation, and sustainable land man-
                                                                           agement, we can work towards preserv-
         A traditional water harvesting system                             able desert. The challenges posed by de-
                                                                           ing the unique ecosystems and
                                                                           livelihoods that depend on this remark-

                                                                           sertification require a multi-faceted ap-
                                                                           proach, involving international
                                                                           cooperation, policy interventions, and
                                                                           community engagement. Only through
                                                                           such concerted efforts can we hope to
                                                                           address the expanding Sahara Desert
                                                                           and ensure a sustainable future for the
                                                                           region and its inhabitants.

           16                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[TIMEKEEPING


































                                                                                          Big Ben clock tower, London
           Tick-to-Tech












           The changing face









           of time

                he journey of clocks and wrist-                            of day. These devices were used by an-
                watches is a fascinating one that                          cient civilizations such as the Egyp-
           Tspans centuries and continents.                                tians, Greeks, and Romans, and were
           From the earliest sundials to the latest                        often made of stone or metal. Sundials
           smart watches, these timekeeping de-                            were accurate enough for most pur-
           vices have evolved in response to                               poses, but they had one major draw-
           changing needs and technological ad-                            back: they could only be used during
           vancements. In this article, we will ex-                        the day.
           plore the history of clocks and wrist-                             To solve this problem, the ancient
           watches, from their earliest origins to                         Greeks invented the water clock, which
           the present day.                                                used the flow of water to measure time.
             The earliest timekeeping devices                              These clocks were more accurate than
           were simple sundials, which used the                            sundials, and could be used at night as
           position of the sun to indicate the time                        well as during the day. Water clocks

           18                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[cated and accurate. The development of
                                                                           the quartz crystal oscillator in the 1920s
                                                                           allowed for the creation of highly accu-
                                                                           rate quartz watches, which quickly be-
                                                                           came the standard for timekeeping.
                                                                           Quartz watches were much more accu-
                                                                           rate than mechanical watches, and were
                                                                           also more affordable, making them ac-
                                                                           cessible to a wider range of people.
                                                                              The next major development in
                                                                           wristwatches came with the invention
                                                                           of the digital watch. The first digital
                                                                           watches were invented in the 1970s,
                                                                           and used LED or LCD displays to show
         Ancient Sundial                                                   the time. These watches were highly
                                                                           accurate, and were also much easier to
                                                                           read than traditional analog watches.
                                                                           Digital watches quickly became pop-
                                                                           ular, and were particularly popular
                                           the mechanical clock. The first mechan-  among younger people.
                                           ical clocks were invented in Europe in   In the 1980s and 1990s, wrist-
                                           the 14th century, and were powered by   watches became even more sophisti-
                                           weights or springs. These clocks were   cated. The development of micropro-
                                           much more accurate than water clocks,   cessors allowed for the creation of
                                           and could be used to measure time with   watches that could do much more than
                                           great precision. Mechanical clocks   just tell the time. These watches could
                                           quickly became popular throughout Eu-  display the date, the day of the week,
                                           rope, and were used for a variety of   and even the phase of the moon. Some
                                           purposes, from regulating the daily ac-  watches even had calculators, alarms,
                                           tivities of monasteries to keeping track   and other features built in.
                                                                              In the 21st century, wristwatches
                                           of the time during battles.     have continued to evolve. The devel-
         Old mechanical clock              widespread, they also became more   opment of smart watches has allowed
                                             As mechanical clocks became more
                                                                           for the creation of watches that can do
                                           complex. In the 16th century, the pen-
                                           dulum clock was invented, which used
                                                                           even more than traditional wrist-
                                           a swinging pendulum to regulate the
                                                                           watches. Smart watches can connect to
                                           movement of the clock's gears. This
                                           made the clock even more accurate, and   the internet, receive emails and text
                                                                           messages, and even make phone calls.
                                           allowed it to keep time with great pre-  They can also track your fitness and
                                           cision. Pendulum clocks quickly be-  health, and can be used to control other
                                           came the standard timekeeping device   devices such as your smartphone or
                                           in Europe, and were used in homes,   your home automation system.
                                           churches, and public buildings.    Despite the many advances in tech-
                                             The next major development in   nology, traditional wristwatches are still
                                           timekeeping came with the invention of   popular today. Many people appreciate
                                           the wristwatch. The first wristwatches   the craftsmanship and elegance of a
                                           were actually worn by women, and   well-made mechanical watch, and enjoy
                                           were little more than small clocks that   the tactile experience of winding the
                                           could be attached to a bracelet. These   watch and setting the time. Mechanical
                                           early wristwatches were not very accu-  watches are also often seen as status
         Pendulum Clock                    accessories.                    and enthusiasts.
                                           rate, and were mostly used as fashion
                                                                           symbols, and are prized by collectors
                                                                              In conclusion, the journey of clocks
                                             It wasn't until the 20th century that
                                                                           and wristwatches is a fascinating one
                                           wristwatches became more practical
                                           and accurate. During World War I, sol-
                                                                           From the earliest sundials to the latest
                                           diers found that carrying a pocket   that spans centuries and continents.
           were used throughout the ancient   watch was inconvenient, so they began   smart watches, these timekeeping de-
           world, and were particularly popular in   wearing wristwatches instead. These   vices have evolved in response to
           China, where they were used to regu-  early military wristwatches were rugged   changing needs and technological ad-
           late the daily activities of the imperial   and reliable, and quickly became pop-  vancements. Whether you prefer a sim-
           court.                          ular among civilians as well.   ple analog watch or a sophisticated
             The next major development in   In the years following World War I,   smart watch, there is a timekeeping de-
           timekeeping came with the invention of   wristwatches became more sophisti-  vice out there that is perfect for you.

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Most expensive watches in the world





                he world of luxury watches is                              places its value at an astonishing $30
                adorned with exquisite crafts-                             million.
           Tmanship, rare materials, and as-                                  Patek Philippe Grandmaster
           tronomical price tags. Let’s explore                            Chime Ref. 6300A-010: This remark-
           some of the most opulent timepieces                             able watch fetched a staggering $31 mil-
           ever created, along with their eye-water-                       lion at auction in Geneva. Its dual-faced
           ing prices:                                                     design, intricate complications, and lim-
             Graff Diamonds Hallucination:                                 ited production make it a true horologi-
           Claiming the title of the world’s most                          cal marvel.
           expensive watch, the Graff Diamonds                                Chopard 201-Carat: As the name
           Hallucination dazzles with a price tag of   display of artistry and extravagance.   suggests, this Chopard watch boasts a
           $55 million. This masterpiece is a kalei-  Graff Diamonds The Fascination:   mind-boggling 201 carats of diamonds,
           doscope of over 110 carats of rare col-  Not far behind, the Graff Diamonds the   including a 15-carat pink diamond. Its
           ored diamonds, set in a mesmerizing   Fascination commands a hefty $40 mil-  price? A cool $25 million.
                                           lion. This watch features a detachable
                                           38-carat diamond that can be worn as a
                                           ring. Talk about versatility.
                                             Breguet Grande Complication
                                           Marie Antoinette: With a fascinating
                                           history, the Breguet Grande Complica-
                                           tion Marie Antoinette was commis-
                                           sioned for the French queen herself. Its
                                           intricate design, including a tourbillon,
                                           perpetual calendar, and minute repeater,














           20                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[GLOBAL SOLIDARITY






































           Rare Disease Day 2024












           Uniting for Hope




                are Disease Day, observed on                               ease Patients: Living with a rare disease
                29th February 2024, is an annual                           presents numerous challenges for pa-
           Rglobal campaign that seeks to                                  tients and their families. Due to the lim-
           raise awareness about rare diseases and                         ited number of cases, rare diseases are
           the challenges faced by those affected                          often poorly understood or misdiag-
           by them. This day serves as a platform                          nosed, leading to delayed or inadequate
           for individuals, organizations, and com-                        treatment. Patients may face difficulty
           munities worldwide to come together,                            accessing specialized healthcare serv-
           share stories, advocate for better support                      ices, finding appropriate medical profes-
           and understanding, and ultimately strive                        sionals, and obtaining accurate infor-
           for improved treatments and outcomes   may be rare individually, collectively,   mation about their condition.
           for those living with rare diseases. Let   they affect millions of people world-  Additionally, the high cost of treatments,
           us delve into the significance and impact   wide. It is estimated that there are over   lack of research funding, and limited
           of Rare Disease Day 2024.       7,000 known rare diseases, with new   availability of support networks further
           Understanding Rare Diseases     ones being discovered regularly. These   compound the challenges faced by rare
             Rare diseases, also known as orphan   conditions often have a genetic basis   disease patients.
           diseases, are a diverse group of dis-  and can manifest in various ways, im-  The Importance of Rare Disease Day
           orders that affect a relatively small   pacting multiple systems within the   Rare Disease Day plays a crucial role
           number of individuals compared to more   body.                  in raising awareness and understanding
           common illnesses. While each disease   The Challenges Faced by Rare Dis-  of these often overlooked conditions. By

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[shedding light on the struggles faced by   lic about specific rare diseases, their im-  Rare Disease Day encourages people
           patients and their families, the campaign   pact on individuals and families, and the   from all walks of life to get involved and
           aims to foster a sense of unity and sup-  urgent need for increased research and   make a difference.
           port. It provides a platform for individ-  funding. By fostering a sense of com-  There are many rare diseases that are
           uals to share their stories, enabling   munity, Rare Disease Day encourages   commonly misunderstood or misdiag-
           others to learn and empathize with their   collaboration, knowledge-sharing, and   nosed. Here are some examples:
           experiences. Moreover, it serves as a cat-  the development of innovative solutions   Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome: This is a
           alyst for advocacy, encouraging govern-  to improve the lives of rare disease pa-  group of inherited disorders that affect
           ments, healthcare professionals, and re-  tients.               the connective tissues in the body.
           searchers to prioritize rare diseases and   The Power of Unity   Symptoms may include joint hypermo-
           allocate resources towards their study,   Uniting for Rare Disease Day em-  bility, skin that bruises easily, severe fa-
           diagnosis, and treatment.       powers patients, caregivers, and advo-  tigue, and chronic pain. It is often mis-
           Promoting Awareness and Advocacy   cates to raise their voices and advocate   diagnosed as fibromyalgia, chronic
             On Rare Disease Day 2024, individ-  for change. By creating a global network   fatigue syndrome, or other connective
           uals and organizations around the world   of support, individuals can amplify their   tissue disorders.
           will come together to organize events,   impact and effect positive change in pol-  Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases:
           campaigns, and fundraisers to promote   icy, research, and healthcare services.   This is a group of disorders that affect
           awareness and support for rare diseases.   Through social media campaigns, educa-  the immune system's ability to fight off
           These initiatives aim to educate the pub-  tional events, and fundraising initiatives,   infections. Symptoms may include
                                                                           frequent infections, autoimmune dis-
                                                                           orders, and allergies. It is often misdiag-
                                                                           nosed as chronic infections or allergies.
                                                                             Huntington's Disease: This is a ge-
         A team of doctors focused on specialized treatment                misdiagnosed as Parkinson's disease or
                                                                           netic disorder that affects the nerve cells
                                                                           in the brain. Symptoms may include in-
                                                                           voluntary movements, cognitive decline,
                                                                           and psychiatric symptoms. It is often

                                                                           Alzheimer's disease.
                                                                             Sickle Cell Anemia: This is a genetic
                                                                           disorder that affects the red blood cells
                                                                           in the body. Symptoms may include
                                                                           pain, fatigue, and organ damage. It is
                                                                           often misdiagnosed as other forms of
                                                                           anemia or chronic pain conditions.
                                                                             Cystic Fibrosis: This is a genetic dis-
                                                                           order that affects the lungs, pancreas,
                                                                           and other organs. Symptoms may in-
                                                                           clude chronic lung infections, digestive

           22                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[problems, and poor growth. It is often
           misdiagnosed as asthma or other respira-
           tory illnesses.
             It's important to note that these are
           just a few examples of the many rare
           diseases that can be misunderstood or
           misdiagnosed. If you or a loved one are
           experiencing unexplained symptoms, it's
           important to seek medical advice and
           advocate for proper testing and diagno-
           sis.
             Diagnosing rare diseases accurately
           can be challenging due to several fac-                                                          Nurse providing patient care
           tors. Here are some of the key chal-
           lenges:
             Lack of Awareness: Many healthcare
           professionals may have limited knowl-
           edge and awareness of rare diseases due
           to their rarity. This can result in mis-  diagnosis or delayed diagnosis as symp-  ulations are often small. This can make
                                           toms might be mistaken for more com-  it challenging to conduct clinical trials,
                                           mon conditions.                 gather sufficient data, and develop ef-
                                             Heterogeneity of Symptoms: Rare   fective treatments.
                                           diseases often exhibit a wide range of   Delayed Onset and Variable Progres-
                                           symptoms that can vary from person to   sion: Some rare diseases may have a de-
                                           person. These symptoms may also over-  layed onset, with symptoms appearing
                                           lap with other more common con-  later in life. Additionally, the progres-
                                           ditions, making it difficult to pinpoint   sion of symptoms can vary widely,
                                           the exact cause.                further complicating the diagnostic pro-
                                             Limited Research and Data: Re-  cess.
                                           search on rare diseases is often limited,   Rare diseases are frequently misdiag-
                                                                              Misdiagnosis and Underdiagnosis:
         Young medical professional ready for cction  ized diagnostic tests and criteria.   ment. Patients may be passed from one
                                           and there may be a lack of comprehen-
                                                                           nosed or underdiagnosed, leading to a
                                           sive data and diagnostic guidelines. This
                                                                           significant delay in appropriate treat-
                                           can hinder the development of standard-
                                                                           specialist to another, undergoing unnec-
                                             Genetic Complexity: Many rare dis-
                                                                           essary tests and treatments before re-
                                           eases have a genetic basis, involving
                                           mutations in specific genes. Genetic
                                                                           ceiving an accurate diagnosis.
                                           testing can be complex and expensive,
                                                                              Addressing these challenges requires
                                                                           a multi-faceted approach involving in-
                                           requiring specialized laboratories and
                                                                           creased awareness, improved education
                                           expertise. Access to genetic testing fa-
                                           cilities may be limited, leading to chal-
                                                                           for healthcare professionals, enhanced
                                                                           collaboration between researchers and
                                           lenges in obtaining accurate diagnoses.
                                             Small Patient Populations: Due to
                                                                           clinicians, and greater investment in
                                                                           rare disease research. Efforts to improve
                                           the rarity of these diseases, patient pop-
                                                                           access to genetic testing, establish spe-
                                                                           cialized centers for rare diseases, and
                                                                           create centralized databases for sharing
                                                                           diagnostic information can also contrib-
                                                                           ute to more accurate and timely dia-
                                                                           gnoses.
                                                                              Rare Disease Day 2024 is an oppor-
                                                                           tunity to come together as a global com-
                                                                           munity, united by the common goal of
         Healthcare professionals in action                                awareness, supporting research, and ad-
                                                                           improving the lives of individuals af-
                                                                           fected by rare diseases. By raising
                                                                           vocating for better healthcare, we can
                                                                           create a more inclusive and compassion-
                                                                           ate society. Let us stand together, em-
                                                                           brace empathy, and work towards a fu-
                                                                           ture where no one's struggle goes
                                                                           dition may be.
                                                                                                       23
           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         unnoticed, no matter how rare their con-]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[CINEMA TRENDS
































           Ghost lights dim




           Bollywood's eerie farewell






           to horror cinema






                ollywood, over the decades, has                            based on Daphne du Maurier's novel
                woven a tapestry of diverse gen-                           "Rebecca," and "Gumnaam" (1965), in-
           Bres, captivating audiences with                                spired by Agatha Christie's "And Then
           its cinematic brilliance. Among the gen-                        There Were None," showcased the in-
           res that once held a prominent place was                        fluence of international literature on In-
           horror, with its ability to send shivers                        dian horror cinema.
           down the spine and create an immersive                             The 1970s and 1980s marked a sig-
           experience for viewers. However, the                            nificant shift in the horror genre, with
           landscape of Bollywood has witnessed a                          movies like "Bhoot Bungla" (1965) and
           significant shift, with horror movies                           "Jaani Dushman" (1979) introducing
           gradually fading away. This transition                          elements of comedy and romance along-
           prompts us to explore the golden era of                         side horror. These films catered to a
           horror movies and the reasons behind                            wider audience and became commercial
           their eventual decline.                                         successes, blending horror with other
           The Golden Era of Horror Movies in                              popular genres.
           Bollywood                                                          One of the most iconic horror movies
             In the past, Bollywood witnessed a                            of the 1990s was "Raaz" (2002), di-
           golden era of horror movies that capti-  genre in Bollywood and became iconic   rected by Vikram Bhatt. It revitalized
           vated audiences with their unique blend   in their own right.   the horror genre in Bollywood and set
           of suspense, supernatural elements, and   During the 1950s and 1960s, Bolly-  the stage for a new wave of horror films
           spine-chilling narratives. Movies like   wood produced several memorable hor-  in the early 2000s. "Raaz" was followed
           "Mahal" (1949) and "Bees Saal Baad"   ror movies that left a lasting impact on   by successful franchises like "1920"
           (1962) set the foundation for the horror   the audience. Films like "Kohra" (1964),   (2008) and "Haunted - 3D" (2011),

           24                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[voking narrative.
                                                                              These recent horror movies have
                                                                           managed to bring back audiences' inter-
         A scene from the Hindi movie 'Kohra': Eerie and suspenseful
                                                                           est in the genre by offering fresh and in-
                                                                           novative storytelling approaches. They
                                                                           have successfully combined elements of
                                                                           horror with other genres, such as
                                                                           comedy and fantasy, to create a unique
                                                                           viewing experience. These films have
                                                                           also showcased the potential for the hor-
                                                                           ror genre to evolve and adapt to the
                                                                           changing tastes of the audience.
                                                                           Why the Shift Away from Horror?
                                                                              One of the main reasons for this shift
                                                                           is the changing tastes of the audience.
                                                                           With the rise of social media and the in-
                                                                           ternet, people now have access to a
                                                                           wider range of content from all over the
                                                                           world. As a result, the audience's expec-
                                                                           tations have changed, and they are now
                                                                           looking for more realistic and relatable
                                                                           content. Horror movies, with their su-
                                                                           pernatural themes and over-the-top
                                                                           scares, no longer appeal to the modern
                                                                           audience.
                                                                              Another reason for the decline of
                                                                           horror movies in Bollywood is the lack
                                                                           of innovation and creativity in the genre.
                                                                           Most horror movies follow a similar for-
                                                                           mula, with jump scares, possessed char-
         A scary Scene of horror movie                                     originality has led to a decline in the
                                                                           acters, and haunted houses. This lack of
                                                                           quality of horror movies being produced
                                                                           in Bollywood.
                                                                              Additionally, the Indian film industry
                                                                           has been facing a lot of competition
                                                                           from Hollywood and other international
                                                                           film industries. Hollywood has been
                                                                           producing some of the most innovative
                                                                           and terrifying horror movies in recent
           which further explored supernatural   Kaushik. "Stree" cleverly blended horror   years, which has made it difficult for
           themes and garnered a dedicated fan   with comedy and social commentary,   Bollywood to keep up.
           base.                           making it a unique and refreshing ad-  The Indian film industry has been
             There have been a few recent horror   dition to the genre. The film received   facing a lot of criticism for its portrayal
           movies in Bollywood that have managed   critical acclaim and became a commer-  of women in horror movies. Many hor-
           to gain popularity and bring back au-  cial success, resonating with both critics   ror movies in Bollywood have been ac-
           diences' interest in the genre. One such   and audiences.       cused of objectifying women and per-
           film is "Stree" (2018), directed by Amar   Another notable horror movie is   petuating harmful stereotypes. This has
                                           "Bhoot: Part One - The Haunted Ship"
                                           (2020), directed by Bhanu Pratap Singh.
                                           Starring Vicky Kaushal, the film offered
                                           a gripping and atmospheric horror ex-
         Director and Producer: Vikram Bhatt  Part One - The Haunted Ship" received                        Director and Producer: Ram Gopal Verma
                                           perience, focusing on a haunted ship and
                                           the mysteries surrounding it. "Bhoot:

                                           positive reviews for its effective scares
                                           and strong performances.
                                             Additionally, "Tumbbad" (2018), di-
                                           rected by Rahi Anil Barve, gained a cult
                                           following for its unique blend of horror,
                                           fantasy, and mythology. The film was
                                           praised for its stunning visuals, at-
                                           mospheric storytelling, and thought-pro-

           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[led to a backlash from the audience and
           has made it difficult for filmmakers to
           produce horror movies that are both en-
           tertaining and socially responsible.
             Saturation of Tropes: Bollywood hor-
           ror films became synonymous with
           clichéd tropes and predictable plotlines,
           contributing to a sense of monotony.
           Filmmakers struggled to introduce fresh
           and innovative concepts within the hor-
           ror genre, leading to a decline in au-
           dience interest.
             Emergence of Other Genres: The in-
           flux of diverse genres in Bollywood,                                                            Vicky Kaushal in Bhoot movie
           such as biopics, crime dramas, and so-
           cial comedies, has diverted both film-
           makers and audiences away from horror.
           Success in exploring real-life stories,
           complex characters, and societal issues
           has encouraged filmmakers to explore   storytelling techniques, leading to a   landscape, reflecting the dynamic nature
           alternative genres.             cross-pollination of ideas and styles.   of the industry. The golden era of horror
             Economic Considerations: Horror   One of the most significant ways in   movies, with classics like "Bees Saal
           films often face challenges in securing   which Hollywood horror movies have   Baad" and "Mahal," set the stage for a
           consistent box office success due to their   influenced Bollywood is through the use   genre that once held a special place in
           reliance on supernatural elements, spe-  of visual effects and technology. Holly-  the hearts of audiences. While the de-
           cial effects, and a gripping atmosphere,   wood has been at the forefront of devel-  cline is evident, the cyclical nature of
           leading to higher production costs. Film-  oping cutting-edge visual effects and   trends suggests that Bollywood may re-
           makers prioritize cost-effective projects   CGI, which have been used to create   visit the horror genre in the future,
           with broader appeal, impacting the pro-  some of the most iconic horror movie   bringing with it a fresh perspective and
           duction of horror movies.       moments. Bollywood filmmakers have   renewed interest in the spooky and su-
             International Influence: The in-  also started to incorporate these tech-  pernatural. Until then, fans of the eerie
           fluence of international cinema, particu-  niques into their films, resulting in more   and uncanny can revisit the classics that
           larly Hollywood, has played a pivotal   visually stunning and immersive horror   defined an era of spine-chilling storytell-
           role in shaping Bollywood trends. The   experiences.            ing in Indian cinema.
           popularity of Hollywood-style thrillers   Moreover, Hollywood horror movies
           and psychological dramas has encour-  have also influenced the themes and
           aged Bollywood to explore alternative   narratives of Bollywood horror films.
           genres, diverting resources from horror.   Many Bollywood horror movies have
             Hollywood horror movies have had a   been inspired by Hollywood classics,
           significant influence on the portrayal   such as "The Exorcist" and "The
           and storytelling of horror films in Bolly-  Omen," and have adapted these stories
           wood. The success of Hollywood horror   to suit the Indian context.
           movies has prompted Bollywood film-  Bollywood's departure from horror
           makers to explore similar themes and   movies marks a shift in the cinematic












         A scary Scene of horror movie













           26                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[TRAVEL






























           Sydney Secrets




           Urban discoveries and






           neighbourhood whispers








                 estled on the eastern coast of   This UNESCO World Heritage site, situ-  Climb experience allows daring individ-
                 Australia, Sydney stands as a   ated on Bennelong Point, is more than a   uals to ascend the arches and take in
           Ncaptivating metropolis that    venue for world-class performances; it is   panoramic views of the city, offering a
           seamlessly combines modernity with a   a living work of art that invites explora-  unique perspective of Sydney's skyline
           rich historical tapestry. This dynamic   tion. Visitors can take guided tours to   and waterways. The bridge's illumina-
           city offers an array of experiences, from   uncover the secrets of its design, marvel   tion at night adds a touch of magic to the
           iconic landmarks to pristine beaches,   at its distinctive sail-like structures, and   city's already enchanting panorama.
           making it a haven for travelers seeking a   enjoy breathtaking views of the harbor   Cultural Hotspots: Sydney's cultural
           diverse and enriching adventure. In this   and cityscape from various vantage   scene is as diverse and dynamic as its
           comprehensive guide, we'll delve deeper   points.               population. The Art Gallery of New
           into the various facets that make Sydney   Adjacent to the Opera House, the   South Wales, located in the picturesque
           a truly exceptional destination.   Sydney Harbour Bridge stands as a   Domain, houses an extensive collection
             Landmarks and Architecture: The   monumental engineering feat. Connect-  that spans Australian, European, and
           Sydney Opera House, an architectural   ing the city's central business district to   Asian art. The gallery's commitment to
           masterpiece designed by Danish archi-  the North Shore, this bridge is more than   fostering a connection between art and
           tect Jørn Utzon, is an iconic symbol not   just a transportation artery; it's an adven-  the community is reflected in its varied
           just of Sydney but of Australia itself.   ture waiting to happen. The Bridge-  programs, exhibitions, and events.


           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[For a deeper exploration of Aus-
                                                                           tralia's natural history, the Australian
                                                                           Museum is a must-visit. Located in the
                                                                           heart of Sydney, this museum is a treas-
                                                                           ure trove of exhibits ranging from an-
                                                                           cient fossils to indigenous artifacts, pro-
                                                                           viding a comprehensive look at the
                                                                           country's rich biodiversity and cultural
                                                                           heritage.
                                                                              The Museum of Contemporary Art
                                                                           Australia (MCA) in Circular Quay
                                                                           serves as a hub for modern art enthusi-
                                                                           asts. With a commitment to showcasing
                                                                           both local and international contempo-
                                                                           rary artists, the MCA offers a thought-
                                                                           provoking journey through the ever-
                                                                           evolving world of visual arts. Moreover,
                                                                           the museum's emphasis on promoting
                                                                           indigenous art contributes to Sydney's
                                                                           cultural narrative.
                                                                              Throughout the year, Sydney hosts a
                                                                           plethora of festivals and events that
                                                                           celebrate its cultural diversity. The
                                                                           Sydney Festival, held in January, trans-
                                                                           forms the city into a vibrant cultural
                                                                           playground with a diverse range of per-
                                                                           formances, exhibitions, and installa-
                                                                           tions. Vivid Sydney, an annual light and
                                                                           music festival, further enhances the
                                                                           city's allure, turning its landmarks into
                                                                           mesmerizing works of art.
                                                                              Natural Wonders: Sydney's natural
                                                                           beauty is showcased in its stunning
                                                                           coastal landscapes, verdant parks, and
                                                                           nearby mountainous regions. Bondi
                                                                           Beach, synonymous with Australian surf
                                                                           culture, is a sun-drenched haven for
                                                                           beach lovers. The Bondi to Coogee
                                                                           Coastal Walk offers a scenic trek along
                                                                           the coastline, passing through sandy
                                                                           coves, dramatic cliffs, and vibrant sea-
                                                                           side communities. Along the way, vis-
                                                                           itors can enjoy the sculptures that dot
                                                                           the path, adding an artistic touch to the
                                                                           already breathtaking views.
                                                                              For those seeking a tranquil escape,
                                                                           the Royal Botanic Garden provides an
                                                                           oasis in the heart of the city. This lush
                                                                           expanse features themed gardens, in-
                                                                           cluding a tropical rainforest and succu-
                                                                           lent garden. Visitors can partake in
                                                                           guided tours, bird watching, or simply
                                                                           indulge in a leisurely picnic surrounded
                                                                           by the beauty of nature.
                                                                              A short drive from the city takes trav-
                                                                           elers to the Blue Mountains National
                                                                           Park, a UNESCO World Heritage site.
                                                                           The park's rugged landscapes, eucalyp-
                                                                           tus-clad valleys, and iconic Three Sisters
                                                                           rock formation make it a haven for
                                                                           hikers and nature enthusiasts. The Sce-
                                                                           nic World attraction adds an element of
                                                                           adventure with its thrilling rides, includ-
                                                       Breathtaking Sydney view
           28                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Sydney festival celebration                                                                       Botanical bliss at the Royal Botanic Garden















                                                                           at the Sydney Fish Market, one of the
                                                                           largest of its kind in the Southern Hemi-
                                                                           sphere. This bustling market offers an
                                                                           extensive array of fresh catches, and vis-
                                                                           itors can either sample seafood delights
                                                                           from various stalls or embark on a be-
                                                                           hind-the-scenes tour to gain insight into
         Gorgeous Sydney beach                                             pride for locals, and the city is dotted
                                                                           the market's operations.
                                                                              Sydney's coffee culture is a source of
                                                                           with countless cafes serving up artisanal
                                                                           brews. Neighborhoods like Surry Hills
                                                                           and Newtown are particularly known for
                                                                           their vibrant cafe scenes, where locally
                                                                           roasted beans and innovative brewing
                                           ing the steepest passenger railway in the   methods have made Sydney a haven for
                                           world, providing a unique and exhilarat-  coffee connoisseurs.
                                           ing perspective of the region.     In conclusion, Sydney's blend of cul-
                                             Culinary Delights: Sydney's culinary   tural richness, natural wonders, and culi-
                                           scene mirrors its multicultural pop-  nary delights makes it a city of endless
                                           ulation, offering a diverse range of din-  exploration. As visitors traverse the di-
                                           ing experiences that cater to every pal-  verse neighborhoods, indulge in its culi-
                                           ate. The historic Rocks district, with its   nary offerings, and immerse themselves
                                           cobblestone streets and charming archi-  in cultural experiences, they'll discover
                                           tecture, is a gastronomic haven. Restau-  the multifaceted charm that makes
                                           rants and pubs here serve up a blend of   Sydney a perennial favorite among
                                           local and international flavors, allowing   global travelers.
                                           visitors to savor delicious meals while   Whether seeking adventure, relaxa-
                                           immersed in the city's colonial history.   tion, or cultural enrichment, Sydney
                                             Chinatown, located in the heart of the   beckons with open arms, promising an
                                                                           unforgettable journey that transcends the
                                           city, is a bustling enclave filled with au-
         Sydney skyline and buildings      cuisine. From dumplings to noodles, the   weave together the old and the new, the
                                           thentic eateries serving delectable Asian
                                                                           ordinary. The city's ability to seamlessly
                                                                           natural and the urban, creates an en-
                                           aromatic dishes reflect the cultural di-
                                           versity that defines Sydney's culinary
                                                                           chanting narrative that leaves an indeli-
                                                                           ble mark on every traveler's heart.
                                           landscape. The vibrant atmosphere,
                                                                           Sydney invites you to explore its vibrant
                                           especially during Chinese New Year
                                           celebrations, adds an extra layer of ex-
                                                                           tapestry, where every thread tells a story,
                                           citement to the dining experience.
                                             Seafood enthusiasts are in for a treat
                                                                           discovery.
                                                                                                       29
           FEBRUARY 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                         and every moment is an opportunity for]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS













           Advocating Genuine
                                                                           2024 Coverage
           Environmental Responsibility    nificance of the Ram Mandir in Ayod-  Commending Safer Internet Day
                                           hya.
             The latest Revoir issue captivated   Prem Singh, Bristol, England, United   I commend your insightful coverage
           me, particularly Navormi Vats' piece on   Kingdom               of Safer Internet Day 2024. The article's
           "The impact of climate change on Gul-                           focus on digital literacy, cyber security,
           marg's snowscape." A crucial explora-  Celebrating Love: Navigating   and fostering respectful online behavior
           tion of global warming's toll on India's   Societal Norms       resonates with the current need for re-
           snow-covered hills. It's disheartening                          sponsible internet use. In an era where
           that while the West, especially the US,   Kudos for the insightful article on   technology is ubiquitous, promoting a
           vocalizes concern about climate change,   Valentine's Day's cultural significance,   safer online environment is paramount.
           their actions tell a different story. The   especially within India's middle-class   Your detailed piece not only raises
           use of lethal weapons and environmental   context. The piece adeptly explores the   awareness but also empowers readers to
           pollutants contradicts their purported   nuanced relationship between love and   navigate the digital world responsibly.
           commitment. Let's amplify the call for   societal norms, shedding light on the   Keep up the excellent work in shedding
           genuine environmental responsibility.   challenges faced by young individuals in   light on crucial issues in the ever-evolv-
           Shahid A. Siddiqui, I.R.S.(Retd)   expressing affection openly. The call to   ing landscape of technology.
           Hamdard Education Society, New   acknowledge the evolving dynamics and   Anuj Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           Delhi, India                    respect cultural intricacies is timely. It's   India
                                           a reminder that amidst global celebra-
           Commending the Splendid         tions, local nuances matter. A thought-  Enlightening Perspectives on
           Coverage of Ram Mandir in       provoking read that resonates with a di-  Navigating Life's Challenges
           Ayodhya                         verse readership.
                                           Nutan Sharma, Delhi, India         I recently read the compelling article
             I am writing to express my heartfelt                          titled "How to prevent frustration from
           appreciation for the recent article on   Urgent Global Attention Needed for   stealing your joy." Its insightful explora-
           Ayodhya's Ram Mandir. The piece mas-  Elephant Seal Tragedy     tion of the emotional trajectory res-
           terfully delves into the cultural and ar-                       onated deeply. The emphasis on mind-
           chitectural marvel that this temple repre-  The recent revelation of H5N1 trans-  fulness, effective communication, and
           sents, offering readers a comprehensive   mission among Patagonian elephant   problem-solving as coping mechanisms
           understanding of its historical roots, in-  seals is a grave concern for biodiversity   is both timely and relevant. I believe this
           tricate design details, and the broader   and human health. The international   piece would greatly benefit readers,
           impact on the community. The author's   community must unite to address this   shedding light on vital aspects of per-
           meticulous exploration of the temple's   threat. The tragic mass die-off signals an   sonal growth and mental well-being.
           construction, materials used, and sym-  urgent need for global research, collabo-  Considering the increasing importance
           bolic significance beautifully encapsu-  ration, and preventative measures. This   of such topics, I recommend featuring
           lates the essence of religious and cul-  issue extends beyond national borders,   this article in the Lifestyle or Wellness
           tural resurgence.               requiring immediate attention to miti-  section.
             The coverage not only serves as an   gate the environmental and potential   Ritu Nanda, Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh,
           informative guide to the readers but also   public health impacts. It's time for swift,   India
           as a celebration of the rich cultural her-  international action to safeguard our
           itage that the Ram Mandir embodies.   ecosystems and communities. Preserve
           Kudos to the author for a well-rounded   the planet's intricate ecosystems.    Letters (limited to one hundred words)
           and insightful piece, providing a nu-  Pankaj Gupta, Phenix City, Alabama,   are welcome and should be addressed
                                                                              to the Editor at Email:
           anced perspective on the profound sig-  United States              revoir@post.com



             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           30                                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR | FEBRUARY 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>