<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 22 I NOVEMBER 16 2025  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: MIKHAIL NILOV










            8                               5                               15































           4-Editorial: Why journalism still matters  24-Tipu in popular imagination today
           5-The journalist’s role in a divided            27-Horoscopes

           world                                           28-Letters

           8-Why smarter is the new stronger               31-Frame of thought

           11-Thinking outside the academy
           15-5 letters that can change the world

           18-When the world watched together

           21-The big cat’s role in military, media &

           myth









           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Truth under fire
     EDITORIAL  Why journalism                                                     Dr. Kamran Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           still matters                                                        Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                              he first casualty when war comes is   Art & Culture Editor
                                              truth. The old saying feels truer than   Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Tever, not just in times of war, but in
                                        the quieter battles of everyday life. Today,   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        journalists around the world find them-    Vishakha Sharma
                                        selves on the frontlines of a new kind of
                                        conflict: not against armies, but against al-  Social Media Editor
                                        gorithms, propaganda and public distrust.
                                           Once, journalism was the public’s win-    Sushil Kumar
                                        dow to the world. Today, that window is
                                        crowded with noise. Anyone with a smart-  Art & Graphics Director
                                        phone can “break news,” and truth often      Vipin Agarwal
                                        struggles to compete with speed. A headline
                                        that sparks outrage travels faster than one
           that seeks understanding. The challenge isn’t just telling the story anymore; it’s prov-  EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           ing that it’s true.
             Across continents, the media’s role is being redefined. In the West, newsrooms are   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           battling misinformation spread by AI-generated deepfakes and politically driven   Editor, United News of India, New
           narratives. In Asia, journalists juggle between government expectations and public
           skepticism. Even in India, the world’s largest democracy, the press walks a delicate   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           line, reporting with responsibility while navigating a complex web of political, social   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           and digital pressures. It’s not easy, but then again, it never was.   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             The irony of the information age is that it’s made people more connected and   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           more suspicious at the same time. Audiences no longer just consume news, they dis-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           sect it, question it, doubt it. Maybe that’s not entirely bad. Healthy skepticism keeps   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           the press accountable. But when skepticism hardens into cynicism, the very idea of   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           truth starts to crumble.
             There are small victories, though. Independent journalists verifying facts with lim-  SUBSCRIPTIONS
           ited resources. Local reporters risking safety to uncover environmental crimes. Pho-
           tojournalists capturing humanity amid chaos. These stories remind us that journalism   Phone +91 20 40199102
           isn’t just about headlines, it’s about heartlines.
             Journalists aren’t perfect. They make mistakes. They miss details. But their pur-  Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           suit of truth, however flawed, is still one of humanity’s most necessary acts. It’s easy   Baner Road,
           to criticize from afar; harder to stand in the rain with a notebook, trying to make   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           sense of a world that often doesn’t.                               Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             As we mark International Journalist Day, maybe we should ask ourselves a differ-  Website www.revoir.in
           ent question, not just what the media gets wrong, but why it still matters when it gets
           it right. Because when journalism works, it builds bridges, not walls. It gives voice to   Legal Advisor
           the unheard and light to the unseen.                                 Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
             In an age of pixels and polarization, journalists remain our imperfect truth-tellers.
           And perhaps that’s exactly why we need them, to remind us that truth, like humanity
           itself, is never perfect, but always worth pursuing.
                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.

         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY







































           Truth in Turmoil                                                The new frontlines of journalism
                                                                              A decade ago, a journalist’s greatest
                                                                           challenge might have been finding the
                                                                           right source or verifying a breaking
                                                                           story before deadline. Today, the chal-
           The journalist’s                                                lenge is more existential: convincing
                                                                           people that truth still matters.
                                                                              Scroll through social media and
                                                                           you’ll find headlines that read like fic-
                                                                           tion, yet gather millions of views. Entire
           role in a divided                                               newsrooms now fight not only for accu-
                                                                           racy but for survival in an ecosystem
                                                                           where engagement often trumps ethics.
                                                                           A false story, laced with outrage, can
                                                                           reach more readers than a well-re-
           world                                                           searched report. That imbalance has
                                                                           forced journalism into a strange dual
                                                                           role, chronicler and combatant, truth-
                                                                           teller and defender of truth itself.
                                                                              When Maria Ressa, the Filipino
           The journalist’s role isn’t just to inform, it’s to remind      Nobel laureate, said, “Without facts, you
                                                                           can’t have truth. Without truth, you can’t
           the world that truth, however fragile, is worth fighting        have trust,” she was speaking for jour-
                                                                           nalists everywhere. In her own country,
           for. By Aarav Sharma                                            she faced arrest for exposing disinfor-
                                                                           mation campaigns and political abuses.
                                                                           But her story isn’t isolated, it’s a mirror
             n times of deceit, telling the truth is   beliefs. The truth, once a common ref-  held up to the global state of press free-
             a revolutionary act. That line, often   erence point, now feels like a battle-  dom.
           Iattributed to George Orwell, feels   field.
           more like prophecy today than warning.   And in the middle of it all stands the   The weight of public distrust
           Open any news feed and you’ll see a   journalist, sometimes respected, often   Somewhere along the line, “main-
           world split not just by borders, but by   doubted, always watched.   stream media” became a slur.

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[claim, it’s already taken root in mil-
                                                                           lions of minds. Yet many persist.
                                                                              In Nigeria, reporters at Dubawa
                                                                           have dedicated entire teams to verifying
                                                                           viral claims in real time. In Ukraine,
                                                                           journalists risk their lives documenting
                                                                           war crimes amid a flood of propa-
         A journalist reporting from a war zone                            ists still publish under pseudonyms just
                                                                           ganda. In Mexico, where reporting on
                                                                           corruption can get you killed, journal-

                                                                           to keep the truth alive.
                                                                           Between power and pressure
                                                                              Journalism has always had uneasy
                                                                           proximity to power. But in many parts
                                                                           of the world, that tension has turned
                                                                           hostile.
                                                                              In Russia, independent outlets have

                                                                           entire newsrooms were dismantled over-
                                                                           night. Even in democratic countries,

                                             “                             been forced into exile. In Hong Kong,
                                                                           subtle pressures, advertiser influence,
              The trust deficit                                            defamation laws, online harassment,

                                             We’re not enemies of          shape what gets printed and what
                Once, journalists were the                                 doesn’t.
             bridge between power and        the state; we’re                 Closer to home, journalists in India
             people. Today, many see them as                               who report on sensitive issues such as
             part of the problem. The 2024   enemies of silence.”          environmental movements or social con-
             Reuters Institute survey shows                                cerns often work under close observa-
             global trust in news has fallen to                            tion. Their work sometimes attracts in-
             40%. The reasons vary, from po-  But trust isn’t lost forever, it’s just   tense public debate or misunderstanding
             litical polarization and sensa-  fractured. And repairing it requires hu-  about intent. Yet, such moments also
             tional headlines to the overwhel-  mility.                    highlight journalism’s essential role,  to
             ming flood of online            It means acknowledging mistakes   ask questions that matter, encourage dia-
             misinformation. But trust can be   publicly. It means admitting when cov-  logue, and ensure that diverse perspec-
             rebuilt. Transparent sourcing,   erage has been uneven, or when stories   tives are heard in a democracy.
             corrections and community en-  have catered more to clicks than clarity.   As one senior reporter in Delhi told
             gagement are slowly redefining   It means going back to what journalism   me, “We’re not enemies of the state;
             the profession’s credibility. Jour-  was meant to be: not a product, but a   we’re enemies of silence.”
             nalism’s revival won’t come from   public service.               That line lingers. Because silence, in
             algorithms, it’ll come from hon-                              many ways, is the real danger, the quiet
             esty, humility and showing that   Misinformation: The invisible   when no one dares to speak truth to
             truth, however complicated, still   enemy                     power.
             matters.                        In the information age, lies travel
                                           faster than light. A rumor born in a pri-  The digital paradox
                                           vate chat group can ripple across con-  Technology was supposed to democ-
             For many, journalists aren’t watch-  tinents before dawn. Deepfakes blur the   ratize journalism. It did, to an extent.
           dogs, they’re “agenda-pushers.” This   line between what’s seen and what’s   Anyone with a smartphone can now
           erosion of trust didn’t happen overnight.   real. And algorithms, designed to keep   record injustice, report local news, or
           Years of sensationalism, corporate in-  us scrolling, feed us what we want to   share their truth. Citizen journalism has
           fluence and political bias have left scars.   believe, not what we need to know.   exposed police brutality, corruption and
           When every outlet claims to be the voice   In 2019, journalists at The Washing-  corporate malfeasance the world over.
           of truth, people stop believing anyone.   ton Post uncovered how misinformation   But democratization also brought
             The 2024 Reuters Institute Digital   campaigns in Brazil, India and the Phil-  fragmentation. The same tools that am-
           News Report found that only 40% of   ippines were coordinated through pri-  plify truth also amplify hate. The same
           people globally say they trust most news   vate networks, often funded by political   platforms that unite voices also divide
           most of the time.               groups. These weren’t amateur trolls,   audiences into echo chambers.
             In the U.S., it’s lower still. In India,   they were professional operations   Traditional news outlets have strug-
           news consumers increasingly rely on so-  weaponizing emotion and identity.   gled to adapt. Many now chase viral
           cial media influencers for political up-  For journalists, this creates a nearly   trends to stay relevant. Others have dou-
           dates. The irony? Many of those in-  impossible task: to chase truth in a race   bled down on investigative depth, hop-
           fluencers borrow their credibility from   where the other runners cheat. By the   ing that substance will outlast noise.
           the very journalists they ridicule.   time fact-checkers debunk a false   Somewhere in between lies the future of

           6                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[“
           journalism, one that’s fast enough for                          consistency.

           the digital age but grounded enough not                            Journalists are not saints or saviors,
           to lose its soul.                 When truth                    they’re human beings navigating impos-
                                                                           sible expectations. They get things
           Courage in the crossfire                                        wrong, they learn, they try again. In that
             Behind every headline is a human   trembles, journalism       persistence lies their strength.
           being, someone who makes calls that                                The next generation of journalists
           could change lives or cost them. In   steadies it”              won’t just need writing skills or investi-
           countries like Afghanistan or Myanmar,                          gative instincts. They’ll need digital lit-
           journalists risk death just for reporting.                      eracy, mental resilience and above all,
           In the U.S., they’re vilified as “enemies   journalist’s task isn’t to make everyone   moral clarity. Because in a world where
           of the people.” In Europe, some live   happy, it’s to make sure no one can say,   truth itself feels negotiable, integrity be-
           under police protection due to extremist   “We didn’t know.”    comes the last anchor.
           threats.
             According to Reporters Without Bor-  The quiet revolution: Solutions   A personal reflection
           ders, over 530 journalists were impris-  journalism                Maybe the real question isn’t what’s
           oned worldwide in 2024. More than 60   Amid all the noise, a new movement   wrong with journalism, but what
           were killed while doing their jobs. These   is gaining ground: solutions journalism.   happens without it?
           aren’t just statistics, they’re stories that   Instead of only exposing problems, it   Without reporters in war zones, how
           never got finished.             highlights credible responses, stories of   would we know the cost of conflict?
             Yet, there’s something quietly heroic   resilience, reform and recovery. It’s not   Without whistleblowers and editors,
           about their persistence. Even in dark   sugar-coating; it’s balance.   how would corruption ever come to
           times, journalists keep showing up, with   For example, rather than just report-  light?
           notebooks, cameras and conviction.   ing on misinformation, The Guardian’s   Without local journalists covering
           They bear witness, so the rest of us can   “Banned Books” series explored how   small towns, who would speak for the
           remember.                       communities are defending access to lit-  unheard?
                                           erature. Or IndiaSpend, which pairs data   When truth trembles, journalism
           The ethics of empathy           with human stories to show how policies   steadies it. And even if people don’t al-
             One of the most difficult questions   actually affect daily life.   ways trust the messenger, the message
           modern journalists face isn’t “Is it true?”   This approach reminds readers that   still matters.
           but “Is it fair?”               journalism isn’t just about crisis, it’s   In the end, the journalist’s role isn’t
             When covering polarized societies,   also about continuity. It rebuilds the one   just to inform, it’s to remind the world
           every word can inflame. Every omission   thing the profession needs most: hope.   that truth, however fragile, is worth
           can be interpreted as bias. Empathy,                            fighting for. Not because it’s easy. But
           therefore, becomes an ethical tool.   Redefining the journalist’s mission   because without it, everything else falls
             When a reporter steps into a refugee   So, what does it mean to be a jour-  apart. ■
           camp, or a flood-hit village, or a court-  nalist in a divided world?
           room filled with grief, their job isn’t   It means accepting that truth will al-
           only to inform, it’s to understand. Not to   ways be contested, but defending it any-
           take sides, but to see sides.   way.                                   When facts
             As Christiane Amanpour once said,   It means resisting cynicism, even
           “We’re not neutral between truth and   when the audience stops believing.     become targets
           falsehood.” Objectivity doesn’t mean   It means remembering that credibility
           detachment; it means discipline. The   isn’t granted by clicks, but earned by   Telling the truth has never
                                                                              been riskier. In 2024 alone, more
                                                                              than 530 journalists were jailed
                                                                              and 60 lost their lives doing their
                                                                              jobs. From Mexico to Myanmar,
                                                                              from Gaza to Moscow, the act of
                                                                              reporting has become an act of
                                                                              defiance. Many continue under
                                                                              pseudonyms, encrypted net-
                                                                              works, or exile, driven by one
                                                                              conviction: stories must be told.
                                                                              Their courage reminds us that
                                                                              journalism isn’t just about pub-
                                                                              lishing information, it’s about
                                                                              protecting the public’s right to
                                                                              know. In an age when disinfor-
                                                                              mation thrives, these truth-tellers
                                                                              remain the last line of defense be-
                                                                              tween democracy and darkness.


           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY







































                                                    Strength Reimagined
                  hen we think of strength,
                  what comes to mind? For
           Wcenturies, it’s been about bi-
           ceps, battlefields and the ability to “take
           it like a man.” But somewhere between   Why smarter
           the boardrooms and the kitchen tables of
           the 21st century, a quiet revolution
           began. Strength, once measured in
           power, dominance and endurance, is
           being redefined. Today, it’s about emo-
           tional resilience, empathy, adaptability           is the new
           and the courage to unlearn old notions
           of manhood.

           In short, smarter is the new
           stronger.
             The shift from muscle to mind                          stronger
             Not long ago, the “ideal man” was
           the stoic provider, tough, silent and de-
           pendable. He fixed the broken chair,
           never the broken conversation. But that
           image doesn’t hold up anymore. In   Real strength has less to do with muscles and more to do with
           workplaces and homes alike, men are
           learning that strength without sensitivity   how you handle what life throws at you. By Naina Kapoor
           is incomplete and often counterproduc-
           tive.
             Technology has changed the playing   empathy. They listen more than they   emotions and those of others, who can
           field. Emotional intelligence has re-  speak. They guide teams not with fear,   admit mistakes and learn from them,
           placed brute force as the most valuable   but with trust.       that’s a man truly in control.
           tool for leadership. Think of Sundar Pi-  It’s not that physical strength has lost
           chai, Satya Nadella, or Ratan Tata,   its value; it’s just no longer the defining   Breaking the mold: The emotional
           leaders who inspire not through intimi-  measure of a man. A man who can stay   evolution
           dation, but through quiet confidence and   calm during chaos, who can manage his   For decades, boys were told not to

           8                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[“



            Strength today isn’t

            about how much

            weight a man can
            lift, it’s about how

            much truth he can

            carry without
            breaking.”



           cry. Vulnerability was seen as weakness.
           But today, that emotional lockdown is
           being challenged.
             Psychologists call it “emotional lit-
           eracy”, the ability to recognize, under-  through humor and humanity.
           stand and express one’s feelings. Men   Modern workplaces now reward
           who cultivate it are not just better part-  those who combine intellect with emo-
           ners and fathers; they’re also better pro-  tional intelligence. The smartest leaders     The rise of emotional
           fessionals. Research shows that teams   know that collaboration beats competi-
           led by empathetic managers perform   tion. The strongest teams are built on in-    intelligence
           significantly better and experience less   clusion, respect and shared purpose.
           burnout.                                                             In a world where collaboration
             In India, this shift is slowly but   Compassion as a superpower   outshines competition, emotional
           surely taking root. Campaigns encourag-  One of the most profound shifts in   intelligence has become the cor-
           ing men to speak about mental health,   redefining strength is the embrace of   nerstone of success. Studies show
           once taboo, are finding resonance. Bol-  compassion. Once dismissed as a “soft   leaders with high EQ foster more
           lywood, too, is part of the conversation.   skill,” empathy has emerged as the   productive teams, lower stress
           Movies like Chhichhore and Dear Zin-  backbone of effective leadership and   and greater loyalty. For men, this
           dagi have portrayed men struggling,   healthy relationships.       means shifting from dominance
           breaking down and rebuilding, without   Men are learning that strength   to dialogue, listening, under-
           shame. These stories help normalize   doesn’t mean standing alone, it means   standing and adapting. The abil-
           what has always been human: imperfec-  standing with others. Being the one who   ity to read a room, empathize
           tion.                           comforts, who forgives, who asks, “Are   with others and manage one’s
             When Virat Kohli spoke publicly   you okay?”, that’s real courage.   emotions now defines real
           about his mental health struggles, it was-  In rural India, grassroots movements   strength. It’s no longer about
           n’t a sign of weakness; it was a reminder   led by men are promoting gender equal-  being the loudest in the meeting,
           that even champions need care. That’s   ity and mental health awareness. These   but the calmest when things fall
           strength reimagined: acknowledging that   are not men seeking headlines; they’re   apart. Emotional intelligence isn’t
           you can’t pour from an empty cup.   men rebuilding communities with com-  just a skill, it’s the new measure
                                           passion. In their quiet persistence lies a   of leadership and men who em-
           Brains over brawn: The power of   new form of heroism.             brace it are redefining what it
           innovation                        Think of the teacher who stays after   means to be strong.
             In an economy driven by ideas, inno-  class to talk to a struggling student, or
           vation has become the new weightlift-  the father, who takes paternity leave
           ing. The men who thrive aren’t those   without shame, or the manager who   are still less likely to seek therapy or
           who work the longest hours but those   listens when an employee says, “I’m not   talk about depression. The numbers are
           who think differently, who can adapt,   okay.” These everyday acts redefine   grim, globally, men are more likely to
           question and collaborate.       masculinity, not as dominance but as   die by suicide than women, often be-
             Take Elon Musk, for instance, often   dignity.                cause they suffer in silence.
           controversial, yet undeniably emblem-                              But the tide is turning. Across urban
           atic of this new strength. His success   The silent battle: Mental health   India, therapy is slowly losing its taboo.
           isn’t powered by muscle but by audacity   and masculinity       Men are showing up in counseling ses-
           and intellect. Or consider Anand Mahin-  Despite all progress, the stigma   sions, joining online support groups and
           dra, who uses social media not to assert   around men’s emotional health remains   even starting podcasts about their heal-
           power, but to connect with people   one of society’s biggest blind spots. Men   ing journeys.

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[“                               India’s changing




                                             Real men don’t
                                                                                    definition of
                                             suppress emotion;
                                                                                  masculinity
                                             they master it.
                                                                                Across India, the image of the
                                             Vulnerability isn’t              “ideal man” is evolving. From
                                                                              classrooms to boardrooms, men
                                             weakness, it’s                   are being encouraged to express
                                                                              emotions, seek mental health help
                                             wisdom in disguise.”             and share family responsibilities.
                                                                              Campaigns like Men Engage and
                                                                              public figures like Virat Kohli
                                           From Competition to Connection     speaking about mental health
                                             There’s another subtle but significant   have helped break old stereo-
                                           shift happening: from competition to   types. The urban Indian man
                                           connection. Earlier, success meant out-  today values empathy as much as
                                           pacing others. Today, it means growing   ambition. He isn’t afraid to cook,
                                           together.                          care, or cry. This quiet transfor-
                                             Men’s support groups, both online   mation is reshaping workplaces
                                           and offline are creating safe spaces to   and homes alike, proving that
                                           talk about vulnerability, career pressures   compassion, not control, builds
             One Mumbai-based therapist shared   and fatherhood. It’s no longer embarras-  stronger relationships. The new
           how her male clients often say, “This is   sing to say, “I’m struggling.”   masculinity isn’t about being per-
           the first time I’ve talked about this.”   In workplaces, mentorship programs   fect; it’s about being human, bal-
           Imagine the courage it takes to say that   are encouraging male leaders to guide   anced and emotionally
           out loud after years of pretending every-  younger employees with compassion   aware.means to be strong.
           thing’s fine.                   rather than control. The idea is no
             The world needs to stop treating   longer to “command respect,” but to
           emotional openness as a liability in men.   earn it, through authenticity and under-  endurance to speak up when silence is
           Because when men heal, so do families,   standing.              easier. The endurance to keep learning,
           workplaces and societies.         This evolution doesn’t make men   unlearning and evolving.
                                           weaker; it makes them more complete.   A man who admits he doesn’t have
           Redefining role models                                          all the answers is not weak; he’s wise.
             Our cultural heroes are changing.   India’s cultural balancing act   As one Indian entrepreneur put it, “I
           From soldiers and athletes to scientists,   In India, tradition and modernity   used to think leadership meant having all
           teachers and fathers, men who embody   often collide. The challenge for Indian   the solutions. Now I know it means hav-
           empathy and ethics are gaining admira-  men is unique: to balance inherited ex-  ing the right conversations.” That’s
           tion.                           pectations with new realities. Many still   where the future lies, not in dominance,
             Take Dr. Devi Shetty, the heart sur-  face pressure to be the primary earners,   but dialogue.
           geon known not just for his medical ge-  the family’s emotional anchor and the
           nius but his humanity, performing thou-  unbreakable one. Yet, the urban Indian   A reflection: Smarter, softer and
           sands of free surgeries for children who   man is learning to share the load, finan-  stronger
           can’t afford them. Or Abhinav Bindra,   cially, emotionally and socially.   If strength once meant standing alone,
           India’s Olympic gold medallist, who   Initiatives like “Men Engage” and   now it means standing together.
           speaks about the mental grind behind   “The Better Man” workshops are help-  Every man, whether a father teaching
           performance.                    ing men question stereotypes, embrace   his son to respect feelings, a manager
             These aren’t men detached from   gender equality and build healthier rela-  promoting mental well-being, or a friend
           emotion; they’re men powered by it.   tionships. Schools, too, are starting to   checking in after a hard week, is part of
             Even at home, the definition of a   teach emotional education, ensuring that   this quiet transformation.
           “real man” is expanding. A man who   the next generation doesn’t inherit out-  The world doesn’t need men who
           cooks, cleans, or takes care of his chil-  dated ideas about masculinity.   never fall. It needs men who rise differ-
           dren isn’t helping, he’s simply being an   Change is gradual, yes, but it’s vis-  ently, not with fists, but with understand-
           equal partner. The pandemic, in a   ible. And that’s what matters.   ing; not by overpowering, but by uplift-
           strange way, accelerated this realization.                      ing.
           As households blurred work and life,   The courage to be human     Because true strength isn’t about how
           many men discovered that care work re-  Maybe strength has never really been   hard you hit, it’s about how deeply you
           quires patience, organization and emo-  about power, it’s always been about en-  care.
           tional strength, qualities every leader   durance, just in different forms. The en-  And in that simple, profound shift, hu-
           needs.                          durance to be kind in a cruel world. The   manity finds its smarter, stronger self. ■

           10                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[INSIGHT
































           Street Philosophy                                               filled with Greek symbols. But in truth,
                                                                           philosophy doesn’t always wear spec-
                                                                           tacles or sit behind a university desk. It’s
                                                                           right there in a tea stall conversation, in a
           Thinking                                                        barber’s advice about patience.
                                                                           farmer’s observation of the seasons, in a


                                                                           This is street philosophy, thinking
                                                                           outside the academy.
                                                                              The philosophers without titles
           outside the                                                     you’ll find them: the auto driver who
                                                                              Walk through any Indian market and
                                                                           talks about karma while negotiating a
                                                                           fare, the chaiwala discussing fairness in
                                                                           cricket selection, the grandmother ex-
                                                                           plaining fate to her grandchildren.
           academy                                                         tialism” or “epistemology,” but they
                                                                              They don’t use words like “existen-
                                                                           wrestle with the same questions: What’s
                                                                           right? What’s real? What’s worth living
                                                                           for?
                                                                              Take, for instance, the village farmer.
           Philosophy isn’t an academic subject. It’s a human instinct. It   His day begins before sunrise. He looks
                                                                           at the sky, studies the soil, reads signs
           happens wherever people dare to wonder. By Rajeev Khanna        nature has left him. In those quiet mo-
                                                                           ments, he’s doing more than agricultural
                                                                           work, he’s thinking about cause and ef-
             A rickshaw driver once said that to   what they want?”        fect, about human dependence on forces
           me on a hot afternoon in Delhi, while   It wasn’t just small talk. It was phi-  beyond control. He’s reflecting on pa-
           we were stuck in traffic. He wasn’t jok-  losophy, raw, unpolished and born out of   tience, cycles, impermanence. Isn’t that
           ing. “Every day,” he continued, “I see   the noise of the streets rather than the   what philosophers call metaphysics?
           people running, shouting, honking, rush-  quiet of classrooms.     Or the barber who listens to dozens of
           ing somewhere. I keep wondering:   We often imagine philosophy as   stories every day, about heartbreak,
           where are they all going? And why do   something belonging to old men in   money, dreams. He develops a sense of
           they look so unhappy if they’re getting   robes, or to professors lost in books   human nature sharper than the blade he

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[The chai stall as


                  a classroom


                Under the tin shade of a chai
             stall, philosophy flows with every
             cup. The discussions here are
             never framed in theories, yet they
             tackle the same questions: fair-
             ness, destiny, success and failure.
             A rickshaw driver might analyze
             politics; a college student might
             question love. Everyone contrib-
             utes and no one grades. These
             conversations are democratic,                                 that too. You just learn how to manage
             spontaneous and brutally honest.                              them.”

             They remind us that thinking    “                                It’s not a grand philosophical state-
             deeply isn’t reserved for scholars,                           ment, but it carries the essence of sto-
             it’s a birthright of every curious   Philosophy isn’t         icism, the art of endurance.
             mind. In many ways, the tea stall                                Similarly, tea stalls across India are
             is India’s version of Plato’s   always written, it’s          miniature universities. Regular cus-
             agora, where ideas brew as easily                             tomers debate everything from democ-
             as tea and understanding is     spoken, argued,               racy to destiny. No one wins, no one
             served without sugarcoating.                                  publishes a paper, but everyone leaves
                                             laughed over and              with a slightly clearer mind.
                                                                              These are spaces where thought is
           holds. He knows when a man’s silence   lived. Sometimes the     democratic. You don’t need credentials
           hides pain, or when laughter is just a                          to contribute. Just curiosity, and perhaps
           mask. Over time, he learns something   deepest thoughts         a few rupees for chai.
           about empathy, ego and truth that no
           textbook could teach.             come from the man             When the ordinary becomes
             Street philosophy isn’t about quoting                         profound
           Plato or debating Kant. It’s about the   pouring your tea, not     Street philosophy thrives on simplic-
           wisdom that arises naturally from ex-                           ity. It often hides behind jokes, meta-
           perience. It’s philosophy lived, not just   the man with a PhD.”  phors, or everyday wisdom.
           studied.                                                           A Mumbai taxi driver once said,
                                                                           “People think they’re steering their
           Why philosophy escaped the      sharpens logic, preserves intellectual   lives. But sometimes, it’s the road that
           classroom                       heritage, but it’s not the whole picture.   decides.” He laughed after saying it, but
             The trouble with academic philoso-  The street adds something raw, some-  it was a perfect summary of determin-
           phy is that it sometimes builds walls   thing urgent. It keeps thinking alive and   ism versus free will, the same debate
           around questions that belong to every-  connected to daily struggle.   that’s filled philosophy books for cen-
           one. There’s a kind of gatekeeping that   Because let’s face it, when your rent   turies.
           happens in universities, the use of spe-  is due, when you’ve lost a job, when   An old vegetable seller in Pune once
           cialized language, footnotes, frame-  you’re deciding whether to forgive   told her young helper, “Don’t be angry
           works, that can make thinking feel like   someone, that’s when philosophy be-  when customers bargain. They’re not
           an elite sport.                 comes real.                     devaluing you, they’re valuing their
             Yet, if we look back, philosophy was                          limits.” That’s moral psychology,
           never meant to be confined. Socrates   The barber’s chair and the tea stall   wrapped in humility.
           talked to shoemakers and merchants.   Spend ten minutes in an Indian   And then there’s the watchman who
           The Buddha spoke under trees, not in   barber shop and you’ll overhear a full-  guards an apartment building at night.
           temples. Kabir sang his philosophy in   fledged symposium. There’s usually a   “Everyone’s afraid of darkness,” he said,
           the lanes of Varanasi, not from a pulpit.   discussion about politics, cricket, infla-  “but without it, no one would notice the
             In modern times, the conversations   tion, or marriage. But underneath all the   stars.”
           just changed form. You’ll find philoso-  noise, there’s reasoning, moral judg-  You can find entire schools of
           phy in memes, rap lyrics, protest slo-  ment, social critique.   thought, existentialism, humanism, sto-
           gans, or even a long chat between   “Life is like hair,” a barber in Luck-  icism, embedded in such lines. The dif-
           friends on a night train. It’s everywhere   now once told me while trimming a cus-  ference is that here, ideas are lived be-
           people try to make sense of life.   tomer’s beard. “You keep cutting it, but   fore they’re spoken.
             Academic philosophy is necessary, it   it always grows back. Problems are like

           12                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Wisdom on


                                                                                  wheels


                                                                                Taxi drivers, bus conductors
                                                                              and delivery riders are philos-
                                                                              ophers of motion. They witness
                                                                              life unfolding in real time, am-
                                                                              bition, chaos, loneliness, laughter,
                                                                              all within a single shift. One
                                                                              Mumbai cabbie once said, “The
                                                                              city teaches you patience. Even
                                                                              the red light has its purpose.” It’s
                                                                              simple but profound. Street phi-
                                                                              losophers don’t analyze theories
                                                                              of time; they live them in traffic.
                                                                              Their reflections are shaped by
                                                                              observation, not abstraction. Each

           Indian streets: A classroom of                                     ride becomes a study in human
                                                                              behavior, each conversation a re-

           contradictions                    “                                minder that knowledge isn’t al-
             India, perhaps more than most                                    ways taught, it’s caught, in mo-
           places, is built for philosophical reflec-  You don’t need a       tion, between miles, silences and
           tion. You can’t walk a hundred meters                              the soft hum of the road.
           without seeing contrasts that make you   degree to ask a deep
           think.
             A luxury car passes a child selling   question.”              ideas between people trying to make
           flowers. A temple bell rings beside a                           sense of living.
           honking bus. A beggar blesses a busi-                              The world may call it small talk,
           nessman.                        liness on Instagram is exploring existen-  but hidden in it is a kind of collective
             The Indian street constantly asks si-  tialism in her own way.   reflection. A shared curiosity about
           lent questions: What is justice? What is   Sure, not every online conversation is   how to live better, think kinder, love
           fate? What does progress mean?   profound. But the instinct, to question,   deeper.
             Our mythology too has always   to connect, to search for meaning, re-  When a chaiwala says, “Sab theek
           blurred the line between divine wisdom   mains the same. Street philosophy has   ho jayega” (Everything will be fine),
           and common sense. Lord Krishna’s   simply gone digital.         he’s not quoting Aristotle, but he’s ex-
           teachings in the Bhagavad Gita didn’t                           pressing faith in the resilience of life,
           happen in a classroom, they happened   Why we need street philosophers   the same kind that philosophy has tried
           on a battlefield. The Buddha’s awaken-  Street philosophy reminds us that   to define for centuries.
           ing began when he stepped outside the   wisdom doesn’t need to be certified.
           palace and saw suffering.       It’s democratic and inclusive. It be-  thinking beyond walls
             In that sense, India’s spiritual her-  longs to the people who live the ques-  Maybe philosophy doesn’t belong
           itage already values “thinking outside   tions, not just those who study them.   only in libraries or lecture halls. Maybe
           the academy.” The streets are alive with   It also keeps philosophy humble.   it also belongs on bus rides, in corner
           questions that philosophers have been   When abstract ideas meet real life, they   shops and on crowded pavements. Be-
           asking for millennia.           become more compassionate. It’s one   cause that’s where most of us live our
                                           thing to discuss justice in theory and   questions, and sometimes, our answers
           Philosophy in the age of        another to hear a daily-wage worker   too.
           smartphones                     talk about what fairness means to him.   Next time you’re waiting for your
             Today, philosophy has found new   Academia often asks, “What is   cab or sipping tea by the roadside,
           streets, digital ones. Social media plat-  truth?” The street asks, “Can I afford   listen carefully. The conversations
           forms, podcasts and comment sections   to tell the truth?” Both are valid, but   around you might not sound “intellec-
           are the new tea stalls. Some of the best   only together do they form the full pic-  tual,” but they might just hold the truth
           modern thinkers aren’t professors but   ture of human thought.   you’ve been searching for.
           comedians, vloggers, or even meme-                                 Philosophy isn’t an academic sub-
           makers.                         The conversation that never ends   ject. It’s a human instinct. It happens
             A stand-up comic wondering why   Maybe that’s the best thing about   wherever people dare to wonder.
           humans worship success but fear failure   street philosophy, it never concludes.   And the street, noisy and unpredict-
           is doing moral philosophy. A teenager   There’s no final answer, no published   able as it is, might just be the most
           posting a thoughtful caption about lone-  thesis, just a continuous exchange of   honest classroom of them all. ■

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT



































           The Power of Hello



           5 letters that can





           change the world                                                building her town didn’t start with lay-
                                                                           ing bricks, it started when neighbors
                                                                           who hadn’t spoken in years finally said
                                                                           hello again. The moment they greeted
                                                                           each other, the ice cracked. Walls began
                                                                           to fall, slowly but surely.
           There’s an old proverb that says, “Peace begins with a
                                                                           A word that travels without a visa
           smile.” Maybe it also begins with a hello. By Riya Verma           Hello has no nationality. It’s been
                                                                           translated into hundreds of languages,
                                                                           hola, bonjour, namaste, konnichiwa,
                                                                           jambo, but its heartbeat remains the
                 ello, it’s one of the first words   The world’s smallest bridge   same. It doesn’t care about your reli-
                 we learn as children and one of   At its core, “hello” is a bridge. It’s a   gion, accent, or skin color. It’s one of
           Hthe easiest to forget as adults.   tiny step toward another person, cross-  those rare words that belong to every-
             Think about it, when was the last   ing over walls of silence, suspicion, or   one.
           time you really said hello? Not the   difference. Whether spoken between   That’s why diplomats often open
           quick, distracted “hey” tossed at a col-  strangers on a train or exchanged across   tense negotiations with a smile and a
           league while scrolling through your   a video call between two nations, it   greeting. It’s not just etiquette, it’s
           phone, but a genuine greeting meant to   carries the same essence: recognition.   strategy. Psychologists say a friendly
           connect, not just to acknowledge? In an   There’s something disarming about   greeting activates what’s called the “rec-
           age where conversations have been re-  it. A greeting says, I see you. And being   iprocity principle.” When someone
           placed by notifications and smiles by   seen, truly seen, is something every   greets us kindly, our brain is wired to re-
           emojis, those five letters and two silent   human being longs for.   turn that warmth. It’s the simplest form
           gestures behind them, carry more power   In post-war Bosnia, an elderly   of peacekeeping.
           than we might think.            teacher once told a journalist that re-  Even on the digital front, where tone

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[The science

                                                                                  behind a greeting

                                                                                When you greet someone,
                                                                              something magical, and biolog-
                                                                              ical, happens. Neuroscientists say
                                                                              even brief social contact releases
                                                                              oxytocin, the brain’s “bonding
                                                                              chemical.” It reduces stress,
                                                                              sharpens empathy and builds
                                                                              trust. That’s why a friendly hello
                                                                              can instantly lift moods and make
                                                                              people feel safe. Small talk may
                                                                              seem trivial, but it’s one of hu-
                                                                              manity’s oldest emotional sur-
                                                                              vival tools. In a disconnected
                                                                              world, a simple greeting doesn’t
                                                                              just open conversation; it heals,
                                                                              calms and reconnects us to the
                                                                              shared rhythm of being human.



                                                                           Hello across divides
                                                                              When Martin Luther King Jr. spoke
                                                                           about building “the beloved com-
                                                                           munity,” he imagined a world where
                                                                           people didn’t just tolerate each other,
                                                                           they reached out. A simple hello is often
                                                                           that reach.
                                                                              In 2019, an initiative in Northern Ire-
                                                                           land encouraged people to greet
                                                                           strangers in divided communities. The
                                                                           campaign, called Hello Peace, saw Cath-
            “                              The lost art of small gestures   olics and Protestants exchange greetings
                                                                           on streets once marked by violence. Or-
                                             Let’s be honest, we live in a world of

                                                                           ganizers said that while the project
                                           hurry. Doors close faster than we can
                                           hold them, screens glow brighter than
                                                                           didn’t solve decades of conflict, it “soft-
            A hello rarely stops
                                           the eyes in front of us. Somewhere be-
                                                                           reconciliation often begins not with big
                                           tween airport lounges and virtual meet-  ened the air.” It reminded people that
            where it starts. It’s a        ings, we’ve started treating greetings as   speeches, but with small hellos.
                                           optional.                          Even online, where hostility often
            ripple that travels              But think of the last time a stranger’s   spreads faster than kindness, a genuine
                                           smile lifted your mood, or a friendly   greeting can reset the tone. It’s remark-
            from one heart to              “hello” broke your morning monotony.   able how starting a heated thread with
                                           Those tiny moments have invisible
                                                                           “Hello, I understand your point but…”
            another, quietly               weight. They can change how a day   can open a door that an angry opener
                                                                           would slam shut.
                                           feels and sometimes, how a person sees
                                           themselves.                        The internet has made communica-
            rewriting how the                Research backs this up. A study from   tion faster but not necessarily friendlier.
                                           the University of Chicago found that   A hello, typed, spoken, or even emoji-
            world feels.”                  commuters who interacted with   ed, can reintroduce empathy to a digital
                                           strangers reported higher levels of hap-  space that’s forgotten what it feels like.
                                           piness than those who kept to them-
           and intent are easily misunderstood, a   selves. Even minimal social contact, a   When hello becomes healing
           “hello” at the start of a message can   smile, a nod, a greeting, triggered feel-  There’s a story of a young nurse in
           soften the sharp edges of a conversation.   ings of belonging and well-being.   Japan who started greeting every patient
           It reminds the person on the other end   So, maybe it’s not just about being   with a gentle “Konnichiwa” and a bow,
           that you’re not a faceless user, you’re   polite. Maybe saying hello is a small act   even those too weak to respond. Over
           human.                          of emotional generosity.        time, families noticed something; pa-

           16                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Every hello is an act

                                                                             of hope, a belief that

                                                                             connection still
                                                                             matters, even

                                                                             between strangers.”


                                                                           time you walk into a shop, a lift, or a
                                                                           waiting room, say hello first. Not me-
                                                                           chanically, but with intent. Notice what
                                                                           happens. Most people will respond.
                                                                           Some will be startled. A few won’t reply
                                                                           at all. But you’ll feel a little lighter. Be-
             The hello habit                                               cause even when a hello isn’t returned, it

                                                                           still affirms your humanity.
                                                                              It’s a declaration that you choose
               Want to make your days                                      connection over indifference.
             warmer? Try the “hello habit.”
             Each morning, make it a point to                              A word worth saving
             greet five people, anyone from                                   In some cultures, greeting is a ritual.
             your bus driver to your barista.                              In parts of Africa, the Swahili “Jambo”
             Notice their reactions and your                               isn’t just a hello; it’s a conversation
             own. Over time, this small ritual                             starter that can unfold into deep sharing.
             can rewire your mood and con-                                 In India, “Namaste” translates to “I bow
             fidence. It reminds you that kind-                            to the divine in you,” a greeting that rec-
             ness doesn’t always need grand                                ognizes equality and respect.
             gestures; sometimes, it’s a word,                                But in urban life, especially in digital
             a glance, a smile. The more you                               ones, the greeting is fading. We reply to
             share it, the more it circles back.                           texts without opening with a hello. We
             Because in the quiet power of   biology. You’re creating a mini moment   email without a salutation. The word is
             hello, we rediscover what it   of emotional safety, the kind that makes   slipping out of habit and maybe out of
             means to belong.              communities thrive.             heart.
                                             It’s fascinating how something as   Perhaps that’s why we need to re-
                                           lightweight as a greeting can carry so   claim it. Because every hello is an act of
           tients began reacting, smiling faintly,   much chemical, psychological and so-  hope, a belief that there’s still room in
           even before medical improvements were   cial impact. Yet, it costs nothing.   the world for connection, even between
           visible. The hospital later made it a pol-                      strangers.
           icy: greet first, treat later.   The echo effect
             That’s the unseen power of a word   A hello rarely stops where it starts.   The final word
           like hello; it can reach places medicine   Say hello to one person and they’re   There’s an old proverb that says,
           can’t. It acknowledges the person before   more likely to greet the next. It’s the   “Peace begins with a smile.” Maybe it
           the problem.                    human equivalent of a ripple effect.   also begins with a hello.
             The same applies in mental health.   In one school in Mumbai, teachers   The world is noisy and divided, yes,
           For someone struggling silently, a sim-  began each morning by greeting every   but it’s also full of people who want to
           ple “hello” can be the first thread of   student at the gate. Within weeks, stu-  be acknowledged. You don’t need to
           connection. It’s not a solution, but it’s a   dents were greeting each other in the   start a movement or write a manifesto to
           signal: You’re not invisible.   corridors, even at home. Parents noticed   make a difference. Sometimes, you just
                                           the shift, less aggression, more open-  need to start a conversation.
           The science of connection       ness. One small word had changed the   So, go ahead, say hello. To the col-
             Neuroscience tells us that humans are   culture of an entire community.   league you usually ignore. To the guard
           wired for social connection. When we   And that’s the quiet revolution of   outside your office. To your neighbor in
           interact, even briefly, our brains release   “hello.” It doesn’t need campaigns or   the lift.
           oxytocin, often called the “bonding hor-  slogans. It just needs repetition.   It won’t change the entire world in an
           mone.” It reduces stress and builds trust.                      instant. But for a fleeting moment, it
             So when you greet someone, you’re   The hello test            might change someone’s world. And
           not just being polite, you’re triggering   Here’s a small experiment. The next   that’s where every real change begins. ■

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Television


     IN FOCUS  When the world









           watched together







           Television’s magic was never about the technology. It was about the moments it created,

           moments when time paused and humanity leaned forward together. By Rohan Kapoor


               or a moment, the whole world   led through: “That’s one small step for   war years of the 1950s and 60s, TV sets
               held its breath. That’s how one re-  man, one giant leap for mankind.”   became modern hearths. Families ar-
           Fporter described July 20, 1969,   It wasn’t just a landing on the moon.   ranged furniture around them. Dinner
           the night humans first walked on the   It was the night the world watched to-  was postponed for the evening news.
           moon. More than 600 million people   gether.                    Broadcasters didn’t just air programs;
           watched it live, their eyes fixed on the                        they orchestrated shared experiences.
           same flickering glow in living rooms,   The box that connected the planet   It’s hard to imagine now, but there
           school halls and tiny village shops.   Before smartphones, before endless   was a time when everyone saw the same
           Neighbors huddled close, antennas were   scrolls and short videos, there was the   thing at the same moment. There were
           adjusted by hand and silence filled the   television, a glowing box that somehow   no spoilers, no binge-watching. You did-
           air before Neil Armstrong’s voice crack-  made the world feel smaller. In the post-  n’t just watch TV, you belonged to it.









































           18                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Television didn’t just

                                                                             show the world; it

                                                                             held it, in laughter, in
                                                                             grief, in wonder.”



                                                                           Cup final, TV turned isolated moments
                                                                           into global memories.
                                                                           When love looked Royal
                                                                              Long before hashtags and viral clips,
                                                                           royal weddings set global viewership
                                                                           records. In 1981, an estimated 750 mil-
                                                                           lion people watched Prince Charles
                                                                           marry Lady Diana Spencer, an unimag-
                                                                           inable audience in a pre-internet age.
                                                                           Streets were deserted, cafes emptied and
                                                                           in some countries, cinemas screened the
                                                                           wedding live.
                                                                              When Prince William married Kate
                                                                           Middleton three decades later, technol-
                                                                           ogy had changed, but the feeling hadn’t.
                                                                           Families still gathered. Commentators
                                                                           still whispered about the dress, the
                                                                           vows, the kiss. It was proof that despite
                                                                           all the noise of modern media, the desire
                                                                           to share big human moments together
                                                                           hadn’t faded.
                                                                              Television, in those hours, felt like
                                                                           the world’s living room.
                                           Shared joy, shared grief        The sports that stopped the world
                                             The power of television was never   If politics and tragedy brought
                  When silence spoke       just in pictures or sound, but in its abil-  viewers together in solemn unity, sports
                                           ity to make millions feel the same emo-  did it with thunderous joy.
              louder than words            tion at once. Take the morning of Sep-  The 1966 FIFA World Cup final be-

                                           tember 11, 2001. Around the world,   tween England and West Germany had
                In 1969, nearly every living   people turned on their televisions to   millions glued to black-and-white
             room that had a television turned   scenes of disbelief, towers burning, an-  screens. Four years later, the Mexico
             toward the same sight, the grainy   chors struggling for words, phone lines   Olympics broadcast the image of Tom-
             silhouette of a man stepping onto   collapsing. Newsrooms became life-  mie Smith and John Carlos raising their
             lunar dust. Neil Armstrong’s   lines.                         fists, a silent protest seen around the
             words, “one small step for man,”   Or go back a decade earlier, February   world.
             echoed in classrooms, cafes and   11, 1990. Cameras waited outside Victor   And who can forget the 1983 Cricket
             crowded homes. For a few mi-  Verster Prison in South Africa. And   World Cup? In India, televisions were
             nutes, the Cold War froze, nations   then, after 27 long years, Nelson Man-  rare then, but those who had them
             forgot their rivalries and human-  dela appeared, walking hand in hand   opened doors and windows wide so
             ity looked up, united by awe. Tel-  with Winnie, his fist raised high. It was   neighbors could peer in. Kapil Dev’s
             evision transformed a distant   a walk the world had waited to see and   grin, the trophy held aloft at Lord’s, it
             event into a shared triumph. That   when it finally happened, people cried   wasn’t just a sporting victory; it was the
             night, the world didn’t just watch   on every continent. Television didn’t   sound of a young nation finding its
             the moon, it felt it. The collective   just broadcast an event; it broadcast a re-  voice.
             gasp, the stunned silence after-  birth of hope.                 Television gave sports emotion. It
             ward, that was television’s great-  Television has always been that, a   made heroes from ordinary people. The
             est broadcast: a moment when   mirror and a megaphone. Whether it was   slow-motion replay, the commentator’s
             everyone truly watched together.  the fall of the Berlin Wall, Princess Di-  gasp, the crowd’s roar, all of it stitched
                                           ana’s wedding, or the first live World   together a language everyone under-

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[rural lives to urban homes and inspired
                                                                           empathy that transcended geography.
                                                                              TV wasn’t always perfect. It could
                                                                           distort reality, sensationalize, simplify.
                                                                           But even its flaws reminded viewers that
                                                                           what they saw was only a piece of the
                                                                           truth, not the whole of it.
                                                                              And yet, despite its imperfections,
                                                                           television often did what politics could-
                                                                           n’t: it united.

                                                                           When we stopped watching
                                                                           together
                                                                              Then came the internet. Streaming.
                                             “                             worlds just for us.
                                                                           Personal screens. Algorithms that curate
                                                                              Today, we don’t wait for the 8 p.m.


                  The day hope                                             news, we scroll through headlines. We
                                                                           don’t gather for live broadcasts, we re-
                                             For one night, TV             play clips on demand. There’s freedom
               walked free                   became the                    in that, sure. But something precious has

                                                                           quietly slipped away: the shared heart-
                                             heartbeat of the              beat.
                February 11, 1990. A nation                                   When the finale of Game of Thrones
             waited and the world held its   planet.”                      aired, it was one of the last times mil-
             breath. Nelson Mandela, after 27                              lions tuned in simultaneously, gasping,
             years of imprisonment, stepped                                arguing and feeling together. Now, even
             into the sunlight and into history.                           that’s rare. We live in an age of person-
             Television cameras followed   From Sydney’s fireworks to New York’s   alization, but not always of togetherness.
             every second of that walk, his   Times Square, billions watched the same   Sometimes, don’t you miss the noise
             raised fist radiating quiet   clock tick toward a new century. For one   of the neighborhood when everyone was
             strength. For millions, especially   night, TV became the heartbeat of the   watching the same match?
             those who had never seen him   planet.
             before, it was like watching hope                             A quiet glow in a noisy age
             take human form. That broadcast   The comfort of the familiar    And yet, television hasn’t vanished.
             didn’t just record freedom; it   Not every moment was historic.   It’s just evolved. News anchors still look
             spread it. In townships, cities and   Sometimes, it was just comforting. The   into cameras that beam across con-
             faraway living rooms, tears   nightly news anchor who greeted you   tinents. Families still argue over re-
             flowed, cheers erupted and a sin-  like family. The sitcom theme you could   motes. Sports finals still fill stadiums
             gle image bridged divides. Tele-  hum by heart. The cartoon that marked   and living rooms alike.
             vision, once again, turned an   Sunday mornings.                 What’s changed is our pace, not our
             event into emotion, reminding us   Television taught generations what   need. We still crave stories that make us
             how humanity feels most deeply   community looked like, even when the   feel part of something bigger and televi-
             when it watches together.     “community” was fictional. Shows like   sion, even now, offers that slow, collec-
                                           Friends, The Cosby Show, Ramayan,   tive rhythm in a world of endless scrolls.
                                           Doctor Who, Cheers and Mahabharat
           stood, even when they didn’t share the   weren’t just entertainment; they were   The glow that never really went out
           same tongue.                    rituals.                           Television’s magic was never about
                                             They shaped speech, fashion, humor,   the technology. It was about the mo-
           The moon, the wall and the      even dinner timings. “Come quickly, it’s   ments it created, moments when time
           millennium                      starting!” was the soundtrack of count-  paused and humanity leaned forward to-
             Some broadcasts are burned into col-  less homes. And in that shared routine   gether. From Armstrong’s first step to
           lective memory because they marked the   lay something deeply human: connec-  Mandela’s first walk, from weddings to
           turning of eras.                tion.                           wars, television didn’t just show the
             In 1969, the moon landing gave hu-                            world; it held it.
           manity faith in possibility. Two decades   When the screen became a mirror   Maybe we’ll never go back to that
           later, in 1989, cameras captured people   Television didn’t just show the   kind of collective watching again. But
           hammering away at the Berlin Wall.   world, it shaped how we saw ourselves.   every time a family laughs together at
           Those scenes, laughter, tears, strangers   In the 1960s, American households   the same show, every time strangers in a
           hugging, spread faster than any propa-  watched civil rights protests live. In the   bar cheer for the same goal, that old
           ganda ever could.               1980s, Ethiopian famine broadcasts   glow flickers back to life, quiet, steady,
             Then came December 31, 1999, the   sparked global charity movements like   timeless. Because deep down, we don’t
           world counting down to the year 2000.   Live Aid. In India, Doordarshan brought   just watch to see. We watch to belong. ■

           20                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Code Name Jaguar                                                lieving the animal’s spirit gave them

                                                                           courage and cunning. Across the Ameri-
                                                                           cas, it became a totem of leadership,
                                                                           transformation and control over chaos.   EXPLORATION
           The big cat’s role                                              away, it’s just evolved. Today, we in-
                                                                              That imagery has never really gone
                                                                           voke the jaguar in the same spirit,
                                                                           whether to brand a fighter jet, a football
                                                                           team, or a luxury car.
           in military, media                                              and Beyond
                                                                              Military precision: operation jaguar
                                                                              In military circles, the name “Jaguar”
                                                                           has a legacy that spans decades and con-
                                                                           tinents. It’s a favorite codename because
           & myth                                                          it says everything without saying too
                                                                           much, fast, silent, lethal.
                                                                              During the 1970s, Britain and France
                                                                           jointly developed the SEPECAT Jaguar,
                                                                           a sleek ground-attack aircraft used by
           Whether on a car badge, a mission patch, or a tribal            several air forces, including India’s. The
                                                                           name wasn’t chosen by chance. The air-
           mask, the jaguar continues to prowl through human               craft was designed to strike with accu-
                                                                           racy and vanish, just like its namesake
           imagination, untamed, unowned and unapologetically              in the jungle. Indian Air Force pilots af-
                                                                           fectionately called it the “Shamsher,”
           alive. By Pooja Mehta                                           meaning “sword,” but everyone knew




             n the jungle, the jaguar moves un-
             seen, silent, decisive and powerful.
           IIsn’t that exactly what every army,
           carmaker, or storyteller wants to be? The
           jaguar has always been more than a big
           cat. It’s a presence, half shadow, half
           thunder. From the rainforests of Central
           and South America to the runways of
           airbases and luxury car showrooms,
           “Jaguar” is a name that refuses to stay
           still. It stalks through our myths, our
           machines and even our military code
           names, embodying the timeless blend of
           beauty and danger that humans can’t
           seem to resist.

           The symbolism beneath the spots
             Unlike lions or tigers, which dom-
           inate open landscapes or are easily
           spotted, the jaguar rules where light and
           dark intertwine. It thrives in the thick,
           tangled green of the Amazon, solitary,
           elusive and incredibly strong. That com-
           bination of stealth and precision ex-
           plains why its name has been borrowed
           so often by humans seeking to project
           power without noise.
             In many ancient cultures, the jaguar
           wasn’t just admired, it was worshipped.
           To the Maya, the jaguar was the guard-
           ian of the underworld, able to cross be-
           tween life and death. Aztec warriors
           painted their faces with spots, calling
           themselves ocēlōmeh, jaguar men, be-

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[The aircraft named

                                                                                  after a predator

                                                                                The SEPECAT Jaguar wasn’t
                                                                              just another jet, it was a statement
                                                                              in motion. Born from a British–
                                                                              French collaboration in the
                                                                              1970s, it became known for pre-
                                                                              cision ground attacks and un-
                                                                              matched durability. The Indian
                                                                              Air Force later adopted it, calling
                                                                              it the “Shamsher” or sword. True
                                                                              to its name, the aircraft struck tar-
                                                                              gets with the stealth and power of
                                                                              its feline namesake. Even today,
                                                                              retired pilots speak of it with af-
                                             “                                never roared, it whispered death.”
                                                                              fection, recalling how “the Jaguar
                                                                              A fitting tribute to an animal that

                                                                              commands respect through si-
                                                                              lence, not spectacle.
                                             The jaguar doesn’t
                                             seek attention; it

                                             earns it. That quiet          sustainability becoming the new luxury,
                                                                           the brand still leans on its feline meta-
                                             confidence appeals            phor, “performance with poise.” That
                                                                           balance between wildness and restraint
                                             to every human                might just be the secret to the jaguar’s
                                                                           lasting appeal.
                                             endeavor that wants           The jaguar in sports and pop

                                                                           culture
                                             to be taken                      Beyond the battlefield and the boule-
                                             seriously.”                   vard, the jaguar has prowled into sports
                                                                           arenas and movie screens, where its
                                                                           symbolism morphs again, this time into
                                                                           resilience and pride.
                                           From runway to roadway: The        In American football, the Jackson-
           what its English name implied: stealthy   jaguar on wheels      ville Jaguars embody the spirit of their
           dominance.                        If the military’s jaguar is the symbol   namesake with teal-and-gold swagger.
             Later, militaries from Latin America   of precision, the automobile’s jaguar is   Their logo, teeth bared, eyes locked,
           to Europe reused the moniker for secret   the symbol of grace. When Jaguar Cars   feels almost like a war cry. Yet there’s
           missions and special forces units. “Oper-  was founded in Britain, its founder Sir   more than ferocity here; the jaguar also
           ation Jaguar” has surfaced more than   William Lyons didn’t just want to make   represents adaptation. The team’s rise in
           once in world history, from peacekeep-  vehicles, he wanted to make statements.   a city better known for beaches than sta-
           ing deployments in Africa to covert anti-  The name “Jaguar,” officially adopted in   diums mirrors the cat’s ability to thrive
           terror operations in the Middle East. The   1945, was chosen to capture an identity:   in diverse terrains.
           repetition of that name says something   sleek, elegant, fast, yet unmistakably   Pop culture has done its share to my-
           profound about human psychology. We   British.                  thologize the animal too. From the Mar-
           borrow animal traits to describe our-  The leaping cat on the hood became   vel universe’s Black Panther, which
           selves when we want to believe we’re in   more than a logo, it became a promise.   draws partly from jaguar mythology, to
           control of nature, when we’re not afraid   To drive a Jaguar was to move with style   films set in Latin America where the cat
           to take on its raw instincts.   and quiet authority. Movie characters,   becomes a spiritual messenger, the jag-
             But there’s irony, too. The real jaguar   spies and statesmen were drawn to it be-  uar is often a bridge between the physi-
           doesn’t fight for glory or conquest. It   cause it projected control without noise.   cal and mystical. Even in fashion and
           hunts only when necessary. Its power   Think of the way a Jaguar E-Type purrs   advertising, its spots are shorthand for
           lies in patience, not aggression. Perhaps   rather than roars; its motion feels cal-  exotic allure, a touch of danger wrapped
           that’s a lesson some military strategies   culated, never desperate.   in elegance.
           could learn from the animal they admire.   Even in today’s electric age, with   And of course, it’s found in music,

           22                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             We borrow the

                                                                             jaguar’s name to

                                                                             symbolize
                                                                             endurance, even as

                                                                             we erode the

                                                                             wilderness that
                                                                             gives it meaning.”



                                                                           Why not the tiger or the eagle or the
                                                                           wolf? The answer might lie in the jag-
                                                                           uar’s balance of opposites. It’s neither
                                                                           the largest cat nor the most famous. But
                  The real jaguar’s                                        it’s the most mysterious. It kills with a
                                                                           single bite through the skull, a rare, sur-
             vanishing realm                                               gical efficiency. It can swim, climb and

                                                                           disappear into the foliage. In that sense,
                                                                           the jaguar embodies mastery of one’s
                While the name thrives in                                  environment without the need for spec-
             global brands and battalions, the                             tacle.
             real jaguar’s world is shrinking.                                That quiet confidence appeals to
             From Argentina to Mexico, its                                 every human endeavor that wants to be
             forest corridors are disappearing                             taken seriously, whether an army divi-
             under deforestation, ranching and                             sion, a car company, or a sports fran-
             urban expansion. Conservation-                                chise. The jaguar doesn’t seek attention;
             ists are working to reconnect hab-                            it earns it.
             itats, “jaguar corridors”, allowing                              And maybe that’s what we crave
             these cats to roam and breed    In mythology, the jaguar was never   most in a noisy world: a reminder that
             freely. Countries like Brazil and   just an animal. It was a shapeshifter, a   true power doesn’t have to announce it-
             Belize have shown that protect-  creature that could walk between   self.
             ing jaguars also safeguards rivers,   worlds. Modern branding and warfare,
             trees and countless other species.   in their own way, echo that, crossing   A reflection in the eyes
             Yet awareness remains low. The   boundaries between nature and technol-  A few years ago, a wildlife photogra-
             irony is stark: humanity cele-  ogy, between spirit and steel.   pher captured a rare image deep in the
             brates the jaguar’s spirit while   Yet the real jaguar, the one with mus-  Pantanal, an adult jaguar stepping out of
             endangering its survival. Protect-  cles under spotted gold, is in trouble.   the water, droplets cascading off its
             ing it means protecting a living   Habitat loss, illegal hunting and climate   golden coat. For a second, the animal
             symbol of balance, power and re-  change have squeezed its range across   locked eyes with the camera, not with
             straint.                      the Americas. Conservationists warn   fear but with indifference, as if to say,
                                           that only about 170,000 remain in the   You may name your machines after me,
                                           wild, scattered across 18 countries. They   but you’ll never truly know me.
           artists from Santana to contemporary   roam corridors of survival that grow nar-  That moment sums up everything the
           rappers have invoked the jaguar to sym-  rower each year.       jaguar has come to mean. It’s the mys-
           bolize independence and fire. Like the   And that’s the paradox, while hu-  tery behind our metaphors, the strength
           animal, it refuses to be tamed.   mans borrow its name to symbolize en-  we aspire to, the silence we fail to
                                           durance, we’re steadily eroding the very   master.
           The myth that moves between     wilderness that gives it meaning. The   Whether on a car badge, a mission
           worlds                          jaguar becomes immortal in our meta-  patch, or a tribal mask, the jaguar con-
             Perhaps what makes the jaguar so   phors even as it risks extinction in real-  tinues to prowl through human imagina-
           captivating is that it’s both real and un-  ity.                tion, untamed, unowned and unapologet-
           real. It exists in dense forests, powerful                      ically alive.
           yet vulnerable to deforestation and it ex-  Why we keep naming things after   And maybe that’s its greatest legacy:
           ists in our imagination, as something we   it                   reminding us that some forms of power
           wish to be.                       It’s tempting to ask, why this animal?   can never be manufactured. ■

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH


































           Myth vs Memory




           Tipu in popular





           imagination                                                     claw with the British Empire. To others,
                                                                           he’s a polarizing figure whose memory
                                                                           is tangled in the vines of religion and re-
                                                                           gional pride. Between the roar and the
                                                                           rumour lies something more fragile,
                                                                           more human, memory.
           today                                                           The making of a legend

                                                                              Tipu Sultan’s story has all the ing-
                                                                           redients of legend: a young prince born
                                                                           in 1750, trained in war and governance,
                                                                           who took on one of the world’s most
           It’s easy to forget that Tipu was, above all, a man. A          powerful empires. He modernized his
                                                                           army, experimented with rocketry and
           ruler juggling diplomacy and destiny, faith and                 even corresponded with the French in
                                                                           the hope of building an anti-British co-
           pragmatism. By Siddharth Mehta                                  alition. His end, on May 4, 1799, sword
                                                                           in hand at Srirangapatna, sealed his
                                                                           transformation from man to myth.
                 istory is written by the victors,   you’ll hear whispers of a king who once   But legends don’t stay static. They
                 they say. But what happens   dared to dream of freedom before free-  breathe, shift and change shape depend-
           Hwhen the victors keep chang-   dom itself was a word that meant India.   ing on who’s telling the story. The Brit-
           ing? Walk through the lanes of Mysuru   To some, Tipu Sultan is the Tiger of My-  ish, predictably, cast him as a tyrant, a
           on a humid November morning and   sore, the brave son who stood claw to   fanatic who persecuted Hindus and

           24                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             The tiger has

                                                                             become a

                                                                             Rorschach test.
                                                                             What one person

                                                                             sees as courage,

                                                                             another sees as
                                                                             hubris.”






                 The Tiger’s

                   dream

               Tipu Sultan’s fascination with
             the tiger went beyond royal sym-
             bolism. The tiger was his identity,
             painted on banners, engraved on
             weaponry, even woven into pal-
             ace motifs. His throne was
             shaped like a golden tiger, its
             claws clutching the world, a vi-
             sion of defiant sovereignty. The
             British later carted away these
             emblems as war trophies, dis-
             playing them in museums across   songs, processions and folk plays re-  despot whose defeat was a moral victory
             London. Yet, even in exile, the   counting his battles. Ask an elderly   for civilization. Missionary tracts, colo-
             tiger roared silently from behind   shopkeeper in the Devaraja Market and   nial dispatches and early English his-
             glass cases, a reminder that for   he’ll tell you stories passed down by his   tories hardened this caricature. Even
             Tipu, power wasn’t just political;   grandfather, who spoke of Tipu’s gar-  after independence, those images per-
             it was psychological. He wanted   dens, his canals, his dream of a self-reli-  sisted, especially in the north Indian dis-
             his enemies to feel the tiger long   ant Mysore.              course where Tipu rarely featured in the
             before they faced it.           To them, Tipu isn’t just a historical   nationalist pantheon dominated by
                                           figure; he’s part of the local soil. His   northern heroes.
                                           memory is tied not to ideology, but to   The irony, of course, is that Tipu
                                           identity. He’s the man who fought for   himself saw beyond sectarian lines. His
           Christians. His own people, in turn, saw   this land, and in the collective memory   court included Hindu ministers like Pur-
           him as a martyr of independence. The   of Karnataka, that still matters.   naiya, his army featured men of many
           truth, as it often does, sits somewhere                         faiths and his letters reveal a practical
           uncomfortably in between.       The divider in the north        ruler more interested in politics than
                                             Yet move northward and the tone   proselytism. But myths are sticky things.
           The hero of Mysore              shifts. In parts of coastal Karnataka,   Once formed, they tend to outlive facts.
             In southern Karnataka, particularly in   Kerala and beyond, Tipu’s name evokes
           Mysuru and Mandya, Tipu’s name is   unease. Here, local accounts speak of   The diaspora’s dilemma
           still spoken with pride. Streets, schools   forced conversions and temple destruc-  Among the Indian diaspora, from
           and public squares bear his name. For   tions. Historians still debate how much   London to Toronto to Singapore, Tipu
           many here, he’s not a symbol of division   of this is propaganda and how much is   Sultan occupies a curious space. For
           but of resistance, the ruler who refused   fact, but in public imagination, those   many, especially those tracing roots to
           to kneel.                       memories run deep.              South India, he represents a bold, pre-
             Every year, during the now-contro-  The British were skilled storytellers.   colonial defiance, a local hero who
           versial “Tipu Jayanti,” one can still feel   To justify their conquest, they painted   stood tall in a world about to be remade
           that admiration in the air, garlands,   Tipu as a bloodthirsty zealot, an Oriental   by empire. His story appears in plays,

           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Tipu in modern

                                                                                    memory

                                                                                Today, Tipu Sultan lives as
                                                                              much on screens as in stone. So-
                                                                              cial media debates flare with
                                                                              every mention of his name, his-
                                                                              tory turned hashtag. Plays like
                                                                              The Dreams of Tipu Sultan and
                                                                              period dramas reimagine him for
                                                                              new generations. In classrooms,
             At the same time, some diaspora  “
           murals and even modern novels like Sal-                            he’s a chapter; on television, a
                                                                              controversy; in Mysore, a mem-
           man Rushdie’s The Enchantress of Flor-                             ory woven into everyday life. For
           ence, which reimagines his legend in                               India’s youth, Tipu’s story often
           dreamlike tones.                  Maybe the real                   sparks a broader question: how
                                                                              do we remember the past without
           communities mirror the polarized de-  challenge is to              rewriting it? Between outrage
           bates back home. Social media posts                                and reverence lies something
           about Tipu spark the same online battles   remember Tipu           subtler, the need to listen to his-
           as in India, history memes, selective                              tory, not argue with it.
           quotes, angry threads. The man who   without turning him
           once fought the East India Company
           now seems trapped in a new battlefield,   into a monument or    Remembering without
           the internet.                                                   worshipping
                                             a monster.”                      Maybe the real challenge is to re-
           The politics of memory                                          member Tipu without turning him into a
             In modern India, history often be-                            monument or a monster. To see him not
           comes a mirror for present politics. And   urged him to flee during the final siege,   as a tool of politics, but as a mirror re-
           Tipu’s image, unfortunately, hasn’t es-  he refused, saying, “Better to live one   flecting the contradictions of his age,
           caped that fate. In Karnataka, his legacy   day as a tiger than a thousand years as a   and ours.
           has been alternately celebrated and cen-  sheep.” Whether he truly said it or not, it   History isn’t meant to comfort. It’s
           sured depending on who’s in power.   captures the spirit with which genera-  meant to complicate, to make us pause
           Statues proposed, then stalled. Festivals   tions remember him, proud, defiant,   and think about how we got here. When
           announced, then cancelled.      tragic.                         we remember Tipu today, we’re not just
             Each act of remembrance becomes a   And yet, the tiger has become a Ror-  remembering a king who fell two cen-
           statement of allegiance. Supporters call   schach test. What one person sees as   turies ago. We’re remembering a mo-
           him a “freedom fighter before 1857.”   courage, another sees as hubris. What   ment when India, fragmented and rest-
           Critics label him “intolerant.” Both sides   one calls faith, another calls fanaticism.   less, was still imagining what freedom
           use history less to understand the past   The debate says less about Tipu and   might look like.
           and more to argue about the present.   more about us, about what we choose to
             The question, then, isn’t who Tipu   honour and what we prefer to forget.   Reflection
           was, but what he means to us now. Is he                            Perhaps the most human way to re-
           a symbol of resistance? A cautionary   Tipu in art and media    member Tipu Sultan is not through the
           tale of zeal? Or a reminder that history,   Popular culture has kept Tipu alive in   lens of ideology, but through empathy.
           like people, resists being neatly catego-  ways history books can’t. From Girish   To recognize that his world, like ours,
           rized?                          Karnad’s celebrated play The Dreams of   was full of uncertainties, shifting loy-
                                           Tipu Sultan to Doordarshan’s 1990s   alties, impossible choices.
           Between myth and man            series that portrayed him as a proto-na-  Standing at the ruins of Sriranga-
             It’s easy to forget that Tipu was,   tionalist hero, the Sultan continues to   patna, where the Cauvery flows quietly
           above all, a man. A ruler juggling diplo-  stride across India’s cultural imagina-  past the walls that once echoed with
           macy and destiny, faith and pragmatism.   tion.                 cannon fire, you can almost feel the hum
           He wrote poetry, collected clocks and   Each new retelling adds layers, a   of unresolved history. It doesn’t roar
           kept a personal library rich with works   symbol of anti-colonial struggle, a com-  anymore, it murmurs, asking not for
           on science and religion. He cor-  plex Muslim monarch, an early modern   judgment, but understanding. Maybe
           responded with the Ottoman Sultan,   visionary. In films and literature, he’s   that’s what Tipu’s legacy truly demands:
           sought French alliances and dreamt of   often depicted in chiaroscuro, half-light,   not blind admiration or blind condemna-
           industrial modernization.       half shadow. Perhaps that’s fitting. True   tion, but the courage to hold both myth
             There’s a story, perhaps apocryphal,   memory rarely comes in black and   and memory in the same hand and still
           but often retold, that when his advisors   white.               see the man behind the crown. ■

           26                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                November 16-30, 2025







           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Fresh inspiration guides you as the month closes.   Your communication shines, use it to express
                     Travel, learning, or new ideas spark excitement.   heartfelt truths. A short trip or project brings re-
                     Your fiery nature feels recharged, but patience in   freshment. Financially, a positive change may
                     communication is vital. Love grows through      come from networking or collaboration. Rela-
                     honesty and humor.                              tionships thrive through shared laughter.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Emotional renewal arrives. You may let go of past   You’re stepping into your power with clarity and
                     disappointments, especially around relationships   calm. Finances and self-worth improve as you
                     or finances. This period favors joint decisions and   take bold, steady steps. Emotionally, you’ve re-
                     long-term planning. Trust your intuition, it won’t   leased old doubts, now confidence becomes your
                     lead you astray.                                greatest asset.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Partnerships take the spotlight. You may see a   Happy Birthday, Sagittarius! The spotlight turns
                     relationship evolve into something deeper or    your way and new beginnings bloom. You feel
                     face choices about balance and independence.    adventurous and ready to embrace life with re-
                     Professionally, teamwork brings success. Listen   newed enthusiasm. A heartfelt wish may finally
                     more than you speak, it builds harmony.         come true.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Work and wellness align now. A new project      Take a pause before December’s rush. Solitude
                     may open doors, but remember to rest and re-    helps you regain emotional strength. A private
                     charge. A creative or romantic connection grows   insight or spiritual breakthrough offers direction.
                     stronger. Routine changes improve your mood     Career plans quietly solidify behind the scenes,
                     and health.                                     trust divine timing.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Romance and joy take center stage. You feel ex-  Your social life brightens, friends and networks
                     pressive, bold and magnetic. Creative ventures   bring both joy and inspiration. Collaborations
                     shine, too. Don’t be afraid to take a risk, your in-  thrive under your inventive ideas. A long-term
                     tuition knows what’s right. Family pride fills   goal begins to take shape. Love feels light-
                     your heart.                                     hearted and full of promise.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Home and family matters reach resolution. A     Pisces, career or public recognition may arrive.
                     comforting sense of stability returns. This is an   You’re in a strong position to take leadership or
                     ideal time for reconnecting with loved ones or   redefine your path. A mentor’s advice helps you
                     planning your next big move. Love feels nurtur-  grow. In love, emotional maturity leads to stabil-
                     ing and secure.                                 ity and peace.


           NOVEMBER 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           Bihar Assembly Polls: A Reflection
                                           trapped, exposes the alarming neglect of
           of Public Mood

                                           safety norms in the mining sector. Such
             The Bihar Assembly election results
                                           tragedies are preventable if strict en-
           reveal a decisive shift in the state’s   one person dead and fifteen feared   Remembering Veteran Actress
           political sentiment. Voters have clearly   forcement of regulations and periodic   Kamini Kaushal
           prioritized development and governance   inspections are ensured. Workers in   The passing of veteran actress Ka-
           over traditional caste and identity politics.   these hazardous industries risk their   mini Kaushal marks the end of an era in
           The mandate reflects growing political   lives daily, often without adequate pro-  Indian cinema. An artist par excellence,
           maturity among citizens, who are   tective measures or emergency systems.   she brought natural grace and emotional
           demanding accountability and    Authorities must fix responsibility on   authenticity to every role she portrayed.
           performance from their leaders. While the   those who overlooked safety protocols   Beginning her career in the 1940s, she
           new government now faces the challenge   and ensure immediate rescue and relief   became one of the earliest female stars
           of fulfilling its promises, the opposition   operations. It is time for the government   to break away from stereotypical por-
           must introspect and play a constructive   to prioritize worker welfare over un-  trayals, infusing depth and dignity into
           role. Bihar’s electorate has shown that   checked industrial greed and take firm   her characters.
           democracy thrives when people vote   action to prevent future disasters.   Her performances in classics such as
           thoughtfully, not emotionally. It is time all   Ramesh Sharma, Delhi, India   Do Bhai, Biraj Bahu, and Shabnam re-
           political parties respect this verdict and                      main benchmarks of subtle artistry. She
           work collectively towards progress,                             worked alongside legends like Dilip
           education, and employment for the youth.   Anti-SIR Call Reflects Public   Kumar, Dev Anand, and Raj Kapoor,
           Kapil Gupta, New Delhi, India   Frustration                     yet her individuality always shone
                                             The “Anti-SIR” call in Tamil Nadu   through. Her strength, humility, and in-
                                           reflects a rising wave of public discon-  tellect made her a respected figure both
           A Grim Reminder of Unending     tent against the misuse of power and ar-  on and off the screen.
           Violence                        rogance perceived in administrative and   Beyond acting, Kamini Kaushal rep-
             The recent blast in Srinagar that   political circles. The slogan has become   resented a generation that valued
           claimed nine lives and injured thirty-two   symbolic of citizens’ frustration with   cinema as a medium of storytelling
           others is a tragic reminder of how fragile   governance that often appears detached   rather than spectacle. Her journey from
           peace remains in Kashmir. Such acts of   from ground realities. While democracy   black-and-white films to contemporary
           terror not only take innocent lives but   welcomes dissent, it also demands that   cinema stands as a testament to her en-
           also shatter the hopes of lasting stability   elected representatives remain sensitive,   durance and passion for the craft. With
           in the region. The incident highlights the   transparent, and accountable to the   her passing, Indian cinema loses one of
           urgent need for stronger intelligence co-  people they serve.   its most graceful pioneers, whose leg-
           ordination and strict security measures   Instead of dismissing the call as mere   acy will inspire generations to come.
           to prevent similar attacks. Beyond im-  political noise, authorities should inter-  Kamini Kaushal’s passing ends an era
           mediate responses, long-term peace can   pret it as a wake-up message to restore   of grace and talent, leaving Indian
           only be achieved through dialogue, re-  humility and responsibility in public dis-  cinema richer through her timeless leg-
           habilitation, and addressing the local   course. Constructive engagement with   acy.
           population’s aspirations. The govern-  citizens can rebuild lost trust and   Alka Vashisht, Mumbai, Maharash-
           ment must ensure justice for the victims   strengthen the democratic fabric. Tamil   tra, India
           and restore faith in the peace process.   Nadu’s civic maturity lies not in con-
           Naresh Bhati, Amritsar, Punjab, India   frontation but in dialogue that bridges
                                           the gap between the rulers and the ruled.   Letters (limited to one hundred
                                           Genuine reform, not reaction, will an-  words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           Sonbhadra Quarry Collapse       swer the people’s call.            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
             The recent collapse of a stone quarry   Ramesh Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           in Sonbhadra, Uttar Pradesh, which left   India


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           28                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | NOVEMBER 16 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Damir K



      "Adopt the pace of nature: her secret is patience."

                                                   –  Ralph Waldo Emerson]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>