<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 03  I  FEBRUARY 01 2025  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: ANIL SHARMA





               9



                                                            24













                                                            15                                       18
















           4-Editorial: Marriage or partnership?           24-Why someone instantly attracts us
           5-How tech shapes relationships today  28-Horoscopes

           9-Is marriage still the ultimate goal?          29-Letters

           12-The art of staying together

           15-Women and heart health
           18-Faith as the ultimate medicine

           21-Hijab in the modern world















           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                                3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Rethinking Commitment
     EDITORIAL  Marriage                                                          Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           or partnership?                                                      Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                                arriage, once considered the cor-    Navormi Vats
                                                nerstone of society, has under-
                                        Mgone a remarkable transformation
                                        over the centuries. Once an institution gov-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        erned by tradition, dutyand economic con-  Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        siderations, marriage is now defined by
                                        individual choice, loveand evolving societal   Social Media Editor
                                        values. The question arises; does marriage   Vikas Babbar
                                        still hold the same significance in a world
                                        where love and commitment can exist bey-  Art & Graphics Editor
                                        ond legal or religious boundaries?           Vipin Kumar
                                           Historically, marriage was a contractual
                                        arrangement, a means to secure alliances,
                                        wealthand lineage. Love, if it flourished,   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           was a fortunate outcome rather than a prerequisite. Over time, the rise of romantic
           ideals reshaped the narrative, placing emotional connection at the heart of marital   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           unions. However, as modernity reshapes human relationships, the traditional concept   Editor, United News of India, New
           of marriage is being questioned more than ever.                   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             One of the most significant shifts in contemporary society is the increasing ac-  Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           ceptance of live-in relationships. Many couples today choose to cohabit without le-  Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           galizing their union, valuing companionship and mutual growth over institutional   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           validation. This trend is fueled by a desire for flexibility, self-discoveryand freedom   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           from societal pressures.                                          N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
             At the heart of this transformation is the realization that commitment is not nec-  Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           essarily measured by wedding vows but by everyday actions of care, respectand part-
           nership. Many couples find deep fulfillment in relationships without needing the   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           formal stamp of marriage. They share homes, raise childrenand build lives together
           based on mutual understanding rather than external expectations.     Phone +91 20 40199102
             However, marriage still holds cultural, emotionaland legal significance. It pro-  Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           vides security, social recognitionand a structured framework for family life. For   Baner Road,
           some, it remains a powerful symbol of love and dedication, while for others; it repre-  Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           sents societal conformity rather than personal fulfillment. The increasing rates of di-  Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
           vorce and the changing expectations within marriage highlight the need for a more   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
           fluid and personalized approach to commitment.                       Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
             Ultimately, the evolution of marriage reflects the broader shifts in human relation-  Founding year 2023
           ships. Love is no longer bound by rigid structures; it flourishes in spaces that allow   Subject Multidisciplinary
           individuals to be their truest selves. While marriage continues to be a cherished insti-  Frequency Fortnightly
           tution for many, it is no longer the only path to a meaningful and committed relation-  Format Online
           ship. The true essence of love lies not in a certificate or a ceremony, but in the way   Language English
           two people choose to live and grow together; whether within or outside the bounds of   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           marriage. As society continues to redefine relationships, one truth remains un-  Website www.revoir.in
           changed: love, in its purest form, transcends institutions. Whether married or not,
           what truly matters is the depth of connection and the willingness to journey through   Legal Advisor
           life together.                                                        Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY













































           Love in the digital age                                         macy, commitment, and communication
                                                                           that influences how people experience
                                                                           and navigate relationships.
           How tech shapes                                                 Meeting in the digital world
                                                                              The advent of online dating plat-
                                                                           forms has been one of the most signifi-
                                                                           cant changes in how people meet poten-
                                                                           tial partners. Apps like Tinder, Bumble,
           relationships                                                   and OkCupid have redefined courtship,
                                                                           making it possible to swipe through pro-
                                                                           files and initiate conversations without
                                                                           ever leaving home. These platforms
                                                                           allow individuals to specify preferences,
           today                                                           creating a tailored approach to finding
                                                                           love.
                                                                              Interestingly, online dating has tran-
                                                            By Pooja Mehta  scended its early reputation as a last re-
                                                                           sort. Today, it is a mainstream method
             n an era where technology per-  lenges to the dynamics of modern love.   for meeting partners, with millions of
             meates every facet of life, love and   As Valentine’s Day approaches, it   success stories attesting to its efficacy.
           Irelationships have not been spared.   serves as the perfect occasion to explore   Dating platforms have given rise to
           The digital age has revolutionized how   this remarkable shift. Gone are the days   niche apps as well, such as Hinge for
           people meet, connect, and maintain rela-  when romantic connections were limited   meaningful connections or Grindr for
           tionships. With the advent of smart-  to chance encounters or introductions by   LGBTQ+ individuals, catering to spe-
           phones, social media, and dating apps,   mutual acquaintances. Today, technol-  cific audiences and preferences.
           romance has moved beyond traditional   ogy has democratized love, enabling in-  However, this convenience comes
           settings to a world where screens play   dividuals to find partners across con-  with its challenges. The abundance of
           matchmaker. This transformation has   tinents and cultures. However, with this   choices can sometimes lead to "choice
           brought both opportunities and chal-  revolution comes a redefinition of inti-  paralysis," making it harder to commit

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                                5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[to one person. Additionally, the super-
           ficial nature of swiping culture, which
           often prioritizes physical appearance
           over deeper qualities, raises concerns
           about the authenticity of connections
           formed online.

           The role of social media in modern
           romance
             Social media platforms like Insta-
           gram, Facebook, and Snapchat have be-
           come integral to modern relationships.                                                          A girl talking to her boyfriend on the phone
           They allow couples to share their lives
           in ways that were previously unimagin-
           able. Posting pictures, sharing mem-
           ories, and tagging each other in posts
           have become symbols of affection and
           commitment.
             Social media also helps people main-
           tain connections with their partners,
           especially during times of physical sep-
           aration. It enables couples to stay in-
           volved in each other's lives through
           posts, stories, and comments. However,
           the influence of social media isn’t al-
           ways positive.
             The pressure to project a "perfect" re-
           lationship online can create unrealistic
           expectations. Partners might feel com-
           pelled to curate an idealized version of
           their relationship for public consump-                                                          A couple expressing love through a laptop
           tion, which can lead to dissatisfaction
           and strain. Moreover, issues like cyber-
           stalking, oversharing, and comparison
           with others’ relationships can further
           complicate matters.
           Long-distance love: Bridging the
           gap                             technology ensures that physical dis-
             One of the most profound impacts of   tance is no longer a barrier to shared ex-
           technology on relationships is its ability   periences.
           to sustain long-distance love. Video
           calls, instant messaging, and virtual date   Redefining romance: Digital
           nights have made it possible for couples   expressions of love
           separated by geography to remain con-  The digital age has introduced new
           nected. Platforms like Zoom and What-  ways of expressing love. Virtual hugs,
           sApp have become lifelines for such re-  animated emojis, and heartfelt messages
           lationships, enabling real-time   have replaced handwritten letters and in-
           interaction despite physical distance.   person declarations. While these digital
             For long-distance couples, Valen-  expressions may lack the personal touch                    A girl is busy chatting on a landline phone
           tine’s Day often takes on a digital di-  of their traditional counterparts, they
           mension. Virtual celebrations, such as   resonate with a generation accustomed
           sharing meals over a video call or ex-  to instantaneous communication.
           changing gifts via online delivery serv-  Gift-giving has also adapted to tech-
           ices, have become commonplace. While   nology, with e-cards, digital gift
           technology cannot replace physical pres-  vouchers, and virtual experiences be-
           ence, it provides a semblance of close-  coming popular. Couples can now send
           ness that helps keep the spark alive.   each other personalized messages em-  ality (AR) and virtual reality (VR) offers
             The flexibility of digital communica-  bedded in digital greeting cards or sur-  immersive experiences for couples.
           tion also allows couples to explore cre-  prise one another with subscriptions to   From virtual movie nights to shared
           ative ways of connecting. From playing   streaming services, online courses, or   gaming sessions, technology enables
           online games together to co-watching   even virtual tours of exotic locations.   partners to create memorable moments
           movies through platforms like Teleparty,   Moreover, the rise of augmented re-  in innovative ways.

           6                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Interacting with her friend on a smartphone                                                       Smartphone app for modern dating


















         A girl watching a movie on a laptop, apart from her friend
                                                                              In the future, AI may play an even
                                                                           more significant role, with innovations
                                                                           like virtual relationship coaches and AI-
                                                                           powered chatbots designed to simulate
                                                                           companionship. While these advance-
                                                                           ments offer convenience, they also raise
                                                                           questions about the authenticity of con-
                                                                           nections.

                                                                           Maintaining relationships in a
                                                                           digital world
                                                                              Sustaining relationships in the digital
                                                                           age requires conscious effort. Constant
                                                                           connectivity, while beneficial, can lead
                                                                           to misunderstandings and over-depen-
                                                                           dence. Couples need to set boundaries
                                                                           for digital communication and prioritize
                                                                           in-person interactions to nurture their
           Challenges in digital dating    and tone, makes it harder to gauge a per-  bond.
             While technology has made finding   son’s intentions or emotions. This can   Technology can also be a double-
           and maintaining relationships easier, it   result in misunderstandings and mis-  edged sword when it comes to privacy.
           has also introduced new challenges. One   communications.       Sharing passwords, tracking each
           of the most significant issues is "ghost-                       other’s online activity, or demanding
           ing," where one party abruptly cuts off   The role of AI in modern love   constant updates can erode trust. In-
           communication without explanation.   Artificial intelligence (AI) has further   stead, couples should strive for open
           This phenomenon, made easier by digi-  revolutionized romance. Many dating   communication and mutual respect, en-
           tal communication, can leave lasting   apps now use AI algorithms to match in-  suring that technology complements
           emotional scars, especially for those   dividuals based on compatibility scores,   rather than complicates their relation-
           who invest heavily in online connec-  shared interests, and behavioral patterns.   ship.
           tions.                          These algorithms are becoming increas-
             Catfishing, where individuals create   ingly sophisticated, taking into account   Valentine’s day in the digital age
           fake identities to deceive others, is   nuanced factors such as communication   Valentine’s Day celebrations have
           another concern. Despite advancements   styles and emotional intelligence.   also undergone a digital makeover. From
           in security and verification processes,   In addition to matchmaking, AI is   personalized e-cards to live-streamed
           online platforms remain vulnerable to   being integrated into daily relationship   serenades, technology has made roman-
           misuse. These fraudulent interactions   management. Virtual assistants like Siri   tic gestures more accessible and cre-
           can harm trust and emotional well-  and Alexa can help plan romantic even-  ative. Online platforms offer countless
           being, particularly for individuals seek-  ings, send reminders for anniversaries,   ideas for celebrating, from virtual cook-
           ing genuine connections.        and even suggest thoughtful gift ideas.   ing classes to digital scavenger hunts.
             Furthermore, the fast-paced nature of   Some apps even offer AI-powered rela-  For singles, Valentine’s Day in the
           online interactions can sometimes lead   tionship coaching, providing advice and   digital age is no longer a day to be
           to shallow connections. The absence of   tips for couples looking to strengthen   dreaded. Dating apps often host special
           physical cues, such as body language   their bond.              events or campaigns to help people find

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                                7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[potential matches. Social media cam-
                                                                           paigns encouraging self-love, friendship,
                                                                           and platonic appreciation have also
                                                                           gained traction, shifting the focus from
                                                                           romantic love to a broader celebration of
                                                                           connection.
         Physical meetings are now old-fashioned                           its impact on love and relationships will
                                                                           Looking ahead
                                                                              As technology continues to advance,

                                                                           only deepen. Innovations like the meta-
                                                                           verse promise to create even more im-
                                                                           mersive experiences, allowing couples
                                                                           to "meet" in virtual spaces and share
                                                                           moments that feel real. With such devel-
                                                                           opments, the boundaries of what consti-
                                                                           tutes a relationship may expand even
                                                                           further.
                                                                              However, it is crucial to remember
                                                                           that technology is merely a tool. The es-
                                                                           sence of love lies in genuine human con-
                                                                           nection, empathy, and understanding.
                                                                           While the digital age offers new ways to
                                                                           express these qualities, it cannot replace
                                                                           the depth of face-to-face interactions.
                                                                              Love in the digital age is a complex
                                                                           tapestry of opportunities and challenges.
                                                                           Technology has transformed how people
         Everyone uses digital devices to express love                     screens and algorithms, the fundamental
                                                                           meet, date, and maintain relationships,
                                                                           offering tools that were unimaginable
                                                                           just a few decades ago. Yet, amidst the

                                                                           principles of love remain unchanged:
                                                                           trust, communication, and mutual re-
                                                                           spect.
                                                                              This Valentine’s Day, whether you’re
                                                                           swiping right on a dating app, video-cal-
                                                                           ling a long-distance partner, or sharing a
                                                                           heartfelt post on social media, remember
                                                                           to cherish the human connection that un-
                                                                           derpins it all. After all, love, no matter
                                                                           how it is expressed, remains timeless. ■











         Birthday celebration via live video call                                                          Physical meetings have turned digital
















           8                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH







                                                                                                           A couple in a live-in relationship







         A newly married woman expressing her happiness                    sential to reflect on how this institution





                                                                           has adapted to societal changes and
                                                                           whether these changes align with the
                                                                           true essence of love and commitment.
                                                                           While marriage was once considered a
                                                                           lifelong bond sealed by mutual respect
                                                                           and affection, the dynamics today reflect
                                                                           a shift toward pragmatism and individ-
                                                                           ual fulfillment. This raises the question:
                                                                           Are modern marriages losing their emo-
                                                                           tional depth, or are they simply evolving
                                                                           to meet the needs of contemporary soci-
                                                                           ety?
           Living together, loving together                                Historical foundations of marriage

                                                                              Historically, marriage served pur-
           Is marriage still                                               mantic ideals. In many cultures, it was
                                                                           poses that were far removed from ro-
                                                                           primarily an economic and social ar-
                                                                           rangement designed to consolidate
                                                                           wealth, establish alliances, and ensure
           the ultimate goal?                                              the continuation of family lineage. Love,
                                                                           if it emerged, was often seen as a for-
                                                                           tunate byproduct rather than a prereq-
                                                                           uisite. The idea of marrying for love,
           As we look to the future, it is clear that marriage will        which is so prevalent today, began gain-
                                                                           ing prominence in the 18th and 19th
           continue to evolve, shaped by cultural, economic, and           centuries, particularly in Western so-
                                                                           cieties influenced by the Enlightenment
           personal factors. By Naina Kapoor                               and Romantic movements.
                                                                              This shift was revolutionary, as it
                                                                           placed individual emotions and personal
                  arriage, one of the oldest so-  ing it have shifted dramatically. Love,   happiness above familial obligations and
                  cial institutions, has under-  commitment, and companionship, once   societal norms. The notion of “true
           Mgone profound transfor-        secondary considerations, have now be-  love” became the gold standard, and
           mations throughout human history.   come the cornerstone of modern mar-  marriages rooted in genuine affection
           What began as a contractual agreement   riages. Yet, even as marriage adapts to   often proved more resilient than those
           between families has evolved into a   the values of the times, its relevance and   arranged solely for practical purposes.
           complex institution shaped by cultural,   forms are being questioned like never   Couples who shared a deep emotional
           economic, and personal factors. While   before.                 bond found it easier to navigate chal-
           the core idea of marriage, a union be-  On the occasion of World Marriage   lenges, as their commitment was under-
           tween two people, remains intact, the   Day, a day dedicated to honoring the   pinned by mutual care and understand-
           motivations and expectations surround-  beauty and sanctity of marriage, it is es-  ing rather than external pressures.

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                                9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[for others, the lack of formal constraints
                                                                           allows for a more honest and organic
                                                                           connection, free from societal expecta-
                                                                           tions.
                                                                              The rise of live-in relationships also
                                                                           reflects a broader cultural shift toward
         Marriage in the Christian religion                                delay marriage or forego it altogether in
                                                                           prioritizing individual autonomy. Young
                                                                           adults, in particular, are choosing to
                                                                           favor of cohabitation. This trend is
                                                                           fueled by changing social norms, eco-
                                                                           nomic considerations, and a desire to
                                                                           avoid the perceived risks and responsi-
                                                                           bilities associated with marriage. While
                                                                           live-in relationships offer flexibility,
                                                                           they also challenge traditional notions of
                                                                           commitment and raise questions about
                                                                           the role of long-term partnerships in a
                                                                           rapidly changing world.
                                                                           The role of love in successful
                                                                           marriages
                                                                              Amid these changing trends, one en-
                                                                           during truth remains: marriages founded
                                                                           on genuine love and mutual respect are
         Hindu marriage ceremony                                           dividuals enter into a union driven by a
                                                                           often the most successful. When two in-
                                                                           deep emotional connection, their rela-
                                                                           tionship becomes more resilient to exter-
                                                                           nal pressures. Love fosters patience, em-
                                                                           pathy, and compromise, which are
                                                                           essential for navigating the ups and
                                                                           downs of life together.
           Modern-day marriages: love or   growth and align with their evolving   Studies have consistently shown that
           transaction?                    identities. While this approach can lead   couples who prioritize emotional inti-
             Fast forward to the 21st century, and   to greater self-fulfillment, it can also   macy and open communication are
           the landscape of marriage has shifted yet   create challenges when individual aspi-  better equipped to weather challenges.
           again. While love remains a significant   rations clash with shared goals. The ten-  In contrast, relationships based solely on
           motivator, the pragmatic underpinnings   sion between pursuing personal happi-  convenience or external factors, such as
           of many modern marriages cannot be ig-  ness and maintaining a committed   financial security or social status, tend to
           nored. Today, marriages are increasingly   relationship has become a defining fea-  falter when these factors are no longer
           viewed as partnerships designed to ful-  ture of modern marriages.   relevant. Love, in its truest form, acts as
           fill individual needs, emotional, finan-                        a glue that holds the relationship to-
           cial, or social. This transactional nature   The rise of live-in relationships   gether, transcending the transactional
           of marriage has led to a rise in what can   Parallel to the changing dynamics of   nature of modern unions.
           be termed “need-based unions.”   marriage is the growing acceptance of   Successful marriages often share cer-
             In such arrangements, the relation-  live-in relationships. These arrange-  tain key traits. These include effective
           ship thrives as long as both partners con-  ments, once stigmatized, have gained   communication, shared values, and a
           tinue to fulfill each other’s needs. Ho-  traction as an alternative to traditional   willingness to adapt to changing circum-
           wever, when one party perceives that   marriage. Live-in relationships allow   stances. Couples who invest time and ef-
           their needs, whether emotional support,   couples to explore compatibility and   fort into nurturing their emotional con-
           financial stability, or personal growth,   shared goals without the formal commit-  nection are more likely to build a strong
           are no longer being met, the relationship   ment that marriage entails. For many,   foundation that can withstand life’s chal-
           often deteriorates. Divorce rates, which   this offers a sense of freedom and flex-  lenges. While external factors such as fi-
           have risen significantly over the past   ibility that is absent in the traditional   nancial stability and social support play
           few decades, reflect this trend. The dis-  marital framework.   a role, the emotional bond between part-
           solution of marriage is no longer seen as   However, live-in relationships also   ners remains the most critical deter-
           a taboo but as a viable option for indi-  come with their own set of challenges.   minant of a marriage’s success.
           viduals seeking personal fulfillment.   The absence of legal and societal obliga-
             The increasing focus on individual-  tions can sometimes make it easier for   Challenges facing modern
           ism has also reshaped expectations   one partner to walk away, leading to   marriages
           within marriage. Couples now seek part-  questions about the stability and long-  While the idea of love-based mar-
           nerships that support their personal   term viability of such arrangements. Yet,   riages is ideal, modern realities often

           10                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[A couple celebrating a simple ceremony







         A newlywed couple







                                                                           desire for connection and companion-
                                                                           ship remains constant. The challenge for
                                                                           modern couples will be to redefine com-
                                                                           mitment in a way that aligns with their
         An elderly couple symbolizing lifelong love                       greater personalization and flexibility.
                                                                           values and aspirations while preserving
                                                                           the emotional depth that makes relation-
                                                                           ships meaningful.
                                                                              One possible future for marriage is
                                                                           Couples may choose to define their rela-
                                                                           tionships on their own terms, creating
                                                                           agreements that reflect their unique
                                                                           needs and circumstances. This could in-
                                                                           clude new approaches to cohabitation,
                                                                           parenting, and financial planning, as
                                                                           well as a greater emphasis on emotional
                                                                           well-being and mutual support.
                                                                              On World Marriage Day, it is worth
           complicate this vision. Economic pres-  within relationships, it has also intro-  celebrating the enduring power of love
           sures, shifting gender roles, and the rise   duced new dynamics that couples must   and commitment while also acknowl-
           of individualism have all influenced   navigate. Balancing career ambitions,   edging the ways in which marriage has
           how people approach marriage. The   family responsibilities, and personal   adapted to the changing needs of soci-
           concept of “self-love” and personal   goals requires a high degree of coopera-  ety. While the shift toward need-based
           growth has become increasingly impor-  tion and understanding.   unions and the rise of live-in relation-
           tant, sometimes at the expense of rela-                         ships reflect the evolving priorities of
           tional commitment.              The future of marriage          individuals, the foundation of a success-
             Moreover, the rise of social media   As society continues to evolve, so   ful relationship remains unchanged:
           and dating apps has created a paradox of   too will the institution of marriage. The   genuine love, mutual respect, and shared
           choice, where individuals are constantly   traditional model of lifelong monogamy   goals.
           exposed to potential alternatives. This   may no longer be the default for future   As we look to the future, it is clear
           can lead to unrealistic expectations and   generations. Alternative forms of rela-  that marriage will continue to evolve,
           a tendency to compare one’s partner to   tionships, such as open marriages and   shaped by cultural, economic, and per-
           an idealized version of what a relation-  cohabitation without legal ties, are likely   sonal factors. Yet, amid these changes,
           ship should look like. As a result, many   to gain further acceptance. While these   the essence of a meaningful partnership,
           modern marriages struggle to balance   arrangements may challenge conven-  rooted in love and commitment, will re-
           personal aspirations with the demands of   tional notions of commitment, they also   main a timeless ideal. Whether through
           a committed relationship.       reflect a broader cultural shift toward   traditional marriage or alternative ar-
             Another significant challenge facing   valuing personal happiness and auton-  rangements, the pursuit of a deep, ful-
           modern marriages is the shifting land-  omy.                    filling connection will always be at the
           scape of gender roles. Traditional expec-  At the same time, the essence of mar-  heart of human relationships. By em-
           tations around household responsibilities   riage, a partnership built on trust, love,   bracing both tradition and innovation,
           and breadwinning have given way to   and mutual support, is unlikely to dis-  couples can build partnerships that
           more egalitarian arrangements. While   appear. Even as the forms and expecta-  honor the past while looking toward a
           this shift has led to greater equality   tions of marriage change, the human   hopeful and inclusive future. ■

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Hacks for a healthy relationship
     EXCLUSIVE  The art of








           staying together





           Marriage is often described as a beautiful journey, but every
           couple knows it’s not without its challenges. Balancing love, re-
           spect, and partnership requires more than just chemistry, it takes  Reena’s recipe for

           effort, understanding, and a sprinkle of creativity. While there’s   love and laughter
           no universal recipe for marital bliss, learning from real-life ex-
           periences can offer valuable insights. In this article, we dive into    hat makes a marriage thrive
           the lives of married couples who have mastered the art of staying       for 22 years? Reena, a sea-
           together, sharing their personal tips and tricks for a happy, healthy  Wsoned partner in love and life
           relationship. From handling disagreements with grace to keeping   and an international math educator from
           the spark alive, these stories are packed with wisdom, humor,   Ghaziabad, shares her secrets with a per-
                                                                           fect blend of wisdom and wit.
           and heartfelt advice that will inspire you to nurture your own     Their story began at work, where her
           love story. By staff writer                                     husband’s helpful nature instantly
                                                                           caught her attention. “He wasn’t just
           Juggling life with                                              kind; he was genuinely thoughtful,”
                                                                           Reena recalls. That spark blossomed
           love                                                            into a relationship built on care, love,
                                                                           and unshakable trust, the foundation of
                                                                           their marital success.
               or Dr. Anshul Garg, a Meerut-                                  But, like any couple, they’ve faced
               based dental surgeon and peri-                              their share of disagreements. Reena be-
           Fodontist, marriage is more than a                              lieves in the power of communication.
           bond, it's a journey brimming with                              “Even when we’re poles apart in opin-
           sparks, balance, and unwavering sup-                            ions, we remind ourselves to value each
           port. Reflecting on her first meeting                           other, express gratitude, and understand
           with her husband, Dr. Ankit Garg, a con-                        where the other is coming from,” she
           sultant orthodontist, during their post-                        explains.
           graduate teaching program, she shares,   ing each other, and standing strong to-  Her top love needs? Honesty, trust,
           “There was an immediate spark. As we   gether. These values shape their profes-  and respect. These principles shine
           got to know each other, it just clicked,   sional and personal dynamics. “Juggling   through in how they support each other
           and the rest is history.”       work and home is tough, but my hus-  professionally. “We celebrate every
             Having completed a decade of to-  band’s support makes it manageable. We   milestone, provide emotional strength,
           getherness in December, Dr. Anshul em-  share responsibilities without ego, help-  and share responsibilities to keep things
           phasizes the importance of respecting   ing each other as true partners.”   balanced,” she says.
           boundaries in a dual-career household.   To keep the spark alive, the couple   Despite busy schedules, the couple
           “When both partners are working, chal-  makes time for frequent dinner dates,   carves out 10 minutes daily for non-
           lenges arise. Understanding each other’s   phone calls, and even short breaks every   work conversations, discussing family,
           time management and sharing daily re-  two months. Their shared love for ex-  children, or simply their relationship.
           sponsibilities has been key, especially as   ploring cuisines brings added joy to   And when it’s time to unwind, a long
           a working mother,” she explains.   their routine.               drive together is their ultimate escape.
             Disagreements? She believes in the   Grateful for her husband’s constant   At home, chores are divided smartly
           power of space and reflection. “When   encouragement, Dr. Anshul concludes,   by responsibility rather than task. “It’s
           things heat up, we step back, give it   “He’s stood by me in every situation,   about playing to each other’s strengths
           time, and return to the discussion with   helping me achieve my dreams and in-  and being fair,” Reena reveals.
           cooler heads. Communication is cru-  dependence. That’s a true blessing.”   What does she cherish most in her
           cial,” she shares.                Their story is a testament to the   husband? “His kindness, thoughtfulness,
             For Dr. Anshul, the foundation of   magic of mutual respect, shared dreams,   and the little things he does just to see
           love lies in spending quality time, trust-  and delicious meals! ■   me smile,” she beams. ■

           12                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[their enduring bond, Navin doesn’t hesi-
                                           tate: “Trust and teamwork, it’s as simple
                                           as that.” Disagreements, he believes, are
                                           inevitable, but their resolution lies in the
                                           art of letting go. “We don’t dwell on ar-
                                           guments; we move forward, always,” he
                                           adds with a lawyer’s clarity.
                                             In their professional lives, the duo is
                                           a force to be reckoned with. Working to-
                                           gether as legal practitioners, their days
                                           are filled with stimulating discussions.
                                           “It’s a continuous exchange of ideas,
                                           theories, and insights,” Navin shares.
                                           “Each case teaches us something new,
                                           not just about the law, but about each
                                           other.”
           Keeping the spark               harmonious. Household responsibilities   A tale of friendship,
                                             Life outside the courtroom is equally
           alive                           are tackled with a sense of partnership.   fun, and forever
                                           “We back each other up, whether it’s a
                                           task at home or a challenge at work,” he
                 fter 14 years of love and part-  says, reflecting their seamless synergy.   or Anima, a Basingstoke, UK-
                 nership, lawyer Navin Giri and   When it’s time to unwind, the couple   based IT professional, marriage is
           Ahis wife, Neha Giri, a Van-    finds joy in shared activities, be it a cozy  Fthe perfect blend of friendship,
           couver, Canada-based solicitor and bar-  dinner date, a sporty adventure, or   humor, and unwavering support. Recall-
           rister, exemplify a marriage built on   simply indulging in meaningful conver-  ing how it all began in college back in
           trust, respect, and camaraderie. Their   sation. Asked about what he cherishes   2008, she smiles, “We were best friends
           story began on the law campus, where   most, Navin’s answer is heartfelt: “Her   first. His sense of humor was what drew
           sparks flew amidst books and briefs, ig-  love and kindness, they are the essence   me to him.” Seven years of wedded bliss
           niting a connection that has only deep-  of our marriage.” His story is a master   later, their bond remains as strong as
           ened with time.                 class in balancing love, work, and life, a   ever, built on the foundation of honesty.
             When asked about the cornerstone of   true testament to a happy marriage. ■   “We can’t keep secrets. We’re each
                                                                           other’s safe space,” she reveals.
           Love, laughter,                                                 is simple, resolve it before bedtime. “We
                                                                              When disagreements arise, their rule
           and balance                                                     sometimes agree to disagree, but under-
                                                                           standing each other’s perspective is
                                                                           key,” says Anima. Their love language
                  arriage, for Akash, a Basing-                            thrives on communication, care, and
                  stoke-based IT professional, is                          support, which form the core of their re-
           Mbuilt on trust, teamwork, and                                  lationship.
           life's simple joys. Reminiscing about the                          Balancing careers, Anima is in awe
           beginning, he says, “We met in college,                         of her husband’s selflessness. “He’s my
           became friends first, and gradually grew                        biggest supporter, he’s even moved con-
           closer. It was her simplicity and                               tinents for me without a second thought
           grounded nature that truly won me                               about his own career.” Despite busy
           over.”                                                          schedules, they prioritize meaningful
             Seven years into their journey to-                            moments. “Evening walks are sacred.
           gether, Akash firmly believes that trust   tends to their careers and household re-  It’s when we talk about everything, our
           is the backbone of their relationship.   sponsibilities. “When one of us has a   day, future plans, and dreams, without
           “We’re at a point where we trust each   hectic day, the other naturally steps in to   distractions,” she shares.
           other completely, and that’s what keeps   manage things. It’s not about dividing   The couple thrives on shared activ-
           us strong,” he shares. When disagree-  tasks; it’s about supporting each other.”   ities, shopping, traveling, and indulging
           ments arise, their approach is refresh-  Evenings are their sanctuary for con-  in culinary adventures. Household re-
           ingly practical. “We listen to each other,   nection. “Our conversations stretch end-  sponsibilities are tackled with a no-rules
           find common ground, or let the matter   lessly, from dinner till bedtime,” Akash   approach. “We do everything together,
           rest overnight. The next morning always   says with a smile. As for their favorite   dishes, cooking, and laundry. It’s all
           feels like a clean slate.”      pastimes, shopping, long drives, cook-  about teamwork and flexibility,” Anima
             Akash’s perspective on love is   ing, and movie nights top the list. What   explains.
           equally inspiring. “With the right per-  is he most grateful for? “Her love, care,   Grateful for her husband’s unwaver-
           son, love itself fulfills all needs, it’s the   and understanding. She’s my confidant,   ing belief in her, she concludes, “He un-
           foundation that everything else builds   my anchor, and the one person I can   derstands me like no one else, even the
           upon,” he explains. This philosophy ex-  share anything with.” ■   things I don’t say.” ■

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[SPECIAL REPORT








































           Let the beat go on



           Women and






           heart health                                                    the truth. Heart disease remains the



                                                                           number one leading cause of death for
                                                                           women in the United States, claiming
                                                                           more lives annually than all forms of
           Everyone has a role to play in promoting women’s                cancer combined. This staggering reality
                                                                           underscores the importance of initiatives
           heart health. Communities, healthcare providers, and            like Women’s Heart Week, a dedicated
                                                                           time to focus on awareness, prevention,
           policymakers must work together to create an                    and education about women’s cardiovas-
                                                                           cular health.
           environment where women feel empowered to
           prioritize their well-being. By Anaya Gupta                     Heart disease and women: Myths
                                                                           and misconceptions
                                                                              One of the greatest obstacles in ad-
                 eart health often takes a back-  age or gender, but it is particularly dan-  dressing heart disease in women is the
                 seat when it comes to women’s   gerous for women due to factors that are   persistent myth that it’s more of a men’s
           Hhealth discussions, overshad-  often ignored.                  issue. Historically, research, media rep-
           owed by other prevalent health concerns   For many years, heart disease has   resentation, and even clinical guidelines
           such as breast cancer or reproductive   been primarily associated with men, and   have focused primarily on male sub-
           health issues. However, cardiovascular   this has created a dangerous misconcep-  jects, leaving a gap in knowledge about
           disease is a silent, often underestimated   tion that women are less susceptible.   how cardiovascular disease presents in
           killer. It does not discriminate based on   However, this couldn’t be further from   women. This gap in understanding has

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Stress and heart health                                                                           A woman jogging in the morning








           far-reaching consequences, including   velop high blood pressure, high choles-  can yield significant long-term benefits.
           misdiagnoses, delayed treatments, and   terol, and other risk factors.
           overlooked symptoms.                                            Prioritize a heart-healthy diet:
             The truth is that women often present   Pregnancy-related risks:   Diet plays a crucial role in maintain-
           different symptoms during a heart attack   Complications during pregnancy,   ing heart health. Women should focus on
           than men, and these symptoms are more   such as preeclampsia, gestational dia-  consuming more fruits, vegetables,
           likely to be subtle. While men com-  betes, or high blood pressure, not only   whole grains, nuts, and lean proteins
           monly report crushing chest pain,   put women at immediate risk but also   while limiting saturated fats, processed
           women often experience:         increase the likelihood of developing   foods, and sugars. Foods like salmon,
             • Unusual fatigue that doesn’t go   heart disease later in life. These con-  flaxseeds, and walnuts, which are rich in
           away with rest                  ditions can cause lasting damage to   omega-3 fatty acids, can reduce inflam-
             • Shortness of breath, even without   blood vessels and the heart.   mation and lower the risk of heart dis-
           exertion                                                        ease.
             • Nausea or vomiting          Autoimmune diseases:
             • Discomfort or pain in the jaw, neck,   Women are disproportionately af-  Stay physically active:
           shoulders, or upper back        fected by autoimmune diseases such as   Exercise strengthens the heart and
             • Lightheadedness or fainting epi-  lupus and rheumatoid arthritis. These   improves circulation. The American
           sodes                           conditions can cause chronic inflamma-  Heart Association recommends at least
             Because these symptoms can be   tion, which damages blood vessels and   150 minutes of moderate-intensity exer-
           easily mistaken for stress, anxiety, indi-  increases cardiovascular risk.   cise per week. Activities like brisk walk-
           gestion, or other non-life-threatening                          ing, cycling, swimming, or even dancing
           conditions, many women delay seeking   Lifestyle pressures:     can help lower blood pressure and cho-
           medical help. This delay can be life-  Modern women often juggle multiple   lesterol levels.
           threatening, as early intervention during   responsibilities, career, caregiving, and
           a heart attack is critical to survival and   household management, leaving little   Quit smoking:
           recovery.                       time to focus on their health. This can   Smoking significantly increases the
                                           lead to poor eating habits, lack of exer-  risk of heart disease, and women who
           Why women are at unique risk    cise, and unmanaged stress, all of which   smoke are at an even higher risk when
             The unique biological, hormonal, and   are risk factors for heart disease.   using hormonal contraceptives. Quitting
           societal factors affecting women in-                            smoking is one of the most effective
           crease their vulnerability to heart dis-  Mental health impact:   ways to protect heart health.
           ease. Here’s a deeper dive into these   Depression and anxiety are more
           risks:                          prevalent in women and are strongly   Monitor key health metrics:
                                           linked to heart health. Chronic stress el-  Regularly check your blood pressure,
           Hormonal changes:               evates cortisol levels, which can lead to   cholesterol levels, blood sugar, and body
             Estrogen, a hormone prevalent in   high blood pressure, unhealthy weight   weight. These metrics provide early
           women during their reproductive years,   gain, and other cardiovascular issues.   warning signs and allow for timely inter-
           offers some protection against heart dis-                       vention.
           ease by keeping blood vessels flexible.   Prevention: small steps, big
           However, after menopause, estrogen   impact                     Manage stress effectively:
           levels decline, and the risk of cardiovas-  The good news is that heart disease is   Stress management is not just a men-
           cular disease rises sharply. Postmeno-  largely preventable with proactive life-  tal health concern, it’s a vital aspect of
           pausal women are more likely to de-  style changes. Even small adjustments   heart health. Incorporating mindfulness

           16                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[risks women face. These programs en-
                                                                           courage women to advocate for them-
                                                                           selves and seek medical attention when
                                                                           needed.

                                                                           Improved diagnostics:
                                                                              Advanced imaging techniques, such
                                                                           as coronary computed tomography an-
         A doctor-patient consultation                                     ages or damage in smaller blood vessels,
                                                                           giography (CCTA), help identify block-
                                                                           something often missed in traditional
                                                                           tests.

                                                                           Gender-specific rehabilitation
                                                                           programs:
                                                                              Cardiac rehabilitation programs de-
                                                                           signed specifically for women address
                                                                           not only physical recovery but also emo-
                                                                           tional and mental health aspects, ensur-
                                                                           ing holistic care.
         A woman heart patient admitted to the hospital                    moting women’s heart health. Com-
                                                                           Supporting women’s heart health
                                                                              Everyone has a role to play in pro-

                                                                           munities, healthcare providers, and poli-
                                                                           cymakers must work together to create
                                                                           an environment where women feel em-
                                                                           powered to prioritize their well-being.
                                                                           Here are some actionable steps:
                                                                              Spread awareness: Use platforms
                                                                           such as social media, workplaces, or

                                                                           about heart health in women.
                                                                              Advocate for research: Support fund-
                                                                           ing for gender-specific cardiovascular
                                           tions. Stick to one drink per day or less.   community events to share information
                                                                           research to bridge the knowledge gap.
                                                                              Encourage screenings: Organize
                                           Ensure quality sleep:           heart health screening events, especially
                                             Sleep is often overlooked but is cru-  for underserved populations, to detect
                                           cial for heart health. Women who sleep   risks early.
                                           less than seven hours per night are at a
                                           higher risk of obesity, high blood pres-  A call to action
                                                                              As we observe Women’s Heart Week,
                                           sure, and diabetes, all contributors to   let us not just reflect but act. This ded-
                                           heart disease.
         A young lady symbolizing stress   Treatment and research: Progress   heart health is a critical issue that de-
                                                                           icated time is a reminder that women’s
                                           and innovations
                                                                           serves ongoing attention, not just during
                                                                           one week of the year, but every day.
                                             In recent years, the healthcare com-
                                                                              Heart disease is preventable, and
                                           munity has made strides in recognizing
                                           and addressing women’s heart health
                                                                           awareness is the first step. By under-
                                                                           standing the unique risks women face,
                                           needs. Here are some of the key ad-
                                           vancements:
                                                                           couraging proactive healthcare, we can
                                                                           reduce the burden of cardiovascular dis-
                                           Precision medicine:             adopting heart-healthy habits, and en-
           practices like yoga, meditation, or jour-  Personalized treatments based on a   ease.
           naling can help reduce stress levels and   woman’s unique genetic, hormonal, and   Women have long been the backbone
           improve overall well-being.     lifestyle factors are becoming more ac-  of families and communities, often
                                           cessible, offering better outcomes.   prioritizing everyone else’s needs over
           Limit alcohol intake:                                           their own. But self-care isn’t a luxury,
             While moderate alcohol consumption   Awareness campaigns:     it’s a necessity. Let’s rewrite the narra-
           has been linked to some heart health   Initiatives like the Go Red for   tive. Let’s ensure that the beat goes on
           benefits, excessive drinking can lead to   Women campaign have been instrumen-  for all women, loud and strong, for gen-
           high blood pressure and other complica-  tal in raising awareness about the unique   erations to come. ■

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Healing beyond the physical                                          ife is a delicate balance of tri-
                                                                                umphs and challenges, and no
                                                                           Lone is immune to the adversities
                                                                           that life presents. Illness, in particular,
     INSIGHT  Faith as the                                                 can feel like an unrelenting storm, shak-
                                                                           ing individuals to their core and often
                                                                           isolating them in its wake. In these mo-
                                                                           ments, faith and spirituality become a
           ultimate medicine                                               source of comfort and guidance, offering
                                                                           a sanctuary for the weary. Across cul-
                                                                           tures and eras, spirituality has been intri-
                                                                           cately tied to the healing process, pro-
                                                                           viding hope where there is despair and
                                                                           strength where there is fragility.
           Spirituality offers more than just comfort, it provides            World day of the sick, observed
           strength, resilience, and a renewed sense of purpose            every year on February 11, serves as a
                                                                           poignant reminder of the importance of
           in the face of illness and adversity.  Whether through          caring for those who are unwell, physi-
                                                                           cally or mentally. This day, established
                                                                           by Pope John Paul II in 1992, empha-
           prayer, meditation, or the support of a community, faith        sizes the critical role of faith in healing,
           empowers individuals to find peace and hope in their            not only for the sick but also for their
                                                                           caregivers. It highlights the need for a
           struggles. By Aarav Sharma                                      holistic approach to health that tran-
                                                                           scends physical care and addresses the
                                                                           emotional and spiritual needs of individ-
                                                                           uals. Faith, in its diverse forms, often
                                                                           becomes the anchor that helps people
                                                                           navigate the turbulent waters of illness
                                                                           and adversity.
                                                                           Spirituality: A pillar of strength in
                                                                           illness
                                                                              The connection between spirituality
                                                                           and health has been the subject of much
                                                                           research and discussion. While modern
                                                                           medicine focuses on diagnosing and
                                                                           treating the body, spirituality delves into
                                                                           the heart and soul, providing emotional
                                                                           resilience and mental clarity. The in-
                                                                           tegration of these two facets can lead to
                                                                           a comprehensive healing process, ad-
                                                                           dressing both physical and emotional
                                                                           well-being.
                                                                              When faced with illness, many indi-
                                                                           viduals turn to spiritual practices like
                                                                           prayer, meditation, or chanting to find
         Hands clasped in prayer, symbolizing hope and faith
                                                                           peace amidst uncertainty. These prac-
                                                                           tices not only calm the mind but also
                                                                           have tangible effects on the body. For
                                                                           example, prayer and meditation have
                                                                           been shown to lower stress levels, re-
                                                                           duce blood pressure, and improve the
                                                                           immune system. This mind-body con-
                                                                           nection underscores the profound impact
                                                                           spirituality can have on overall health.
                                                                              Faith also serves as a coping mecha-
                                                                           nism, helping individuals find meaning
                                                                           and purpose in their struggles. It fosters
                                                                           resilience by encouraging a positive out-
                                                                           look, even in the face of seemingly in-
                                                                           surmountable challenges. By placing
                                                                           their trust in a higher power or divine

           18                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[covery or a group offering emotional
                                                                           and practical assistance, these acts of
                                                                           kindness reinforce the idea that no one is
                                                                           alone in their struggles.
                                                                              Religious communities often organ-
                                                                           ize visits to the sick, offer counseling,
                                                                           and provide meals or financial support
                                                                           to those in need. These gestures, while
                                                                           seemingly small, can have a profound
                                                                           impact on the mental and emotional
                                                                           health of both patients and caregivers.
                                                                           The shared belief in a higher power or
                                                                           common values creates a bond that tran-
                                                                           scends individual hardships, fostering a
                                                                           collective resilience.
                                                                              For caregivers, who often bear the
                                                                           physical and emotional burden of tend-
                                                                           ing to the sick, this community support
                                                                           can be a lifeline. Faith-based practices,
                                                                           such as group prayer or communal wor-
                                                                           ship, offer moments of respite and re-
                                                                           newal, allowing caregivers to recharge
                                                                           and continue their vital work.

                                                                           Universality of spiritual practices
                                                                              Spirituality is not confined to any
         A family praying together by a hospital bed                       offers unique practices and perspectives,
                                                                           single religion or culture, it is a univer-
                                                                           sal concept that manifests in various
                                                                           ways across the globe. Each tradition

                                                                           yet they all share the common goal of
                                                                           providing comfort and guidance in times
                                                                           of need.
                                                                              In Christianity, prayer and faith in
                                                                           God’s plan are central to coping with ad-
                                                                           versity. Many find solace in Bible verses
                                                                           that affirm God’s presence during trials,

                                                                           walk through the darkest valley, I will
           plan, people often find the strength to   express fears and hopes, creating a sense   such as Psalm 23:4: “Even though I
           endure pain and hardship, believing that   of connection with a higher power that
           their suffering is part of a greater pur-  can be deeply comforting.
           pose.                             In some cases, faith even helps pa-
                                           tients redefine their relationship with
           Coping with chronic illness     their illness. Instead of viewing their
           through faith                   condition as a burden, they may see it as
             For those battling chronic illnesses,   an opportunity for personal growth, re-
           the journey can be physically exhausting   flection, and a deeper understanding of
           and emotionally draining. The long-term   life’s purpose. This shift in perspective
           nature of such conditions often leads to   can be transformative, turning adversity
           feelings of helplessness and despair. Ho-  into an avenue for self-discovery and
           wever, spirituality can provide a sense of   spiritual awakening.
           control and stability in an otherwise un-
           predictable situation.          The role of community in spiritual                              A person performing Hindu rituals for faith and healing
             Take, for example, the practice of   healing
           mindfulness meditation, which has its   Another significant aspect of spiritu-
           roots in Buddhism but is now widely   ality is the sense of community it
           embraced in secular settings. This prac-  fosters. Illness often isolates individuals,
           tice encourages individuals to focus on   but faith communities provide a network
           the present moment, reducing anxiety   of support that can make all the differ-
           about the future and regrets about the   ence. Whether it’s a congregation com-
           past. Similarly, prayer provides a way to   ing together to pray for someone’s re-

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Embracing spirituality in daily life
                                                                              For those seeking to explore the heal-
                                                                           ing power of faith, there are simple yet
                                                                           profound ways to incorporate spiritual-
                                                                           ity into daily life:
                                                                              Daily reflection: Spend a few mo-
                                                                           ments each day in prayer, meditation, or
         A devotee reading the Holy Quran                                  spiritual or religious group to build
                                                                           silent contemplation to reconnect with
                                                                           your inner self.
                                                                              Join a community: Engage with a

                                                                           meaningful connections and find sup-
                                                                           port.
                                                                              Practice gratitude: Keep a gratitude
                                                                           journal to focus on the positive aspects

                                                                              Seek guidance: Talk to a spiritual
                                                                           leader, counselor, or trusted mentor for
           fear no evil, for you are with me.”                             of life, even during tough times.
             Hinduism emphasizes the idea of sur-
           rendering to the divine through devotion
           (bhakti) and meditation (dhyana).
           Chanting mantras and practicing yoga
           are common ways to connect with one’s
           inner self and find peace amidst turmoil.
             In Islam, submission to Allah’s will
           is a fundamental principle. Muslims turn
           to prayer (salah) and the Quran for guid-
           ance, trusting in Allah’s wisdom and
           finding peace in the belief that all
           events, good or bad, are part of a divine
           plan.                                                                                           A devotee reading the Holy Quran
             Buddhism offers a unique perspec-
           tive on suffering, teaching that it is an
           inherent part of life. Through mindful-
           ness and meditation, individuals learn to
           accept their pain and find liberation
           from it by cultivating compassion and
           detachment.                     larly, rehabilitation programs for add-  support and clarity.
             Even indigenous and tribal traditions   iction, such as Alcoholics Anonymous,   Explore nature: Spend time in natural
           emphasize the connection between the   often incorporate spiritual principles to   settings, which can be deeply spiritual
           body, spirit, and nature. Rituals, songs,   foster recovery and resilience.   and rejuvenating.
           and storytelling often play a significant                          On World Day of the Sick, we are re-
           role in the healing process, reminding   Navigating challenges in spiritual   minded of the profound connection be-
           individuals of their place within the   healing                 tween faith, spirituality, and healing.
           larger web of life.               While spirituality offers numerous   Spirituality offers more than just com-
                                           benefits, it is not without challenges.   fort, it provides strength, resilience, and
           Spirituality in modern healthcare   People’s beliefs and practices vary   a renewed sense of purpose in the face
             In recent years, the medical field has   widely, and what brings comfort to one   of illness and adversity. Whether
           increasingly recognized the importance   person may not resonate with another.   through prayer, meditation, or the sup-
           of spirituality in healing. Many hospitals   Medical professionals must approach   port of a community, faith empowers in-
           now include chaplains, meditation   spirituality with sensitivity, respecting   dividuals to find peace and hope in their
           rooms, and spiritual counseling as part   each patient’s unique background and   struggles.
           of their services. These initiatives reflect   preferences.        In a world often marked by uncer-
           a growing understanding that health is   Additionally, there is the risk of rely-  tainty, the healing power of faith is a tes-
           not just about treating symptoms but   ing solely on spiritual practices while   tament to the human spirit’s capacity to
           about addressing the whole person,   neglecting medical treatment. True heal-  endure and thrive. By embracing spiritu-
           body, mind, and spirit.         ing requires a balanced approach that   ality, we not only navigate life’s chal-
             Palliative care is one area where spir-  combines faith with evidence-based   lenges with grace but also discover the
           ituality plays a crucial role. For patients   care. It’s also important to avoid spiri-  transformative power of hope and con-
           facing terminal illnesses, spiritual prac-  tual bypassing, using faith to suppress or   nection. Through faith, we find not just
           tices provide comfort and help them   ignore difficult emotions instead of ad-  healing, but a deeper understanding of
           come to terms with the end of life. Simi-  dressing them directly.   ourselves and our purpose. ■

           20                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Beyond Tradition


           Hijab in the modern                                                                                   SPOTLIGHT






           world






                   By Rohan Kapoor

                he hijab, a headscarf worn by
                Muslim women, has long been a
           Tsymbol of modesty, faith, and
           identity. However, in the modern world,
           it also stands as a focal point for debates
           on religious freedom, gender equality,
           and cultural diversity. Misunderstood by
           many and politicized by others, the hijab
           transcends its fabric, becoming a state-
           ment of self-expression and resilience
           for millions of women globally.
             Since its inception in 2013, World
           Hijab Day, observed on February 1st,
           has served as a platform to raise aware-
           ness and challenge stereotypes about the
           hijab. Founded by Nazma Khan, a Ban-
           gladeshi-American, the day encourages
           women of all backgrounds to experience
           wearing a hijab for a day, fostering em-
           pathy and understanding. It symbolizes
           a global effort to dispel myths surround-
           ing modest clothing and to highlight the
           freedom of choice for Muslim women in
           how they dress.

           The hijab: Symbol of faith,
           modesty, and identity
             The hijab derives its significance
           from Islamic teachings that promote
           modesty in thought, action, and attire.
           For many Muslim women, wearing the
           hijab is a deeply personal decision, re-
           flecting their relationship with their
           faith. It is not just an accessory; it em-
           bodies principles of dignity, humility,
           and spirituality.
             However, the hijab's meaning varies
           greatly. While some wear it as a spiritual
           act of devotion, others embrace it as a
           cultural tradition or a feminist statement
           of agency in choosing how to present
           themselves. Despite its varied interpreta-
           tions, the hijab often sparks polarized
           views, ranging from admiration of its
           symbolism to misconceptions that it rep-
           resents oppression.

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Challenging misconceptions
             In many parts of the world, the hijab
           has become a lightning rod for debates
           over women's rights and integration.
           Critics often argue that it is a tool of pa-
           triarchal control, failing to recognize
           that, for most women who wear it, the
           hijab is an empowering choice. Miscon-
           ceptions about the hijab frequently arise
           from limited understanding of Islamic
           practices, cultural diversity, and the                                                          A hijabi woman confidently working in an office
           agency of Muslim women.
             For instance, in countries like France,
           laws banning the hijab in schools and
           public spaces have been justified in the
           name of secularism. However, such pol-
           icies can marginalize Muslim women,
           forcing them to choose between their
           faith and their public identity. These ac-
           tions inadvertently perpetuate the very
           inequality they claim to oppose. Con-
           versely, in nations where wearing the
           hijab is legally enforced, women often
           lose the autonomy to decide for them-
           selves, further complicating the narra-
           tive of choice.
             World Hijab Day provides an oppor-
           tunity to confront these misconceptions.
           Through workshops, dialogues, and
           events, it fosters understanding that the
           hijab is neither universally oppressive                                                         Hijabi models wearing modest yet stylish attire
           nor universally mandated but is, instead,
           a multifaceted expression of personal
           belief.

           Expanding appeal: Hijab beyond
           religious boundaries
             While traditionally associated with
           Islamic faith, the hijab has found utility   Modest fashion: A global
           and appeal beyond religious contexts.   movement
           Increasingly, women from various faiths   The modern era has witnessed the
           and cultural backgrounds have adopted   rise of modest fashion, a movement that
           hijab-like coverings for practical pur-  celebrates clothing styles reflecting
           poses. In urban areas plagued by pollu-  modesty without compromising on con-
           tion, women often use scarves or wraps   temporary trends. Modest fashion, in-
           to shield their faces and hair from dust   cluding hijabs, long dresses, and loose-
           and harmful environmental particles.   fitting garments, has found its place in
           The hijab, in such scenarios, becomes a   global fashion markets, challenging con-
           practical accessory, blending functional-  ventional beauty standards.
           ity with modesty.                 Major fashion brands and designers
             Interestingly, young women across   have embraced modest wear, recogniz-
           diverse cultures have also found the   ing the demand for inclusive clothing
           hijab or similar coverings useful in   lines. Collections by brands like Dolce                  Artistic hijab photography
           maintaining anonymity, especially in so-  & Gabbana, H&M, and Nike feature
           cial settings like dating. By partially   stylish hijabs and modest apparel, cater-
           concealing their features, they feel more   ing to a diverse clientele. This inclusion
           comfortable navigating public spaces,   has not only normalized modest fashion
           shielding themselves from unwarranted   but also created a space for Muslim   ization of hijabs risks diluting their spir-
           attention. This evolving use underscores   women to celebrate their identity   itual essence. For some, the blending of
           how the hijab’s essence as a protective   through design and style.   faith-based attire with global fashion
           garment transcends religious bound-  However, the intersection of modesty   trends may appear contradictory. Non-
           aries, offering universal relevance in a   and fashion is not without its complex-  etheless, modest fashion advocates be-
           modern, interconnected world.   ities. Critics argue that the commercial-  lieve that such evolution allows women

           22                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[A hijabi girl with her boyfriend on a date                                                        Different hijab styles
















                                                                           move beyond token gestures of diversity
                                                                           and work toward genuine understanding.
                                                                           Education plays a vital role in achieving
                                                                           this. Incorporating lessons about differ-
                                                                           ent cultures, religions, and traditions in
         Hijabi woman engaged in daily activities                          World Hijab Day, can encourage com-
                                                                           school curricula can help dismantle prej-
                                                                           udices from an early age. Similarly,
                                                                           public campaigns, like those inspired by

                                                                           munities to celebrate diversity rather
                                                                           than fear it.
                                                                              Media representation is equally cru-
                                                                           cial. While the portrayal of hijabi
                                                                           women in film, television, and advertis-
                                                                           ing has improved, stereotypes still
                                                                           persist. Positive and nuanced representa-
                                                                           tions of Muslim women can challenge
                                                                           these tropes, showcasing the rich tapes-
           to express their individuality while hon-  but also pave the way for a more inclu-  try of experiences within the hijabi
           oring their beliefs.            sive world.                     community.
                                                                              The hijab in the modern world is far
           Hijab as a catalyst for dialogue   Empowering women through     more than a piece of cloth; it is a symbol
             The hijab also serves as a conver-  choice                    of resilience, identity, and
           sation starter, challenging societal norms   At its core, the hijab is about choice.   empowerment. Observances like World
           and fostering cross-cultural dialogue. In   Whether a woman chooses to wear it as   Hijab Day shine a light on the lived
           workplaces, schools, and public spaces,   an expression of faith or opts not to, her   experiences of Muslim women, chal-
           hijabi women often face questions about   autonomy should be respected. Empow-  lenging misconceptions and promoting
           their attire. While these interactions can   erment comes from the ability to make   empathy.
           sometimes stem from bias, they also   decisions free from coercion, be it socie-  In an increasingly globalized world,
           offer opportunities to educate and de-  tal, familial, or governmental.   fostering inclusion and understanding is
           bunk stereotypes.                 Prominent hijabi figures, such as ath-  more important than ever. By respecting
             For instance, many non-Muslims   letes, models, and politicians, have   individual choices and celebrating diver-
           wrongly assume that wearing the hijab   broken barriers and inspired others.   sity, societies can move closer to a
           is forced upon women, failing to con-  Women like Ibtihaj Muhammad, the first   future where the hijab, and the women
           sider the nuanced reasons behind the   hijab-wearing Olympian for Team USA,   who wear it, are embraced as integral
           choice. By sharing their stories, Muslim   and Halima Aden, the first hijab-wea-  parts of our shared humanity.
           women humanize their experiences,   ring model to grace international maga-  Through dialogue, education, and
           shifting the narrative from one of "other-  zine covers, have redefined notions of   inclusion, we can dismantle barriers and
           ness" to one of shared humanity.   success and visibility. Their achieve-  build a world that values every person’s
             Moreover, initiatives like "hijab-  ments highlight that wearing a hijab   right to express themselves freely.
           friendly" workplace policies and inclu-  does not limit ambition or potential.   Whether worn for faith, practicality, or
           sion programs have emerged, enabling                            personal expression, the hijab
           better representation and accommoda-  Fostering inclusion through   exemplifies the beauty of choice and the
           tion for hijabi women. These changes   awareness                power of individuality in a complex,
           not only challenge societal prejudices   To embrace inclusion, societies must   modern society. ■

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION








































           The Invisible Magnetism                                         signal to others that they are trustworthy,
                                                                           empathetic, and open, inviting deeper
                                                                           connections. This natural allure reminds
                                                                           us that the energy we carry often speaks
           Why someone                                                     louder than words, influencing the way
                                                                           others perceive and feel around us.

                                                                           What is an aura?
           instantly attracts us                                           ble energy field that surrounds every liv-
                                                                              The aura is believed to be an invisi-
                                                                           ing being. Spiritual traditions and mod-
                                                                           ern metaphysical beliefs suggest that the
                                                                           aura reflects the physical, mental, and
           Aura Awareness reminds us of the profound power of              emotional health of an individual. An-
                                                                           cient cultures, including those of India,
           our personal energy, an often unseen but ever-present           Egypt, and China, recognized the pres-
                                                                           ence of these energy fields and devel-
           force that shapes our experiences. By Ishita Desai              oped practices like chakra balancing and
                                                                           Reiki to maintain their harmony.
                                                                              The aura is said to have various
                 ave you ever met someone who   flects qualities like confidence, kind-  layers or "bodies" that interconnect to
                 seemed to light up a room or   ness, and emotional intelligence, cre-  reflect different aspects of our being:
           Hmade you feel instantly com-   ating a sense of comfort and appeal that   Physical layer: Closest to the body,
           fortable and drawn to them? Often, this   we can't always explain rationally.   this layer is associated with physical
           attraction is attributed to their aura, their   Such an attractive aura doesn't come   health.
           unique energy field that radiates   from looks or words alone; it's the   Emotional layer: Linked to our feel-
           warmth, positivity, and balance. When a   energy that a person emanates. Someone   ings and emotional well-being.
           person has a strong, vibrant aura, it can   who has worked on self-awareness,   Mental layer: Reflects our thoughts,
           make them more magnetic and ap-  emotional balance, and mindfulness   attitudes, and beliefs.
           proachable, almost as if they're envel-  often cultivates a harmonious aura that   Spiritual layer: Represents our
           oped in an invisible force that resonates   draws people in. Their positive energy   higher self and sense of purpose.
           deeply with others. This type of aura re-  and balanced aura can subconsciously   Each layer is believed to interact with

           24                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Colorful aura energy fields                                                                       Silhouettes with radiant energy











                                                                           Try meditation and breathwork
                                                                              Meditation is a powerful way to tune
                                                                           into your aura. Focusing on breathwork
                                                                           or practicing mindfulness helps calm the
                                                                           mind and may lead to sensations of
                                                                           energy around the body. Visualizing
                                                                           your energy radiating outwards in colors
                                                                           or light can be a meditative experience
                                                                           that brings you closer to sensing your
         Human connection through light                                    Practice grounding techniques
                                                                           aura.

                                                                              Grounding is essential to maintaining
                                                                           a balanced aura. This involves recon-
                                                                           necting with the earth’s natural energy,
                                                                           which can help cleanse and stabilize
                                                                           your aura. Practicing grounding exer-
                                                                           cises, such as walking barefoot on grass,
                                                                           hugging a tree, or simply spending time
           the others, making the aura a complex   stance, every human body emits an elec-  in nature, can positively influence your
           and dynamic energy system that mirrors   tromagnetic field, which can be meas-  energy.
           our internal states.            ured using devices like electrocardio-
                                           grams (ECGs) and                Engage in aura cleansing
           The purpose of aura awareness   magnetoencephalograms (MEGs). Re-  Sometimes, our auras can be clouded
             Aura Awareness encourages us to   search in biofield science explores how   by negative energy or emotional block-
           deepen our understanding of our own   this energy may affect our health and in-  ages. Techniques for cleansing the aura
           energy field, examine its impact on our   teractions with the environment.   include:
           lives, and develop habits to maintain a   From a spiritual perspective, auras   Smudging: Burning sage or other
           balanced and healthy aura. By tuning   are more than mere electromagnetic   herbs to cleanse and purify the energy
           into our energy, we can gain insights   fields; they are dynamic reflections of   field.
           into our emotions, relationships, and   our inner worlds. Many believe that cul-  Sound therapy: Using sound vibra-
           physical well-being, leading to a more   tivating a positive aura can enhance   tions from instruments like singing
           harmonious life.                one's well-being, attract positive experi-  bowls, tuning forks, or gongs to break
             It also raises awareness about the im-  ences, and foster more meaningful con-  up stagnant energy.
           portance of self-care and emotional bal-  nections with others.    Salt baths: Bathing in saltwater can
           ance. For many, observing this becomes                          help clear negative energy from the
           a chance to address stress, release neg-  Learn about your own aura   body and aura.
           ative energy, and cultivate positivity.   One way to start understanding your   Crystals: Stones like amethyst, clear
                                           aura is by exploring practices that allow   quartz, and selenite are believed to clear
           The science and spirituality of   you to sense or visualize it. Some indi-  and amplify auras.
           auras                           viduals believe they can “see” auras as
             While scientific studies on auras re-  colors or sense them as a feeling of   Seek professional aura readings
           main limited, the concept of an energetic   warmth or tingling. This perception can   Some practitioners, often known as
           field surrounding the body aligns with   be developed through meditation, mind-  energy healers or aura readers, special-
           certain biological phenomena. For in-  fulness, and visualization exercises.   ize in assessing auras. Aura photogra-

           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Aura photography of a smartphone                                                                  Aura photography of animals














           phy, often called Kirlian photography, is
           one method used to capture the energy
           field’s colors and intensity. While the in-
           terpretation of these photographs varies,
           they can offer insight into the current
           state of your energy and guide you to-
           ward practices for improvement.

           Develop self-awareness and
           emotional resilience
             Our emotions have a direct impact on
           our aura. Cultivating positive emotions,
           practicing gratitude, and releasing neg-
           ative thought patterns can significantly
           enhance your aura’s health. Journaling,
           seeking therapy, or talking to a trusted
           friend can help you process emotions                                                            Aura photography of sea animals
           and maintain a positive energetic bal-
           ance.

           Practice kindness and
           compassion
             Positive interactions with others can   flect a grounded, ambitious nature.
           strengthen and elevate our aura. Acts of   Orange: Linked to creativity, joy,
           kindness and compassion resonate bey-  and sociability. An orange aura often in-
           ond our physical selves, enhancing not   dicates a playful and warm personality.
           only our own energy but also that of   Yellow: Represents intellect, con-
           those around us. On Aura Awareness,   fidence, and happiness. Those with a
           practice intentional kindness, empathy,   yellow aura are often optimistic and cu-
           and understanding, and notice how this   rious.
           affects your mood and energy.     Green: Connected to healing, com-
                                           passion, and growth. Green auras often
           Understanding aura colors and   signify nurturing individuals.
           their meanings                    Blue: Reflects calm, intuition, and
             People who claim to see auras often   communication. A blue aura may indi-
           describe them in terms of colors, with   cate a person with a peaceful and honest
           each color believed to carry specific   nature.                                                 The aura effect of a woman
           meanings. Here’s a basic overview of   Purple: Related to spirituality and
           common aura colors:             imagination. A purple aura suggests a
             Red: Associated with physical   deep connection to one’s inner world
           energy, passion, and vitality. It may re-  and higher consciousness.

           26                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[cleansing and balancing practices can
                                                                           reduce stress, promote inner peace, and
                                                                           support physical health.
                                                                              Increased self-knowledge: Under-
                                                                           standing your energy helps you become
                                                                           more aware of your thoughts, emotions,
                                                                           and behaviors, encouraging personal
                                                                           growth.
                                                                              Greater spiritual connection: Aura
         Feet touching the grass for aura health                           The importance of aura awareness
                                                                           awareness can open doors to deeper
                                                                           spiritual practices, leading to a sense of
                                                                           purpose and fulfillment.


                                                                           in today’s world
                                                                              In an increasingly fast-paced and dig-
                                                                           itally driven world, it’s easy to lose
                                                                           touch with our inner selves. Aura
                                                                           Awareness is a reminder to pause, re-
                                                                           connect, and become mindful of the
                                                                           energy we carry and share with others.
                                                                           By doing so, we contribute to a more
                                                                           harmonious world, one individual at a
                                                                           time.

                                                                           Celebrating aura awareness every
                                                                           day
                                                                              By making aura awareness part of
                                                                           your daily routine, you can cultivate an
                                                                           energy field that not only reflects well-
                                                                           being but also promotes it. Simple prac-
                                                                           tices like daily meditation, mindful in-
                                                                           teractions, and regular aura cleansing
                                                                           can make a lasting difference.
                                                                              Aura Awareness reminds us of the
                                                                           profound power of our personal energy,
         Meditation in nature                                              that shapes our experiences. By under-
                                                                           an often unseen but ever-present force
                                                                           standing and nurturing our auras, we
                                                                           create lives filled with positivity, resil-
                                                                           ience, and compassion, qualities that en-
                                                                           hance our personal journeys and enrich
                                                                           the lives of those we touch.
                                             White: Represents purity and protec-  In closing, understanding the mag-
                                           tion. White auras are often seen in those   netic quality of certain people reminds
                                           who are balanced and spiritually at-  us of the powerful influence our energy
                                           tuned.                          has on those around us. When someone
                                             While these interpretations vary, un-  exudes a positive, balanced aura, it natu-
                                           derstanding aura colors can be a fun way   rally resonates with others, making them
                                                                           feel at ease and drawn to their presence.
                                           to explore personality traits and emo-
         An invisible magnetism that attracts anyone  How aura awareness can improve   tle energy we sense rather than the
                                           tional states.
                                                                              This magnetic attraction is often an
                                                                           unspoken connection, rooted in the sub-
                                                                           words we hear. By cultivating self-
                                           your life
                                             Embracing awareness of your aura
                                                                           awareness and nurturing a positive aura,
                                           can lead to positive changes in many
                                                                           we not only enhance our own well-being
                                                                           but also create a warm and inviting
                                           areas of life. Here’s how:
                                                                           energy that can inspire, comfort, and at-
                                             Improved relationships: Becoming
                                           more attuned to your energy helps you
                                                                           tract others on a deeper level. The in-
                                           understand how your emotions affect
                                                                           fluence of aura is a reminder of how
                                                                           profoundly we can impact the lives of
                                           others and can lead to healthier, more
                                           harmonious interactions.
                                             Enhanced well-being: Regular aura
                                                                           presence. ■
           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in   those around us simply through our   27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                             February 01-15, 2025










          ARIES                                            LIBRA
          March 21 - April 19                              Sept. 23 - October 22

                    This period brings fresh energy for career growth.   Libra, your career prospects improve; network-
                    Expect recognition at work, but avoid impulsive   ing helps. A surprise in love life keeps things in-
                    decisions. Romance flourishes for singles, while   teresting. Finances need planning; avoid impul-
                    couples strengthen their bonds. Health-wise, focus   sive purchases. Stay active to maintain energy
                    on fitness and stress management.                levels.

          TAURUS                                           SCORPIO
          April 20 - May 20                                October 23 - November 21

                    Finances improve, but budgeting is key.          Scorpio, transformation is on the horizon. Career
                    Relationships may require patience, listen more   growth is slow but steady. Relationships require
                    and react less. Work demands attention; don’t    clarity; avoid unnecessary arguments. Finances
                    ignore details. Health remains stable, but avoid   are stable, but saving is advised. Health requires
                    overindulgence in food and leisure.              attention to diet.

          GEMINI                                           SAGITTARIUS
          May 21 - June 20                                 Nov. 22 - December 21

                    A social period awaits, with new connections     Sagittarius, An adventurous time; travel or new
                    and friendships blossoming. Career-wise, team-   experiences may arise. Professionally, innova-
                    work leads to success. Love life sees exciting   tive ideas shine. Love life is exciting for singles,
                    developments. Health-wise, ensure a balanced     while couples find renewed passion. Physical fit-
                    diet and regular exercise.                       ness is key.

          CANCER                                           CAPRICORN
          June 21 - July 22                                December 22 - January 19

                    A career breakthrough is possible, but effort is   Capricorn, Hard work pays off in career matters.
                    needed. Family matters may demand attention;     Financial stability grows, but avoid risky deals.
                    stay calm. Financially, be cautious with invest-  Family time brings joy. Relationships require
                    ments. Emotional well-being is crucial; engage   honesty. Your health remains good with a focus
                    in self-care activities.                         on rest.

          LEO                                              AQUARIUS
          July 23 - August 22                              January 20 - February 18

                    Confidence is your asset this period. A leader-  Aquarius, creativity flows, benefiting work and
                    ship opportunity arises at work. Love life sees   personal life. Your romantic opportunities are
                    passion but beware of misunderstandings. Fi-     strong. Financially, expect gains from past in-
                    nances are steady, and travel may be on the      vestments. Health is good, but emotional balance
                    cards. Prioritize relaxation to avoid burnout.   is key.

          VIRGO                                            PISCES
          August 23 - September 22                         February 19 - March 20

                    A methodical approach at work brings rewards.    Pisces, Intuition guides you well. Work sees pos-
                    Financial gains are likely, but avoid overspend-  itive changes. Love life is harmonious, but you
                    ing. Relationships require patience; open conver-  set clear boundaries. Don’t forget to avoid finan-
                    sations help. Health is stable, but mental relaxa-  cial risks. Your health remains good, but relaxa-
                    tion is needed.                                  tion is essential.


           28                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           A landmark income tax relief for   measures. With over 30 crore attendees
           the middle class                expected, the authorities must prioritize
             The Union Budget 2025 has     crowd management and emergency pro-  ible journey of Hritik, who regained mo-
           introduced a ground-breaking income tax   tocols to prevent further accidents.   bility through a successful bilateral hand
           relief that significantly benefits taxpayers,   The government's decision to restrict   transplant, highlights the power of resil-
           particularly the middle class. With the   VIP movement on significant bathing   ience, medical innovation, and hope.
           new tax regime, individuals earning up to   days is a positive step. Nevertheless,   Sanjay Kumar Manglik, Mumbai,
           ₹12 lakh will now be exempt from income   more robust infrastructure and real-time   Maharashtra, India
           tax, a substantial increase from the   monitoring are essential to ensure the
           previous threshold of ₹7 lakh. This change   safety of all pilgrims. As we honor this
           is expected to provide approximately ₹1   sacred tradition, let us not compromise   A heartfelt tribute to Dr.
           lakh crore in relief to taxpayers,   on the well-being of our fellow devo-  Merajuddin Ahmed
           enhancing their disposable income and   tees.                      Wonderful tribute to the departed
           stimulating economic activity.   Rakesh K. Sharma, Lucknow, Uttar   soul. Dr. Merajuddin was loved not only
             Additionally, the rebate under Section   Pradesh, India       in Meerut but across Pan India. Despite
           87A has been raised to ₹60,000, further                         not holding any position of power in his
           easing financial burdens. These measures                        later years, his popularity grew manifold
           reflect a commendable commitment to   A hopeful new beginning for Hritik   due to his unwavering love for the
           supporting the middle class and fostering   The recent story of Hritik Singh Pari-  weaker sections of society, including
           economic growth. By prioritizing   har, who received a new pair of hands   farmers and the poor. His wisdom and
           taxpayer relief, the government is taking a   after a tragic train accident, is a testa-  invaluable suggestions on local matters,
           crucial step towards a more equitable tax   ment to human resilience and medical   and particularly on education, were gen-
           system.                         advancement. Losing both hands in such   erously offered to all who sought his
             Such reforms are crucial for fostering a   a horrific incident could have shattered   guidance.
           more equitable tax system and supporting   anyone's spirit, yet Hritik's journey   His passing is indeed a great loss for
           the aspirations of millions of taxpayers.   showcases the power of hope and deter-  Meerut, as well as for his family,
           Bushra Shaikh, Pune, Maharashtra,   mination.                   friends, and admirers. His elder brother,
           India                             His successful bilateral hand trans-  Dr. Siraj, was a close friend of mine, and
                                           plant not only restores his physical abil-  Dr. Merajuddin always treated me with
                                           ities but also symbolizes a fresh start for   the same affection and warmth. His chil-
           Concerns regarding Maha Kumbh   him and his family. It is heartening to   dren; Faiz Mehmood, Badar Mehmood,
           safety                          see how medical professionals are push-  and daughter Aamra, along with his
             The ongoing Maha Kumbh Mela in   ing the boundaries of what's possible in   wife, Mrs. Maliha, stood by him as pil-
           Prayagraj, celebrated as the world's   transplant surgery. This remarkable   lars of strength and grace.
           largest religious gathering, has drawn   achievement should inspire further in-  His memories and noble deeds will
           millions of devotees to the sacred   vestments in healthcare innovations.   continue to inspire us for years to come.
           Triveni Sangam. However, recent tragic   As we celebrate Hritik's recovery, let   May Allah grant him highest place in
           incidents, including a stampede during   us also advocate for improved safety   Jannah. Aameen.
           the auspicious Mauni Amavasya, have   measures on our railways to prevent   Shahid A. Siddiqui IRS (Retd.), Tali-
           raised serious concerns about safety   such accidents in the future. The incred-  mabad, Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           FEBRUARY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 www.revoir.in                               29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                      |
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024


                                                                               V
                                                                               V
                                                                             .in
                                                                              .in
                                                                                ol. 3, No.2 |
                                                                                ol. 3, No.1 |
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                .in
                                                                                        DECEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                          AUGUST

                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                   16 2025
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                                   01 2025
                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                         OCT

                                                                                        |

                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                         |
                                                                                          | AUGUST 01 202432
           32
           32
           32
           3232
                                                        .revoir www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | NOVEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | OCTOBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                    www
                                                    www
           32
           3232
           32
           32                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025OBER 16 2023
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32
           32
           32
                                                                     www
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                    www
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in REVOIR
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                       www
                                                                        .revoir
                                                             .in
                                                            www
                                                        .revoir
                                                             .in
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                                .revoir
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>