<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 16  I  SEPTEMBER 16 2024  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I  PHOTO COURTESY: BJP.ORG





               5



                                                            11













                                                             8                                        27
















           4-Editorial                                     24-Workout that fits your life
           5-Modi’s Journey: Dreams to destiny             27-Uniting cultures through cinema

           8-Heart health matters                          30-Horoscopes

           11-The voice that defined an era                31-Letters

           15-Turning vision into action
           18-Balance work and life

           21-The power of being single















           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Early Wrap-Up
     EDITORIAL  The new                                                             Editor-in-Chief




                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           work revolution                                                        Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                           n today’s fast-paced work environment,   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                           the pressure to work long hours often
                                        Icomes at the expense of personal well-     Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        being. The concept of the 4pm Finish Day
                                        presents a refreshing alternative, aiming to   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        boost productivity while prioritizing mental   Sushil Kumar
                                        health and work-life balance. As companies
                                        worldwide begin to experiment with        Social Media Editor
                                        flexible work hours, the idea of finishing   Vishakha Sharma
                                        the day earlier is quickly gaining ground as
                                        a practical and effective approach to   Art & Graphics Director
                                        modern work culture.                         Vipin Agarwal
                                           The appeal of a 4pm Finish Day lies in
                                        its simplicity. Rather than asking employees
           to work more, it encourages them to work smarter. Numerous studies have shown
           that productivity does not increase with longer hours. In fact, after a certain point,   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           fatigue sets in, leading to diminished focus and effectiveness. By condensing the
           workday, employees are motivated to focus on high-priority tasks and cut out   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           unnecessary distractions. This, in turn, leads to higher-quality output in less time.   Editor, United News of India, New
             Beyond productivity, the mental health benefits of a shorter workday are   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           undeniable. As burnout and stress become increasingly common in many industries,   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           finding ways to alleviate this pressure is more critical than ever. An early finish offers   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           employees time to unwind, pursue personal interests, and spend time with family—  Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           all vital components of a well-rounded life. This balanced approach helps prevent   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           burnout, fostering a healthier, happier workforce.
             However, the 4pm Finish Day is not without its challenges. Not all industries can   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           easily accommodate an earlier end to the day. Customer service roles, healthcare, and   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           other essential sectors may find it difficult to implement such a change without
           disrupting operations. Moreover, some traditional workplaces may resist the shift,   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           viewing longer hours as a sign of commitment and hard work. Overcoming these
           cultural barriers requires a clear understanding of the benefits and a willingness to   Phone +91 20 40199102
           adapt.                                                            Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             For companies ready to embrace the 4pm finish, the key is to set realistic   Baner Road,
           expectations and focus on outcomes rather than hours. Managers should ensure that   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           employees are not simply asked to fit the same amount of work into a shorter time   Email revoir@post.com
           frame but are supported in working efficiently. Creating an environment where   Website www.revoir.in
           productivity and well-being go hand in hand can make this transition smoother and
           more successful.
             The 4pm Finish Day represents a forward-thinking approach to work. By   Legal Advisor
           embracing this shift, businesses can promote healthier, more productive teams while   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           offering employees the time they need to enjoy life outside of work. It’s a small
           change with the potential for significant impact, signaling a move towards a more   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           balanced and thoughtful work culture.                            all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[COVER STORY









































           Modi’s Journey



           Dreams to destiny







           What is undeniable, however, is the impact Narendra Modi has had on

           India’s political and social landscape. His journey from a small town in

           Gujarat to the Prime Minister’s Office is a story of ambition, resilience, and a
           relentless pursuit of goals. By Naina Kapoor



                 n September 17, 2024, India   cal landscape of India but also touched   him the values of hard work, persever-
                 celebrates the 74th birthday of   the lives of millions.   ance, and humility, traits that would later
           Oone of its most influential                                    define his political career.
           leaders, Narendra Damodardas Modi.   Early life and struggles      As a child, Modi was known for his
           From his humble beginnings in a small   Narendra Modi was born in 1950 in   inquisitiveness and passion for reading.
           town in Gujarat to his ascension as the   Vadnagar, a small town in Gujarat. The   Despite the economic hardships, he
           Prime Minister of India, Modi’s life is a   third of six children, his early life was   managed to secure an education, attend-
           testament to the power of determination,   marked by financial struggles. His   ing the local school in Vadnagar. His
           political acumen, and a relentless pursuit   father, Damodardas Mulchand Modi, ran   teachers remember him as a diligent stu-
           of goals. This article delves into his   a tea stall at the local railway station,   dent, particularly interested in history
           journey, exploring the human side of a   where young Narendra often helped.   and politics. Even at a young age, Modi
           man who has not only shaped the politi-  These humble beginnings instilled in   exhibited leadership qualities, often or-

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Young Narendra Modi                                                                               Narendra Modi in his childhood









           ganizing plays and events in school.   periences deepened his understanding of   what came to be known as the ‘Gujarat
           These early experiences laid the founda-  India’s diverse cultures and religious   Model’ of development. This model fo-
           tion for his future role as a leader.   philosophies.           cused on industrialization, infrastructure
             Modi’s early encounters with the   Upon his return, Modi plunged into   development, and attracting foreign in-
           Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh (RSS) at   the political arena, joining the BJP in   vestment. Under his leadership, Gujarat
           the age of eight significantly shaped his   1985, when the party was still in its nas-  saw rapid economic growth, with im-
           worldview. He became a pracharak   cent stages. His organizational skills and   proved roads, electricity, and a thriving
           (campaigner) for the RSS, which intro-  dedication quickly earned him rec-  business environment. Modi’s vision for
           duced him to the world of politics and   ognition. Modi played a crucial role in   Gujarat was clear: to make it a hub of
           social service. The disciplined and na-  strengthening the party’s base in Guja-  industry and innovation.
           tionalist ideology of the RSS resonated   rat, working closely with senior leaders
           deeply with Modi, and he gradually rose   like L.K. Advani and Atal Bihari   The road to the Prime Minister’s
           through its ranks, developing a strong   Vajpayee. His efforts bore fruit in 1995   office
           network and honing his leadership   when the BJP came to power in Gujarat   By 2013, Modi had become a house-
           skills.                         for the first time.             hold name in India. His success in Guja-
                                             Modi’s rise within the BJP was mete-  rat, combined with his oratory skills and
           The making of a leader          oric. In 2001, he was appointed as the   a carefully crafted image as a man of the
             In 1971, a young Modi made a life-  Chief Minister of Gujarat, a role that   people, made him the frontrunner for the
           altering decision to leave his home and   catapulted him into the national spot-  Prime Ministerial candidate of the BJP.
           travel across India. This journey was not   light. His tenure as Chief Minister was   In 2014, Modi led the BJP to a historic
           just a physical one but also a spiritual   marked by significant economic growth   victory, winning 282 seats in the Lok
           and intellectual quest. He spent two   and development in the state.   Sabha, the first time a single party had
           years traveling to various ashrams, in-                         secured a majority since 1984.
           cluding the Belur Math in West Bengal   The Gujarat model          Modi’s victory was seen as a man-
           and the Ramakrishna Mission. These ex-  As Chief Minister, Modi championed   date for change. His campaign had















         Narendra Modi in his youth                                                                        As a pracharak (campaigner) in the RSS











           6                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Modi as Chief Minister of Gujarat













           promised economic growth, devel-
           opment, and good governance under the
           slogan ‘Sabka Saath, Sabka Vikas’ (To-
           gether with all, Development for all). As
           Prime Minister, Modi set out to trans-
           form India, launching ambitious pro-
           grams such as ‘Make in India,’ ‘Digital
           India,’ and ‘Swachh Bharat Abhiyan’
           (Clean India Mission).

           The human side of Narendra Modi
             Beyond the political persona, Naren-
           dra Modi is a man of deep convictions
           and simplicity. Despite his high office,                                                        Modi's swearing-In as Prime Minister (2014)
           he has often spoken about his love for
           nature, particularly his morning walks
           and photography. Modi’s personal life is
           marked by discipline; he follows a strict
           daily routine, which includes yoga and
           meditation. His frugal lifestyle and
           vegetarian diet have been widely dis-
           cussed, reflecting his roots in Gujarat’s   often accompanies a life dedicated to   leadership will continue to shape the na-
           culture.                        politics.                       tion’s trajectory. On his birthday, it is
             Modi is also known for his communi-                           worth reflecting not just on his achieve-
           cation skills, both in terms of public   The legacy of Narendra Modi   ments but also on the human side of a
           speaking and his use of social media. He   As Narendra Modi celebrates his   man who has dedicated his life to the
           has effectively used platforms like   74th birthday, his legacy remains a topic   service of his country. ■
           Twitter and Instagram to connect with   of intense debate. For his supporters,
           people, sharing glimpses of his life,   Modi is a visionary leader who has
           thoughts, and government initiatives.   transformed India, bringing devel-
           His monthly radio program, ‘Mann Ki   opment, stability, and pride to the na-
           Baat,’ has become a platform for him to   tion.
           directly address the nation, sharing his   What is undeniable, however, is the
           thoughts on various issues and encour-  impact Narendra Modi has had on
           aging citizens to participate in nation-  India’s political and social landscape.
           building.                       His journey from a small town in Guja-
             However, Modi’s journey has not   rat to the Prime Minister’s Office is a
           been without personal sacrifices. His   story of ambition, resilience, and a re-
           decision to remain unmarried and devote   lentless pursuit of goals. Whether one
           his life to the nation has often been   agrees with his policies or not, Modi’s
           highlighted as an example of his com-  influence on India will be felt for gener-
           mitment to public service. Yet, this   ations to come.
           choice also reflects the loneliness that   As India looks to the future, Modi’s

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[World Heart Day



     INSIGHT  HEART HEALTH






           MATTERS






           By raising awareness and encouraging people to

           adopt heart-healthy behaviors, we can

           significantly reduce the impact of cardiovascular
           disease. By Aarav Sharma




                                                                           encourage lifestyle changes, and advo-
                                                                           cate for government policies that sup-
                                                                           port better heart health.

                                                                           The importance of heart health
                                                                              The heart is the most vital organ in
                                                                           the body, responsible for pumping blood
                                                                           and supplying oxygen and nutrients to
                                                                           the tissues while removing carbon diox-
                                                                           ide and waste. Given its critical role,
                                                                           maintaining a healthy heart is essential
                                                                           for overall well-being. However, mod-
                                                                           ern lifestyles, increasing stress, poor
                                                                           diets, and sedentary behavior are con-
                                                                           tributing to a rise in cardiovascular dis-
                                                                           eases worldwide.
                                                                              Heart disease affects people of all
                                                                           ages and backgrounds. According to
                                                                           WHO, cardiovascular diseases cause
                                                                           31% of global deaths, with more than
                  orld Heart Day is observed   lished in 1999 by the World Heart Fed-  75% of these deaths occurring in low-
                  every year on September 29   eration (WHF) in partnership with the   and middle-income countries. CVD is
           Wto raise awareness about car-  World Health Organization (WHO). The   an umbrella term that includes heart at-
           diovascular diseases (CVD) and pro-  goal was to draw global attention to the   tacks, strokes, heart failure, and arrhyth-
           mote heart health globally. Initiated by   fact that heart diseases and stroke are the   mia, among other conditions.
           the World Heart Federation (WHF), it   world’s leading cause of death, respon-  What makes heart disease particu-
           serves as a reminder of the importance   sible for over 18 million deaths each   larly alarming is that it is often preventa-
           of heart care and a platform to educate   year. By focusing on awareness and edu-  ble. While genetic predisposition plays a
           individuals about how they can reduce   cation, WHF aims to create a healthier   role, lifestyle factors such as smoking,
           their risk of heart disease, the leading   environment, encourage heart-healthy   unhealthy diets, physical inactivity, and
           cause of death worldwide. In this article,   behavior, and ultimately reduce the bur-  excessive alcohol consumption are the
           we explore the origins, significance,   den of cardiovascular disease.   leading causes of CVD.
           common risk factors, preventive meas-  Initially, World Heart Day was cele-
           ures, and ongoing global initiatives   brated on the last Sunday of September,   Common risk factors for
           aimed at tackling heart disease.   but in 2011, September 29 was set as the   cardiovascular disease
                                           fixed date for the annual observance.   Unhealthy diet: Diets high in trans
           The origins of world heart day   The day serves as a vital platform to   fats, saturated fats, salt, and sugar signif-
             World Heart Day was first estab-  educate people on preventive measures,   icantly increase the risk of heart disease.

           8                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Overconsumption of processed foods
           and sugary drinks can lead to obesity,
           diabetes, and high cholesterol, all of
           which are risk factors for CVD.
             Physical inactivity: A sedentary life-
           style increases the likelihood of devel-
           oping hypertension (high blood pres-
           sure), obesity, and poor cholesterol
           levels. Regular physical activity
           strengthens the heart, improves blood
           circulation, and helps control weight.
             Tobacco use: Smoking is a major
           contributor to heart disease. Chemicals
           in tobacco smoke damage the lining of
           blood vessels, leading to atherosclerosis
           (hardening of the arteries), which re-
           stricts blood flow to the heart.
             Alcohol consumption: Excessive al-
           cohol intake is linked to high blood
           pressure, irregular heartbeats, and weak-
           ened heart muscles, all of which in-
           crease the risk of CVD.
             Stress: Chronic stress contributes to
           hypertension and unhealthy behaviors
           such as overeating, smoking, or drink-
           ing, which indirectly affect heart health.
             High blood pressure (hyperten-
           sion): Hypertension is often called a "si-
           lent killer" because it may not show
           symptoms but gradually damages ar-
           teries and increases the risk of heart at-
           tacks and strokes.
             Diabetes: High blood sugar damages
           blood vessels and the nerves that control
           the heart. People with diabetes are more
           likely to develop heart disease.
             Obesity: Excess body weight puts
           strain on the heart and is associated with
           high cholesterol, high blood pressure,
           and diabetes.                                                                                   Left: Cycling for heart health  Top: People exercising outdoors
             Age and family history: While life-
           style factors are controllable, some risk
           factors such as age and genetics are un-
           avoidable. People over 65 or those with
           a family history of heart disease should
           be particularly vigilant.         Whole grains: Foods such as brown
                                           rice, oats, and quinoa help control cho-
           Prevention of heart disease     lesterol and blood sugar levels.
             While cardiovascular disease remains   Healthy fats: Unsaturated fats found
           a leading cause of death, much can be   in olive oil, nuts, seeds, and fish reduce
           done to prevent it. The key to reducing   cholesterol levels.
           heart disease lies in making informed,   Reduced salt intake: High sodium
           proactive lifestyle choices. Here are   levels are linked to hypertension, a
           some simple steps to prevent heart dis-  major contributor to heart disease.
           ease:
                                           Regular exercise
           Eat a heart-healthy diet          Regular physical activity can reduce
             A balanced diet is crucial to main-  the risk of heart disease by strengthen-
           taining heart health. Focus on:   ing the heart and improving blood cir-
             Fruits and vegetables: Rich in vita-  culation. Aim for at least 150 minutes of               Yoga for heart health
           mins, minerals, and fiber, these help   moderate aerobic activity or 75 minutes
           lower blood pressure and reduce inflam-  of vigorous exercise weekly. Even sim-
           mation.                         ple activities like walking, swimming, or

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[cycling can make a significant differ-  and promote mental well-being.   talks, walks, and fitness challenges.
           ence.                                                           These events are designed to engage
                                           Monitor blood pressure and      communities in a fun, participatory way,
           Quit smoking                    cholesterol levels              while also disseminating essential infor-
             Smoking is one of the most signifi-  Regular check-ups with your doctor   mation about heart health.
           cant risk factors for heart disease. By   can help you monitor your blood pres-
           quitting smoking, you improve blood   sure, cholesterol, and blood sugar levels,   The role of governments and
           circulation, lower your blood pressure,   ensuring that any potential issues are ad-  organizations
           and reduce the likelihood of a heart at-  dressed early.           Governments and international or-
           tack or stroke. Nicotine replacement                            ganizations play a crucial role in com-
           therapies and support groups can help   World heart day themes and global   bating cardiovascular disease. Policies
           those struggling with tobacco addiction.   initiatives          that promote healthier environments,
                                             Each year, World Heart Day adopts a   such as reducing tobacco consumption,
           Limit alcohol intake            specific theme to focus attention on par-  promoting healthier food options, and
             Moderate alcohol consumption may   ticular aspects of heart health. Recent   improving access to healthcare, are es-
           have some protective effects on the   themes have included "Use Heart to   sential for reducing the global burden of
           heart, but excessive drinking can be   Connect" and "Heart Heroes," empha-  CVD.
           harmful. Limit alcohol intake to rec-  sizing the importance of connecting   The WHF collaborates with govern-
           ommended levels—no more than one   people to heart health initiatives and   ments, NGOs, healthcare providers, and
           drink per day for women and two for   celebrating individuals who champion   the private sector to initiate heart health
           men.                            heart care. Campaigns often include the   programs worldwide. The “25 by 25”
                                           use of digital platforms, community   initiative is one example, aiming to re-
           Manage stress                   events, and public health messages to   duce premature deaths from non-com-
             Long-term stress can harm heart   drive home the importance of preven-  municable diseases, including cardio-
           health by raising blood pressure and en-  tion.                 vascular disease, by 25% by 2025.
           couraging unhealthy habits. Techniques   Organizations around the world mark   World Heart Day serves as a re-
           like meditation, yoga, deep breathing,   World Heart Day with activities such as   minder that heart disease remains a criti-
           and mindfulness can help reduce stress   heart-health screenings, educational   cal global health issue. By raising
                                                                           awareness and encouraging people to
                                                                           adopt heart-healthy behaviors, we can
                                                                           significantly reduce the impact of car-
                                                                           diovascular disease. Prevention, early
         Bottom: A doctor checking blood pressure                          Whether through healthier lifestyles,
                                                                           detection, and intervention are key to
                                                                           ensuring a future where heart disease is
                                                                           less prevalent, and more lives are saved.
                                                                           supportive communities, or effective
                                                                           public health policies, we all have a role
                                                                           to play in protecting our hearts and pro-
                                                                           moting heart health for all. ■
































           10                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Lata Mangeshkar                                                 five siblings, and all of them went on to

                                                                           make a mark in the Indian music indus-
                                                                           try, with her sisters Asha Bhosle and
                                                                           Usha Mangeshkar being notable singers
           The voice that                                                  themselves.                           SPOTLIGHT
                                                                              Her early initiation into music came
                                                                           from her father, who recognized her im-
                                                                           mense talent and began teaching her
                                                                           classical music. However, tragedy struck
                                                                           the family when Pandit Deenanath
           defined an era                                                  passed away in 1942, leaving a young
                                                                           Lata to shoulder the responsibility of
                                                                           supporting her family. This marked the
                                                                           beginning of her journey in the Indian
                                                                           film industry.
                                                                              Lata began her career at the age of
           Lata Mangeshkar’s legacy is not confined to the sheer           13, singing for Marathi films. Her first
           number of songs she sang or the awards she received.            song, "Naachu Yaa Gade," was for the
                                                                           Marathi film Kiti Hasaal in 1942. Ho-
           Her voice became the soundtrack of millions of lives,           wever, it was her entry into Bollywood
                                                                           in the late 1940s that set her on a path to
           capturing every emotion from joy and love to sorrow             becoming a legend.
           and patriotism. By Anaya Gupta                                  Rise to stardom

                                                                              The turning point in Lata Mangesh-
                                                                           kar’s career came in 1949 when she
                ata Mangeshkar, often referred to   birth anniversary, let us explore the life   sang "Aayega Aanewala" for the film
                as the "Nightingale of India," was   and legacy of this extraordinary singer.   Mahal. This song, composed by Khem-
           Lmore than just a playback singer.                              chand Prakash, became a sensation and
           She was an icon, a voice that tran-  Early life and musical beginnings   established Lata as the leading playback
           scended generations and genres, leaving   Lata Mangeshkar was born into a   singer in the Hindi film industry. Her
           an indelible mark on Indian cinema and   musical family. Her father, Pandit Dee-  voice was fresh, melodious, and had a
           music. Born on September 28, 1929, in   nanath Mangeshkar, was a classical   unique ability to convey deep emotions.
           Indore, Madhya Pradesh, her contrib-  singer and theater artist, and her mother,   Filmmakers and composers soon real-
           ution to Indian music and culture is un-  Shevanti, belonged to the musical Deva-  ized that Lata’s voice could elevate the
           matched. As we remember her on her   dasi community. Lata was the eldest of   narrative of their films, making her an





































           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    11  Lata Mangeshkar: A paly back singer who can never be forgotten]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Receiving the Bharat Ratna  Lata Mangeshkar with S.D. Burman and R.D. Burman










                                                        Top left: Young Lata
                                                        Left: Lata with Indira Gandhi




           indispensable part of the industry.   in over 36 languages, including Marathi,   acters. Her emotional depth and impec-
             In the decades that followed, Lata   Bengali, Tamil, Telugu, Malayalam,   cable technique allowed her to connect
           Mangeshkar became synonymous with   Kannada, Gujarati, and even some for-  with the audience at an intimate level,
           playback singing in Indian cinema. Her   eign languages. Her ability to adapt to   making her songs unforgettable.
           collaboration with legendary music di-  different linguistic and cultural contexts   The rise of Lata Mangeshkar also
           rectors such as S.D. Burman, R.D. Bur-  made her a pan-Indian icon.   brought about significant changes in the
           man, Shankar-Jaikishan, Naushad,   Her repertoire extended beyond film   Indian music industry. Her success
           Madan Mohan, and Laxmikant-Pyarelal   songs. Lata also lent her voice to bha-  prompted a shift in the perception of
           resulted in some of the most iconic   jans, ghazals, classical compositions,   playback singers, who until then were
           songs in Bollywood history. Songs like   and patriotic songs. Her rendition of "Ae   often seen as mere background artists.
           "Pyar Kiya To Darna Kya" from Mug-  Mere Watan Ke Logon" in 1963, a trib-  Lata’s prominence and the demand for
           hal-e-Azam (1960), "Lag Ja Gale" from   ute to Indian soldiers who had died in   her voice elevated the status of playback
           Woh Kaun Thi? (1964), and "Ajeeb   the Sino-Indian war, moved Prime Min-  singers, giving them recognition and re-
           Dastan Hai Yeh" from Dil Apna Aur   ister Jawaharlal Nehru to tears and be-  spect on par with actors and composers.
           Preet Parai (1960) are just a few exam-  came a timeless patriotic anthem.
           ples of her versatility and unmatched                           A career spanning over seven
           talent.                         The icon of playback singing    decades
                                             Lata Mangeshkar’s voice became the   Lata Mangeshkar’s career spanned
           Versatility across languages and   voice of Indian heroines for over five   over seven decades, making her one of
           genres                          decades. Whether it was the tragic roles   the longest-serving and most prolific
             One of the most remarkable aspects   portrayed by Meena Kumari, the viva-  playback singers in the world. With over
           of Lata Mangeshkar’s career was her   ciousness of Madhubala, the elegance of   30,000 songs to her credit, she holds a
           ability to sing in multiple languages.   Nargis, or the innocence of Sridevi,   Guinness World Record for being the
           While she is most celebrated for her   Lata’s voice seamlessly captured the es-  most recorded artist in history.
           contributions to Hindi cinema, Lata sang   sence of these actresses and their char-  Her voice remained timeless. Even as

           12                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[new generations of singers and com-  in the form of professional rivalries,   joy and love to sorrow and patriotism.
           posers entered the industry, Lata con-  most notably with Mohammed Rafi, one   As we remember her on her birth anni-
           tinued to dominate with her ethereal   of the greatest male playback singers of   versary, we celebrate not just a singer
           voice. In the 1990s, she lent her voice to   the time. The two had a well-doc-  but a cultural icon whose contribution to
           songs like "Dil To Pagal Hai" from the   umented disagreement over royalty pay-  Indian music and cinema will remain
           eponymous film (1997) and "Jiya Jale"   ments in the 1960s, which led to a brief   timeless.
           from Dil Se (1998), proving that her   period of estrangement. However, they   Her songs will continue to echo
           voice could resonate with contemporary   eventually reconciled, and their collabo-  through the corridors of Indian cinema,
           audiences as well.              rations produced some of the most   and her voice will forever resonate in
             Her accolades are numerous. Lata   memorable duets in Indian cinema.   the hearts of those who grew up listen-
           Mangeshkar was honored with several                             ing to her melodies. Lata Mangeshkar
           prestigious awards, including the Bharat   Legacy and influence   truly was, and always will be, the voice
           Ratna, India’s highest civilian honor, in   Lata Mangeshkar’s influence on In-  of India. ■
           2001. She was also awarded the Padma   dian music is immeasurable. She set the
           Bhushan (1969), Padma Vibhushan   gold standard for playback singing, in-
           (1999), and the Dadasaheb Phalke   spiring countless singers, including her
           Award (1989), among many others. In-  own sister Asha Bhosle, who went on to
           ternationally, she was recognized with   carve her niche in the industry. Singers
           the Legion of Honour by France in   like Shreya Ghoshal, Alka Yagnik, and
           2007.                           Sunidhi Chauhan have all cited Lata as
                                           their inspiration.
           Challenges and triumphs           Her contribution to Indian music has
             Despite her immense success, Lata   also been acknowledged globally. She
           Mangeshkar faced her share of chal-  was one of the few Indian artists whose
           lenges. In the early stages of her career,   work transcended national borders, earn-
           she struggled to find a foothold in the   ing her a devoted fanbase worldwide.
           industry dominated by established
           singers. Her high-pitched voice was ini-  The eternal voice                                     During leisure time
                                             Lata Mangeshkar’s legacy is not con-
           tially criticized, and she was often com-
         Bottom: Lata Mangeshkar performing live  sistence helped her overcome these ob-  voice became the soundtrack of millions
                                           fined to the sheer number of songs she
           pared unfavorably to her contempo-
                                           sang or the awards she received. Her
           raries.
             However, Lata’s dedication and per-
                                           of lives, capturing every emotion from
           stacles. She worked tirelessly, constantly
           honing her skills and evolving as a
           singer. Her decision to take classical
           music lessons under Ustad Aman Ali
           Khan further refined her technique, al-
                                                                                                           Lata with Balasaheb Thackeray
           lowing her to master the nuances of In-
           dian classical music, which she inte-
           grated into her playback singing.
             Another significant challenge came















                                                                                                           With Hridaynath Mangeshkar












           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[The dreamer’s Spirit




           Turning vision                                                                                        IN-DEPTH







           into action







           World Dream Day is a celebration of human potential and the power of dreams.

           It serves as a reminder that our aspirations, when nurtured and pursued with
           determination, can lead to extraordinary outcomes. By Riya Verma




                  orld Dream Day, celebrated
                  on September 25th every
           Wyear, is an international day
           dedicated to empowering individuals,
           communities, and organizations to
           dream big, set visionary goals, and take
           action toward achieving them. It serves
           as a reminder of the power of dreams
           and aspirations, not only for personal
           fulfillment but also for creating positive
           change in the world. The day encour-
           ages people to reflect on their dreams
           and ambitions, work toward making
           them a reality, and collaborate with
           others to build a better future.

           The origins of world dream day
             The idea of World Dream Day was
           conceived by Ozioma Egwuonwu, a
           transformation strategist, and founder of   workshops, seminars, community
           BurnBright International, an organiza-  events, and online campaigns that in-
           tion focused on helping people and or-  spire individuals to pursue their dreams,
           ganizations achieve their full potential.   no matter how big or small.
           Ozioma launched World Dream Day in
           2012 with a clear vision: to create a   The importance of dreams
           global movement that encourages   Dreams are often seen as intangible
           people to take responsibility for their   thoughts, desires, or visions of the fu-
           dreams and make them actionable.   ture. They reflect our deepest aspirations
           Through this initiative, she aimed to   and can drive us to achieve greatness.
           foster a culture of hope, vision, and   Psychologically, dreams serve as a
           proactive change.               source of motivation, providing individ-
             World Dream Day has grown from a   uals with a sense of purpose and direc-
           grassroots initiative into an international   tion in life. A dream can be as simple as
           celebration, with participants from over   mastering a new skill or as ambitious as
           50 countries engaging in various activ-  changing the world. Regardless of the
           ities aimed at personal growth, com-  size or scope of the dream, the process
           munity development, and global trans-  of working toward it brings a sense of
           formation. The day is marked by   accomplishment and fulfillment.

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[World Dream Day emphasizes the
           idea that dreams are not just personal
           ambitions; they have the potential to im-
           pact entire communities and even the
           world. By encouraging people to ac-
           tively pursue their dreams, the day pro-
           motes the notion that collective action
           can lead to significant social and global
           transformation. This collective vision
           forms the core of the movement, as
           dreamers around the world are inspired                                                          Determination to dream and make it come true
           to collaborate, share ideas, and take con-
           crete steps toward solving societal chal-
           lenges.
           Themes and focus areas
             Each year, World Dream Day re-
           volves around a specific theme to guide
           participants in focusing their energy and
           intentions. These themes often address
           relevant global issues or personal devel-
           opment goals. For example, past themes
           have included topics like “Dream To-
           gether,” which encouraged collaboration
           and teamwork, and “Reimagine,” which
           urged people to rethink the future in
           light of global challenges such as the
           COVID-19 pandemic.
             The focus areas of World Dream Day
           encompass various aspects of life, in-                                                          The process of turning vision into action
           cluding:
             Personal growth: Encouraging indi-
           viduals to reflect on their personal aspi-
           rations, strengths, and passions.
             Education: Fostering a love for learn-
           ing and encouraging people to dream
           about a future where education is acces-  tance of mental and physical well-being   Celebrating World Dream Day is a
           sible to all.                   in the pursuit of dreams.       deeply personal experience, as it re-
             Entrepreneurship: Inspiring budding   By focusing on these areas, World   volves around individual aspirations and
           entrepreneurs to innovate and create so-  Dream Day serves as a platform for in-  unique visions for the future. However,
           lutions for global challenges.   dividuals to harness their potential, set   there are several common ways to par-
             Social change: Motivating individ-  actionable goals, and work toward cre-  ticipate in this global movement:
           uals and organizations to work toward   ating a better world for themselves and   Setting and sharing goals: On World
           social justice, equality, and sustainabil-  others.             Dream Day, participants are encouraged
           ity.                                                            to write down their dreams, both big and
             Well-being: Highlighting the impor-  How to celebrate world dream day   small, and share them with others. This
                                                                           act of sharing helps to create a support-
                                                                           ive community of dreamers who can in-
                                                                           spire and motivate one another.
                                                                              Attending workshops and events:
                                                                           Many organizations and communities
                                                                           host events, workshops, and seminars on
                                                                           this day, focusing on personal devel-
                                                                           opment, leadership, and social impact.
         Books can play a positive role                                    dreams into reality.
                                                                           These events provide valuable tools and
                                                                           strategies to help individuals turn their
                                                                              Community engagement: World
                                                                           Dream Day also highlights the impor-
                                                                           tance of giving back to the community.
                                                                           Many participants take part in com-
                                                                           munity service projects, mentoring pro-
                                                                           grams, or charity initiatives to support

           16                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[others in achieving their dreams.   spired by World Dream Day, launched a   ment—it’s about collective action. The
             Collaborative projects: The day en-  project aimed at reducing plastic waste   day emphasizes the importance of
           courages collaboration between individ-  in their city. They created an innovative   dreaming together and working toward a
           uals, businesses, and organizations. This   recycling system that turned plastic   common goal. In today’s interconnected
           could involve starting a joint venture, or-  waste into construction materials, help-  world, global challenges such as climate
           ganizing a community event, or simply   ing to address both environmental and   change, inequality, and poverty require
           working together to brainstorm ideas for   housing challenges. Their dream of cre-  collaborative solutions. World Dream
           making positive change.         ating a cleaner, more sustainable com-  Day fosters a sense of unity by encour-
             Reflection and mindfulness: Dream-  munity became a reality, and their proj-  aging people from all walks of life to
           ing is not just about ambition; it’s also   ect has since gained international   come together, share their dreams, and
           about clarity and mindfulness. Some   recognition.              work toward a shared vision for a better
           people use World Dream Day as an op-  Similarly, in India, a group of women   world.
           portunity to meditate, reflect on their   from rural areas came together on World   In an era where many face uncer-
           personal goals, and assess their progress.   Dream Day to discuss their dreams of fi-  tainties and challenges, World Dream
           This reflective practice allows individ-  nancial independence. With the support   Day provides hope. It reminds us that
           uals to realign their dreams with their   of local NGOs, they were able to start   our dreams are powerful forces that can
           values and take focused action.   small businesses and cooperatives that   drive change, not just for ourselves but
                                           not only provided them with a steady in-  for future generations. By promoting a
           Stories of inspiration          come but also empowered them to be-  culture of dreaming and doing, the day
             World Dream Day has inspired   come leaders in their communities.   inspires individuals to believe in their
           countless individuals and organizations   These stories illustrate the transfor-  potential and contribute to a brighter fu-
           to pursue their dreams and make mean-  mative power of dreams and how World   ture.
           ingful contributions to society. Some of   Dream Day serves as a catalyst for   World Dream Day is a celebration of
           the most inspiring stories involve people   change by motivating people to take ac-  human potential and the power of
           who, despite facing significant ob-  tion.                      dreams. It serves as a reminder that our
           stacles, managed to achieve their goals                         aspirations, when nurtured and pursued
           and create a lasting impact on their com-  The global impact of dreaming   with determination, can lead to extraor-
           munities.                       together                        dinary outcomes. Whether it’s personal
             For example, in 2020, a group of   At its core, World Dream Day is   growth, social change, or community
           young entrepreneurs from Kenya, in-  about more than just individual achieve-  development, the act of dreaming—cou-
                                                                           pled with action—has the power to
                                                                           shape a better world.
                                                                              By embracing the spirit of World
         Youthful entrepreneurs pursuing dreams                            Through collaboration, reflection, and
                                                                           Dream Day, individuals and organiza-
                                                                           tions are not just imagining a better fu-
                                                                           ture; they are actively creating it.
                                                                           dedication, World Dream Day continues
                                                                           to inspire people around the globe to
                                                                           dream big, take action, and transform
                                                                           their visions into reality. ■











         Power of collective dreaming and teamwork


















           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION  The 4pm Finish                                           implementation of the six-hour workday
                                                                              One significant example is Sweden’s
                                                                           in certain sectors, where the focus was
           Balance
                                                                           on achieving the same level of produc-
                                                                           tivity in fewer hours. These experiments
                                                                           often led to impressive results: employ-
                                                                           ees reported higher satisfaction, better
                                                                           mental health, and maintained or even
                                                                           increased productivity levels. Inspired
           work and life                                                   Finish Day gained momentum and
                                                                           by these findings, the idea of the 4pm
                                                                           spread to other parts of the world.

                                                                           The benefits of a 4pm finish day
                                                                              The appeal of a 4pm Finish Day lies
           While there are challenges to overcome, the potential           in its potential to address several press-
                                                                           ing issues in today’s workforce. From
           benefits in terms of productivity, job satisfaction, and        enhancing productivity to improving
                                                                           mental health, the benefits are vast.
           work-life balance make the 4pm Finish Day an idea worth
           considering. By Karan Malhotra                                  Increased productivity




             n the hustle and bustle of modern
             work culture, where overtime has
           Ioften become the norm, the concept
           of a "4pm Finish Day" emerges as a re-
           freshing and innovative strategy to pro-
           mote productivity, well-being, and
           work-life balance. This idea, which is
           gaining traction in various industries
           worldwide, encourages businesses and
           employees to adopt a structured work-
           day that wraps up earlier than the con-
           ventional 9-to-5. It’s more than just an
           early finish; it represents a shift in how
           we think about work, efficiency, and the
           importance of time outside the office.
           The origins of 4pm finish day
             The idea of finishing the workday at
           4 pm traces its roots to the evolving dis-
           cussions about productivity and mental
           health in the workplace. Traditional
           working hours, rooted in the industrial
           revolution, were initially designed for
           factory workers, and they have since
           been inherited by various other indus-
           tries. However, the modern work envi-
           ronment has changed drastically, with
           the rise of digital tools, remote work,
           and new work dynamics.
             As companies began experimenting
           with flexible hours and shorter work-
           days, the concept of a "4pm Finish Day"
           surfaced as an attempt to find the sweet
           spot between maintaining productivity
           and avoiding burnout. Early trials of this
           approach were seen in Scandinavian
           countries, known for their strong em-
           phasis on work-life balance and em-
           ployee well-being.

           18                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[An individual working on a laptop                                                                 A busy office environment













             One of the key arguments in favor of
           a shorter workday is that productivity
           does not necessarily correlate with the
           number of hours worked. Studies have
           shown that employees are often more
           productive in shorter time frames. When
           given a clear goal and a limited amount
           of time to complete it, people tend to
           focus better and eliminate distractions.
             The early finish encourages workers
           to prioritize their most important tasks
           during the day and work efficiently.
           Rather than stretching out work to fill an                                                      Happy employees leaving work
           eight-hour window, employees with a
           4pm finish focus on high-impact tasks
           and make better use of their time.

           Improved mental health and well-
           being                           ish allows them to pick up children from   businesses to meet deadlines. For indus-
             Burnout has become a widespread   school, spend quality time with family,   tries that rely on client-facing roles or
           issue in modern workplaces. Long   or manage household responsibilities.   customer service, finishing the workday
           hours, coupled with the pressures of   For others, it provides the opportunity to   early might be impractical.
           meeting deadlines, can lead to stress,   pursue personal development, whether
           anxiety, and other mental health chal-  through further education, exercise, or   Adjusting work expectations
           lenges. A 4pm Finish Day offers a solu-  creative endeavors.       One major challenge is adjusting
           tion by giving employees more time to                           work expectations. Employees might
           decompress after work, engage in   Attracting and retaining talent   feel pressured to complete the same
           hobbies, spend time with family, or pur-  In a competitive job market, com-  amount of work in less time, which
           sue personal goals.             panies are constantly looking for ways   could lead to stress and rushed output.
             Finishing at 4 pm creates a healthier   to attract and retain top talent. Offering   Companies need to ensure that the
           boundary between work and personal   flexible work options, including a 4pm   workload is reasonable and that employ-
           life. Employees who have time for self-  Finish Day, can be a powerful incentive.   ees aren’t simply being asked to cram
           care, exercise, or leisure activities are   It signals that a company values em-  more tasks into a shorter day.
           more likely to feel refreshed and moti-  ployee well-being and understands the
           vated, leading to improved mental   importance of work-life balance. In a   Industry-specific barriers
           health and a happier workforce overall.   world where younger generations are   Not all industries are suited to a 4pm
                                           prioritizing mental health and personal   finish. For example, customer service
           Work-life balance               fulfillment, such initiatives can make a   roles, retail, and healthcare often require
             Maintaining a healthy work-life bal-  company stand out as a desirable em-  longer hours to meet the needs of clients
           ance is essential for long-term job satis-  ployer.             and patients. In such sectors, it may be
           faction and employee retention. A 4pm                           challenging to adopt a universal early
           Finish Day can help employees reclaim   Challenges and criticisms   finish, though alternative approaches
           precious hours that would otherwise be   While the 4pm Finish Day concept   like staggered shifts or flexible work
           lost to commuting or additional work-re-  offers numerous benefits, it’s not with-  schedules could be considered.
           lated tasks.                    out its challenges. Some argue that re-
             For working parents, this schedule   ducing work hours could lead to a drop   Cultural resistance
           can be a game-changer. The earlier fin-  in productivity or make it difficult for   Some traditional work cultures may

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Flexibility is key. Some businesses
                                                                           might adopt a 4pm finish only on certain
                                                                           days of the week, while others might
                                                                           offer it as an option for employees who
                                                                           need it. Customizing the approach based
                                                                           on company needs can increase the like-
                                                                           lihood of success.
                                                                              The concept of a 4pm Finish Day is
                                                                           more than just a trend; it represents a
                                                                           thoughtful approach to rethinking how
                                                                           we work. In a world where employee
                                                                           well-being is becoming increasingly im-
                                                                           portant, businesses that embrace flex-
                                                                           ibility and prioritize mental health are
           resist the shift toward a shorter workday.   work while still allowing for an earlier   likely to thrive. While there are chal-
           In countries where long hours are seen   finish.                lenges to overcome, the potential bene-
           as a sign of dedication and hard work,                          fits in terms of productivity, job satisfac-
           the idea of finishing early could be met   Set clear expectations   tion, and work-life balance make the
           with skepticism. Managers and employ-  It’s important to clearly communicate   4pm Finish Day an idea worth consid-
           ees alike may need time to adjust to the   the goals and expectations of a 4pm Fin-  ering.
           notion that productivity isn’t tied to   ish Day. Employees should understand   As the global workforce continues to
           hours spent at the desk.        that the emphasis is on working effi-  evolve, it’s clear that innovative ap-
                                           ciently rather than rushing to finish   proaches to work schedules like the 4pm
           Implementing a 4pm finish day:   tasks. Management should also ensure   Finish Day will play a critical role in
           Best practices                  that the workload is realistic and achiev-  shaping the future of work. The key is
             For companies considering a 4pm   able within the shortened day.   finding the right balance between pro-
           Finish Day, careful planning and com-                           ductivity and well-being, creating an en-
           munication are key. Here are some best   Flexible implementation   vironment where employees can per-
           practices to ensure a smooth transition   A one-size-fits-all approach may not   form at their best while still enjoying the
           and maximize the benefits:      work for every company or industry.   personal time they deserve. ■

           Pilot programs
             Before fully committing to a 4pm
           finish, companies can implement pilot
           programs to gauge the impact on pro-
           ductivity and employee satisfaction. A
           trial period allows both managers and
         Bottom: Family time or leisure  schedule is feasible and beneficial.                              Relaxing activities at work
           employees to assess whether the new


           Focus on core hours
             One way to ensure productivity is
           maintained is to establish core hours
           during the day when all employees are
           expected to be available. This can pre-
           vent miscommunication or delays in








                                                                                                           A calm, empty office after 4pm













           20                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  Self Love



           The power of






           being single







         By Siddharth Mehta  National Singles Day celebrates the freedom, fulfillment,
           and joy of being single. It challenges societal norms that
           prioritize romantic relationships, reminding us that self-

           love, growth, and independence are equally valuable.





                                                                                 ational Singles Day is a day
                                                                                 dedicated to celebrating individ-
                                                                           Nuals who embrace their single
                                                                           status and the unique joys, challenges,
                                                                           and freedoms that come with it. Ob-
                                                                           served annually in the United States on
                                                                           the third Saturday of September, this day
                                                                           is a chance to recognize single people,
                                                                           whether by choice or circumstance, for
                                                                           their accomplishments, self-reliance,
                                                                           and personal growth. Unlike Valentine’s
                                                                           Day or similar occasions focused on ro-
                                                                           mantic relationships, National Singles
                                                                           Day promotes self-love, independence,
                                                                           and community among those who may
                                                                           not be in a romantic partnership.
                                                                           Origins of national singles day
                                                                              The concept of a day dedicated to
                                                                           singles is relatively new but has gained
                                                                           traction in recent years, paralleling shift-
                                                                           ing societal views on relationships, mar-
                                                                           riage, and personal fulfillment. National
                                                                           Singles Day in the United States was in-
                                                                           spired by similar observances around the
                                                                           world, such as China’s Singles’ Day
                                                                           (November 11), which is a massive
                                                                           commercial and social phenomenon.
                                                                           However, the American version is less
                                                                           about consumerism and more about re-
                                                                           flecting on personal goals, ambitions,
                                                                           and the value of independence.
                                                                              As traditional expectations around
                                                                           marriage and relationships have
                                                                           evolved, the number of single adults in
                                                                           the U.S. has steadily increased. In 2021,
                                                                           for example, over 50% of U.S. adults

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Singles are lonely: Many single
                                                                           people lead rich social lives filled with
                                                                           meaningful friendships, family relation-
                                                                           ships, and community connections.
                                                                           Studies have shown that singles often
                                                                           maintain more varied social circles than
                                                                           their married counterparts, which can
                                                                           lead to greater overall life satisfaction.
                                                                              Singles are unhappy or unfulfilled:
                                                                           Research increasingly suggests that sin-
                                                                           gle individuals are just as happy, if not
                                                                           more so, than those in romantic relation-
                                                                           ships. This is because single people can
                                                                           focus on their personal goals and desires
                                                                           without the compromises that come with
                                                                           being in a relationship.
                                                                              Single life is unstable: This myth per-
                                                                           petuates the idea that marriage or a long-
                                                                           term partnership is the only source of se-
                                                                           curity. However, single people often
                                           come along. National Singles Day helps
           were unmarried, a significant rise from
                                                                           exhibit high levels of self-reliance and
         Self-care moments: Enjoying a good book  growing demographic and the under-  not a transitional phase but a valid, ful-  Celebrating national singles day:
                                           to dismantle these stereotypes by pro-
           previous decades. National Singles Day,
                                                                           independence, which can lead to both
                                           moting the message that being single is
                                                                           emotional and financial stability.
           thus, serves as a recognition of this
                                           filling life choice.
           standing that fulfillment and happiness
                                                                           Ways to participate
           can be found outside the confines of ro-
                                           Some of the most common
           mantic relationships.
                                                                              There are many ways to celebrate
                                           misconceptions include:
                                                                           National Singles Day, whether privately
           The importance of national singles
           day
             The idea of National Singles Day is
           more than just acknowledging one's re-
           lationship status; it’s about fostering a
           sense of empowerment among single
           people. The celebration is significant be-
           cause it challenges longstanding societal
           norms that prioritize marriage and ro-
           mantic partnerships as the primary path
           to happiness. For many, being single
           offers the freedom to pursue personal
           passions, career goals, and deep friend-
           ships, without the obligations often as-
           sociated with a romantic partnership.
             It also allows individuals to focus on
           self-care and self-improvement. Many
           singles take this time to cultivate
           hobbies, learn new skills, and engage in
           activities that bring them joy and fulfill-
           ment. National Singles Day encourages
           the celebration of these accomplish-
           ments and serves as a reminder that hap-
           piness is not dependent on having a part-
           ner.
           Myths and misconceptions about
           being single
             Despite the increasing prevalence of
           singlehood, there are still many myths
           and misconceptions surrounding it. For                                                          Solo work: Enjoying drawing
           a long time, society has framed being
           single as something temporary or in-
           complete, suggesting that single people
           are waiting for their "better half" to

           22                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Friends laughing and enjoying












           or with friends. Here are a few ideas:   The role of social media
             Self-care and pampering: Use the day   Social media has played a significant
           to treat yourself with self-care activities.   role in the growing popularity of Na-
           Whether it's booking a spa day, indul-  tional Singles Day. Platforms like Insta-
           ging in your favorite hobby, or spending   gram, TikTok, and Twitter provide
           time in nature, taking the time to focus   spaces where single individuals can
           on your well-being is a great way to   share their stories, offer advice, and con-
           honor yourself.                 nect with others. The use of hashtags
             Solo travel or adventure: For those   such as #NationalSinglesDay, #Sin-  with being single. It challenges societal
           who enjoy exploring, National Singles   gleAndHappy, or #SelfLove is wide-  norms that prioritize romantic relation-
           Day is the perfect excuse to embark on a   spread, allowing for a sense of solidarity   ships and reminds people that self-love,
           solo trip or adventure. Traveling alone   and community among singles across   personal growth, and independence are
           allows for self-reflection, personal   the country.             just as valuable as traditional partner-
           growth, and the freedom to make your   Social media influencers, bloggers,   ships. Whether you’re single by choice
           own decisions without having to accom-  and public figures often use National   or circumstance, this day is an opportu-  Bottom: Solo Dining
           modate another person's preferences.   Singles Day as an opportunity to chal-  nity to celebrate your individuality and   Top: Solo tea
             Organize a singles meetup: Many   lenge the stigma around being single.   the unique journey of living life on your
           singles find joy in connecting with   Their messages encourage followers to   own terms. ■
           others who share similar experiences.   embrace their independence, focus on
           Organizing or attending a National Sin-  self-love, and reject societal pressures to
           gles Day event or meetup can foster a   conform to traditional relationship
           sense of community and belonging,   norms.
           whether it's through social gatherings,
           hiking groups, or local clubs.   Why national singles day matters
             Focus on personal goals: Use the day   National Singles Day is important
           to reflect on your life goals and aspira-  because it reminds society that being
           tions. Whether it’s advancing your ca-  single is not a problem to be solved but
           reer, developing a new skill, or working   a valid and fulfilling life choice. The day
           on a creative project, National Singles   brings attention to the growing number
           Day can be a time to refocus your   of people choosing to prioritize them-
           energies on what matters most to you.   selves, their careers, and their passions
             Celebrate with friends: Many singles   over conforming to the pressure to be in
           have a strong circle of friends who act   a relationship.
           as a support system and extended   For those who are single and happy,
           family. National Singles Day is an op-  National Singles Day is a chance to
           portunity to express gratitude for these   celebrate that freedom. For those who
           relationships, perhaps by hosting a   may feel societal pressure to couple up,
           dinner party, movie night, or a fun out-  the day serves as a reminder that their
           ing.                            worth is not tied to their relationship
             Give back to the community: Single   status. And for everyone, it’s an oppor-
           people often have the time and resources   tunity to reflect on the importance of
           to give back to their communities. Vol-  self-love, independence, and the power
           unteering on National Singles Day is a   of community.
           meaningful way to celebrate by contrib-  National Singles Day celebrates the
           uting to a cause you're passionate about.   freedom, fulfillment, and joy that come

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Workout

     IN FOCUS   that fits







           your life






           Teenager Workout Day
           is an opportunity to
           highlight the

           importance of fitness
           among adolescents.

           With increasing
           sedentary lifestyles and

           screen time, promoting
           physical activity is more

           important than ever.
           By Rohan Kapoor



             n a world where technology dom-
             inates much of our daily lives, phys-
           Iical activity among teenagers is be-
           coming increasingly vital. The rapid
           advancements in digital entertainment
           and social media often pull young
           people away from the essential habit of
           regular exercise. To combat the growing
           concerns about adolescent health and se-
           dentary lifestyles, the idea of Teenager
           Workout Day has emerged as an initia-  ness, learn the value of a healthy life-  running, swimming, or resistance train-
           tive to inspire teenagers to develop life-  style, and recognize the long-term bene-  ing, working out during teenage years is
           long fitness routines.          fits of physical activity.      a building block for long-term health.
           The importance of physical      Physical benefits               Mental and emotional benefits
           activity in teenagers             The advantages of regular exercise   Physical activity is not only about en-
             The teenage years are pivotal for   for teenagers extend far beyond improv-  hancing physical strength and endur-
           both physical and mental development.   ing their physical appearance. Engaging   ance; it plays a crucial role in emotional
           During adolescence, bodies go through   in regular physical activities helps im-  well-being. Teenage years are often
           significant changes, and maintaining an   prove cardiovascular health, strengthens   marked by emotional turbulence due to
           active lifestyle ensures that these   bones and muscles, boosts metabolism,   hormonal changes, academic pressures,
           changes happen healthily. Unfortunately,   and enhances flexibility. During adoles-  and social dynamics. Exercise acts as a
           teenagers are often the victims of physi-  cence, when the body is still developing,   natural stress reliever, triggering the re-
           cal inactivity due to academic pressures,   regular exercise aids in the formation of   lease of endorphins — hormones that
           screen addiction, or a lack of motiva-  stronger bones, reducing the risk of os-  boost mood and reduce feelings of anx-
           tion. This is where Teenager Workout   teoporosis later in life. It also helps reg-  iety and depression. Furthermore, exer-
           Day comes into play — a designated   ulate body fat, lowers cholesterol levels,   cise improves cognitive function and
           day to encourage teens to prioritize fit-  and boosts stamina. Whether it’s through   concentration, which can help teenagers

           24                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[perform better academically. In this
           sense, Teenager Workout Day is not just
           about promoting physical fitness but
           also about advocating for mental well-
           ness.
           Common barriers to teenage
           fitness
             Despite the many benefits of exer-
           cise, teenagers often face barriers that
           hinder their motivation to stay active.
           These obstacles include:
             Lack of time: With school, home-
           work, and extracurricular activities,
           many teenagers feel they don’t have
           enough time to work out.
             Screen time addiction: Video games,
           social media, and streaming services                                                            Teens practicing yoga
           consume a large portion of teenagers’
           free time, making it difficult to incorpo-
           rate exercise into their routines.
             Lack of motivation: Without immedi-
           ate rewards, many teenagers may not   ina. Activities like jogging, cycling,   yoga, it also helps teenagers develop
           recognize the long-term benefits of exer-  swimming, and even dancing are excel-  mindfulness and relaxation techniques.
           cise. Some may also feel intimidated by   lent cardio options for teenagers. These   Yoga improves flexibility, reduces
           gym environments or certain sports.   exercises not only burn calories but also   stress, and enhances focus. These bene-
             Social pressure: Teenagers may avoid   boost lung capacity and improve overall   fits are particularly helpful during the
           working out due to body image issues or   cardiovascular fitness.   academic and emotional pressures of ad-
           fear of being judged by their peers. This                       olescence. Simple yoga poses like the
           can create a negative cycle of inactivity.   Sports and group activities   downward dog, child’s pose, and cobra
             Teenager Workout Day aims to break   Teenagers who prefer more social   stretch can easily be incorporated into a
           down these barriers by creating a posi-  forms of exercise can engage in team   teenager’s daily routine.
           tive, inclusive environment where teen-  sports such as basketball, soccer, volley-
           agers feel empowered to participate in   ball, or tennis. These activities offer   Strength training
           physical activity without fear of judg-  both physical and social benefits by pro-  While some may associate strength
           ment or failure.                moting teamwork, discipline, and co-  training with adults, it is equally benefi-
                                           operation. Group fitness classes, like   cial for teenagers, provided they follow
           How to get started on teenager   yoga or dance, are also great options for   proper guidance. Strength training with
           workout day                     teenagers who enjoy exercising in a sup-  light weights or resistance bands helps
             The main goal of Teenager Workout   portive and engaging environment.   build muscle strength, improves posture,
           Day is to make fitness accessible, fun,                         and boosts metabolism. However, teens
           and sustainable for teens. It is essential   Yoga and mindfulness   should avoid heavy weights unless
           to introduce a variety of workout op-  In addition to the physical benefits of   under the supervision of a coach or
           tions that cater to different interests and
           fitness levels. Here are some practical
           ways teens can get involved and get
           started with their fitness journey:

           Bodyweight exercises
             For teenagers who are new to work-
           ing out, bodyweight exercises are an ex-
           cellent way to build strength without
           needing any equipment. Exercises like
           push-ups, squats, lunges, and planks
           help develop core strength and improve
           muscle endurance. These exercises can
           be performed anywhere, making them
           perfect for teens who may not have ac-
           cess to a gym.                                                                                  A teen performing workout
           Cardio workouts
             Cardiovascular exercises are essen-
           tial for heart health and improving stam-

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Outdoor activities: Teens cycling                                                                A Teen using a Hula hoop













           trainer to prevent injury.      and motivated.                  cognitive function and concentration,
                                             Track progress: Tracking fitness pro-  leading to better performance in school.
           Tips for teens to stay motivated   gress, whether through a journal or a fit-  Mental resilience: Learning to over-
             Maintaining a fitness routine can be   ness app, helps teenagers stay motivated   come fitness challenges helps teenagers
           challenging, especially for teenagers   by seeing how far they’ve come. It also   develop resilience, discipline, and a pos-
           with busy schedules. However, with the   provides a sense of accomplishment, re-  itive attitude that extends into other
           right mindset and strategies, staying mo-  inforcing the benefits of their hard work.   areas of life.
           tivated becomes easier:                                            Teenager Workout Day is an opportu-
             Set achievable goals: Teenagers   Long-Term Benefits of Regular   nity to highlight the importance of fit-
           should start by setting small, realistic fit-  Teen Workouts    ness among adolescents. With increasing
           ness goals, such as working out for 20   The habits teenagers form during   sedentary lifestyles and screen time,
           minutes a day or running a certain dis-  their adolescent years often carry into   promoting physical activity is more im-
           tance. As they achieve these goals, they   adulthood. Engaging in regular exercise   portant than ever. By making exercise
           can gradually increase the intensity or   as a teenager leads to lifelong benefits,   accessible, fun, and rewarding, Teenager
           duration of their workouts.     including:                      Workout Day empowers young people
             Find what you love: The key to   Increased longevity: Regular physi-  to take control of their physical and
           maintaining a workout routine is finding   cal activity during adolescence helps   mental well-being, laying the foundation
           an activity that teenagers enjoy. Whether   build a foundation for a healthier life,   for a healthier, more active future. ■
           it’s dancing, swimming, or skateboard-  reducing the risk of chronic illnesses
           ing, choosing a fun activity makes exer-  like heart disease, obesity, and diabetes.
           cise feel less like a chore.      Improved self-esteem: As teenagers
             Incorporate friends: Working out   see progress in their fitness levels and
           with friends not only makes fitness more   physical appearance, they often experi-
           enjoyable but also creates a support sys-  ence a boost in self-confidence and self-
           tem for staying on track. Group work-  esteem.
           outs, sports, or fitness challenges are ex-  Better academic performance: Physi-
           cellent ways for teens to stay connected   cal fitness is closely linked to improved












         Teenagers exercising together













           26                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[FEATURE




































           Bollywood's Legacy


           Uniting cultures





           through cinema






           As Bollywood moves forward, it will undoubtedly

           continue to shape and reflect the dreams, hopes,                dia's silent film era began. The very first
                                                                           Indian feature film, Raja Harishchandra,
           and emotions of audiences, both in India and                    directed by Dadasaheb Phalke in 1913,
                                                                           laid the foundation for what would be-
           across the globe. By Ishita Desai                               come one of the largest film industries
                                                                           in the world. The silent era gave way to
                                                                           sound with Alam Ara in 1931, marking
                ollywood, the vibrant and color-  September 24, honors this rich cine-  the birth of "talkies" in Indian cinema.
                ful film industry based in Mum-  matic heritage and highlights the impact   This was a turning point, as the use of
           Bbai, India, has transcended bor-  Bollywood has had on entertainment,   music, dialogue, and elaborate song-
           ders and cultures to become a global   culture, and society across the globe.   and-dance sequences became key fea-
           phenomenon. Known for its captivating                           tures of Bollywood films.
           storytelling, memorable music, and dra-  Origins of Bollywood: A journey   By the 1950s and 60s, Bollywood ex-
           matic flair, Bollywood continues to win   through time          perienced its golden age, producing
           the hearts of millions worldwide. World   The roots of Bollywood can be traced   timeless classics such as Mother India
           Bollywood Day, celebrated annually on   back to the early 20th century when In-  (1957), Mughal-e-Azam (1960), and

           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Legendary Bollywood filmmaker Yash Chopra                                                         Dilip Kumar in the Bollywood movie Mughal-e-Azam


















           Sholay (1975). Directors like Guru Dutt,   mixes and dance performances, while   cars, winning eight Academy Awards,
           Raj Kapoor, and Mehboob Khan, along   Bollywood-style clothing, such as lehen-  including Best Picture, brought Bolly-
           with stars like Dilip Kumar, Nargis, and   gas and sarees, has become fashionable   wood’s stylistic influence into the global
           Madhubala, helped shape Bollywood's   in many parts of the world.   limelight.
           distinct style. These films were not only                          Bollywood stars, too, have crossed
           artistic achievements but also socially   Bollywood’s influence on global   over into international cinema. Actors
           relevant, often reflecting the changing   cinema                like Priyanka Chopra, Irrfan Khan, and
           political and cultural landscapes of post-  The influence of Bollywood on   Deepika Padukone have worked in Hol-
           independence India.             global cinema cannot be overstated.   lywood, helping bridge the gap between
                                           Over the years, many international film-  Indian and Western cinema. Priyanka
           The global appeal of Bollywood   makers have taken inspiration from Bol-  Chopra, in particular, has become a
             Bollywood has always had an inter-  lywood's distinct style of filmmaking.   global icon, balancing her successful
           national presence, but in recent decades,   The industry's grand musical numbers,   Bollywood career with prominent roles
           its reach has expanded significantly. In-  dramatic narratives, and opulent sets   in Hollywood films and TV shows like
           dian diaspora communities in the United   have inspired Hollywood and other film   Quantico. Irrfan Khan, known for his
           States, the United Kingdom, the Middle   industries around the world.   versatile performances, left a significant
           East, and other countries have played a   Movies like Slumdog Millionaire   impact on both Bollywood and Holly-
           vital role in popularizing Bollywood   (2008), directed by British filmmaker   wood, with roles in films like Life of Pi
           films outside India. However, it's not   Danny Boyle, incorporated many ele-  (2012) and Jurassic World (2015).
           just Indian expats who love Bolly-  ments typical of Bollywood films, such
           wood—people from diverse back-  as a strong emotional narrative, ro-  Bollywood's social impact
           grounds are drawn to the unique blend   mance, and of course, an iconic dance   Beyond entertainment, Bollywood
           of melodrama, romance, action, and   sequence. The film's success at the Os-  has played a crucial role in addressing
           music that defines the industry.
             One of the key reasons for Bolly-
           wood's universal appeal is its ability to
           connect with the emotions and aspira-
           tions of viewers. Bollywood films often
           emphasize themes like family, love,
           friendship, and perseverance, which res-
           onate across cultures. The inclusion of
           vibrant song-and-dance numbers has
           also set Bollywood apart from other
           global cinemas. Films such as Dilwale
           Dulhania Le Jayenge (1995), Kabhi
           Khushi Kabhie Gham (2001), and 3 Id-
           iots (2009) have been embraced by au-
           diences worldwide, becoming cultural
           touchstones.
             In addition to its storytelling, Bolly-                                                       Left: Deepika Padukone   Right: Priyanka Chopra
           wood has had a significant impact on
           global fashion, music, and dance. Bolly-
           wood songs have inspired countless re-

           28                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[and shaping societal attitudes. The in-  new and refreshing side of Indian youth   shift has created opportunities for more
           dustry has been a platform for film-  culture. The rise of women-centric films   experimental and niche storytelling, but
           makers to discuss important social is-  like Queen (2014) and Piku (2015)   it has also put pressure on traditional
           sues such as gender equality, poverty,   marks a shift toward more empowered   box-office revenues.
           mental health, and corruption. Films like   and complex female protagonists.   Another challenge is the growing
           Taare Zameen Par (2007), which fo-  The industry's portrayal of LGBTQ+   competition from regional Indian
           cused on dyslexia and the importance of   characters and themes has also evolved,   cinema, which is producing high-quality
           understanding children's educational   with films like Shubh Mangal Zyada   content in languages such as Tamil, Te-
           needs, and Pink (2016), which high-  Saavdhan (2020) offering progressive   lugu, Malayalam, and Kannada. Films
           lighted issues of consent and women's   representations of same-sex relation-  like Baahubali (2015) and RRR (2022)
           rights, have had a profound impact on   ships. Through these narratives, Bolly-  have garnered international attention,
           societal debates.               wood is contributing to a broader con-  proving that Bollywood is no longer the
             In recent years, Bollywood has in-  versation about inclusivity and   only Indian cinema making waves
           creasingly embraced more diverse   acceptance in Indian society.   globally.
           stories and characters. Films like Gully                           Despite these challenges, Bollywood
           Boy (2019), inspired by the lives of   The role of music in Bollywood   continues to adapt. The industry's ability
           street rappers in Mumbai, showcased a   Music has always been a defining   to reinvent itself, embrace new technol-
                                           feature of Bollywood films, often serv-  ogy, and tell stories that reflect contem-
                                           ing as an emotional anchor for the plot.   porary issues ensures that it remains rel-
                                           Songs from Bollywood films have a   evant in an ever-evolving world of
                                           way of transcending linguistic and cul-  entertainment.
                                           tural barriers, making them beloved by
                                           audiences across the world. Whether it's   Celebrating World Bollywood Day
                                           the classical melodies of the 1950s or   World Bollywood Day is more than
                                           the fusion of traditional and contempo-  just a day to celebrate films; it's an op-
                                           rary styles in modern cinema, Bolly-  portunity to honor a cultural legacy that
                                           wood's music has evolved to stay rel-  has inspired generations. Fans around
                                           evant while retaining its essence.   the globe come together to watch classic
                                             Composers like R.D. Burman, A.R.
                                                                           films, listen to iconic songs, and partici-
         Salman Khan                       Rahman, and Shankar-Ehsaan-Loy have   pate in events that celebrate the spirit of
                                                                           Bollywood. From film festivals to dance
                                           made their mark on the global music
                                                                           performances, this day brings people
                                           scene, while playback singers like Lata
                                           Mangeshkar, Kishore Kumar, and Arijit
                                                                           united by their love for Hindi cinema.
                                           Singh are iconic voices that have shaped   from diverse backgrounds together,
                                           generations. A.R. Rahman, in particular,   World Bollywood Day is also a time
                                           has gained international recognition,   to reflect on the industry's future and
                                           winning multiple awards, including two   how it can continue to be a beacon of
                                           Oscars for his work on Slumdog Mil-  creativity, cultural exchange, and social
                                           lionaire.                       influence. As Bollywood moves for- Bottom: Rani Mukerji on an outdoor set as director
        Bottom: Amitabh Bachchan   Right: Shahrukh Khan   Bollywood        emotions of audiences, both in India and
                                                                           ward, it will undoubtedly continue to
                                           Challenges and future of
                                                                           shape and reflect the dreams, hopes, and
                                             While Bollywood continues to thrive,
                                                                           across the globe.
                                           it faces challenges in a rapidly changing
                                                                              In celebrating World Bollywood Day,
                                                                           we celebrate not just an industry, but a
                                           media landscape. The rise of streaming
                                                                           cultural phenomenon that has brought
                                           platforms like Netflix, Amazon Prime,
                                                                           joy, inspiration, and connection to mil-
                                           and Disney+ Hotstar has led to a shift in
                                                                           lions. ■
                                           how audiences consume content. This

















           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                            September 16-30, 2024









           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     The end of September will bring a surge of      As your birthday season approaches, you’ll feel
                     motivation. You’ll feel inspired to tackle lingering   more in tune with yourself and those around
                     tasks and projects with renewed energy. Be sure to   you. It’s a time for balance and harmony. Profes-
                     manage your time well, as work-life balance will   sionally, cooperation will be key to success, so
                     be crucial.                                     embrace teamwork.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     This period encourages you to seek stability and   This period brings intense focus and determina-
                     comfort in your surroundings. Whether at work or   tion. You’ll have the energy to push through ob-
                     home, focus on creating a space that makes you   stacles and achieve your goals. In relationships,
                     feel grounded. Relationships will be harmonious,   trust will be a central theme, so ensure you
                     but be careful not to overcommit.               maintain open communication.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Your communication skills will be front and     The end of September brings opportunities for
                     center during this period. Use this time to ex-  learning and personal growth. This is a great
                     press your thoughts and ideas clearly, as they’ll   time to explore new interests or dive into educa-
                     be well-received. Networking opportunities will   tional pursuits. In your relationships, maintain
                     arise, so take advantage of them.               open-mindedness and be willing to compromise.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     The end of September will call for emotional in-  Capricorn, discipline and hard work will be your
                     trospection. Take time to recharge and nurture   focus. Use this time to strengthen the foundation
                     yourself. Relationships may need extra care, so   you’ve been building in your career or personal
                     be open and honest with your feelings. At work,   life. Relationships will benefit from your reli-
                     focus on tying up loose ends.                   ability and support.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Your charisma will attract attention during this   Aquarius, your creative energy will be flowing
                     period, making it a great time to take the lead on   during this period. Take advantage of this to pur-
                     projects or initiate new ventures. However, be   sue innovative ideas or start new projects. In re-
                     mindful of others' opinions and avoid being     lationships, be open to unconventional ap-
                     overly assertive.                               proaches and new perspectives.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     The focus will be on details and organization.   Pisces, this period encourages emotional healing
                     Use this time to fine-tune your plans and execute   and growth. Take time to focus on self-care and
                     them methodically. Your analytical mind will    reflect on your personal journey. Relationships
                     help you solve problems both in work and per-   will be supportive, so lean on your loved ones
                     sonal life.                                     for guidance.


           30                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Debate on PM's Visit to CJI’s   his motivations and the implications for
           Residence                       governance in Delhi.
             The recent visit of Prime Minister   Critics, including BJP leaders, have   ture these models in India underscores a
           Narendra Modi to Chief Justice DY   labeled the resignation a "PR stunt,"   strategic shift towards local production,
           Chandrachud's residence for Ganesh   suggesting it is a calculated move to re-  potentially reducing reliance on China.
           Chaturthi has ignited a heated debate   store his tarnished image ahead of up-  As consumers eagerly await pre-orders,
           regarding the appropriateness of such   coming elections. They argue that he is   the iPhone 16 series is poised to drive
           interactions between the executive and   attempting to evade accountability while   significant sales and reinforce Apple's
           judiciary. Critics argue that this meeting   shifting blame to others within his party.   market presence in the smartphone in-
           raises concerns about judicial impartiality,   Conversely, AAP supporters view this as   dustry.
           suggesting it could undermine public   a bold step towards seeking public val-  Naresh Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,
           confidence in the judiciary, especially   idation of his integrity, emphasizing   India
           given ongoing legal matters involving the   Kejriwal's commitment to democracy.
           government. Opposition leaders have   As Delhi approaches elections, the
           called for the Chief Justice to recuse   ramifications of this resignation will be   Yechury’s Passing: A Void in Indian
           himself from cases involving the   closely scrutinized, influencing both   Politics
           government due to perceived conflicts of   public perception and political dynamics   The passing of Sitaram Yechury, the
           interest.                       in the capital.                 General Secretary of the Communist
             Conversely, supporters assert that this   Manisha Sharma, New Delhi, India   Party of India (Marxist), at the age of 72
           visit is a cultural celebration, emphasizing                    is a profound loss for Indian politics. Ye-
           the importance of personal relationships                        chury, who succumbed to a prolonged
           in a democratic society. They argue that   iPhone 16 Series Launch:   illness after being hospitalized for an
           such gatherings should not be politicized,   Innovations and Impact   acute respiratory infection, was a stal-
           as they reflect personal faith rather than   The launch of the iPhone 16 series   wart of leftist ideology and a prominent
           political maneuvering. Ultimately, this   marks a significant moment for Apple,   figure in coalition politics.
           controversy highlights the delicate   introducing impressive upgrades and   His political journey, marked by sig-
           balance between maintaining judicial   new features that cater to diverse con-  nificant contributions since his student
           independence and embracing cultural   sumer needs. With the iPhone 16 start-  days, showcased his commitment to
           practices in India's diverse society.   ing at $799 and the iPhone 16 Plus at   civil liberties and social justice. Ye-
           Ravi Kumar Anand, New Delhi, India   $899, Apple has maintained competitive   chury's strategic acumen helped navi-
                                           pricing, crucial for attracting both loyal   gate the complexities of Indian politics,
                                           customers and new users.        making him a respected leader across
           Kejriwal’s Resignation Sparks     The introduction of the A18 chip en-  party lines.
           Controversy                     hances performance, while the re-  As tributes pour in from various po-
             Arvind Kejriwal's announcement to   vamped camera system promises stun-  litical leaders, it is evident that his leg-
           resign as Delhi Chief Minister within   ning photography capabilities. Notably,   acy will continue to inspire future gener-
           two days has sparked significant contro-  the customizable Action Button and im-  ations. His departure leaves a void in the
           versy and debate. Coming just days after   proved durability reflect Apple’s com-  political landscape that will be hard to
           his release on bail from a corruption   mitment to innovation.   fill.
           case, this decision raises questions about   Moreover, the decision to manufac-  Sunil Singh, Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           SEPTEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                            .in
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                                       32
                                                                                      |

                                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 01 2024
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32                                                      wwwwww.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024
           32
                                                                   www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024
           32
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>