<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 04  I  FEBRUARY 16 2025     ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             11



                                                             5













                                                            8                                        20
















           4-Editorial: Young women, bold                  20-The rise of energy drinks in modern
           leadership                                      life

           5-Young women changing the world                24-The symbolism of pipe smoking

           8-Why child care matters                        27-Horoscopes

           11-Igniting courage and strength                28-Letters
           15-A beacon of hope for stray animals

           18-A life dedicated to social change















           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                                3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Shaping a New Era
     EDITORIAL  Young women,                                                      Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           bold leadership                                                      Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                           n every corner of the world, young        Navormi Vats
                                           women are rising as catalysts of change,
                                        Ichallenging conventions and redefining
                                        leadership. Their voices echo in parlia-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        ments, boardrooms, classrooms and streets;   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        demanding justice, equality and progress.
                                        As they step forward with courage and con-  Social Media Editor
                                        viction, they reshape societies and inspire   Vikas Babbar
                                        future generations to dream beyond limita-
                                        tions.                                   Art & Graphics Editor
                                           The presence of young women in leader-    Vipin Kumar
                                        ship is not merely symbolic; it is transfor-
                                        mative. From Malala Yousafzai’s relentless
                                        fight for girls’ education to Greta Thun-  EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           berg’s global climate activism, these leaders are dismantling traditional hierarchies
           and proving that leadership is not bound by gender or age. They bring fresh perspec-  D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           tives, empathy-driven policies and an unwavering commitment to social justice.   Editor, United News of India, New
             But change does not come without resistance. Gender biases, systemic barriers   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           and deeply ingrained societal norms still impede progress. Women in politics, for in-  Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           stance, face scrutiny beyond their male counterparts, with their credibility often ques-  Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           tioned based on appearance rather than ability. In business, female entrepreneurs   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           struggle with unequal access to funding and opportunities. Yet, despite these chal-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           lenges, young women continue to rise, their resilience fueled by purpose and com-  N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           munity support.                                                        Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             Leadership is not a solitary pursuit; it thrives on collective strength. Across the
           world, mentorship programs, women’s networks and grassroots movements are em-  SUBSCRIPTIONS
           powering young women to take charge.
             Education plays a fundamental role in fostering this change. When young girls are   Phone +91 20 40199102
           encouraged to think critically, embrace leadership roles and challenge societal norms,   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           they grow into empowered women who contribute meaningfully to their com-  Baner Road,
           munities. Countries that prioritize gender-inclusive policies in education and govern-  Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           ance see tangible improvements in economic growth, health outcomes and overall   Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
           societal well-being.                                               Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
             The rise of young women leaders signals a future where leadership is more inclu-  Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
           sive, compassionate and solution-oriented. Their impact is not confined to feminist   Founding year 2023
           movements; it extends to economic reforms, environmental policies and global peace   Subject Multidisciplinary
           initiatives. They advocate not just for gender equality but for a fairer, more sustain-  Frequency Fortnightly
           able world.                                                              Format Online
             As societies, we must ensure that the momentum does not wane. Supporting   Language English
           young women in leadership requires systemic change; eliminating barriers, fostering   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           inclusive policies and amplifying their voices. The world stands at the cusp of a para-  Website www.revoir.in
           digm shift, one where leadership is defined not by gender but by vision and action.
           And as young women continue to lead the future, they illuminate a path for a better,   Legal Advisor
           more just world for all.                                             Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[COVER STORY





















                                                                                                             Trisha Shetty, founder of SheSays
















           Leading the Future                                                 n recent years, the world has wit-

                                                                              nessed a seismic shift in the way
                                                                           Ileadership is perceived and prac-
           Young women                                                     patriarchal structures, leadership is in-
                                                                           ticed. No longer confined to traditional
                                                                           creasingly being redefined by young
                                                                           women who are breaking barriers, chal-
                                                                           lenging norms and creating impactful
                                                                           change across various sectors. From
           changing the                                                    to social activism, young women are
                                                                           politics to entrepreneurship, education
                                                                           stepping into roles of influence and re-
                                                                           sponsibility, proving that the future is
                                                                           not only female but also bright, inclu-
                                                                           sive and transformative. This article
           world                                                           delves into the rise of young women
                                                                           leaders, their contributions to shaping a
                                                                           better world and the role of initiatives
                                                                           like World Thinking Day in nurturing
                                                                           the next generation of female trail-
           The rise of young women leaders is not just a                   blazers.

           trend; it is a testament to the enduring power of               World thinking day: A catalyst for
                                                                           female leadership
           resilience, creativity and collaboration. From                  nually on February 22, is more than just
                                                                              World Thinking Day, celebrated an-
           politics to entrepreneurship, education to social               a day of reflection; it is a global move-
                                                                           ment that empowers girls and young
           change, young women are proving that                            women to think critically, act boldly and
                                                                           lead fearlessly. Originating from the
           leadership knows no gender. By Naina Kapoor                     Girl Guides and Girl Scouts movement,
                                                                           this day encourages young women to

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                                5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Chandrani Murmu, India’s youngest MP                                                              A female entrepreneur working on her laptop
















           explore their potential, embrace leader-
           ship roles and contribute to their com-
           munities. In a world where gender dis-
           parities still persist, World Thinking
           Day serves as a reminder that girls and
           women are not just participants in the
           journey toward progress but are also its
           architects. By fostering skills like prob-
           lem-solving, teamwork and empathy,                                                                Right: Aditi Gupta, co-founder of Menstrupedia
           this initiative equips young women with                                                         Left: Trisha Shetty, founder of SheSays
           the tools they need to navigate complex
           challenges and emerge as leaders in
           their respective fields.

           The Indian scenario: A rising tide
           of female leadership
             In India, the rise of young women
           leaders is particularly significant given   Young women leaders in politics:
           the country’s complex socio-cultural   Breaking the glass ceiling
           landscape. Historically, Indian women   Politics, often considered a male bas-
           have faced systemic barriers to educa-  tion, is witnessing a surge of young
           tion, employment and political partici-  women leaders who are redefining gov-
           pation. However, the tide is turning.   ernance and policy-making. Figures like
           Today, young women are not only enter-  Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez in the United
           ing traditionally male-dominated fields   States and Jacinda Ardern in New Zea-
           but are also excelling in them. From   land have shown that young women can
           grassroots activism to corporate board-  lead with empathy, resilience and
           rooms, Indian women are making their   vision.
           presence felt.                    In India:                                                     Falguni Nayar, founder of Nykaa
             One notable example is Malala You-  Young politicians like Chandrani
           safzai, who, though not Indian, has in-  Murmu, who became the youngest
           spired countless young women in India   Member of Parliament at the age of 25,
           to fight for their right to education.   are challenging stereotypes and proving
           Closer home, young leaders like Trisha   that age and gender are no barriers to
           Shetty, founder of SheSays, are working   effective leadership.   Entrepreneurship: Young women
           tirelessly to combat gender-based vio-  These leaders are not just participat-  at the helm of innovation
           lence and promote gender equality. Sim-  ing in politics; they are transforming it.   The entrepreneurial landscape is
           ilarly, Sneha Biswas, a young engineer   By prioritizing issues like climate   another arena where young women are
           and social entrepreneur, is leveraging   change, education and healthcare, they   making significant strides. Across the
           technology to improve menstrual hy-  are addressing the needs of the most   globe, female entrepreneurs are launch-
           giene in rural India. These women ex-  vulnerable sections of society. Their   ing startups that are not only profitable
           emplify the transformative power of fe-  leadership styles, often characterized by   but also socially impactful. In India,
           male leadership and serve as role   collaboration and inclusivity, offer a   young women like Falguni Nayar,
           models for millions of girls across the   refreshing contrast to the adversarial   founder of Nykaa and Upasana Taku,
           country.                        politics of the past.           co-founder of MobiKwik, are leading

           6                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[leaders of tomorrow. By encouraging
         A young woman delivering a speech to an audience
                                                                           girls to think critically and act compas-
                                                                           sionately, this initiative instills in them
                                                                           the confidence to lead. Activities like
                                                                           community service projects, leadership
                                                                           workshops and global collaborations
                                                                           provide young women with practical ex-
                                                                           perience and a sense of purpose. More-
                                                                           over, World Thinking Day fosters a
                                                                           sense of solidarity among girls from di-
                                                                           verse backgrounds, reminding them that
                                                                           they are part of a global movement for
                                                                           change.
                                                                              In India, organizations like the Girl
                                                                           Guides and Girl Scouts are using World
                                                                           Thinking Day to address local chal-
                                                                           lenges while promoting global citizen-
                                                                           ship. For instance, initiatives that focus
                                                                           on environmental sustainability, digital
                                                                           literacy and gender equality are helping
                                                                           young women develop the skills and
       Left: Kirthi Jayakumar, Gender Security Project  Right: Sneha Biswas, Early Steps Academy   able Development Goals, World Think-
                                                                           knowledge they need to lead in a rapidly
                                                                           changing world. By aligning these ef-
                                                                           forts with the United Nations Sustain-

                                                                           ing Day is ensuring that young women
                                                                           are not just prepared for the future but
                                                                           are also actively shaping it.

                                                                           A future shaped by young women
                                                                           leaders
                                                                              The rise of young women leaders is

                                                                           enduring power of resilience, creativity
                                                                           and collaboration. From politics to en-
                                                                           trepreneurship, education to social
                                                                           change, young women are proving that
           the charge in the tech and e-commerce   tion is a testament to the transformative   not just a trend; it is a testament to the
           sectors. These women are not just build-  power of learning. In India, young   leadership knows no gender. Their
           ing businesses; they are creating ecosys-  women like Kirthi Jayakumar, founder   stories inspire us to imagine a world
           tems that empower other women, gener-  of The Gender Security Project, are   where equality is not just an ideal but a
           ate employment and drive economic   using education to challenge stereotypes   reality.
           growth.                         and promote gender equality. By cre-  World Thinking Day serves as a bea-
             What sets these young entrepreneurs   ating safe spaces for dialogue and learn-  con of hope, reminding us that the jour-
           apart is their ability to identify gaps in   ing, these leaders are empowering the   ney toward a better world begins with
           the market and address them with inno-  next generation to question societal   empowering young women. By equip-
           vative solutions. For instance, Aditi   norms and advocate for their rights.   ping them with the skills, knowledge
           Gupta, co-founder of Menstrupedia, has   Moreover, young women are increas-  and confidence to lead, this initiative is
           revolutionized the way menstrual health   ingly taking on leadership roles in edu-  cultivating a generation of female
           is discussed in India by creating educa-  cational institutions, both as students   leaders who are ready to tackle the chal-
           tional content that is both accessible and   and educators. They are organizing   lenges of tomorrow. As we celebrate
           culturally sensitive. Such initiatives   workshops, mentoring peers and initiat-  their achievements and support their as-
           highlight the unique perspectives that   ing campaigns that address issues like   pirations, we take a step closer to a fu-
           young women bring to entrepreneurship   mental health, climate change and digi-  ture that is not only female but also fair,
           and underscore the importance of foster-  tal literacy. These efforts not only en-  inclusive and transformative.
           ing an environment where their ideas   hance the educational experience but   In the words of Ruth Bader Gins-
           can thrive.                     also prepare young women to take on   burg, “Women belong in all places
                                           leadership roles in their communities   where decisions are being made.” The
           Education and social change:    and beyond.                     rise of young women leaders is a power-
           Empowering the next generation                                  ful affirmation of this belief and with
             Education is often hailed as the great   The role of world thinking day in   initiatives like World Thinking Day, we
           equalizer and young women leaders are   cultivating future leaders   can ensure that this momentum con-
           leveraging it as a tool for social change.   World Thinking Day plays a pivotal   tinues to grow. The future is indeed fe-
           Malala Yousafzai’s fight for girls’ educa-  role in nurturing the young female   male and it is brighter than ever. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                                7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE





































           Raising the Future                                              as a global reminder of the importance
                                                                           of supporting children, particularly those
                                                                           in foster care and vulnerable situations.
                                                                           This day highlights the need for compre-
                                                                           hensive care, quality education and
           Why child care                                                  emotional support to help every child
                                                                           reach their full potential. Across the
                                                                           world, governments, organizations and
                                                                           individuals come together to advocate
                                                                           for policies and programs that prioritize
           matters                                                         By acknowledging the significance of
                                                                           children's well-being and development.
                                                                           such initiatives, we recognize the pro-
                                                                           found impact of nurturing young minds
                                                                           on the future of humanity. The obser-
                                                                           vance of this day also serves as an op-
           Caring for children today is an investment in the future.       portunity to reflect on the current state
                                                                           of child welfare and the areas that re-
           By providing young minds with proper education,                 quire immediate attention and improve-
                                                                           ment.
           emotional support and physical well-being, we lay the
                                                                           The importance of early childhood
           foundation for a better tomorrow. By Rajeev Khanna              care and education
                                                                              Early childhood is a critical period of
                                                                           brain development, where experiences
                he future of our world depends   gent and responsible individuals who   shape cognitive abilities, social skills
                on the care and education we pro-  will shape a brighter tomorrow. The im-  and emotional resilience. Studies have
           Tvide to children today. From the   pact of this investment extends beyond   shown that children who receive quality
           earliest years of life, children require a   individual success; it influences eco-  care and education in their early years
           nurturing environment that fosters their   nomic development, societal stability   are more likely to excel academically,
           physical, emotional and intellectual   and the overall progress of humanity.   develop strong interpersonal relation-
           growth. These formative years lay the   Understanding the profound role that   ships and become productive members
           foundation for their lifelong well-being,   early childhood care plays in shaping   of society. Conversely, children deprived
           success and contributions to society. By   our future underscores the necessity of   of proper care and learning opportunities
           investing in early childhood care and   prioritizing these efforts on a global   face challenges such as low self-esteem,
           education, we ensure that future genera-  scale.                poor academic performance and diffi-
           tions grow into compassionate, intelli-  Every year, World Care Day serves   culty integrating into society. Research

           8                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[vide children with a sense of belonging,
                                                                           care and encouragement, ensuring they
                                                                           grow into well-adjusted and compas-
                                                                           sionate individuals. The presence of car-
                                                                           ing and attentive adults in a child's life
         Children playing on the school campus                             greater ease.
                                                                           significantly contributes to their emo-
                                                                           tional security and resilience, allowing
                                                                           them to navigate life’s challenges with


                                                                           Programs and initiatives
                                                                           supporting underserved children
                                                                              Across the globe, numerous initia-
                                                                           tives and programs have been estab-
                                                                           lished to support children in underserved
                                                                           communities. These efforts aim to pro-
                                                                           vide children with access to quality edu-
                                                                           cation, healthcare and emotional sup-
                                                                           port, ensuring they have a fair chance at
                                                                           success regardless of their socioeco-
                                                                           nomic background. Governments, non-
                                                                           governmental organizations and private
                                                                           institutions continue to collaborate in
                                                                           creating programs that promote equity
                                                                           and inclusion in early childhood care.
                                                                           Early childhood education
         A mentor guiding a young child                                    the Children focus on expanding access
                                                                           programs
                                                                              Organizations like UNICEF and Save

                                                                           to early childhood education, particu-
                                                                           larly in disadvantaged regions. These
                                                                           programs provide essential learning ma-
                                                                           terials, train educators and establish
                                                                           child-friendly learning spaces. By ensur-

                                                                           communities receive early education,
                                           trition, healthcare and safe environments   ing that children from marginalized
                                                                           these programs help bridge the gap be-
                                           play a crucial role in shaping a child’s   tween privileged and underserved chil-
                                           growth and overall well-being. Children   dren, creating a more equitable society.
                                           who have access to adequate healthcare   Moreover, early education programs
                                           and nutritious food are more likely to   equip children with fundamental literacy
                                           thrive physically and mentally. Ad-  and numeracy skills that enhance their
                                           ditionally, providing a secure and sup-  readiness for formal schooling.
                                           portive home environment helps chil-  School feeding programs
         A caring adult playing with a child  Governments and organizations world-  cant barriers to learning. Organizations
                                           dren develop a sense of stability and
                                           confidence that carries into adulthood.
                                                                              Hunger and malnutrition are signifi-
                                           wide have recognized the importance of
                                                                           such as the World Food Programme
                                           addressing child malnutrition and
                                                                           (WFP) run school feeding programs that
                                           healthcare accessibility, launching var-
                                                                           provide nutritious meals to children in
                                                                           impoverished areas. These meals not
                                           ious initiatives to ensure that no child is
                                                                           only support physical health but also im-
                                           deprived of basic needs.
                                             Emotional well-being is another pil-
                                           lar of childhood development. Children
                                                                           formance. When children receive adequ-
                                                                           ate nutrition, they are better equipped to
                                           who grow up in loving, supportive envi-  prove concentration and academic per-
           conducted by child development experts   ronments develop stronger self-esteem,   absorb knowledge and participate ac-
           has consistently demonstrated the last-  emotional intelligence and problem-  tively in their education. Several coun-
           ing effects of early intervention pro-  solving skills. Emotional neglect, on the   tries have adopted national school meal
           grams in improving children's cognitive   other hand, can lead to anxiety, depres-  programs as a strategy to combat child
           and social outcomes.            sion and difficulties in forming healthy   hunger and encourage school atten-
             Nurturing a child’s physical devel-  relationships. Schools, families and   dance, leading to higher enrollment and
           opment is equally important. Proper nu-  communities must work together to pro-  retention rates.
           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                                9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[A smiling child with a cat                                                                        Children celebrating a birthday









           Mentorship and emotional support
           initiatives
             Children who face difficult family
           situations or have experienced trauma
           often struggle with emotional chal-
           lenges. Mentorship programs, such as
           Big Brothers Big Sisters, connect chil-
           dren with positive role models who pro-
           vide guidance, support and encourage-                                                           Children engaged in work in a safe environment
           ment. Similarly, counseling and mental
           health programs in schools help children
           process their emotions and develop
           healthy coping mechanisms, preventing
           long-term psychological distress.
           Studies have shown that children who
           have at least one trusted mentor in their
           lives are more likely to develop resil-
           ience and a positive self-image.   tively to society, driving economic   creativity, think critically and develop
                                           growth, innovation and social harmony.   problem-solving skills, they grow into
           Technology-driven education     Governments and stakeholders must rec-  individuals who drive change and pro-
           access                          ognize that the cost of inaction in early   gress. Many of the world’s greatest
             In the digital age, technology has be-  childhood development far outweighs   leaders, scientists and entrepreneurs at-
           come a powerful tool in bridging educa-  the investment required to support these   tribute their success to the care and edu-
           tional disparities. Non-profits like One   initiatives.         cation they received as children. Pro-
           Laptop per Child and Khan Academy                               grams that promote STEM education,
           offer free or low-cost digital resources to   Stronger societies and economies   entrepreneurship and leadership skills at
           children in remote areas, ensuring that   Countries that prioritize early child-  an early age help develop future vision-
           they have access to high-quality learning   hood education experience long-term   aries who can address global challenges.
           materials. Online learning platforms   economic growth. Well-educated indi-  Caring for children today is an in-
           provide children with the opportunity to   viduals are more likely to secure stable   vestment in the future. By providing
           acquire new skills and knowledge, re-  employment, contribute to the economy   young minds with proper education,
           gardless of their geographic or economic   and break the cycle of poverty. Studies   emotional support and physical well-
           limitations. Technology-driven educa-  show that every dollar invested in early   being, we lay the foundation for a better
           tion is particularly beneficial in regions   childhood education generates signifi-  tomorrow. Programs and initiatives that
           where traditional schooling infrastruc-  cant returns by reducing social welfare   focus on underserved children play a
           ture is lacking, providing children with   costs, lowering crime rates and increas-  crucial role in bridging social gaps and
           an alternative means to continue their   ing workforce productivity. Nations that   ensuring that every child has an equal
           education.                      allocate resources toward childhood de-  opportunity to succeed. As World Care
                                           velopment ultimately build a more com-  Day reminds us each year, our collective
           The long-term benefits of       petitive and sustainable economy.   efforts in nurturing children determine
           investing in children                                           the direction of our society and the qual-
             Investing in early childhood care and   Fostering innovation and   ity of our future. By fostering a culture
           education yields long-term benefits that   leadership           of care, support and education, we em-
           extend beyond individual success. A   A society that nurtures young minds   power the next generation to create a
           well-nurtured child grows into a well-  fosters innovation and leadership. When   world that is not only more prosperous
           rounded adult who contributes posi-  children are encouraged to explore their   but also more compassionate and just. ■

           10                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Hope’s flame                                                    endure and persist. Psychologists and re-

                                                                           searchers have long studied the pro-
                                                                           found impact of hope on the human psy-
           Igniting courage                                                benefits on mental health and overall   INSIGHT
                                                                           che, concluding that it has tangible
                                                                           well-being.
                                                                              Dr. Shane Lopez, a prominent re-
                                                                           searcher in positive psychology, empha-
           and strength                                                    likely to set and achieve goals, demon-
                                                                           sized that hopeful individuals are more
                                                                           strate greater resilience and maintain a
                                                                           higher quality of life. According to his
                                                                           studies, hope is a crucial predictor of
           Hope is the heartbeat of the human spirit. It is the            success, well-being and happiness. It in-
                                                                           stills optimism, encourages problem-
           light that shines in the darkness, guiding                      solving and reduces the likelihood of
                                                                           falling into despair.
           individuals through challenges and inspiring them               Stories of hope in adversity
                                                                              History is replete with inspiring
           to keep moving forward. By Pooja Mehta                          stories of individuals who have demon-


                hroughout human history, hope
                has remained an unwavering
           Tforce that propels individuals for-
           ward, even in the face of adversity. It is
           the invisible yet potent force that instills
           resilience, courage and determination.
           When confronted with challenges that
           seem insurmountable, it is hope that al-
           lows individuals to envision a future
           beyond their suffering. This powerful
           emotion serves as an anchor in turbulent
           times and acts as a guiding light, illumi-
           nating the path towards a better tomor-
           row.
             Every year, on February 17th, the
           world celebrates World Human Spirit
           Day, a day dedicated to recognizing the
           strength and resilience of the human
           spirit. This observance encourages
           people to reflect on the boundless poten-
           tial within them and how hope fuels
           their journey. The significance of this
           day lies in its emphasis on the indomita-
           ble will of individuals to overcome chal-
           lenges, cultivate inner peace and inspire
           others. More than just an abstract con-
           cept, hope is a transformative force that
           has played a crucial role in shaping
           countless lives and uplifting com-
           munities worldwide.
           The transformative power of hope
           in the human spirit
             Hope is more than just wishful think-                                                         A small amount of hope can light up despair
           ing; it is an essential driver of human re-
           silience. It motivates people to push for-
           ward even in dire circumstances,
           reinforcing their belief in the possibility
           of positive change. When everything
           seems lost, hope provides the strength to

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[strated extraordinary resilience and de-
           termination in the face of hardship.
           Their experiences illustrate how hope
           serves as a guiding light, enabling
           people to navigate the darkest times
           with unwavering faith.

           Malala Yousafzai: A voice for
           education
             One of the most compelling modern-                                                            A rescue team saving a person from the rubble
           day examples of hope fueling the human
           spirit is the story of Malala Yousafzai.
           Born in Pakistan, Malala became an ad-
           vocate for girls' education at a young
           age. Despite facing threats from extrem-
           ist groups, she continued to speak out,
           determined to fight for the right to edu-
           cation. In 2012, she survived a life-
           threatening attack by the Taliban but re-
           fused to be silenced. Instead, she
           emerged stronger, using her platform to
           advocate for global education rights.
           Her story embodies the power of hope in
           driving change, proving that one voice
           can inspire millions.
           Nelson Mandela: A legacy of
           resilience                                                                                      A patient deep in thought while resting in a hospital bed
             Nelson Mandela, South Africa’s re-
           vered leader, spent 27 years in prison
           during the apartheid era. Yet, he never
           lost hope in his vision of a free and
           equal society. His belief in a better fu-
           ture sustained him through years of im-
           prisonment, enabling him to emerge as a
           unifying force for his country. Man-
                                           dela’s perseverance is a testament to   more optimistic but also better equipped
                                           how hope can empower individuals to   to handle stress, anxiety and depression.
                                           remain steadfast in their convictions,   Studies have shown that hope serves as
                                           even in the most trying circumstances.   a psychological buffer, reducing the im-
                                                                           pact of negative emotions and fostering
                                           The Chilean Miners: Survival    a sense of control over one’s life.
                                           against the odds
                                             In 2010, 33 miners were trapped un-  Hope as a catalyst for mental well-
                                           derground for 69 days in a collapsed   being
         A blooming flower emerging through cracks in concrete
                                           mine in Chile. With limited supplies and   Hope is closely linked to mental re-
                                           an uncertain rescue timeline, the situ-  silience, which allows individuals to
                                           ation seemed dire. However, the miners   adapt to adversity. Research in the field
                                           clung to hope, supporting one another   of positive psychology suggests that
                                           and maintaining faith that they would be   people with a strong sense of hope ex-
                                           saved. Their endurance and unity be-  perience lower levels of stress and
                                           came a global symbol of human resil-  higher levels of happiness. Hopeful indi-
                                           ience. When they were finally rescued,   viduals tend to adopt a proactive ap-
                                           their story demonstrated how hope can   proach to problem-solving, viewing ob-
                                           sustain the human spirit, even in life-  stacles as temporary rather than
                                           threatening situations.         insurmountable.
                                                                              A study conducted by Dr. C. R.
                                           Psychological and emotional     Snyder, a leading psychologist in hope
                                           benefits of hope                theory, found that individuals with high
                                             Scientific research underscores the   levels of hope exhibit greater motivation
                                           numerous benefits of hope on mental   to achieve their goals. His research em-
                                           health. Hopeful individuals are not only   phasized the “hope theory”, which

           12                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Children playing despite harsh conditions















                                                                                                           A bridge stretching into the horizon
         Unity and the power of hope in overcoming challenges












                                                                              Engage in acts of kindness: Helping
                                                                           others creates a ripple effect of hope and
                                                                           strengthens the human connection.
                                                                              Maintain faith in the future: Believ-
                                                                           ing in the possibility of better days
                                                                           ahead fosters resilience and optimism.

                                                                           Hope’s role in a changing world
           posits that hope consists of three key   only transforms individual lives but also   As the world faces global challenges
           components: goal-setting, pathway   shapes the course of humanity. It is the   such as climate change, conflicts and
           thinking and agency thinking. In simpler   spark that ignites innovation, fuels so-  pandemics, hope remains an essential
           terms, hopeful individuals set meaning-  cial movements and inspires people to   force that drives progress. Activists,
           ful goals, strategize ways to achieve   create a better world. As we observe   leaders and everyday individuals con-
           them and maintain the confidence that   World Human Spirit Day, it is crucial to   tinue to demonstrate the power of hope
           they can succeed.               recognize the significance of hope in   in creating meaningful change. The abil-
                                           sustaining the human spirit and propel-  ity to envision a brighter future em-
           Hope’s role in physical health   ling us forward.               powers people to take action and perse-
             Beyond mental health, hope has been                           vere against odds.
           linked to better physical health out-  Cultivating hope in everyday life   Hope is the heartbeat of the human
           comes. Studies have shown that patients   Hope is not reserved for extraordi-  spirit. It is the light that shines in the
           with a hopeful outlook tend to recover   nary circumstances; it can be nurtured in   darkness, guiding individuals through
           faster from illnesses, have lower levels   daily life. Here are a few ways individ-  challenges and inspiring them to keep
           of inflammation and even exhibit longer   uals can cultivate hope and harness its   moving forward. On World Human
           lifespans. A study published in the jour-  transformative power:   Spirit Day, we celebrate the resilience,
           nal Psychosomatic Medicine found that   Practice gratitude: Focusing on the   courage and unwavering determination
           heart disease patients with a hopeful at-  positives in life helps foster a hopeful   that hope instills in humanity. Whether
           titude were more likely to engage in   outlook.                 in personal struggles or collective en-
           healthy behaviors and adhere to treat-  Set realistic goals: Having clear,   deavors, hope fuels the journey, proving
           ment plans, ultimately improving their   achievable objectives provides a sense   that as long as we dare to dream, there is
           prognosis.                      of purpose and direction.       always a way forward. By embracing
                                             Surround yourself with positivity:   hope, we empower ourselves and others
           Hope as a guiding light for the   Engaging with supportive communities   to rise above adversity, turning even the
           future                          and uplifting content reinforces a hope-  most difficult circumstances into oppor-
             Hope is a powerful force that not   ful mindset.              tunities for growth and transformation.■

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Karma Foundation



           A beacon of hope                                                                                  SPOTLIGHT





           for stray animals





           Karma Foundation exemplifies the power of

           compassion in action. Through their relentless efforts,

           they have saved thousands of lives and set new
           benchmarks in animal welfare. By Aarav Sharma



             n a world where stray and com-
             munity animals often struggle for
           Isurvival, Pune-based Karma Foun-
           dation stands as a sanctuary of hope,
           care and rehabilitation. Established with
           the vision of ensuring that no creature
           suffers, this foundation provides com-
           prehensive veterinary care, sterilization
           and rehabilitation services. By address-
           ing the dire needs of animals in distress,
           Karma Foundation has set a precedent
           for compassionate service and holistic
           animal welfare. The foundation’s com-
           mitment to animal welfare is deeply em-
           bedded in its operational ethos, ensuring
           that every action taken is geared toward
           creating a safer, healthier and more hu-
           mane environment for animals.

           The journey of compassion: Priya
           Kailad’s vision
             Priya Kailad, the President and   a society where people and animals co-  Aditya Makharia: A visionary
           Founder of Karma Foundation, em-  exist in harmony.             leader in animal welfare
           barked on a path of service fueled by   The suffering of stray animals in   Serving as the Vice President and
           empathy and a deep-rooted commitment   Pune prompted Priya to take decisive   Co-Founder of the Karma Foundation,
           to animal welfare. Her early education at   action, leading to the establishment of   Aditya Makharia brings both entrepre-
           St. Joseph's High School laid the foun-  the Karma Foundation. The foundation   neurial expertise and deep empathy to
           dation for her compassionate outlook.   emerged as a haven for injured, aban-  the organization. As a third-generation
           Further studies at Symbiosis College in   doned and sick animals, offering them   entrepreneur in the car rental industry,
           psychology and liberal arts expanded   medical treatment and a nurturing envi-  Aditya has successfully led Makson
           her understanding of societal well-being,   ronment. Under her leadership, the foun-  Luxury Cars LLP to national promi-
           while her time at Jnana Probodhini in   dation has grown into a well-respected   nence. Despite his business commit-
           Pune solidified her resolve to bring   organization, inspiring many to contrib-  ments, he remains dedicated to philan-
           about meaningful change. Her passion   ute to the cause of animal welfare. Her   thropy, playing a pivotal role in Karma
           for understanding human and animal   dedication has not only made a tangible   Foundation’s mission. His ability to bal-
           psychology played a pivotal role in   difference in the lives of animals but has   ance his business and philanthropic en-
           shaping her approach toward stray ani-  also created a ripple effect in society, en-  deavors is a testament to his unwavering
           mals. She realized that animal welfare is   couraging individuals to step forward   dedication to animal welfare.
           not merely about rescuing and treating   and take responsibility for the creatures   Aditya’s education at The Doon
           injured animals but also about fostering   around them.         School in Dehradun and his experience

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Controlling overpopulation with
                                                                           compassion
         Priya Kailad & Aditya, founders, Karma Foundation                 ing unchecked breeding, the foundation
                                                                              To combat the overpopulation of
                                                                           stray animals, Karma Foundation offers
                                                                           free sterilization services. By prevent-
                                                                           not only mitigates suffering but also
                                                                           promotes a healthier coexistence be-
                                                                           tween humans and animals. Ad-
                                                                           ditionally, free anti-rabies vaccinations
                                                                           are administered to ensure a safer envi-
                                                                           ronment for both animals and the com-
                                                                           munity. Overpopulation is one of the
                                                                           primary causes of suffering among stray

                                                                           tition for resources, higher chances of
                                                                           disease outbreaks and more instances of
                                                                           human-animal conflict. The founda-
           as a national-level table tennis player   works around the clock, responding to   animals, as it leads to increased compe-
                                                                           tion’s sterilization efforts are aimed at
           have shaped his leadership and compet-  distress calls and emergencies, often   addressing this issue in a humane and
           itive spirit. His belief in the principle of   putting their own safety on the line to   effective manner.
           “live and let live” is reflected in his re-  ensure an animal gets the urgent care it   Through sustained sterilization pro-
           lentless efforts to rehabilitate animals   needs. These efforts have not only saved   grams, the foundation has managed to
           and promote their welfare. Through his   countless lives but have also fostered a   reduce the number of homeless animals
           vision and commitment, the foundation   greater sense of compassion within the   on the streets significantly. These ef-
           has expanded its reach, rescuing and re-  community, encouraging more individ-  forts have also led to a decrease in
           habilitating thousands of animals an-  uals to participate in rescue missions   cases of road accidents involving ani-
           nually. His ability to channel his success   and offer assistance.   mals and instances of animal cruelty.
           in business into making a meaningful
           difference in the realm of animal welfare
           sets an example for many aspiring entre-
           preneurs who wish to merge their pro-
           fessional achievements with social re-
           sponsibility.

           Rescue and rehabilitation:
           Providing a second chance
             At the heart of Pune, Karma Founda-
           tion operates a multi-specialty charitable
           hospital dedicated to rescuing and re-
           habilitating stray animals. Beyond medi-
           cal treatments, the organization provides                                                       A dog undergoing surgery
           a refuge for animals in distress, offering
           them a chance at a renewed life.
           Through every act of kindness, the foun-
           dation contributes to creating a society
           where the well-being of all beings is a
           shared responsibility. The rescue and re-
           habilitation efforts go beyond basic
           medical care, as they focus on rein-
           tegrating animals into safer environ-
           ments, ensuring they receive continuous
           care and, wherever possible, facilitating
           adoptions so that these animals find per-
           manent, loving homes.
             One of the most crucial aspects of the
           foundation’s work is its hands-on ap-                                                           Doctors working diligently to do their best
           proach to rescuing animals in dire situ-
           ations. Be it a severely injured dog on
           the streets, an abandoned pet left to fend
           for itself, or an animal suffering from
           malnutrition, the foundation ensures that
           help reaches them in time. The team

           16                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[An injured dog being prepared for surgery













                                                                                                           Post-surgical care



         A devoted team on a mission to rescue helpless animals


                                                                           vis, who was then the Deputy Chief
                                                                           Minister of Maharashtra, honored
                                                                           Karma Foundation with an award, ce-
                                                                           menting its reputation as a trailblazer in
                                                                           animal welfare.
                                                                           Future plans: Expanding the reach
                                                                           of compassion
                                                                              Karma Foundation envisions a future
                                                                           where veterinary care extends beyond
                                                                           urban boundaries to rural India. Their
                                                                           upcoming initiatives include expanding
                                                                           medical aid to rural communities where
                                                                           veterinary assistance is scarce, empow-
                                                                           ering farmers with animal healthcare
           By working closely with local com-  Achievements and impact     knowledge and conducting rabies pre-
           munities, the foundation raises aware-  Karma Foundation’s efforts have   vention awareness programs. The foun-
           ness about the importance of steriliza-  yielded remarkable results, making a   dation also plans to establish a sanctuary
           tion and vaccination, ensuring that   significant impact on animal welfare in   for specially-abled animals, providing
           people understand their role in creating   Pune. Over the years, the foundation has   long-term rehabilitation and a safe space
           a safe and controlled animal population.   vaccinated over 50,000 animals against   for those unable to survive on the
                                           rabies, ensuring both human and animal   streets. Sustainable models, such as vet-
           Breaking barriers to veterinary   safety. More than 10,000 animals have   erinary training programs and pet taxi
           care                            been rescued and rehabilitated, with   services, will continue to fund these ini-
             Karma Foundation’s Community   many of them finding permanent homes   tiatives, ensuring that the foundation re-
           Clinic operates on a philanthropic   or safe environments where they can   mains self-sufficient while making a
           model, ensuring that financial con-  thrive. The foundation’s community   lasting impact.
           straints never hinder access to essential   clinic has provided treatment to over   Karma Foundation exemplifies the
           medical care for stray animals. The   20,000 animals, offering everything   power of compassion in action. Through
           clinic provides free treatments, vaccina-  from emergency care to routine check-  their relentless efforts, they have saved
           tions and surgeries, addressing both im-  ups. The sterilization initiative has suc-  thousands of lives and set new bench-
           mediate and long-term health concerns.   cessfully conducted over 20,000 proce-  marks in animal welfare. By combining
           This initiative is a testament to the   dures, significantly reducing stray   medical care, community engagement
           transformative power of generosity in   animal overpopulation. During the   and sustainable funding models, they
           animal healthcare.              COVID-19 lockdown, the foundation   have created a self-sufficient system that
             The clinic not only caters to stray   played a crucial role in feeding over   continues to make a difference. As they
           animals but also offers affordable treat-  500,000 animals, ensuring that those   expand their reach to rural areas and es-
           ment for pets from low-income fam-  who depended on scraps and leftovers   tablish new initiatives, the foundation
           ilies, ensuring that no animal is de-  for survival were not left starving during   remains steadfast in its mission to create
           prived of medical care due to financial   the crisis. Recognizing their outstanding   a world where every animal is treated
           limitations.                    contribution to society, Devendra Fadna-  with dignity and care. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[EXCLUSIVE















                                                                                                           Dr. Priti Kale, founder of Jio Foundation











           Dr. Priti Kale



                                                                           The inspiration behind Jio
           A life dedicated                                                foundation
                                                                              Dr. Kale's calling for social work
                                                                           began early. Visiting her father's native
                                                                           village, Fattepur, she witnessed the
                                                                           harsh realities of rural life; lack of roads,
           to social change                                                opportunities. The stark contrast be-
                                                                           schools, healthcare, and employment
                                                                           tween urban and rural living ignited a
                                                                           lifelong mission within her.
                                                                              "I always felt that these challenges
                                                                           should be addressed," she recalls. "That
           "Every effort counts," she emphasizes. Together,                realization stayed with me, and when I
                                                                           moved to Pune, I saw similar issues in
           we can create a more just, equitable and                        different forms; education gaps, health-
                                                                           care deficiencies, and lack of economic
           compassionate world. By Anaya Gupta                             opportunities. That’s when I knew I had
                                                                           to do something."
                                                                              This desire to create change led to
                                                                           the birth of Jio Foundation, an organiza-
                 r. Priti Kale, founder of Jio   Marriage brought her to Pune, where   tion dedicated to improving education,
                 Foundation, Pune, has dedicated   she became part of an educated and in-  healthcare, and economic empowerment
           Dher life to uplifting communities   fluential family. With her husband, Dilip   for underprivileged communities.
           and fostering sustainable change. Born   Kale, a successful businessman, and her
           in Ahmedpur, a town in Maharashtra’s   father-in-law holding a high-ranking po-  Overcoming challenges and
           Latur district, her upbringing was   sition in the education department, she   establishing a vision
           steeped in the values of education and   found unwavering support to pursue her   Like any transformative initiative,
           service. With both parents in the educa-  passions; be it education, business, or   setting up Jio Foundation came with
           tion sector; her father a college principal   social work. Over the years, she has   hurdles. Securing funding, assembling a
           and her mother running a school; Dr.   earned multiple degrees, including a   committed team, and forming partner-
           Kale was raised with a deep sense of so-  Ph.D. in Corporate Finance, an MBA in   ships were some of the initial struggles.
           cial responsibility.            Corporate Law, and certifications in   However, Dr. Kale’s determination
             "My parents instilled in me the   yoga and classical music. Her diverse   never wavered. Through extensive re-
           values of culture, humanity, and civic   expertise and strong educational back-  search and community engagement, the
           duty," she shares. "They shaped me into   ground laid the foundation for her future   foundation identified its core focus areas
           the person I am today."         initiatives.                    and set about making a tangible impact.

           18                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Educational support for underprivileged children
         Dr. Priti constantly updates herself to help the needy


















                                                                           Jio Foundation expanding its reach,
                                                                           strengthening partnerships, and advocat-
                                                                           ing for policy changes to address sys-
             One of their first major projects fo-  broadened my perspective," she shares.   temic social issues. She firmly believes
           cused on empowering women. Work-  "I’ve seen resilience in the most difficult   that NGOs will play an increasingly crit-
           shops on digital literacy, financial   situations, and it has only strengthened   ical role in tackling global challenges.
           schemes, market access, and personality   my commitment."          To young individuals aspiring to
           development provided women with the   Her dedication has meant making   work in the social sector, her message is
           tools to achieve economic independ-  personal sacrifices; setting aside her   clear: "Be passionate, persistent, and pa-
           ence. "The response was incredible," she   own business ventures and hobbies to   tient. Listen, learn, and adapt. Most im-
           says. "Seeing women gain confidence   focus on social work. But the rewards   portantly, believe in the power of collec-
           and become self-reliant proved we were   far outweigh any loss.   tive action to drive change."
           on the right path."               One memory stands out vividly. Dur-  As for those looking to contribute,
                                           ing the COVID-19 lockdown, Jio Foun-  there are many ways to get involved;
           A legacy of impact and          dation was distributing food to slum   volunteering, donating resources, or
           achievements                    areas and senior citizens. An elderly   simply spreading awareness about the
             Over the years, Jio Foundation has   couple, both over 80, reached out, un-  cause. "Every effort counts," she empha-
           made remarkable strides. They have es-  able to get food due to their age and   sizes. "Together, we can create a more
           tablished sustainable livelihood pro-  health. With no volunteers nearby, Dr.   just, equitable, and compassionate
           grams, taught skills like solar equipment   Kale personally delivered meals to their   world."
           assembly, and leveraged social media   doorstep. "Their gratitude, the tears in   Summing up her journey, Dr. Kale
           for economic growth. Medical camps   their eyes; it was the best award I could   describes it as "satisfactory, meaningful,
           have provided healthcare to thousands,   ever receive," she says. "No honor or   holy, and joyful." Her parting advice to
           while educational initiatives continue to   recognition compares to that moment."   her younger self? "Let’s work together
           uplift underprivileged children and                             to create a more beautiful world. Life is
           women.                          A vision for the future         beautiful, and the world is beautiful;
             "One of our most challenging times   Looking ahead, Dr. Kale envisions   let’s make it even more so." ■
           was during the COVID-19 pandemic,"
           Dr. Kale recalls. "Reaching affected
           communities, securing medicines, and
           ensuring people had access to hospital
           beds was overwhelming. But our team
           adapted, stayed informed, and worked
           relentlessly to provide relief."
             Measuring impact is a crucial part of
           their work. "We rely on community
           feedback, data analysis, and expert eval-
           uations to refine our approach," she ex-
           plains. "It’s important to constantly                                                           Cultivating greenery as a personal passion
           evolve and ensure we’re addressing real
           needs."
           A personal commitment to change
             Her work with Jio Foundation has
           been life-changing for Dr. Kale. "It has

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH
















































           Fueling the hustle                                                 n a world that thrives on speed, effi-
                                                                              ciency, and multitasking, the de-
                                                                           Imand for instant energy solutions
                                                                           has never been greater. Energy drinks
                                                                           have emerged as an integral part of the
           The rise of                                                     modern hustle, providing a quick boost
                                                                           to individuals navigating hectic sched-
                                                                           ules. From students burning the mid-
                                                                           night oil to professionals powering
           energy drinks                                                   become a go-to source of energy. But
                                                                           through deadlines, these beverages have
                                                                           how did energy drinks carve a niche for
                                                                           themselves, and what makes them so es-
                                                                           sential in contemporary lifestyles?
           in modern life                                                  The rise of energy drinks

                                                                              Energy drinks first gained promi-
                                                                           nence in the late 20th century, with
                                                                           brands like Red Bull leading the charge.
           Energy drinks have become a symbol of modern                    Their promise of increased alertness, en-
                                                                           hanced physical performance, and a
           ambition and resilience, fueling individuals across             quick energy fix resonated with a gener-
                                                                           ation that increasingly prioritized pro-
           various walks of life. By Aditya Joshi                          ductivity. Over time, the market ex-

           20                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Assorted energy drink brands on display                                                           Coffee paired with an energy drink

















           panded, introducing a variety of flavors,   study session, energy drinks promise an   Cultural and social acceptance
           sugar-free options, and natural formula-  immediate energy boost. The caffeine   Energy drinks have embedded them-
           tions to cater to diverse consumer pref-  content, combined with sugar or sugar   selves in popular culture. From esports
           erences.                        substitutes, acts as a quick pick-me-up,   tournaments to music festivals, they are
             Today, energy drinks represent a   enabling individuals to stay alert and   marketed as lifestyle products. Their vi-
           multi-billion-dollar industry. According   productive.          brant branding and association with
           to market research, global sales are ex-                        high-energy events have made them
           pected to surpass $100 billion by 2030,   Convenience in a bottle   symbols of an active, ambitious life-
           driven by increasing demand from   Unlike brewing coffee or preparing a   style.
           younger consumers, athletes, and busy   snack, energy drinks offer a ready-to-
           professionals. The evolution of energy   consume solution. The portability of   Energy drinks and students
           drinks has transformed them from a   these beverages makes them perfect for   For students, energy drinks have be-
           niche product into a mainstream lifestyle   people on the move, whether commut-  come synonymous with late-night study
           choice.                         ing, traveling, or working long hours.   marathons and exam preparation. The
                                                                           pressure to excel academically often
           Why energy drinks appeal to     Targeted formulations for specific   leads to long hours of reading, writing,
           modern lifestyles               needs                           and revising, and energy drinks provide
             The appeal of energy drinks lies in   Modern energy drinks are not one-  the fuel to keep going.
           their ability to cater to the demands of a   size-fits-all. Brands now offer drinks
           fast-paced world. Here are some key   with added vitamins, electrolytes, and   Fighting fatigue
           reasons they’ve become a staple for so   herbal extracts like ginseng or guarana,   Caffeine, the primary ingredient in
           many:                           appealing to health-conscious con-  most energy drinks, stimulates the cen-
                                           sumers. Some are even tailored to en-  tral nervous system, improving focus
           Instant energy for long days    hance focus, reduce fatigue, or support   and reducing the perception of tiredness.
             Whether it’s an early morning meet-  physical endurance, catering to students,   This makes it easier for students to con-
           ing, a grueling workout, or a late-night   gamers, and athletes alike.   centrate during extended study sessions.












         A student studying late at night













           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[A Cognitive edge
             Some energy drinks claim to enhance
           mental clarity and memory, which is
           particularly appealing to students. Ing-
           redients like taurine and B vitamins are
           often marketed as brain-boosting, al-
           though scientific evidence supporting
           these claims remains mixed.
           Accessibility
             Energy drinks are readily available in
           vending machines, convenience stores,
           and supermarkets, making them an easy
           choice for students seeking a quick                                                             Athletes drinking energy drinks for fitness
           energy fix.

           Fueling professionals on the go
             For working professionals, energy
           drinks serve as an antidote to workplace
           fatigue. Whether it’s meeting tight dead-
           lines, traveling for business, or enduring
           long hours in the office, these beverages
           help employees stay sharp and produc-
           tive.

           Surviving the daily grind
             The high-paced nature of modern
           work environments often leaves little
           room for rest. Energy drinks offer pro-
           fessionals a way to combat the mid-af-
           ternoon slump or stay awake during
           overnight shifts.

           A productivity tool
             Energy drinks are often seen as tools
           to boost productivity, enabling profes-
           sionals to power through demanding                                                              Energy drinks from various brands
           tasks. Their stimulating effects can im-
           prove reaction times, alertness, and
           overall performance during critical mo-
           ments.

           Networking and socializing
             Beyond their functional benefits,   redients like caffeine and beta-alanine,   and Rockstar have heavily invested in
           energy drinks have also found a place in   which are known to improve stamina   sponsoring athletes and sports events,
           professional networking and social set-  and endurance during workouts. Con-  making their products synonymous with
           tings. From business mixers to corporate   suming an energy drink before exercise   physical prowess and adventure.
           events, they are often served as non-al-  can help athletes push their limits and
           coholic options, appealing to those who   achieve better results.   Concerns and moderation
           want to stay energized without consum-                             While energy drinks are undeniably
           ing alcohol.                    Post-workout recovery           popular, they are not without contro-
                                             Some energy drinks are formulated   versy. Excessive consumption can lead
           The role of energy drinks in sports   with electrolytes and amino acids, mak-  to side effects such as increased heart
           and fitness                     ing them suitable for post-workout re-  rate, anxiety, and disrupted sleep. Health
             Athletes and fitness enthusiasts are   covery. These drinks help replenish lost   professionals often caution against rely-
           another key demographic for energy   nutrients and reduce muscle fatigue.   ing too heavily on these beverages, par-
           drinks. These beverages often feature                           ticularly for adolescents and individuals
           ingredients designed to enhance physi-  Sponsorship and branding in   with pre-existing health conditions.
           cal performance, making them a popular   sports
           choice in gyms and sporting arenas.   The association of energy drinks with   The Sugar debate
                                           extreme sports and athleticism has   Many energy drinks are criticized for
           Pre-workout boost               further cemented their place in the fit-  their high sugar content, which can con-
             Many energy drinks contain ing-  ness world. Brands like Monster Energy   tribute to weight gain and other health

           22                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[issues. However, the rise of sugar-free
           and low-calorie options has provided
           healthier alternatives for consumers.

           Caffeine overload
             Caffeine, while beneficial in mod-
           erate amounts, can be harmful in excess.
           Overconsumption of energy drinks has
           been linked to cases of caffeine toxicity,
           emphasizing the need for responsible
           usage.
           Regulation and labeling
             Governments and health organiza-
           tions are increasingly scrutinizing
           energy drink marketing and labeling
           practices. Some countries have intro-
           duced restrictions on sales to minors or
           mandated clearer labeling to inform con-
           sumers about potential risks.                                                                   The energy drink craze

           The future of energy drinks
             As consumer preferences continue to
           evolve, the energy drink industry is
           adapting to meet new demands. Innova-
           tions in formulation, sustainability, and
           marketing are shaping the future of this
           dynamic sector.

           Health-conscious options
             The growing emphasis on health and
           wellness has led to the rise of natural
           energy drinks, which use organic ing-
           redients, plant-based caffeine, and mini-
           mal sugar. These products appeal to con-
           sumers seeking a cleaner energy boost.                                                          Participant enjoying an energy drink at an extreme sports event
           Sustainability efforts
             Many energy drink companies are
           committing to sustainable practices,









                                           such as using recyclable packaging and   excellence to professionals striving for
                                           sourcing ingredients ethically. This shift   success and athletes pushing their physi-
                                           reflects the values of environmentally   cal limits, these beverages provide the
                                           conscious consumers.            energy and focus needed to keep up with
                                                                           today’s demands.
         Stylishly designed energy drink can  needs. Advances in technology could   powerful allies in the hustle of modern
                                           Customization and personalization
                                                                              However, as with any lifestyle pro-
                                             The future may also see personalized
                                                                           duct, moderation and informed choices
                                                                           are key. While energy drinks can be
                                           energy drinks tailored to individual
                                           enable consumers to create custom for-
                                                                           life, they should be consumed respon-
                                           mulations based on their activity levels,
                                                                           sibly to avoid potential health risks. As
                                                                           the industry continues to innovate and
                                           health goals, and dietary preferences.
                                                                           adapt, energy drinks are poised to re-
                                             Energy drinks have become a symbol
                                           of modern ambition and resilience, fuel-
                                                                           main an integral part of our daily rou-
                                           ing individuals across various walks of
                                                                           come. ■
                                           life. From students chasing academic
           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in   tines, powering the hustle for years to  23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION                                                       Top: Scientist Albert Einstein and his pipe


                                                                           Bottom: Sherlock Holmes with a pipe



































           More than just smoke


                                                                           cerns and changing social attitudes, its
           The symbolism                                                   where iconic figures have made the pipe
                                                                           legacy continues in literature and film,
                                                                           an unforgettable cultural artifact. The
                                                                           day serves as an opportunity for pipe en-
                                                                           thusiasts and cultural historians to re-
                                                                           flect on the influence of this age-old tra-
           of pipe smoking                                                 dition and how it continues to shape
                                                                           perceptions today.
                                                                           The literary legacy of pipe smoking
                                                                              The most famous literary figure asso-
           Pipe smoking has played a significant role in literature,       ciated with pipe smoking is undoubtedly
                                                                           Sherlock Holmes, the brilliant detective
           cinema, and cultural symbolism, representing                    created by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle.
                                                                           Holmes’ curved briar pipe is as iconic as
           wisdom, intellectual depth, and a contemplative                 his deerstalker hat, symbolizing his in-
           nature. By Ishita Desai                                         tellectual prowess and methodical rea-
                                                                           soning. The pipe not only serves as a
                                                                           physical prop but also as an extension of
                hroughout history, pipe smoking   vision has reinforced its cultural signifi-  his character; an indicator of deep
                has held a distinct place in human   cance, immortalizing it as a symbol of   thought and contemplation. Holmes’
           Tculture, often associated with   deep thought and a distinguished per-  frequent moments of puffing on his pipe
           wisdom, contemplation, and a refined   sona.                    while solving cases have ingrained the
           lifestyle. From ancient traditions to   Recognized annually, International   image of pipe smoking as a symbol of
           modern artistic representations, the   Pipe Smoking Day celebrates the her-  intelligence.
           image of a pipe smoker has been closely   itage and tradition of pipe smoking, ac-  Beyond Holmes, pipe smoking has
           tied to intellect, sophistication, and an   knowledging its impact on culture and   been a recurring motif in literature, often
           air of mystery. The portrayal of pipe   the arts. While the practice has seen a   associated with wisdom and sophisticat-
           smoking in literature, cinema, and tele-  decline in popularity due to health con-  ion. J.R.R. Tolkien, a devoted pipe

           24                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[A philosopher smoking a pipe                                                                      Bollywood actor, producer and director Guru Dutt












           smoker himself, infused his love for
           pipes into his works, particularly in The
           Lord of the Rings, where Gandalf and
           Bilbo Baggins are frequently depicted
           enjoying pipe weed. Their smoking rit-
           uals symbolize relaxation, camaraderie,
           and a connection to an old-world charm.
           The act of sharing a pipe often serves as
           a metaphor for deep conversations and
           forming bonds, as seen in the Shire’s
           culture. Similarly, figures like C.S.
           Lewis and Mark Twain, both pipe
           smokers in real life, often included pipe-
           smoking characters in their works, rein-
           forcing the notion that intellectuals and
           storytellers are drawn to the ritual.                                                           A vintage tobacco pipe
             Beyond Western literature, many
           Eastern literary works also depict pipe
           smoking. In Chinese and Japanese lit-
           erature, historical figures and wise sages
           are often shown smoking a pipe, signify-  tective’s brilliance. Later adaptations,   smoking characters, reinforcing their
           ing wisdom and experience. The long-  including those starring Robert Downey   depth and complexity. In contrast, mod-
           stemmed pipes in traditional Chinese   Jr. and Benedict Cumberbatch, have   ern Indian cinema has largely moved
           culture, often associated with scholarly   modernized Holmes while maintaining   away from pipe smoking, reflecting con-
           figures, reflect the meditative nature of   the pipe’s cultural association.   temporary concerns about smoking-re-
           pipe smoking. Many classical works and   One of the most distinguished cine-  lated health risks.
           folk tales in China portray elders sitting   matic figures who popularized pipe   Beyond Bollywood, regional Indian
           in courtyards, puffing on their pipes   smoking was Professor Indiana Jones’   films have also depicted pipe smoking
           while imparting wisdom to the younger   mentor, Dr. Henry Jones Sr., played by   as a marker of authority and tradition. In
           generations, reinforcing the notion that   Sean Connery in Indiana Jones and the   Bengali cinema, directors like Satyajit
           pipe smoking is a reflective and intellec-  Last Crusade. His pipe represented   Ray have used pipe-smoking characters
           tual practice.                  scholarly wisdom and old-world charm,   to establish gravitas and intellectual
                                           adding depth to his character.   depth. In films like Nayak, intellectual
           Pipe smoking in cinema and        In Indian cinema, pipe smoking has   characters are often seen smoking a
           television                      also played a crucial role in defining   pipe, using it as a device to establish
             In film, pipe smoking has long been   characters. Bollywood films from the   their contemplative nature. Similarly, in
           associated with authoritative and wise   1950s to the 1970s often featured intel-  South Indian cinema, characters rep-
           characters. Hollywood’s Golden Age   lectual, aristocratic, or villainous char-  resenting old-world wisdom, such as
           saw actors such as Basil Rathbone, por-  acters smoking a pipe. The legendary   landlords or village heads, are often
           traying Sherlock Holmes, emphasizing   Ashok Kumar, known for his nuanced   shown with a pipe, reflecting their status
           pipe smoking as a trademark of the de-  performances, often portrayed pipe-  and wisdom.

           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[The cultural symbolism of pipe   bert Einstein were well-known pipe   concerns and environmental impact, the
           smoking                         smokers, reinforcing the idea that the act   world of pipe smoking has also evolved.
             Pipe smoking’s portrayal in literature   stimulates thought and creativity.   Traditional wooden pipes are now being
           and film has contributed to its enduring   In cinematic and literary narratives,   complemented by eco-friendly pipes
           image as an intellectual and sophisti-  pipe-smoking characters are frequently   made from sustainable materials such as
           cated practice. Unlike cigarette smok-  depicted as mentors, wise elders, or   bamboo and ceramic. Many pipe enthu-
           ing, which is often linked to rebellion or   strategists, reinforcing the association   siasts advocate for organic, additive-free
           impulsivity, pipe smoking is depicted as   with deep thinking. Even in fantasy and   tobacco to minimize harmful effects
           a slow, contemplative activity. Philos-  historical films, pipe smoking remains a   while preserving the ritualistic pleasure
           ophers such as Sigmund Freud and Al-  tool for character development. For in-  of smoking.
                                           stance, in Pirates of the Caribbean, Cap-  The growing popularity of herbal and
                                           tain Hector Barbossa is seen smoking a   non-tobacco smoking blends has also
                                           pipe, adding to his persona as a sea-  contributed to a shift in perception.
                                           soned, worldly pirate. Similarly, in The   Many individuals now opt for nicotine-
                                           Hobbit films, Gandalf’s pipe-smoking   free alternatives, using pipes for relaxa-
                                           scenes serve to emphasize his ancient   tion rather than habitual smoking. The
                                           wisdom and connection to tradition.   renewed interest in pipe craftsmanship,
                                             Pipe smoking is also associated with   particularly handmade pipes from arti-
                                           storytelling traditions. Many cultures   sans, has kept the tradition alive while
                                           have historical figures who would   aligning with contemporary values of
                                           smoke a pipe while narrating folklore or   sustainability.
                                           discussing philosophy. This connection   Shaping public perception: From
         Pipe smoking for fashion          even as fewer people engage in it in   ern society has largely moved away
                                           between smoking and storytelling has
                                                                           tradition to contemporary views
                                           kept the practice alive in symbolic form,
                                                                              Despite its rich cultural history, mod-
                                           daily life.
                                                                           from glorifying smoking in any form
                                           The modern-day perspective: Eco-
                                                                           due to health risks. However, in the
                                                                           world of cinema and literature, pipe
                                           friendly pipes and tobacco
                                             With increasing awareness of health
                                                                           smoking remains a powerful symbol
                                                                           rather than just a habit. The visual ap-
                                                                           peal of a pipe-smoking character con-
         Pipe smoking is now popular among women too                       depiction of smoking in films and TV,
                                                                           tinues to evoke nostalgia, wisdom, and
                                                                           authority.
                                                                              Even as health policies restrict the
                                                                           classic portrayals of pipe smokers re-
                                                                           main deeply ingrained in popular cul-
                                                                           ture. The ritualistic aspect of packing
                                                                           and lighting a pipe, inhaling and exhal-
                                                                           ing the smoke in moments of deep
                                                                           thought, remains a compelling cinematic
                                                                           and literary device.
                                                                              Pipe smoking has played a signifi-
                                                                           cant role in literature, cinema, and cul-
                                                                           tural symbolism, representing wisdom,
                                                                           intellectual depth, and a contemplative
                                                                           nature. Whether in the hands of Sher-
                                                                           lock Holmes solving mysteries, Gandalf
                                                                           reflecting on Middle-earth, or legendary
                                                                           figures in Indian and Hollywood films,
                                                                           the image of a pipe smoker carries an
                                                                           aura of sophistication and thoughtful-
         An elderly woman smoking a pipe                                   legacy, celebrating not just the act of
                                                                           ness. International Pipe Smoking Day
                                                                           serves as a reminder of this enduring
                                                                           pipe smoking but the cultural and artis-
                                                                           tic impact it has had across generations.
                                                                           While modern sensibilities may have
                                                                           shifted away from smoking, the cine-
                                                                           matic and literary legacy of the pipe re-
                                                                           mains timeless, continuing to shape pub-
                                                                           lic perception in meaningful ways. ■

           26                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                February 16-28, 2025






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Career momentum continues; stay focused and     Harmony returns in relationships. Career pro-
                     proactive. Love life flourishes, but balance is   spects are bright, but teamwork is essential. Be
                     needed between personal and professional        cautious with financial decisions, avoid unnec-
                     commitments. Financially, avoid impulsive       essary expenses. A new fitness routine benefits
                     spending. Prioritize self-care to maintain energy.   health.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     A period of stability, but patience is key in   Scorpio, emotional clarity leads to stronger rela-
                     relationships. Professional matters require     tionships. Work requires adaptability, embrace
                     diplomacy, avoid conflicts. Financial gains are   changes. Financially, it’s a stable period. Pay at-
                     possible through smart planning. Health remains   tention to diet and exercise for long-term health
                     good, but relaxation is necessary.              benefits.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     An exciting phase for networking and social-    Sagittarius, an excellent time for travel and new
                     izing. Career progress is steady, but distractions   experiences. Professional growth is steady, and
                     may arise. Love life is adventurous; singles may   creative ideas shine. Romantic opportunities
                     meet someone special. Keep an eye on stress     arise. Keep stress levels in check with outdoor
                     levels and sleep patterns.                      activities.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Work demands increase, but rewards follow.      Capricorn, your career progress continues, but
                     Family matters require attention, avoid emo-    patience is needed. Love life sees steady growth,
                     tional outbursts. Financially, be cautious with in-  listen actively. Financially, wise investments pay
                     vestments. Mental well-being is crucial; med-   off. Maintain a work-life balance to avoid fa-
                     itation can help.                               tigue.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     A leadership role may present itself; embrace it   Aquarius, your innovative ideas gain rec-
                     with confidence. Romantic relationships deepen,   ognition. Relationships thrive with open com-
                     but don’t let ego interfere. Finances improve   munication. Finances remain strong, but avoid
                     with disciplined spending. Health is stable; focus   risky ventures. Mental well-being improves
                     on fitness.                                     through mindful activities.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, your attention to detail pays off profes-  Pisces, a period of self-reflection leads to emo-
                     sionally. Personal relationships require compro-  tional clarity. Work requires persistence, don’t
                     mise, listen actively and silently. Financially, this   lose your focus and be patient. Love life is ful-
                     is a good period for your savings. Take breaks to   filling, but set realistic expectations. Prioritize
                     avoid burnout.                                  rest and rejuvenation.


           FEBRUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 www.revoir.in                               27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           President's Rule in Manipur
                                           Committee appointed by the govern-
             The imposition of President's Rule in
                                           ment. Currently, no such committee has
           Manipur, following N. Biren Singh's
                                                                           rapidly, creators must exercise caution
                                           been proposed, making any claims of an
           resignation, raises questions about   made by an independent Fare Fixation   day’s digital era, where content spreads
           resolving ethnic strife and restoring   imminent hike baseless.   and sensitivity in their expressions.This
           normalcy. The state has been experiencing   This misinformation appears to stem   case serves as a stark reminder of the
           ethnic conflict between the Meitei and   from the recent fare increase in Benga-  fine line between humor and insensitiv-
           Kuki-Zo communities since May 2023,   luru's metro system, which has sparked   ity. Content creators and influencers
           resulting in over 200 deaths and the   anxiety among metro users in Delhi. As   must recognize their influence and take
           displacement of 60,000 people.   millions of commuters rely on the metro   responsibility for their words. The ongo-
             President's Rule, under Article 356,   daily for affordable and efficient travel,   ing legal scrutiny reflects society’s in-
           effectively transfers state government   it is crucial to prevent unnecessary   creasing demand for ethical behavior
           functions to the Centre2. This marks the   panic. The DMRC’s assurance that fares   and accountability in digital spaces.
           11th time Manipur has been placed under   remain unchanged should provide relief.   Naresh Kumar, Bhopal, Madhya Pra-
           central rule since 1951. The BJP, which   Instead of spreading rumors, efforts   desh, India
           was against President's Rule in principle,   should be made to ensure transparency
           struggled to find a consensus CM   in policy decisions that directly affect
           candidate, leading to this decision.   the public.              Marriage vs. Partnership: A
             Rights activist Irom Sharmila argues   Nandita Sharma, Delhi, India   Perspective on Commitment
           that President's Rule is not a solution and                        I appreciate your thought-provoking
           emphasizes the need for honest political                        editorial, "Marriage or Partnership," in
           will to restore peace. She suggests inviting   The fine line between humor and   the recent issue. While love is the foun-
           the titular king of Manipur to serve as a   accountability      dation of any relationship, the institution
           symbol of unity and forming intra-state   The recent controversy surrounding   of marriage has stood the test of time ac-
           mini-assemblies to represent different   Ranveer Allahbadia’s inappropriate re-  ross cultures and civilizations.
           ethnic groups. Whether President's Rule   marks on India’s Got Latent has esca-  Marriage provides stability, legal rec-
           can resolve the deep-rooted issues   lated to alarming levels, leading to mul-  ognition, and a structured commitment,
           remains to be seen.             tiple FIRs and police investigations. His   ensuring a secure environment for future
           Ashok Gupta, Delhi, India       crude joke about parents has sparked   generations. In contrast, live-in relation-
                                           widespread outrage, resulting in signifi-  ships often lack longevity and create so-
                                           cant backlash, including lost brand deals   cial challenges, especially concerning
           Delhi Metro Fare Hike: Separating   and a noticeable decline in social media   inheritance, family structure, and emo-
           Fact from Fiction               followers.The Assam Police’s summons   tional security. Additionally, I must ap-
             The recent speculation about a fare   and the Supreme Court’s involvement   preciate the beautiful, elegant, and artis-
           hike in the Delhi Metro following the   highlight the gravity of the situation.      tic cover page of this issue; it truly
           AAP government's exit is unfounded   While Allahbadia has issued an apology,   captures the essence of creativity, so-
           and misleading. The Delhi Metro Rail   stating that "comedy is not my forte,"   phistication, and elegance, making it a
           Corporation (DMRC) has officially de-  the incident raises serious questions   visual delight for readers.
           nied any changes to the fare structure,   about the accountability of public fig-  Shahid Ali Siddiqui I.R.S (Retd.) New
           clarifying that revisions can only be   ures and the impact of their words. In to-  Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           28                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA["A horse is the projection of people's dreams

                         about themselves; strong, powerful, beautiful."


                                                   — Pam Brown

































































                                                                                                                Photo credit: Betty]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                                                                                      |
                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                      |
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                      |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                               V
                                                                               V
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                              .in
                                                                              .in
                                                                                ol. 3, No.1 |
                                                                                ol. 3, No.2 |
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                .in

                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                         |


                                                                                          | AUGUST 01 202432
                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                                   16 2025
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                                   01 2025
                                                                                          AUGUST
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                        DECEMBER 01 2024




                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |

                                                    www
                                                        .revoir
                                                        .revoir
           32
                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.4 | FEBRUARY 16 2025DECEMBER 16 2024OBER 01 2024
                                                    www
                                                             .in
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                            www
                                                            www
                                                             .in
           32
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025OBER 16 2023
           32
           32
           32
           32
           3232
           32
           3232
           32
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                            .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                            .in
                                                                       www
                                                                   www
                                                                    www
                                                                    www
                                                                .revoir
                                                                .revoir
                                                                   www
                                                                     www
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                     www
                                                                    .in
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in REVOIR
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>