<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                       VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 07 I  APRIL 01 2025  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: MARINA ABROSIMOVA








           11                     15                                                                 19


















           22                                                                                         5
                                   8


















           4-Editorial: How fake news distorts re-         18-Remembering Dr. Sunita Saxena
           ality                                           19-The quiet crisis of lost playtime

           5-Social media and health perception            22-When bodies speak louder than

           8-The real cost of fake news                    words
           11-The cultural shifts in a work-from-          25-Party etiquette in the modern era

           home era                                        28-Horoscopes

           15-Emotional intelligence in romantic           29-Letters

           relationships





           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                   3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[The Viral Trap
     EDITORIAL  How fake news                                                     Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           distorts reality                                                     Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                           n an era where information travels faster   Navormi Vats
                                           than ever, the battle between truth and
                                        Ivirality has become a defining challenge   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        of our time. Social media platforms, once   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        hailed as democratizing forces, now serve
                                        as conduits for both enlightenment and    Social Media Editor
                                        deception. The spread of fake news is no     Vikas Babbar
                                        longer a trivial concern, it shapes elections,
                                        fuels social unrest and undermines trust in   Art & Graphics Editor
                                        institutions. But why does misinformation    Vipin Kumar
                                        thrive and what are the consequences of its
                                        unchecked proliferation?
                                           Falsehoods have an undeniable     EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
                                        advantage over facts: they are often more
           sensational, emotionally charged and easily digestible. Studies show that   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           misinformation spreads faster and reaches wider audiences than the truth. In a digital   Editor, United News of India, New
           landscape where engagement drives algorithms, virality becomes the ultimate   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           currency. The more outrageous the claim, the more likely it is to be shared,   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           reinforcing biases and deepening ideological divides.             Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             The human mind is wired to seek information that confirms existing beliefs. Fake   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           news exploits this tendency, creating echo chambers that insulate individuals from   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           opposing viewpoints. The consequences extend beyond mere misunderstanding.
           Misinformation about public health crises, for instance, has led to vaccine hesitancy,   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           undermining efforts to control global pandemics. Similarly, politically motivated   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           disinformation has eroded democratic institutions, sowing distrust among citizens
           and weakening electoral integrity.                                      SUBSCRIPTIONS
             In the age of misinformation, journalists and fact-checkers have become frontline
           warriors. Yet, their efforts often feel like an uphill battle against an endless wave of   Phone +91 20 40199102
           deceptive content. While initiatives like AI-driven fact-checking tools and media   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           literacy campaigns aim to combat false narratives, their effectiveness hinges on   Baner Road,
           public willingness to engage critically with information. The challenge remains: how   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           do we cultivate a culture that values truth over engagement metrics?   Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
             Social media companies have responded with varying degrees of commitment.   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
           Platforms like X (formerly Twitter), Facebook and WhatsApp have integrated fact-  Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
           checking systems, flagged misleading posts and adjusted algorithms to curb the   Founding year 2023
           spread of disinformation. However, these measures are often reactive rather than   Subject Multidisciplinary
           preventative.                                                         Frequency Fortnightly
             The fight against fake news is not solely the responsibility of tech companies or   Format Online
           journalists, it requires collective vigilance. Citizens must develop critical thinking   Language English
           skills, educators must promote media literacy and policymakers must enforce   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           accountability without infringing on free expression. Truth may not always be as   Website www.revoir.in
           viral as falsehood, but its preservation is essential for the integrity of societies
           worldwide.                                                               Legal Advisor
                                                                                 Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Truth or trend?



           Social media and health                                                                               IN-DEPTH




           perception






                By Siddharth Mehta

             n today’s hyper-connected world, so-
             cial media has become a primary
           Isource of information for millions.
           Whether it is news updates, lifestyle
           trends, or health advice, platforms like
           Facebook, Twitter, Instagram and Tik-
           Tok are shaping public opinions and be-
           haviors. While this digital shift has de-
           mocratized information, it has also
           blurred the line between credible knowl-
           edge and misinformation, raising con-
           cerns about the accuracy and reliability
           of health-related content online.
             World Health Day serves as a timely
           reminder to analyze the profound impact
           social media has on public health. From
           promoting awareness about diseases and
           preventive care to fueling the spread of
           unverified medical claims, the digital
           landscape plays a crucial role in shaping
           health perceptions and behaviors. For
           general readers, healthcare profes-
           sionals, policymakers, researchers and
           tech analysts, understanding this in-
           fluence is essential to leveraging social
           media for positive health outcomes
           while mitigating its risks.
           The dark side: Misinformation and
           its consequences
             Despite its benefits, social media is
           also a breeding ground for misinfor-
           mation. A growing number of people
           rely on online posts rather than qualified
           doctors for medical advice. One alarm-
           ing trend is self-prescription based on
           viral social media posts. Many individ-
           uals begin taking medicines without
           proper medical consultation, believing
           in unverified health claims that may be
           misleading or even harmful. This behav-
           ior can lead to drug interactions, incor-                                                       A young woman scrolling through her phone
           rect dosages and worsening health con-
           ditions.
             Another prevalent issue is the wide-
           spread adoption of “Dadi Maa and Nani
           Maa ke Nuskhe” (grandmother’s home
           remedies). While some traditional

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                   5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[HASHTAG


            The power of social
            media in health

            awareness

              Social media has revolutionized
            the way health information is shared
            and consumed. During global health
            crises, such as the COVID-19 pan-
            demic, these platforms played a cru-                                                           A doctor describing the medicine
            cial role in disseminating critical in-
            formation about symptoms,
            preventive measures, and vaccina-
            tion. Public health organizations, in-
            cluding the World Health Organiza-
            tion (WHO) and the Centers for   remedies have scientific merit, others   ified claims linking vaccines to severe
            Disease Control and Prevention   lack empirical support and can be inef-  side effects have led to decreased vacci-
            (CDC), leveraged social media to   fective or dangerous. For example, con-  nation rates, posing a public health
            reach a vast audience with scientifi-  suming excessive turmeric for inflam-  threat. The impact of this has been ob-
            cally backed guidelines.       mation without understanding dosage   served during the COVID-19 pandemic,
              Beyond emergencies, social   recommendations or replacing pre-  where false claims about vaccine ing-
            media campaigns have successfully   scribed antibiotics with herbal concoc-  redients and side effects led to hesitancy
            raised awareness about chronic dis-  tions can pose significant health risks.   in many parts of the world.
            eases, mental health, fitness, and nu-  Many people believe that natural   Fitness and mental health advice –
            trition. Hashtags like #MentalHeal-  remedies are completely safe, overlook-  Social media has encouraged fitness and
            thAwareness and                ing the fact that certain herbs can inter-  mindfulness practices, but unrealistic
            #HeartHealthMonth have fostered   act with medications or cause side ef-  body standards and unverified psycho-
            discussions, reduced stigma, and en-  fects.                   logical advice can lead to self-esteem is-
            couraged healthier lifestyles. More-  Furthermore, the rise of unregulated   sues and mental health struggles. Some
            over, influencers and healthcare pro-  health influencers has exacerbated the   influencers, despite lacking proper cre-
            fessionals are using these platforms   issue. Some promote miracle cures and   dentials, provide mental health advice
            to educate the public through engag-  alternative treatments without scientific   that can sometimes trivialize serious
            ing content, live Q&A sessions, and   backing, leading vulnerable individuals   mental disorders.
            expert interviews, making health   to follow potentially harmful practices.   Medical crowdsourcing – Patients
            education more accessible.     The phenomenon of "echo chambers",   often seek medical advice from online
                                           where users are repeatedly exposed to   communities instead of professionals.
                                           the same type of content, can reinforce   While support groups can provide emo-
                                           misinformation and create resistance to   tional backing, self-diagnosis and peer
                                           evidence-based medicine.        recommendations can delay proper
                                                                           treatment. This phenomenon is particu-
                                           Social media’s influence on health   larly concerning in the case of rare dis-
                                           attitudes and behaviors         eases, where misinformation can lead
                                             The way social media presents health   patients to disregard professional medi-
                                           information significantly influences   cal advice in favor of anecdotal experi-
                                                                           ences.
                                           public attitudes and behaviors. This can
         A grandmother preparing a homemade remedy  treme diets, detox teas and supplements   has the potential to drive meaningful
                                           be seen in:
                                                                           How social media can be used for
                                             Diet trends and fad diets – Many
                                                                           positive change in healthcare
                                           social media influencers promote ex-
                                                                              Despite its challenges, social media
                                           without scientific backing. While some
                                                                           health improvements. By leveraging its
                                           of these trends encourage healthier eat-
                                                                           reach and engagement, various stake-
                                           ing, others can lead to disordered eating
                                                                           holders can transform social media into
                                           habits and nutritional deficiencies. The
                                                                           a credible health resource:
                                           glorification of unattainable body im-
                                           ages further exacerbates issues related to
                                                                              Enhancing digital literacy – Edu-
                                           self-esteem and body dysmorphia.
                                                                           cating the public on how to differentiate
                                             Vaccine hesitancy – Misinformation
                                                                           mation is crucial. Schools, governments
                                                                           and social media companies can col-
                                           reluctance in some communities. Unver-
           6                               regarding vaccines has fueled fear and   between credible sources and misinfor-
                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[A doctor giving professional advice                                                               A confused lady looking for health advice on social media














                                           led discussions can provide trustworthy   tech companies – Social media com-
                                           alternatives to unverified claims. Hospi-  panies should integrate expert health
                                           tals and medical schools can also col-  panels to review content and implement
                                           laborate with influencers to spread ev-  warning labels for questionable medical
                                           idence-based health information in an   advice. Facebook, YouTube and Twitter
                                           engaging format.                have started taking steps in this direc-
                                             Community-based health cam-   tion, but more needs to be done to com-
                                           paigns – Governments and NGOs can   bat the vast spread of misinformation.
                                           utilize social media for targeted health   Encouraging responsible journal-
                                           campaigns, focusing on disease preven-  ism – News agencies and journalists
                                           tion, vaccination drives and mental   play a role in ensuring that health news
                                           health awareness. Interactive campaigns   is accurately reported. Sensationalism in
                                           that involve the audience, such as live   health reporting can lead to unnecessary
                                           sessions with doctors or Q&A threads,
                                                                           panic and misinformation. Ethical jour-
         A girl receiving a vaccine        ity.  Encouraging responsible in-  prevent misleading health claims.
                                           can create a sense of trust and credibil-
                                                                           nalism practices should be reinforced to
                                                                              Social media is a double-edged
                                                                           sword when it comes to public health.
                                           fluencers – Influencers must be held ac-
                                                                           On one hand, it is an incredible tool for
                                           countable for the health information
                                           they share. Partnering with medical ex-
                                                                           education and supporting positive be-
                                           perts and referencing scientific studies
                                                                           havioral changes. On the other, it am-
                                           can enhance the credibility of their   spreading awareness, fostering health
           laborate on digital literacy initiatives to   content. Brands and advertisers should   plifies misinformation, promotes unsafe
           promote critical thinking. Teaching indi-  also prioritize working with health in-  self-medication practices and influences
           viduals to verify sources, cross-check   fluencers who adhere to ethical and ev-  risky health behaviors.
           information and recognize biased   idence-based practices.         For social media to serve as a reliable
           content can significantly reduce the                            source of health information, all stake-
           spread of false health claims.   The role of policymakers and   holders, including general readers,
             Fact-checking and regulation – So-  public health officials   healthcare professionals, policymakers,
           cial media platforms must work along-  To ensure that social media serves as   researchers and tech analysts, must col-
           side health organizations to flag and re-  a force for good in healthcare, policy-  laborate to ensure accuracy, regulate
           move misleading health content.   makers and public health officials need   content and enhance digital literacy. By
           Algorithms should prioritize reliable   to take proactive steps:   leveraging its potential while minimiz-
           sources, while policymakers should in-  Stronger policies on health misin-  ing its risks, we can transform social
           troduce stricter regulations against med-  formation – Governments must work   media into a powerful ally for global
           ical misinformation. The integration of   with tech companies to regulate mis-  health.
           AI-driven content moderation could be a   leading health claims and enforce trans-  As we observe World Health Day, let
           potential solution to detecting and re-  parency in content algorithms.   this be a moment to reflect on how we
           ducing harmful content in real time.   Funding for health communication   consume and share health information
             Engaging healthcare professionals   – Increased investment in digital health   online. The responsibility lies not just
           – Encouraging doctors, researchers and   communication can improve outreach   with institutions but with each individ-
           medical institutions to be more active on   efforts and ensure accurate information   ual to question, verify and promote reli-
           social media can help counteract misin-  reaches diverse populations.   able health knowledge for a healthier so-
           formation. Verified accounts and expert-  Public health collaboration with   ciety. ■

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                   7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SPECIAL REPORT







































           Truth vs. Virality                                               AI-Powered Fact-


                                                                            Checking: Grok’s Role on X
           The real cost of                                                  ingly vital in fact-checking, with
                                                                               Artificial intelligence is increas-

                                                                             tools like Grok, developed by xAI
                                                                             for X (formerly Twitter), playing a
           fake news                                                         bots, Grok leverages real-time X
                                                                             unique role. Unlike traditional chat-
                                                                             data to verify information, aiming
                                                                             to combat misinformation on a plat-
                                                                             form known for rapid news dissemi-
                                                                             nation. Its ability to analyze posts
                                                                             and trends offers potential for swift
           While platforms like Facebook, Twitter, WhatsApp and              fact-checking, but concerns persist.

           Instagram have implemented various measures to                    Experts worry about AI’s limita-
                                                                             tions in detecting nuance, like sar-
           curb false information, the challenge of balancing free           casm and its reliance on potentially
                                                                             biased or unverified X content.
           speech and factual accuracy persists.  By Riya Verma              While Grok’s updates in 2025 have
                                                                             improved accuracy, its past errors,
                                                                             like false election claims, highlight
             n an era where information is in-  trol this influx of misleading content,   the risks, underscoring the need for
             stantly accessible and widely shared,   fact-checking has emerged as a critical   human oversight in AI-driven truth-
           Isocial media has become a double-  tool to uphold truth in the online sphere.   seeking efforts.
           edged sword. While it empowers indi-  Observed on April 2nd, International
           viduals with knowledge and fosters   Fact-Checking Day serves as a reminder
           global connections, it also serves as a   of the importance of verifying infor-  institutions to fueling public health
           breeding ground for misinformation.   mation before accepting it as truth. This   crises. As social media giants like Face-
           False claims about health, politics and   day emphasizes the necessity of fact-  book, Twitter (now X), WhatsApp and
           social issues can spread rapidly, in-  checking in an age where misinfor-  Instagram navigate the complex land-
           fluencing public perception and behav-  mation can have real-world con-  scape of moderating content, it is crucial
           ior. As digital platforms struggle to con-  sequences, from eroding trust in   to examine how these platforms are ad-

           8                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[A confused reader looking at misleading headlines                                                 Fake news on social media displayed on a phone




















                                                                           accuracy. If deemed misleading, Face-
                                                                           book reduces its reach, attaches warning
                                                                           labels and notifies users who have inter-
                                                                           acted with the post. Additionally, re-
                                                                           peated offenders face penalties, such as
                                                                           reduced visibility or account suspension.
                                                                           Twitter (X): Community notes and
         Fact-checking is important for society                            ized fact-checking model through its
                                                                           policy enforcement
                                                                              Twitter (X) has adopted a decentral-

                                                                           "Community Notes" feature. Users con-
                                                                           tribute contextual information to poten-
                                                                           tially misleading tweets and if approved
                                                                           by a diverse group of contributors, these
                                                                           notes appear alongside the original post.
                                                                           While this approach promotes crowd-
                                                                           sourced accountability, it also raises
                                                                           concerns about the effectiveness of self-
                                                                           moderation in combating misinfor-
           dressing misinformation and the chal-  content and fake news shape public   mation at scale.
           lenges they face in balancing free   opinion. Given the influence of social
           speech with accuracy.           media in shaping narratives, fact-check-  WhatsApp: Limits on forwarding
                                           ing has become a necessary intervention   and automated fact-checking
           The rise of misinformation on   to safeguard public discourse.     Given its end-to-end encryption,
           social media                                                    WhatsApp faces unique challenges in
             The digital age has revolutionized the   How social media platforms are   moderating misinformation. Unlike pub-
           way information is consumed. However,   addressing misinformation   lic platforms, fact-checkers cannot di-
           with the democratization of content cre-  To curb the spread of falsehoods,   rectly monitor messages. To counter the
           ation, misinformation has found fertile   major social media platforms have im-  spread of false claims, WhatsApp has
           ground. Social media algorithms prior-  plemented various fact-checking mech-  implemented limits on message for-
           itize engagement, often amplifying sen-  anisms. While their approaches differ,   warding, preventing viral distribution of
           sational or controversial content, regard-  the common goal is to reduce the visibil-  unverified content. It has also intro-
           less of its accuracy. This has led to the   ity of misleading content and provide   duced chatbots that allow users to verify
           widespread dissemination of misleading   users with reliable information.   forwarded messages through partner-
           information, particularly in critical areas                     ships with fact-checking organizations.
           such as health, elections and global   Facebook: Third-party fact-
           crises.                         checking and content labeling   Instagram: Content moderation
             For instance, during the COVID-19   Facebook (now Meta) has one of the   and ai-driven fact-checking
           pandemic, misinformation about un-  most extensive fact-checking programs,   Instagram, also under Meta, employs
           proven treatments, vaccine risks and   partnering with over 90 independent   AI-driven content moderation alongside
           government conspiracies flourished on-  fact-checking organizations worldwide.   human fact-checkers. Posts that contain
           line. The same pattern is observed dur-  When a piece of content is flagged as   misinformation are blurred with a warn-
           ing elections, where manipulated   potentially false, fact-checkers assess its   ing label and users must click through to

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[view them. Additionally, misleading
           health-related content is deprioritized in
           search results to prevent its widespread
           circulation.

           Challenges in balancing free
           speech and accuracy
             While fact-checking is essential in                                                           AI bots Grok analyze information on social media
           combating misinformation, social media
           platforms face several obstacles in en-
           suring both accuracy and freedom of ex-
           pression.

           The subjectivity of truth and bias
           allegations
             Determining what constitutes "misin-
           formation" is often subjective. Critics ar-  Checking Network (IFCN) provide
           gue that fact-checking organizations   transparent methodologies and source-
           may have political or ideological biases,   based analysis to debunk false claims.
           leading to concerns about selective cen-
           sorship. Content moderation policies   Key Functions of Fact-Checkers:
           have sparked debates about whether   Verification of viral content: Identify-
           platforms should have the authority to   ing and correcting misleading infor-
           determine what is true and what is not.   mation circulating widely on social
                                           media.
           The speed and scale of            Educating the public: Encouraging
           misinformation                  digital literacy and teaching users to
             Misinformation spreads faster than   critically assess online content.
           fact-checks can be issued. A single mis-  Collaborating with platforms: Work-
           leading post can reach millions before   ing with tech companies to flag, reduce,
           being flagged. Fact-checking organiza-  or remove harmful misinformation.
           tions, though diligent, often play catch-  Providing context: Explaining why
           up, struggling to keep pace with the   certain claims are false, rather than                    Fact-checking in action
           sheer volume of false information cir-  simply labeling them as misinformation.
           culating online.
                                           Moving forward: strengthening
           Algorithmic challenges and echo   digital integrity
           chambers                          While fact-checking is a crucial tool,   Strengthening fact-checker
             Social media algorithms are designed   it is not a standalone solution. To create   support
           to prioritize engagement over accuracy.   a healthier digital ecosystem, social   Independent fact-checking organiza-
           Users are often trapped in echo   media companies, governments and the   tions require funding, resources and
           chambers, where they are exposed pri-  public must take collective action.   stronger collaborations with tech com-
           marily to content that aligns with their                        panies to scale their efforts effectively.
           beliefs. This makes it harder for fact-  Enhancing ai and human oversight   As social media continues to shape
           checked information to penetrate com-  Advanced AI models can help detect   public opinion, the battle against misin-
           munities resistant to opposing view-  misinformation at scale, but human   formation remains ongoing. While plat-
           points.                         oversight is still necessary to prevent er-  forms like Facebook, Twitter, WhatsApp
                                           rors and ensure fairness in moderation   and Instagram have implemented var-
           Resistance to fact-checking     decisions.                      ious measures to curb false information,
             Many social media users view fact-                            the challenge of balancing free speech
           checking as an infringement on their   Promoting media literacy   and factual accuracy persists. Fact-
           freedom of speech. Some dismiss   Educational initiatives should teach   checkers play a pivotal role in this fight,
           flagged content as censorship, reinforc-  users how to identify misinformation,   yet they alone cannot solve the problem.
           ing mistrust in both fact-checkers and   differentiate between credible and dubi-  A multi-faceted approach, combining
           the platforms enforcing these policies.   ous sources and fact-check independ-  technological innovation, public aware-
                                           ently.                          ness and transparent governance, is es-
           The role of fact-checkers in a                                  sential to ensuring a more informed and
           digital world                   Increasing transparency in      responsible digital landscape.
             Fact-checkers play an indispensable   moderation policies        On this International Fact-Checking
           role in verifying claims and educating   Platforms must be transparent about   Day, let us acknowledge the critical role
           the public about misinformation. Organ-  their fact-checking criteria and algo-  of truth in our digital age and commit to
           izations like Snopes, PolitiFact, Fact-  rithms to build trust among users and re-  fostering a more fact-driven online
           Check.org and the International Fact-  duce accusations of bias.   world. ■

           10                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Co-workers or strangers?                                        ideas, strengthen professional relation-
                                                                           ships and enhance workplace camarade-
                                                                           rie. These moments, though seemingly
           The cultural                                                    sense of belonging and community.     INSIGHT
                                                                           small, played a crucial role in fostering a
                                                                              Remote work, however, has signifi-
                                                                           cantly reduced these spontaneous ex-
                                                                           changes. Now, most conversations are
                                                                           scheduled via video calls or chat plat-
           shifts in a work-                                               forms, eliminating the natural ebb and
                                                                           flow of daily interactions. Employees no
                                                                           longer run into colleagues serendipi-
                                                                           tously, which can lead to a sense of iso-
                                                                           lation. Over time, this lack of casual
           from-home era                                                   connection can impact collaboration,
                                                                           creativity and even job satisfaction.
                                                                              This shift also influences mentorship
                                                                           and career growth opportunities. In tra-
                                                                           ditional offices, younger employees or
           The transition to remote work has reshaped not just how         newcomers benefit from overhearing
                                                                           conversations, receiving informal guid-
           we work but also how we socialize. By Rohan Kapoor              ance and observing workplace dy-
                                                                           namics. With remote work, much of this

                he shift to remote work has rev-
                olutionized professional life, of-
           Tfering flexibility, eliminating
           commutes and allowing employees to
           work from the comfort of their homes.
           However, alongside these benefits, a sig-
           nificant transformation is unfolding, our
           social lives are evolving in ways we
           never anticipated. The casual coffee
           break chats, spontaneous brainstorming
           sessions and impromptu after-work
           gatherings that once defined office cul-
           ture are now fading, leaving many to
           wonder: How do we maintain social
           connections in a remote-first world?
             On the occasion of Global Work
           from Home Day, it is crucial to examine
           how this shift is altering social dy-
           namics. While remote work has pro-
           vided unparalleled freedom, it has also
           disrupted traditional means of social in-
           teraction. Professionals across indus-
           tries, whether remote workers, HR
           leaders, or researchers, are grappling
           with the long-term effects on communi-
           cation, collaboration and even mental
           well-being. As we adapt to this new re-
           ality, understanding the challenges and
           solutions is vital for fostering a bal-
           anced, socially connected work-life en-
           vironment.

           The decline of spontaneous office
           interactions
             In traditional office settings, inter-
           actions often happen organically. A                                                             Virtual team meeting
           chance encounter at the coffee machine,
           a quick conversation in the hallway, or
           an informal desk chat could spark new

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Intentional

                 socialization

               Remote workers need to be
            proactive in seeking social inter-
            actions. Scheduling regular virtual
            check-ins with colleagues, partici-
            pating in industry networking
            events and engaging in hobby-
            based online groups can help main-
            tain a sense of connectedness.
               Additionally, setting up local
            meetups for remote workers within                                                              Workers in an office
            the same city or region can help
            bridge the gap between digital and
            face-to-face interactions. Many re-
            mote professionals are now organ-
            izing informal co-working meetups,
            where they gather at cafés or shared
            spaces to work alongside others.


           organic learning is lost, making profes-
           sional development a more deliberate ef-
           fort that requires proactive planning and
           structured mentorship programs.

           The shift in team-building and
           workplace culture
             Team-building activities, once a sta-
           ple of corporate culture, have also un-                                                         Work-from-café scene
           dergone a dramatic transformation. In-
           person retreats, office parties and group
           lunches are being replaced by virtual
           events. While organizations have at-
           tempted to recreate team bonding   active on-boarding programs and virtual   breaks and virtual fitness challenges to
           through online escape rooms, virtual   open-door policies.      encourage employees to bond in new
           coffee breaks and digital team games,                           ways.
           many employees find these interactions   How remote workers are seeking   However, these virtual gatherings are
           less engaging than their in-person coun-  new social avenues    not a one-size-fits-all solution. Some
           terparts.                         Despite these challenges, remote pro-  employees find them awkward or
             Moreover, remote work can lead to a   fessionals are finding creative ways to   forced, highlighting the importance of
           fragmented workplace culture. New em-  maintain social connections and foster a   offering diverse engagement options.
           ployees, in particular, may struggle to   sense of community. Recognizing that   Organizations that provide flexibility, al-
           integrate into a company’s ethos when   traditional office interactions are no   lowing employees to opt into the activ-
           their primary form of interaction is   longer viable, many are turning to alter-  ities that suit their personalities, tend to
           through screens. The absence of physi-  native means to build and sustain rela-  see better participation and engagement.
           cal presence makes it harder for teams to   tionships.
           build trust, resulting in weaker interper-                      Online communities and
           sonal relationships. Companies that fail   The rise of virtual happy hours and   networking platforms
           to address this shift risk fostering a dis-  social events         Platforms like Slack, Discord and
           connected and disengaged workforce.   Virtual happy hours, online trivia   LinkedIn have evolved beyond their
             HR leaders and managers face an on-  nights and digital coffee chats have be-  professional networking roots into social
           going challenge: How can they ensure   come popular ways for remote teams to   hubs where remote workers connect,
           that employees feel a sense of belonging   stay connected. While these events can-  share experiences and engage in casual
           in a digital workspace? Some companies   not fully replicate the warmth of face-to-  conversations. Industry-specific online
           are experimenting with hybrid models   face interactions, they offer a structured   communities, such as those found on
           where employees meet in person period-  way for colleagues to unwind and so-  Reddit and Facebook Groups, also serve
           ically to maintain a sense of connection,   cialize outside of work-related discus-  as vital spaces for remote employees to
           while others are emphasizing digital-  sions. Some companies are even incor-  seek advice, vent frustrations and cele-
           first cultural initiatives, such as inter-  porating wellness sessions, meditation   brate wins together.

           12                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Future of work concept                                                                            Virtual reality in office work









                                           particular, benefit from co-working   The future of social connection in
                                           spaces as they provide structured envi-  remote work
                                           ronments that help maintain work-life   As remote work continues to evolve,
                                           boundaries while also offering the op-  so too will our methods of maintaining
                                           portunity to meet new people. Some   social connections. Advances in tech-
                                           workers opt for 'work-from-café' setups,   nology, such as virtual reality meetings
                                           choosing social work environments to   and AI-driven collaboration tools, may
                                           combat isolation.               further bridge the gap between physical
                                                                           and digital interactions. Additionally, as
                                           Balancing work and social well-  companies refine their remote work
                                                                           strategies, new best practices for foster-
                                           being in a remote world
         A worker at home doing office work  professionals maintain strong social   connection is an essential component of
                                                                           ing social bonds will emerge.
                                             The evolution of remote work pres-
                                           ents an undeniable challenge: How can
                                                                              What remains clear is that human
                                           connections while enjoying the benefits
                                                                           both professional and personal fulfill-
                                           of flexibility and autonomy? The answer
                                                                           ment. While remote work has undeni-
                                                                           ably changed how we interact, it has
                                           lies in a balanced approach that blends
                                                                           also opened the door for innovative
                                           digital and in-person interactions.
                                                                           ways to connect, collaborate and build
                                           Redefining workplace culture
                                                                           traditional office walls.
                                             Corporate leaders and HR profes-
                                                                              The transition to remote work has
                                           sionals must recognize that remote work   meaningful relationships beyond the
             Some remote workers have turned to   requires a redefinition of workplace cul-  reshaped not just how we work but also
           mastermind groups, small, focused on-  ture. Investing in mentorship programs,   how we socialize. While the decline in
           line groups where professionals ex-  digital on-boarding experiences and hy-  spontaneous office conversations and
           change ideas, discuss challenges and   brid team-building activities can help   traditional team-building activities pres-
           support each other’s growth. These   bridge the gap between remote and in-  ents challenges, remote professionals
           groups not only provide social inter-  person workforces.       are actively seeking new ways to main-
           action but also serve as valuable career   Organizations that create open com-  tain and strengthen their social lives.
           development tools.              munication channels, prioritize em-  From virtual happy hours to co-working
                                           ployee well-being and encourage team   spaces, the landscape of professional re-
           The popularity of co-working    bonding through diverse initiatives will   lationships is evolving to meet the de-
           spaces                          foster more engaged and socially con-  mands of a digital-first world.
             For those craving an office-like at-  nected remote employees.   On this Global Work from Home
           mosphere without the rigidity of tradi-                         Day, it is worth reflecting on the social
           tional work settings, co-working spaces   Embracing hybrid work models   implications of remote work and ex-
           have become a compelling solution.   A hybrid model, where employees   ploring ways to foster deeper connec-
           These spaces offer a middle ground,   split their time between home and the   tions despite physical distance. By em-
           providing remote professionals with the   office, can provide the best of both   bracing intentional socialization,
           opportunity to engage with like-minded   worlds. Many companies are adopting   redefining workplace culture, and adop-
           individuals, network and collaborate in a   this approach, allowing employees to   ting inclusive, flexible hybrid models,
           shared environment. Many co-working   enjoy flexibility while still benefiting   remote professionals and organizations
           spaces even host social events, further   from in-person interactions that foster   alike can ensure that flexibility does not
           fostering a sense of community.   stronger relationships and collaboration.   come at the cost of meaningful human
             Freelancers and digital nomads, in                            connection. ■

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[COVER STORY




































           Loving with empathy                                             determine whether a relationship flour-

                                                                           ishes or falters. This article explores
                                                                           how emotional intelligence enhances ro-
           Emotional                                                       mantic relationships and provides practi-
                                                                           cal strategies to strengthen love through
                                                                           self-awareness, empathy and communi-
                                                                           cation.
           intelligence in                                                 Understanding emotional
                                                                           intelligence in relationships
                                                                              Emotional intelligence refers to the
                                                                           ability to recognize, understand and
                                                                           manage one’s emotions while also being
                                                                           attuned to the emotions of others. In ro-
           romantic                                                        mantic relationships, EQ manifests in
                                                                           several key ways:
                                                                              Self-awareness: Understanding one’s
                                                                           own emotions and their impact on the
                                                                           relationship.
           relationships                                                   effectively, preventing impulsive reac-
                                                                              Self-regulation: Managing emotions
                                                                           tions.
                                                                              Empathy: Tuning into a partner’s
                                                                           emotions, fostering deeper connection.
                                                                              Social skills: Communicating openly,
                ove is more than passion and at-  empathy, resolve conflicts constructively   resolving conflicts and nurturing trust.
                traction, it requires deep under-  and foster an emotionally rich bond.   and emotional intimacy despite chal-
                                                                              Motivation: Committing to growth
           Lstanding, effective communica-
                                             In a world where relationships face
        By Aditya Joshi  chemistry and compatibility play vital   tions and personal struggles, emotional   healthier, more fulfilling relationships
                                                                           lenges.
                                           pressures from careers, social expecta-
           tion and emotional resilience. While
                                                                              Couples with high EQ experience
                                           intelligence becomes a crucial tool for
           roles, emotional intelligence (EQ) is the
                                           sustaining love. The ability to manage
                                                                           because they can navigate emotional
           true foundation of a lasting and fulfilling
                                           emotions, understand a partner’s feel-
           romantic relationship. Couples who cul-
                                                                           complexities with grace and understand-
           tivate EQ can navigate challenges with
                                           ings and communicate effectively can
           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in      ing.                        15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Why EQ matters more than IQ in
           love
             While intelligence and shared inter-
           ests can contribute to compatibility,
           studies suggest that emotional intelli-
           gence plays a far greater role in relation-
           ship success. A high IQ may help in
           solving complex problems, but it is EQ
           that enables couples to address emo-
           tional challenges, resolve disagreements
           and sustain affection over time.
             A lack of emotional intelligence
           often leads to miscommunication, unmet
           expectations and growing resentment.                                                            A partner comforting the other
           For example, if one partner fails to rec-
           ognize when the other is feeling stressed
           or unheard, it can create emotional dis-
           tance. On the other hand, a partner with
           high EQ will pick up on subtle cues and
           respond with empathy and support.

           The role of EQ in conflict resolution
             Disagreements are inevitable in any
           relationship, but the way couples handle
           them determines their long-term suc-
           cess. Emotionally intelligent partners
           approach conflicts with a problem-solv-
           ing mindset rather than a combative one.

           Recognizing emotional triggers
             Understanding personal triggers
           helps prevent unnecessary arguments. If
           one partner reacts strongly to criticism,                                                       A couple holding hands while walking
           self-awareness allows them to pause be-
           fore responding defensively. Similarly,
           recognizing a partner’s triggers fosters
           empathy and prevents escalation.
             For instance, if a person grew up in
           an environment where disagreements
           led to yelling, they may become overly   saying “I feel hurt when…” rather than
           defensive in conflicts. Recognizing this   “You never listen…” shifts the conver-
           pattern helps both partners approach dis-  sation from accusation to resolution.
           agreements with patience and reassur-  Emotional self-regulation is key. Tak-
           ance rather than aggression.    ing a pause, breathing deeply, or even
                                           stepping away briefly before responding
           Practicing active listening     can prevent arguments from escalating
             Many conflicts stem from misunder-  into hurtful exchanges.
           standings. Active listening, giving full
           attention, validating emotions and para-  Finding common ground
           phrasing for clarity, helps partners feel   Rather than focusing on winning an
           heard and reduces defensiveness.   argument, couples with high EQ seek
             Instead of waiting for their turn to   mutual solutions. Compromise becomes
           speak, emotionally intelligent individ-  easier when both partners feel respected
           uals focus on truly understanding their   and valued. This means replacing a
           partner’s perspective. This includes   competitive mindset with a collaborative
           maintaining eye contact, nodding in ac-  one, where the goal is not to be right but
           knowledgment and responding thought-  to strengthen the relationship.
           fully rather than reacting impulsively.
                                           Strengthening emotional bonds
           Managing emotions constructively   through empathy                                              A couple feeling close
             Instead of resorting to blame, emo-  Empathy is the ability to understand
           tionally intelligent couples express emo-  and share a partner’s feelings, creating
           tions with “I” statements. For example,   emotional intimacy and trust. Emo-

           16                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Mastering the art of timing
                                                                              Difficult conversations require the
                                                                           right timing. Bringing up a sensitive
                                                                           issue when a partner is exhausted or
                                                                           stressed may lead to unnecessary con-
                                                                           flict. Waiting for a calm moment en-
                                                                           hances receptiveness.
         A couple calmly resolving a conflict                              derstand that boundaries protect rela-
                                                                           Setting healthy boundaries
                                                                              Emotionally intelligent couples un-

                                                                           tionships rather than restrict them. Re-
                                                                           specting personal space, emotional
                                                                           needs and individuality strengthens trust
                                                                           and autonomy within the relationship.

                                                                           Building resilience in love
                                                                              Long-term relationships require resil-
                                                                           ience, the ability to adapt and grow to-
                                                                           gether through life’s challenges.

                                                                           Embracing change together
                                                                              Change is inevitable, whether it’s ca-
                                                                           reer shifts, parenthood, or personal
                                                                           growth. Emotionally intelligent couples
                                                                           view change as an opportunity to evolve
                                                                           rather than a threat to stability.
         A couple meditating together                                      appreciation
                                                                           Practicing gratitude and

                                                                              Expressing gratitude regularly fosters
                                                                           positivity. Simple acts, like acknowledg-
                                                                           ing a partner’s effort or reminiscing
                                                                           about happy moments, reinforce emo-
                                                                           tional connection.

                                                                           Maintaining emotional self-care
           tionally intelligent couples prioritize   more compassionate viewpoint.   A healthy relationship starts with
           empathy as a daily practice, not just dur-                      emotionally healthy individuals. Priori-
           ing conflicts.                  Nonverbal cues matter           tizing self-care, personal passions and
                                             Sometimes, emotions are conveyed   mental well-being contributes to a bal-
           Emotional validation            more through tone, facial expressions   anced partnership.
             Validation doesn’t mean agreeing   and body language than words. Tuning   When both partners take responsibil-
           with everything a partner says, but it   into these cues enhances emotional re-  ity for their own emotional health, they
           does mean acknowledging their emo-  sponsiveness.               bring their best selves into the relation-
           tions as real and important. A simple “I   A gentle touch, a reassuring nod, or   ship, reducing dependency and fostering
           understand why you feel that way” can   even sitting closer during a difficult con-  a more enriching partnership.
           make a world of difference.     versation can communicate support in   Emotional intelligence is the invisi-
             When one partner dismisses the   ways words cannot.           ble thread that weaves strong, resilient
           other’s feelings, it can lead to frustration                    romantic relationships. By fostering
           and emotional distance. Instead, validat-  Promoting healthy communication   self-awareness, empathy and healthy
           ing emotions fosters security and con-  Effective communication is the   communication, couples can navigate
           nection.                        bridge between emotional understanding   love with greater depth and understand-
                                           and relationship success. Emotionally   ing. Whether resolving conflicts,
           Perspective-taking              intelligent couples prioritize clarity, hon-  strengthening bonds, or embracing
             Stepping into a partner’s shoes   esty and kindness in their interactions.   change, emotional intelligence trans-
           fosters deeper connection. If one partner                       forms love into a lifelong journey of
           is overwhelmed with work, instead of   Expressing needs without fear   connection and growth.
           dismissing their stress, the other can   Many couples struggle with un-  In a world where many relationships
           offer reassurance and support.   spoken expectations. Openly expressing   crumble under stress and miscommuni-
             Couples who practice perspective-  needs, whether for affection, space, or   cation, nurturing EQ is not just benefi-
           taking are less likely to hold grudges be-  reassurance, prevents resentment and   cial, it is essential for building a love
           cause they see issues from a broader,   misunderstandings.      that stands the test of time. ■

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[A Timeless Melody



     PROFILE  Remembering





           Dr. Sunita





           Saxena





           In loving memory – A tribute by Dr. Kamran Zuberi


                 pril 14 signifies the birth anni-  practice and pedagogy of Indian classi-  found a permanent place in her home,
                 versary of Dr. Sunita Saxena, an   cal music. Her versatility in Khayal,   one in her drawing room and the other in
           Aextraordinary figure whose life   Thumri, Dadra and Kajri showcased not   her upstairs hall, until her last days.
           was an ode to music, education and deep   just her mastery over diverse genres but
           personal connections. Though she de-  also her ability to breathe life into each   A Moment of Joy That Still
           parted this mortal realm on December 8,   note, each rhythm.    Resonates                         Dr. Sunita Saxena (File Photo)
           2016, her legacy remains an eternal   I had the privilege of highlighting the   Sunita Didi once shared her wish for
           symphony in the hearts of those who   work and contributions of some of her   a profile brochure and I took it upon my-
           knew and admired her.           students in the field of music through   self to design and print one for her.
                                           various articles published in leading   When I handed it over, she was over-
           A Serendipitous Encounter       newspapers across the country. She once   joyed. Later, she showed it to her close
             My first brush with Dr. Sunita Sax-  playfully reprimanded me for writing   friend, Dr. Manorama Trikha, Head of
           ena was not in a concert hall or a class-  extensively about her disciples while   the English Department at CCS Univer-
           room, but through a chance visit to my   omitting her own name. At the time, I   sity, Meerut. The first question Dr.
           Botany professor Dr. N.P. Saxena’s res-  never imagined that we would lose her   Trikha asked was, “Who wrote this?”
           idence during my BSc studies. The air   so soon. In hindsight, every article,   When Sunita Didi inquired why, her
           was filled with the soulful strains of   every mention of her students’ achieve-  friend replied, “Whoever has written this
           classical music emanating from the   ments was, in its essence, a reflection of   truly respects you from the heart.” That
           upper floor, melodies that I later discov-  her influence and dedication to the   moment remains etched in my memory
           ered belonged to the voice I had so heard   world of music.     because it reflected the depth of our
           on All India Radio. That was my first in-                       bond, one built on admiration and deep
           troduction to Sunita Didi, a name I   Personal Bonds and Unforgettable   regard.
           would come to cherish for the rest of my   Moments
           life.                             Over the years, our connection deep-  An Enduring Presence
             It was through my younger brother,   ened and she became a part of my ex-  The day the news of her passing
           Javidan Zuberi, that I eventually had the   tended family. She would call me for ad-  reached me from Didi’s elder brother Dr.
           privilege of meeting her in person. From   vice and I always felt a sense of   N.P. Saxena sir, an ineffable sense of
           that moment on, she became an integral   fulfillment in being able to assist her in   loss settled over me. Even today, there
           part of my family and though she hu-  any way. Helping her was never just a   are moments when I long to visit her
           morously suggested that I should ad-  duty, it was an honor. The happiness she   home to hear her voice filling the air
           dress her as an aunt (Bua), I continued   expressed in simple gestures left a last-  with melody. But the house, the temple
           calling her 'Didi', a term that symbolized   ing imprint on me.   within, the familiar settings, all have
           not just respect but an irreplaceable fam-  One such instance was when I took   faded with time. What remains, ho-
           ilial bond.                     some photographs of her with my SLR   wever, is the indelible imprint she left on
                                           camera. When I enlarged and gifted two   my heart.
           A Luminary in Music and Education   of them to her, she treasured them im-  Like a lingering fragrance, her mem-
             Dr. Sunita Saxena was not merely a   mensely. She once told me that people   ory is a presence that never fades.
           performer, she was an institution in her-  would often ask about the photographer   Though she is no longer with us in form,
           self. A Doctor of Philosophy in Music   who had captured her so beautifully and   her music, her teachings and the warmth
           and the Head of the Department of   she would reply with a smile, "The one   of her spirit continues to resonate, ensur-
           Music at R.G. Postgraduate College,   who clicked these isn’t someone who   ing that Sunita Didi’s melody remains
           Meerut, she devoted her life to both the   just takes photographs." These pictures   eternal. ■

           18                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY









































           Childhood at Risk                                               cation, safety and health, play is a funda-
                                                                           mental aspect of development that de-
                                                                           serves equal attention. As we celebrate
                                                                           this day, it is crucial to address the de-
                                                                           cline of unstructured play in children’s
           The quiet crisis                                                lives and explore ways to restore its sig-
                                                                           nificance.

                                                                           The decline of play in modern
                                                                           childhood
           of lost playtime                                                has transformed drastically. Several fac-
                                                                              Over the past few decades, childhood
                                                                           tors contribute to the diminishing role of
                                                                           play in children's daily lives:
                                                                              Academic pressures: With increased
                                                                           competition, school curriculums have
           By fostering an environment that values free play, we           become more rigorous. Many children
                                                                           attend long hours of school followed by
           can ensure that childhood remains a time of joy,                tuition and homework, leaving little
           discovery and boundless imagination. By Aarav Sharma            room for recreational activities. Even
                                                                           preschoolers face structured learning
                                                                           schedules, limiting their freedom to en-
                                                                           gage in spontaneous play. Standardized
                hildhood, once defined by laugh-  time to explore, create and interact   testing, early academic tracking and pa-
                ter-filled playgrounds and end-  freely. This shift has far-reaching impli-  rental expectations to excel in studies
           Cless imagination, is increasingly   cations, impacting their cognitive, emo-  often come at the cost of leisure and cre-
           overshadowed by the pressures of mod-  tional and social well-being in ways that   ativity.
           ern life. Structured routines, academic   society is only beginning to understand.   Technology and screen time: The rise
           competition, digital distractions and   Recognizing this concern, Inter-  of digital entertainment has replaced tra-
           heightened social expectations are en-  national Children’s Day serves as a re-  ditional outdoor and imaginative play.
           croaching on the simple joys of play. In   minder of the need to protect and prior-  Many children spend hours on smart-
           a world that values productivity over lei-  itize the right to play. While discussions   phones, tablets, or gaming consoles,
           sure, children are often left with little   on children’s rights often focus on edu-  leading to a sedentary lifestyle with

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Children playing in a park                                                                        A kid building with blocks










           fewer opportunities for face-to-face so-
           cial interaction. Video games and social
           media, while engaging, often do not pro-
           vide the same level of sensory and phys-
           ical engagement that traditional play
           does. As a result, many children struggle
           with attention spans, reduced physical
           activity and a lack of interpersonal skills.
             Urbanization and safety concerns:
           In densely populated cities, safe and ac-
           cessible play spaces are scarce. Parental
           fears about crime, traffic and accidents
           further discourage outdoor play, confin-                                                        A group of children playing with toys
           ing children to indoor activities. In many
           urban areas, playgrounds and parks have
           been replaced with high-rise buildings
           and commercial complexes, leaving
           fewer spaces for children to engage in
           free play. Parents who are overprotective
           or overly cautious also contribute to this   in multiple domains:   role-playing, engaging in rough-and-
           decline, as many prefer structured, adult-                      tumble activities, or drawing their feel-
           supervised environments over independ-  Cognitive development:   ings, play helps them navigate complex
           ent outdoor play.               Enhancing creativity and problem-  emotions such as fear, frustration and
             Social expectations and extracur-  solving skills             joy. Additionally, unstructured play re-
           ricular overload: Many parents enroll   Play is a natural vehicle for learning.   duces stress, allowing children to un-
           their children in multiple extracurricular   When children engage in pretend play,   wind and regulate their emotions effec-
           activities, believing that structured learn-  they experiment with different scenarios,   tively. Research from child psychology
           ing enhances future prospects. While   roles and ideas, fostering critical think-  suggests that children who engage in
           such activities are beneficial, an over-  ing, creativity and problem-solving   regular play show greater emotional sta-
           scheduled routine can leave little time   skills. Building structures with blocks,   bility, improved mood regulation and
           for unstructured, self-directed play.   inventing stories, or engaging in make-  lower levels of anxiety and depression.
           Dance classes, music lessons, coding   believe worlds strengthens their ability
           workshops and sports training often take   to think abstractly and develop innova-  Social development: Fostering
           precedence over spontaneous, child-  tive solutions. Studies suggest that chil-  communication and empathy
           driven play, leading to a loss of creativ-  dren who engage in imaginative play de-  Play encourages collaboration and
           ity and autonomy.               velop stronger executive function skills,   negotiation. When children engage in
                                           which include planning, decision-mak-  group activities, they learn essential so-
           Why play matters: Cognitive,    ing and adaptability.           cial skills such as sharing, taking turns,
           emotional and social benefits                                   resolving conflicts and understanding
             Unstructured play, free from adult in-  Emotional development:   others' perspectives. These interactions
           tervention and rigid guidelines, is essen-  Managing stress and building   lay the foundation for emotional intelli-
           tial for a child's holistic development.   resilience           gence and empathy, crucial skills for
           Research in psychology, education and   Children express and process emo-  adulthood. Games that involve coopera-
           neuroscience highlights its significance   tions through play. Whether they are   tion, teamwork and role-playing enable

           20                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[A cityscape without playgrounds                                                                   A child burdened with a heavy school bag















                                                                           Policymakers and child advocates:
                                                                           Enforcing the right to play
                                                                              Develop public play areas: Govern-
                                                                           ments should prioritize the creation of
                                                                           child-friendly parks, playgrounds and
         Parents and children playing together                             Regulations should mandate adequate
                                                                           green spaces in urban planning.
                                                                              Enforce play-friendly school policies:

                                                                           recess periods and discourage excessive
                                                                           academic workload in early childhood
                                                                           education.
                                                                              Support community play initiatives:
                                                                           Investment in after-school programs,
                                                                           community centers and public libraries
                                                                           ties.
                                                                              Implement play-based policies: En-
                                                                           courage workplaces to provide parental
           children to understand social cues, navi-  terials that allow for imaginative explo-  can provide accessible play opportuni-
           gate friendships and develop interper-  ration rather than passive consumption.   leave and flexible hours, allowing par-
           sonal relationships that shape their fu-  Model playfulness: Engage in playful   ents to spend more quality time engag-
           ture social lives.              interactions, such as family game nights   ing in play with their children.
                                           or outdoor adventures, reinforcing the
           Creating opportunities for play: A   value of leisure and fun.   Reclaiming childhood, one playful
           shared responsibility             Trust unstructured play: Avoid micro-  moment at a time
             Reclaiming childhood play requires a   managing playtime; let children lead and   As we observe International chil-
           collective effort from parents, educators,   make their own discoveries.   dren’s day, we must reflect on the chang-
           policymakers and communities. Each                              ing landscape of childhood and take
           plays a pivotal role in restoring balance   The role of schools and educators   decisive steps to restore the lost essence
           and ensuring that children have the free-  Incorporate Play-Based Learning:   of play. A society that neglects play is
           dom to engage in meaningful play ex-  Schools should integrate recess, inter-  one that stifles creativity, emotional
           periences.                      active activities and play-based learning   well-being and social harmony in its fu-
                                           methods into their curriculum.   ture generations.
           What parents and guardians can    Create Play-Friendly Environments:   Play is not a luxury, it is a necessity.
           do                              Schools can design open spaces with   It is a child's first language, their mode
             Prioritize free time: Reduce overly   minimal restrictions, encouraging physi-  of self-expression and a fundamental
           structured schedules and allow children   cal activity and social interaction.   right that should never be compromised.
           to explore activities of their choice with-  Recognize the Value of Unstructured   By fostering an environment that values
           out interference.               Play: Educators should advocate for bal-  free play, we can ensure that childhood
             Limit screen time: Encourage out-  ancing academic rigor with recreational   remains a time of joy, discovery and
           door play, board games, or creative sto-  opportunities.        boundless imagination. The responsibil-
           rytelling as alternatives to digital enter-  Offer Flexible Schedules: Schools   ity lies with all of us, parents, educators,
           tainment.                       should avoid excessive homework loads   policymakers and communities, to create
             Encourage open-ended play: Provide   and allow sufficient breaks for recre-  a world where children are free to be
           simple toys, art supplies and natural ma-  ational play.        children once more. ■

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION















         A street performance highlighting social issues





















                 rt has long been a vehicle for re-  Political performance art
                 sistance, but performance art,
           Awhere the body itself becomes
           the medium, takes activism to an inti-
           mate and visceral level. Whether   When bodies speak
           through silent endurance, provocative
           gestures, or immersive engagement, art-
           ists use their own physical presence to
           communicate powerful messages. From   louder than words
           environmental destruction and police
           brutality to gender inequality and racial
           injustice, performance artists worldwide
           have transformed their bodies into in-  Political performance art is more than spectacle, it is a form
           struments of protest, forcing audiences
           to confront uncomfortable truths.   of resistance that forces society to confront its deepest
             As we celebrate World Art Day, it is   inequalities. Whether through silent endurance, radical self-
           crucial to recognize how performance
           art has challenged oppressive systems,   exposure, or immersive narratives, artists use their bodies to
           questioned authority and amplified mar-  amplify the voices of the unheard. By Naina Kapoor
           ginalized voices. This unique form of
           political expression transcends linguistic
           barriers, resonating deeply with spec-  physically experiencing or simulating   loaded gun, exposing the human capac-
           tators across cultures. By embodying   pain, restriction, or endurance, they   ity for both tenderness and violence.
           suffering, resilience and defiance, artists   compel audiences to witness and engage   Bruguera, a Cuban artist, has been ar-
           turn their performances into acts of so-  with the issues they highlight. This form   rested multiple times for her perform-
           cial activism, creating a dialogue that   of art is often raw and unscripted, allow-  ances critiquing government censorship,
           extends beyond galleries and onto the   ing spontaneity and direct human con-  proving that political performance art
           streets, digital spaces and even political   nection to evoke empathy and action.   carries real-world risks.
           arenas.                           Artists like Marina Abramović and
                                           Tania Bruguera have redefined how the   Global examples of political
           The body as a symbol of protest   body can challenge authority.   performance art
             Performance artists deploy their   Abramović’s 1974 piece Rhythm 0 in-  Ai Weiwei’s Refugee Crisis Art
           bodies in ways that make oppression   vited the public to interact with her body   (China): The Chinese dissident artist Ai
           tangible and resistance undeniable. By   using objects ranging from a feather to a   Weiwei has staged numerous politically

           22                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[A street performance highlighting gender inequality                                               A protester covered in body paint






















                                                                           Chandralekha’s intersection of
                                                                           dance and protest
                                                                              Choreographer Chandralekha fused
                                                                           classical dance with contemporary polit-
                                                                           ical issues. Her performances critique
         A scene from 12 Years a Slave                                     of resistance.
                                                                           consumerism, gender roles and national-
                                                                           ism, transforming the stage into a space


                                                                           Dalit performance art as
                                                                           resistance
                                                                              Dalit artists like Sheetal Sathe use
                                                                           folk and street performances to confront
                                                                           caste-based discrimination. Her group,
                                                                           Kabir Kala Manch, has faced persecu-
           charged performances. In Law of the   Rajkamal Kahlon’s Artistic   tion for their outspoken critique of so-
           Journey (2017), he filled a gallery with   Disobedience (India-USA)   cial hierarchies.
           thousands of life jackets from real refu-  Indian-American artist Rajkamal
           gees, highlighting the plight of displaced   Kahlon deconstructs colonial history   Political performance art in
           populations. His 2016 act of posing as   through performance and visual art. Her   cinema
           the drowned Syrian toddler Alan Kurdi   2011 work Did You Kiss the Dead   While live performance art remains a
           sent a harrowing message about the   Body? explores the violence of state   crucial form of protest, films have also
           human cost of political indifference.   power by reinterpreting forensic autopsy   served as a medium for bodily protest.
                                           photographs of detainees.       Both Bollywood and Hollywood have
           Pussy Riot’s Defiant Performances                               produced films where the characters’
           (Russia)                        Political performance art in India   physical experiences serve as a meta-
             The Russian feminist punk group   India has a rich history of using the   phor for broader social struggles.
           Pussy Riot has used guerrilla-style per-  body as a tool for protest, from street
           formances to protest Vladimir Putin’s   plays to hunger strikes. Artists have   Bollywood films as political
           policies. Their 2012 unauthorized per-  adapted traditional forms to create polit-  performance art
           formance in a Moscow cathedral against   ically charged performances addressing   Bandit Queen (1994): The biopic of
           church-state collusion led to imprison-  caste discrimination, gender violence   Phoolan Devi, a lower-caste woman
           ment, drawing global attention to Rus-  and government policies.   who became a rebel leader, embodies
           sia’s suppression of free speech.                               the intersection of gender and caste op-
                                           Mallika Sarabhai and gender     pression.
           Elia Alba’s The Supper Club (USA)   equality                       Article 15 (2019): A gripping tale of
             American artist Elia Alba stages po-  Dancer-activist Mallika Sarabhai has   a police officer confronting caste-based
           litically charged dinner performances   used Bharatanatyam to challenge patri-  crimes, showcasing the systemic injus-
           where artists, activists and scholars dis-  archal norms. Her performance Shakti:   tices deeply entrenched in Indian soci-
           cuss racial injustice while dressed as   The Power of Women deconstructs   ety.
           their alter-egos, challenging societal   gender violence through movement, giv-  Pink (2016): A courtroom drama that
           narratives about race and identity.   ing voice to silenced women.   challenges India’s victim-blaming cul-

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[ture and underscores women’s right to
           consent.
           Hollywood films as political
           performance art
             12 Years a Slave (2013): The physi-
           cal suffering of enslaved individuals is
           used as a visceral indictment of histori-
           cal and contemporary racism.
             V for Vendetta (2005): The protago-
           nist’s transformation and endurance of
           torture serve as a metaphor for rebellion                                                       Ayushmann Khurrana in Article 15
           against authoritarian rule.
             Judas and the Black Messiah (2021):
           The portrayal of Black Panther leader
           Fred Hampton highlights how the U.S.
           government criminalized Black libera-
           tion movements.

           Performance art in political
           elections
             Beyond art galleries and films, per-
           formance art has found its way into po-
           litical elections. Politicians often use
           their bodies symbolically to connect
           with voters or make statements.
             Ukraine’s Volodymyr Zelenskyy: Be-
           fore becoming president, Zelenskyy, a
           comedian and actor, performed satirical                                                         Mallika Sarabhai performing a dance piece
           acts criticizing corruption, setting the
           stage for his political career.
             India’s protest rallies: Political
           leaders and activists frequently use
           hunger strikes, silent marches and theat-
           rical gestures to challenge governmental
           policies.
             Donald Trump’s rallies: Trump’s
           highly choreographed rallies blur the
           lines between performance art and polit-
           ical spectacle, mobilizing his base
           through calculated gestures and expres-
           sions.
           The future of political performance
           art
             In the digital age, political perform-                                                        Ai Weiwei’s refugee-themed performance installations
           ance art has extended beyond physical
           spaces to virtual platforms. Social media
           allows activists to broadcast live per-
           formances, transforming activism into a
           global phenomenon. Movements like
           #MeToo, Black Lives Matter and cli-
           mate activism have integrated digital
           performance, where bodies remain cen-
           tral to protest even in virtual spaces.
             As art enthusiasts, scholars, activists   Political performance art is more   brate creativity in all its forms, we must
           and general audiences engage with these   than spectacle, it is a form of resistance   also acknowledge the courage of those
           performances, it is crucial to recognize   that forces society to confront its deep-  who put their bodies on the line to chal-
           their power. The body, in its vulnerabil-  est inequalities. Whether through silent   lenge injustice and inspire change. Their
           ity and strength, continues to be an un-  endurance, radical self-exposure, or im-  performances, often at great personal
           yielding force against oppression, em-  mersive narratives, artists use their   risk, remind us that art is not just about
           bodying the struggles and aspirations of   bodies to amplify the voices of the un-  aesthetics but about shaping the world
           entire generations.             heard. On World Art Day, as we cele-  we live in. ■

           24                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT


































           The Do’s and Don’ts                                             fluenced by the times, shaped by social

                                                                           conventions and cultural movements. In
                                                                           the past, formal parties were the stan-
           Party etiquette in                                              seating arrangements and clear hierar-
                                                                           dard, with rigid dress codes, structured
                                                                           chical roles. Today, the landscape has
                                                                           changed significantly:

           the modern era                                                  Dress codes: From formal attire to
                                                                           "come as you are"
                                                                              Gone are the days when attending a
                                                                           party required adhering to strict dress
                                                                           codes. While black-tie events and
           Modern party etiquette reflects the cultural and                themed parties still exist, many modern
                                                                           gatherings embrace a more relaxed ap-
           technological shifts shaping our society.  By Ishita Desai      proach. The "come as you are" philoso-
                                                                           phy, rooted in inclusivity and personal
                                                                           expression, has gained popularity, allow-
               arties have long been a corner-  unity and joy through gatherings, it is   ing guests to feel comfortable in their
               stone of human social interaction,   worth examining how party etiquette has   own skin. However, this shift does not
           Pevolving from structured gath-  transformed. From the rise of digital in-  mean complete disregard for decorum;
           erings with strict etiquette to dynamic,   vitations to the shift towards casual, in-  understanding the host’s expectations re-
           free-flowing celebrations. Over the   clusive events, modern celebrations re-  mains crucial.
           years, the unwritten rules governing   flect broader societal trends.
           party behavior have shifted in response   Understanding these changes can help   Invitations: The rise of digital RSVP
           to cultural, technological and genera-  both hosts and guests navigate contem-  culture
           tional changes. What was once consid-  porary social expectations with con-  Traditionally, party invitations were
           ered impolite or inappropriate may now   fidence and grace.     sent via mail, often requiring formal
           be the norm, while behaviors that were                          RSVPs. Today, digital invitations
           once acceptable may now be frowned   The evolution of party etiquette:   through social media, event platforms
           upon.                           Then vs. now                    and messaging apps have become the
             On World Party Day, a celebration of   Party etiquette has always been in-  norm. While these methods offer con-

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[venience and accessibility, they also in-
           troduce new challenges, such as guests
           failing to RSVP or last-minute cancella-
           tions. Respecting the host’s planning ef-
           forts by responding promptly remains a
           key aspect of modern party etiquette.

           Social media and party behavior
             The advent of social media has dras-
           tically altered party etiquette. Sharing
           party moments online has become sec-                                                            A diverse group of people at a modern party
           ond nature, but this practice comes with
           ethical considerations. Posting photos or
           videos without consent, especially from
           private gatherings, can lead to privacy
           concerns. The modern rule of thumb:
           “Ask before you tag” to respect the pri-
           vacy of fellow guests.

           Inclusivity and accessibility
             Modern parties increasingly prior-
           itize inclusivity. Whether it's ensuring a
           venue is accessible to all guests, offering
           non-alcoholic drink options, or fostering
           a safe and welcoming environment for
           diverse identities, today’s hosts are more
           conscious of making celebrations enjoy-
           able for everyone. The shift from exclu-
           sive guest lists to open-door policies in
           many social circles reflects a broader
           movement towards inclusivity.

           The Do’s and Don’ts of                                                                          A table with a variety of drinks
           contemporary partying
             As social norms continue to evolve, a
           new set of "unwritten rules" governs the
           modern celebration. Here’s a fun guide
           to help you navigate them:      or excessive tagging without consent.
                                           Monopolize conversations – Being a
           Do’s                            good listener is just as important as con-
             Respect the RSVP – If you’ve com-  tributing to discussions. Bring unex-
           mitted to attending, show up or inform   pected guests – Unless it’s an open invi-
           the host in advance if plans change.   tation, always ask before bringing a
           Dress appropriately – Even in casual   plus-one. Overindulge – Whether in
           settings, being mindful of the event’s   food, drinks, or attention-seeking behav-
           tone is key. Engage with different guests   ior, moderation is key.
           – Making an effort to mingle rather than
           staying in closed groups fosters a wel-  Why these changes matter: The
           coming atmosphere. Be mindful of tech-  bigger social picture
           nology – If taking photos, ensure that   The shifting norms of party etiquette                  Friends enjoying a party
           everyone involved is comfortable being   reflect larger societal movements. The
           captured. Know your limits – Whether   rise of digital culture, increased aware-
           it’s alcohol consumption or personal   ness of inclusivity and the prioritization
           space, respecting boundaries is funda-  of mental well-being all play roles in
           mental. Offer to help – A simple gesture   shaping how we celebrate today.   updates instead of personal interactions
           like bringing a dish, cleaning up, or as-                       can sometimes lead to miscommunica-
           sisting the host goes a long way.   The digital influence on party   tions. Finding a balance between digital
                                           dynamics                        convenience and genuine human con-
           Don’ts                            Technology has made it easier to plan   nection is the modern challenge.
             Arrive excessively late – Fashionably   and communicate party details, but it
           late is acceptable, but making the host   has also created new etiquette dilemmas.   Changing attitudes toward alcohol
           wait disrupts the flow of the event.   Ghosting an event, mass-inviting ac-  and substance use
           Overshare online – Avoid live-streaming   quaintances, or relying on social media   Unlike in past decades, where exces-

           26                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[A casual "come as you are" party                                                                  A digital party invitation displayed on a smartphone













                                                                           ities, healthy food options and even re-
                                                                           laxation spaces.
                                                                              One thing remains certain, while tra-
                                                                           ditions may change, the essence of cele-
                                                                           brations remains the same: fostering
                                                                           human connection, joy and shared ex-
                                                                           periences. By embracing the evolving
         A lively yet respectful dance floor                               inclusive and meaningful.
                                                                           norms of party etiquette, we ensure that
                                                                           our gatherings continue to be enjoyable,
                                                                              Modern party etiquette reflects the
                                                                           cultural and technological shifts shaping
                                                                           our society. While certain traditions re-
                                                                           main, the rules of social gatherings have
                                                                           become more fluid, emphasizing inclu-

                                                                           derstanding these evolving norms, both
                                                                           hosts and guests can navigate contempo-
                                                                           rary celebrations with ease and mindful-
           sive drinking was often normalized at   biodegradable decor and locally sourced   sivity, respect and adaptability. By un-
           parties, today’s younger generations are   food.                ness.
           more conscious of their alcohol intake.   Hybrid parties – With the rise of vir-  As we observe World Party Day, it’s
           Many gatherings now feature sophisti-  tual connections, hybrid events combin-  an opportunity to appreciate how cele-
           cated mocktails and alcohol-free zones,   ing in-person and digital participation   brations bring people together, bridging
           acknowledging the diverse preferences   may become more common.   differences, embracing diversity, pro-
           of attendees.                     Wellness-focused celebrations –   moting inclusivity and fostering shared
                                           Parties integrating mindfulness activ-  joy in an ever-changing world. ■
           Gender norms and consent culture
             The party scene has also been af-
           fected by the broader cultural shift to-
           wards respect and consent. The #MeToo
           movement has heightened awareness
           around personal boundaries, making re-
           spectful interactions at social events
           more important than ever. Party hosts
           and attendees are increasingly mindful
           of creating environments where every-
           one feels safe and respected.
           Looking ahead: The future of party                                                              A party balancing fun and personal boundaries
           etiquette
             As societal values continue to evolve,
           party etiquette will likely adapt to new
           cultural shifts. Future trends may in-
           clude:
             Eco-conscious partying – Sustainable
           party planning, including digital invites,

           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                April 01-15, 2025









           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     This is a period of new beginnings. Career growth   Professional life is steady, and teamwork brings
                     is promising, but avoid impulsive decisions. Love   success. Romance is fulfilling, but don’t hesitate
                     life is passionate, but patience is needed.     to express your feelings. Financially, avoid risks.
                     Financially, keep expenses in check. Prioritize   Engage in creative hobbies to maintain emo-
                     physical fitness and mental relaxation.         tional balance.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Stability is key this fortnight. Work progresses   Scorpio, Transformation continues in career and
                     steadily, and long-term planning is beneficial.   personal life. Love life benefits from deep emo-
                     Romance flourishes with open communication.     tional connections. Your financial planning is
                     Financially, avoid unnecessary splurges. Focus on   crucial. Focus on both physical and mental well-
                     improving your diet and sleep patterns.         being.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     A dynamic time with new career opportunities.   Sagittarius, An adventurous time with exciting
                     Social connections help in professional growth.   opportunities. Career moves bring long-term
                     Love life is playful but requires honesty. Be   benefits. Love life is lively but requires commit-
                     mindful of financial decisions. Engage in out-  ment. Stay active and explore new hobbies for
                     door activities for a refreshed mind.           better health.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     You may feel emotionally sensitive, so avoid    Capricorn, Your discipline pays off in profes-
                     overthinking. Career demands effort, but results   sional matters. Relationships are stable but re-
                     will come. Love life requires patience and un-  quire effort to keep things interesting. Finan-
                     derstanding. Financially, stability improves with   cially, wise investments pay off. Take breaks to
                     smart savings. Prioritize self-care.            prevent exhaustion.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Your confidence is high, making it a great time   Aquarius, Creativity and innovation push your
                     for leadership roles. Romantic relationships are   career forward. Love life is rewarding with deep
                     exciting but require balance. Financially, invest-  conversations. Finances are stable, but avoid
                     ments could be beneficial. Maintain a regular ex-  overspending. Prioritize emotional and mental
                     ercise routine for overall well-being.          well-being.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     A productive time for work, but avoid overbur-  Pisces, Trust your instincts this period. Career
                     dening yourself. Love life is smooth if you com-  growth is steady, and romance is fulfilling. Fi-
                     municate openly. Financially, savings should be   nancially, stability is within reach. Ensure
                     prioritized. Focus on stress management tech-   adequate rest and mindfulness practices to stay
                     niques like meditation.                         balanced.


           28                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Urgent Attention Needed on      inforces the need for responsible speech,
           Myanmar-Thailand Earthquake     especially by public figures.
             The recent earthquake that struck   In today’s polarized environment,   well, it serves as a reminder of the vi-
           Myanmar and Thailand has once again   where rhetoric often fuels division, this   brant and dynamic nature of our film in-
           highlighted the vulnerability of the region   judgment sets a crucial precedent. It em-  dustry, capable of producing content that
           to natural disasters. With a magnitude   phasizes that free speech is not absolute   captivates and inspires.
           exceeding 6.0, the tremors caused   and must align with constitutional mo-  Keerti Gupta, Bhopal, Madhya Pra-
           significant damage to infrastructure and   rality. The verdict should serve as a   desh, India
           left thousands in distress. The affected   warning against inflammatory state-
           communities urgently need international   ments disguised as political expression.
           aid, including medical assistance, shelter,   As a democratic society, we must up-  Meerut's Shehar Qazi Dispute Ends
           and food supplies.              hold freedom of speech but also ensure   Dramatically
             This disaster also raises concerns about   that it does not threaten public order.   The controversy over the appoint-
           preparedness in earthquake-prone areas.   The Supreme Court’s stance is a wel-  ment of the Shahar Qazi of Meerut has
           Governments must invest in resilient   come step in maintaining this balance.   finally come to an end in a dramatic
           infrastructure, early warning systems, and   Sharad Kumar Sharama, New Delhi,   fashion. Following the demise of Shahar
           efficient disaster response mechanisms to   India               Qazi Professor Zainus Sajidin, his son,
           minimize future casualties. Additionally,                       Dr. Zainus Salekeen, was appointed as
           global humanitarian organizations should                        the new Shahar Qazi by the people of
           step up their efforts to provide relief and   The Success of 'Sikandar' at the   the city in a traditional turban ceremony.
           rehabilitation.                 Box Office                      However, a dispute arose when, the very
             As the world watches, it is crucial that   The recent release of the film 'Sikan-  next day, Qari Shafiq ur Rehman Qasmi
           we act swiftly to support those affected.   dar' has garnered significant attention   was also crowned with a turban by his
           Solidarity and proactive measures can   due to its impressive box office perform-  supporters, leading to a conflicting
           make a difference in rebuilding lives and   ance. The movie's compelling narrative   claim.
           ensuring better preparedness for the   and stellar performances have resonated   This development divided the city
           future.                         with audiences, leading to substantial   into two groups, causing intense tension
           Rakesh Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,   commercial success. This achievement   and resentment. Qari Shafiq was even
           India                           highlights the evolving tastes of cinema-  barred from delivering sermons after
                                           goers and underscores the importance of   Namaz in most mosques. With Eid ap-
                                           quality storytelling in the industry.   proaching, uncertainty loomed over who
           SC’s Bold Stand on Free Speech in   The success of 'Sikandar' not only re-  would lead the Namaz at the Shahi Eid-
           Imran Pratapgarhi’s Case        flects the filmmakers' dedication but   gah.
             The Supreme Court’s recent judg-  also sets a positive precedent for future   Eventually, realizing that the major-
           ment in Imran Pratapgarhi’s case has   productions aiming to balance artistic   ity supported Dr. Zainus Salekeen, Qari
           drawn a clear boundary between free   integrity with mainstream appeal. It is   Shafiq withdrew his claim and joined
           speech and hate speech. While freedom   encouraging to witness such films re-  hands with Dr. Salekeen, thus resolving
           of expression is a fundamental right, it   ceiving both critical acclaim and finan-  the dispute.
           cannot be misused to incite violence or   cial rewards.         Nadeem Akhtar Siddiqui, Meerut
           communal disharmony. The ruling re-  As the film continues to perform   City, Uttar Pradesh, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           APRIL 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 www.revoir.in                                  29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA["Adopt the pace of nature: her secret is patience."


                              – Ralph Waldo Emerson








































































                                                                                                                Photo credit: Valeska Huyskens]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                      |


                                                                                 ol. 3, No.5 |
                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                      |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                       |


                                                                                       |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                              ol. 3, No.4 |
                                                                              ol. 3, No.3 |
                                                                               V
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                              .in
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                              .in
                                                                               V
                                                                                ol. 3, No.1 |
                                                                                V
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                ol. 3, No.2 |
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                .in

                                                                                         JANUAR

                                                                                          AUGUST
                                                                                         JANUAR

                                                                                          | AUGUST
                                                                                         |

                                                                                                   16 2025
                                                                                                   16 2025
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                 Y 01 202432
                                                                                                 Y

                                                                                        DECEMBER 01 2024

                                                                                        DECEMBER 16 2024

                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                        FEBRUAR

                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                         OCT

                                                                                        FEBRUAR
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                                        .revoir
                                                        .revoir
                                                         .revoir
                                                      .revoir
                                                  www.revoir
                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.6 | MARCH 16 2025MARCH 01 2025 01 2025 01 2025OBER 16 2023
                                                      www
                                                           .in
                                                             .in
                                                              REVOIR Magazine
                                                              REVOIR Magazine
                                                             .in
                                                           .in
                                                            www
                                                            www
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32                                     wwwwwwwww www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.7 | APRIL 01 2025OBER 01 2024
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32
           323232
           32
           3232
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                             V
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                       www
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                             .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                             V
                                                                            .in
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                            .in
                                                                .revoir
                                                                 REVOIR Magazine
                                                                   www
                                                                .revoir
                                                              .in
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                                                                   www
                                                                     www
                                                                     www
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                    .in
                                                                    www
                                                                    www
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in REVOIR
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>