<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                       VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 09 I  MAY 01 2025         ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             17



                                                            14













                                                            8                                        10
















           4-Editorial: Still a mother,                    24-The science of the perfect cocktail
           still waiting                                   27-Remembering Javidan’s beautiful

           5-Labor in the age of automation                life

           8-Words to heal a fractured world               28-Horoscopes

           10-No longer needed, still deeply               29-Letters
           loved?

           14-The global lens of Indian cinema

           17-When comedy becomes a weapon

           21-The vulnerability of digital love









           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                     3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[The loneliest role
     EDITORIAL  Still a mother,                                                    Dr. Kamran Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           still waiting                                                        Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                              here was a time when she was the    Art & Culture Editor
                                              sun around which her family orbited.   Navormi Vats
                                        TShe soothed fevers with a touch,
                                        stitched buttons with half-blind fingers and   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        remembered everyone’s birthdays when no   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        one else could. Yet somewhere along the
                                        way, between packed lunchboxes and quiet
                                        goodbyes at college gates, her world began   Social Media Editor
                                        to shrink. Her identity, once tied tightly to   Vikas Babbar
                                        the role of mother, slowly unspooled as her
                                        children grew into independence. And so   Art & Graphics Director
                                        begins a quieter chapter: not tragic, but    Vipin Agarwal
                                        quietly sorrowful, where the warmth of
                                        being remembered is often outweighed by
           the chill of being forgotten.                                     EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             On Mother’s Day, tributes flow freely: social media posts, floral deliveries and
           breakfast-in-bed traditions. But for many aging mothers, especially those living   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           alone, these gestures arrive more as reminders of absence than affirmations of   Editor, United News of India, New
           presence. The deeper question looms, are they still needed, or merely remembered?
           The love may not have faded, but its expression, its urgency, its daily necessity has.   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           And with that diminishment comes an emotional terrain rarely mapped in mainstream   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           discourse: the loneliness of those who gave everything, now uncertain of their place   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           in a family that no longer depends on them.                       Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
             This phenomenon, while intimate, is hardly isolated. Across cultures, from rural   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           Indian villages to European suburbs and American retirement communities, the aging   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           mother becomes increasingly invisible. No longer central to the household   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           machinery, she is often edged out of relevance. This is not always intentional. Life,
           with its unrelenting pace, pulls children into their own orbits. Yet intention does not   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           absolve impact. Emotional neglect, unlike physical absence, leaves no visible scars,
           yet it corrodes just the same.
             Sociologists have noted how women’s identities, especially in patriarchal cultures,   Phone +91 20 40199102
           are deeply entwined with caregiving roles. When that role diminishes, what remains?   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           A woman with decades of wisdom, wit and tenderness, now navigating a world   Baner Road,
           where her purpose feels vague and her voice too soft to be heard. And yet, despite the   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           hurt, most aging mothers do not demand, they wait, they forgive, they quietly hope.   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             But perhaps it is not too late to reimagine how we value mothers, not just when   Website www.revoir.in
           we need them, but when they need us. Academia, policy and civil society must do
           more to center elderly women in conversations around aging, loneliness and   Legal Advisor
           intergenerational care. Memory alone is not enough; it must be accompanied by   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           meaningful presence, by regular conversation, by asking her what she needs, not just
           remembering what she once gave.
             For the forgotten mother is not without love. But love, to matter, must be felt. And
           to feel it, she must no longer be forgotten.                     Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.


         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH

































           Machines vs. Mankind                                            The double-edged sword of
                                                                           automation
                                                                              Technology as a liberator
                                                                              Advocates of automation often argue
                                                                           that AI and robotics offer liberation,
                                                                           from dangerous, monotonous and physi-
           Labor in the age  cally exhausting tasks. Machines excel
                                                                           in environments hostile to human health,
                                                                           such as deep mining or chemical man-
           of automation                                                   ufacturing, significantly reducing occu-
                                                                           pational hazards. In healthcare, robotic-
                                                                           assisted surgeries can increase precision
                                                                           and lower complication rates, while AI
                                                                           diagnostics can analyze vast amounts of
           The relationship between machines and mankind                   patient data more quickly than a human
                                                                           doctor could.
           is neither inherently antagonistic nor inherently                  Moreover, automation holds the po-
                                                                           tential to unlock human creativity. If
           utopian. By Siddharth Mehta                                     machines handle repetitive labor, hu-
                                                                           mans may pursue higher-order roles,
                                                                           those involving empathy, strategy, de-
                 s the world stands at the cusp of   cially on the occasion of May Day, his-  sign and innovation. Historically, tech-
                 a technological transformation,   torically dedicated to the dignity of   nological revolutions have displaced
           Aartificial intelligence (AI) and   labor and the struggle for workers’   some jobs but created others. The Indus-
           robotics are no longer confined to labo-  rights. Today, the conflict is not only   trial Revolution, for instance, rendered
           ratories or science fiction films. From   about wages or working hours but about   many artisanal jobs obsolete but gave
           self-checkout counters in grocery stores   the very relevance of human labor in an   rise to new sectors and economies of
           to AI-generated legal advice and robot-  increasingly automated economy.    scale.
           assisted surgeries, automation is rapidly   For policy makers, labor advocates,
           permeating industries once thought im-  union leaders, researchers, technologists   Technology as a threat
           mune to disruption. For better or worse,   and the global citizenry, the question is   Yet, for every optimistic prediction,
           machines are becoming co-workers and   no longer if AI will reshape the work-  there’s an unsettling counter-narrative.
           in some cases, replacements.    force, but how, when and at what cost or   The rise of AI and robotics is already re-
             This shift demands reflection, espe-  benefit.                sulting in job displacement across multi-  ►►

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                     5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[A delivery robot navigating an urban environment                                                  AI-powered robotic arm operating on an assembly line




















        ►  ple sectors. From truck drivers and fac-
           tory workers to legal clerks and even
           journalists, automation is encroaching
           on roles that once offered stable liveli-
           hoods. In developing economies, where
           labor is often cheaper than machines,
           automation threatens to leapfrog tradi-
           tional industrial growth, denying mil-
           lions a path out of poverty.
             Unlike past technological transitions,
           the pace and scope of AI-driven change
           are unprecedented. Generative AI can                                                            Side-by-side comparison of a human and a robot
           now produce human-like text, images
           and code, challenging the assumption
           that creativity is an exclusively human
           trait. When machines can compose
           music, write essays and diagnose medi-
           cal conditions, what remains uniquely
           human?

           Global impact: Automation across   inequality, both within and between na-  Rewriting the social contract
           borders                         tions.                             Education and reskilling: One of
             The labor impact of automation is not                         the most pressing challenges and oppor-
           uniformly distributed. In high-income   Psychological toll: The human cost   tunities, is reimagining education. Life-
           countries, where the cost of human labor   beyond employment    long learning must become the norm,
           is high, automation is often seen as a   Beyond economics lies a quieter,   with governments and employers col-
           cost-saving measure. In contrast, in   more insidious cost: the psychological   laborating to offer reskilling programs
           lower-income nations, the same technol-  impact of redundancy. For many, work   that are accessible, affordable and rel-
           ogies risk stalling the development of   is more than a paycheck, it provides   evant.
           labor-intensive industries such as textile   structure, identity and purpose. As auto-  Curricula must emphasize not just
           manufacturing or customer service.   mation disrupts traditional career paths,   technical skills but also soft skills, criti-
             However, automation also presents   it risks fostering a sense of obsolescence   cal thinking, adaptability, emotional in-
           opportunities for leapfrogging. In coun-  and alienation. This is particularly acute   telligence, which are harder to automate.
           tries lacking infrastructure, AI-based so-  among older workers or those in manual   As AI takes over rule-based tasks, the
           lutions in education, health and agricul-  trades who may lack the resources or   future belongs to those who can learn
           ture can improve access and efficiency.   time to retrain.      continuously and pivot quickly.
           For example, drone-based crop monitor-  Mental health professionals are be-
           ing in Sub-Saharan Africa or AI-driven   ginning to report what some term “auto-  Rethinking work and value
           language translation tools in multilin-  mation anxiety”, a growing sense of fu-  The conversation must also evolve
           gual societies can address systemic   tility as human relevance is seemingly   beyond employment. As automation re-
           gaps.                           eclipsed by machines. If not addressed   duces the total number of jobs, we may
             Policy makers, therefore, face a com-  proactively, this emotional fallout could   need to decouple income from work al-
           plex calculus: how to harness the bene-  rival the financial disruption caused by   together. Proposals like Universal Basic
           fits of automation without exacerbating   automation.           Income (UBI) are gaining traction,   ►►

           6                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[►  though they remain controversial.
           Critics argue UBI may disincentivize
           productivity, while supporters see it as a
           safety net for a world where full em-
           ployment may no longer be feasible.
             Additionally, we must reconsider
           what types of work society values. Care-
           giving, volunteering and creative en-
           deavors, often unpaid or underpaid,
           might gain new appreciation in an era
           where economic contribution is no                                                               Workers demand protection during a Labor Day rally
           longer the sole measure of worth.

           A cultural reflection: Why Ray still
           matters
             In considering labor’s place in the
           age of automation, it's worth turning
           briefly to the world of art. Satyajit Ray,
           the legendary Indian filmmaker, often
           explored themes of human dignity, so-
           cial change and modernization. In films
           like Mahanagar (The Big City), he cap-
         Self-driving vehicle navigating an urban setting  human struggle remains relevant in the          Human and robotic hands
           tured the anxieties of a working-class
           family confronting urban transfor-
           mation.
             Ray’s sensitivity to the nuances of

           global cinematic conversation today. His
           characters are rarely passive victims or
           triumphant heroes; they are nuanced in-
           dividuals navigating complex social
           shifts, just like the modern worker con-
           fronting AI. As automation changes the
           very fabric of human labor, Ray’s em-
           phasis on empathy, dignity and adapta-
           tion provides a poignant reminder: pro-
           gress must not erase humanity.


                                           Policy pathways: Steering toward   Toward a humane technological
                                           an inclusive future             future
                                             For governments and global institu-  The  relationship  between  machines
                                           tions, the task ahead is monumental but   and  mankind  is  neither  inherently  an-
                                           not insurmountable. Thoughtful, inclu-  tagonistic  nor  inherently  utopian.  It  is,
                                           sive policy is essential.       like  all  human  progress,  a  story  in  the
                                             Labor protection laws must evolve to   making,  written  not  just  in  code,  but
                                           include gig workers and those affected   in  policy  decisions,  corporate  board-
                                           by AI-driven job loss.          rooms,  classrooms  and  households.
                                             Corporate responsibility should go   As  we  commemorate  May  Day,  it
                                           beyond profit-maximization to include   is  imperative  to  honor  not  just  the
                                           ethical deployment of automation.   labor  of  the  past  but  to  envision  the
                                             Global collaboration is crucial. Auto-  labor  of  the  future.  A  future  where
                                           mation is not a localized phenomenon;   machines  enhance  human  capability,
                                           international bodies must coordinate on   not  replace  it.  A  future  where  dignity,
                                           standards, taxation models (such as   equity  and  innovation  coexist.
                                           robot taxes) and social protections.   The  age  of  automation  is  not  a
                                             Crucially, workers must be given a   distant  horizon,  it  is  here.  The  ques-
                                           seat at the table. Trade unions and labor   tion  is:  will  we  navigate  it  with  fore-
                                           organizations need to modernize their   sight,  compassion  and  wisdom,  or
                                           platforms to engage with AI-related is-  allow  it  to  unfold  as  an  unchecked
                                           sues, advocate for fair transitions and   force?  The  answer  lies  not  in  the  al-
                                           ensure that automation is with workers,   gorithms  we  build,  but  in  the  values
                                           not against them.               we  uphold. ■

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                     7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  Iwords became Pope Francis’s most
             n an age increasingly defined by di-
             vision, hostility and uncertainty,
           powerful instrument of healing. Across
           cultures and continents, he wielded lan-
           guage not as a tool of power, but as a
           balm for the wounded spirit of human-
           ity. His speeches, encyclicals and spon-
           taneous acts of empathy consistently of-
           fered a vision of solidarity, humility and
           hope, not only for the Catholic faithful
           but for all people of goodwill.
             Pope Francis passed away after a
           prolonged illness in Rome on the early
           morning of Monday, April 21, 2025, at
           the age of 88. He was laid to rest at the
           Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore in
           Rome on Saturday, April 26, 2025.
             The passing of Pope Francis marks
           the end of an era characterized by a
           deeply human papacy, one that leaned
           heavily on the healing power of lan-
           guage. As the world reflects on his re-  THE VOICE OF POPE FRANCIS
           markable leadership, it is worth examin-
           ing how his words, grounded in
           compassion and clarity, stitched together
           the torn fabric of our shared existence.   Words to heal a
           A language of compassion:
           Speeches that stirred souls
             From his very first words as pope,
           “Buona sera”, delivered simply and
           warmly from the balcony of St. Peter’s   fractured world
           Basilica, Francis set a new tone. He re-
           jected grandiosity in favor of intimate
           connection. His speeches were often
           conversational, laced with parables, im-
           agery and rhetorical questions that drew   Pope Francis’s legacy, now cast in the stillness of his
           listeners inward.
             In addressing the U.S. Congress in   passing, will endure not solely in policies or
           2015, Francis invoked figures like Abra-
           ham Lincoln and Martin Luther King Jr.,   pronouncements, but in the transformative language
           speaking of dreams, dignity and dia-
           logue. He did not scold or divide; in-  he gifted to a weary world. By Anaya Gupta
           stead, he invited leaders to reflect on
           their moral responsibility. Even when
           addressing fraught topics like immigra-  Encyclicals that echoed beyond   language made these dense theological
           tion, economic inequality, or environ-  the church              reflections accessible to the ordinary
           mental degradation, he chose words that   More formal, yet no less powerful,   reader. He drew from parables, historical
           elevated rather than alienated, bridging   were Pope Francis’s encyclicals, doc-  memory and personal experience, weav-
           political chasms through appeals to   uments that channeled centuries of theo-  ing a tapestry that made complex real-
           shared humanity.                logical tradition into responses to mod-  ities feel intimate and urgent.
             His use of repetition, a hallmark of   ern crises. Laudato Si’ (2015) remains a   Rather than prescribing rigid solu-
           great oratory, reinforced urgent themes,   landmark text, addressing climate   tions, Francis’s encyclicals extended in-
           mercy, fraternity, justice, embedding   change not merely as a scientific or po-  vitations, to care, to listen, to act. In
           them into the consciousness of a global   litical issue, but as a moral imperative   doing so, he expanded the Church’s
           audience.                       rooted in the interconnectedness of all   moral vocabulary, aligning faith with a
             Each speech, whether in the slums of   life.                  global ethic of compassion.
           Rio de Janeiro or the corridors of the   In Fratelli Tutti (2020), Francis con-
           European Parliament, seemed infused   fronted the fractures of contemporary   The power of the unscripted
           with a deep understanding: those words,   society, racism, economic exclusion,   moment
           when spoken with authenticity, could   populism, with a call to universal broth-  Some of Pope Francis’s most moving
           turn estrangement into encounter.   erhood. His choice of simple, evocative   communications occurred sponta-  ►►

           8                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[life as a "journey," the planet as a "com-
                                                                           mon home", Francis offered not mere
                                                                           diagnosis, but a roadmap for renewal.
                                                                           His words often recognized the broken-
                                                                           ness of the world, yet pointed unfail-
                                                                           ingly to the possibility of healing, pro-
         Crowd gathered in St. Peter’s Square                              sible, poetic, broke down barriers not
                                                                           vided we chose the difficult paths of
                                                                           compassion and solidarity.
                                                                              His rhetorical style, earnest, acces-

                                                                           only between the Church and the secular
                                                                           world, but between disparate peoples
                                                                           yearning for meaning and connection.
                                                                           For many, he restored the credibility of
                                                                           moral leadership in public life, remind-
                                                                           ing all that gentleness and strength are
                                                                           not opposites but partners.
                                                                              Pope Francis’s legacy, now cast in
        ►  neously; moments unmediated by po-  just five words. Here was a leader who   the stillness of his passing, will endure
           diums or prepared texts. His silent   understood that language was not   not solely in policies or pronounce-
           prayer at the border fence in Lampedusa   merely what was spoken, but what was   ments, but in the transformative lan-
           for drowned migrants; his embrace of a   embodied.              guage he gifted to a weary world. His
           disfigured man in St. Peter’s Square; his                       speeches stirred, his encyclicals taught
           impromptu blessing of a child with dis-  A voice of hope in a cynical world   and his spontaneous acts inspired. Al-
           abilities ,  these acts spoke volumes bey-  In an era where political rhetoric   ways, his words were bridges, spanning
           ond words.                      often deepens wounds, Pope Francis   divides between nations, creeds and
             Yet even when he did speak in such   consistently modeled a different kind of   wounded hearts.
           moments, his words were succinct, al-  leadership: one rooted in hope without   In a fractured era, he proved that
           most whispered, carrying emotional   naïveté, in realism without resignation.   words, when wielded with love, humil-
           weight far greater than their length.   He acknowledged pain, of refugees, of   ity and courage, can still heal, and can
           “Who am I to judge?” perhaps one of   the poor, of the Earth itself, yet he re-  still build a future where none seemed
           the most quoted phrases of his papacy,   fused to let suffering have the last word.   possible. His voice may be silent now,
           encapsulated an entire vision of humil-  Through his persistent use of meta-  but the echo of his compassion will con-
           ity, acceptance and radical empathy in   phors, the Church as a "field hospital,"   tinue to resound across the world. ■













         The body of Pope Francis is carried into St. Peter’s Basilica

























           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                     9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Forgotten Mothers                                               identity and social invisibility. For gen-

                                                                           eral readers, policymakers, grown-up
                                                                           children, social workers and global ad-
                                                                           vocates of aging and gender issues, this
     INSIGHT  No longer                                                    piece offers an invitation to rethink how
                                                                           societies value mothers once their con-
                                                                           ventional role ends.

                                                                           The silent void after nurturing ends
           needed, still                                                   comes the central axis around which
                                                                              For many women, motherhood be-
                                                                           their identity spins. From birth through
                                                                           the adolescent years of their children,
                                                                           mothers often suppress personal dreams,
                                                                           careers and social ambitions to focus on
           deeply loved?                                                   last child leaves home? When the daily
                                                                           nurturing. But what happens when the
                                                                           rituals, packing lunchboxes, waiting for
                                                                           school buses, managing endless laundry,
                                                                           cease, what fills the gap?
                                                                              This phase, often termed the "empty
                                                                           nest," can trigger a profound identity cri-
           Motherhood does not end when children grow                      sis. While some women discover new
                                                                           paths or return to old passions, countless
           up; it simply shifts in form. By Riya Verma                     others struggle to reframe their purpose.
                                                                           “Who am I, if not someone’s mother?”
                                                                           becomes an aching question. The void is
                                                                           not only emotional but societal. In many
                 cross cultures and continents,   active role and presence. The transition   cultures, once a woman’s children are
                 the image of a mother is re-  from essential caregiver to peripheral   grown, her visibility diminishes. Her
           Avered, nurturing, selfless and   figure is often unspoken and its emo-  opinions are less sought, her presence
           ever-present. From lullabies whispered   tional toll rarely acknowledged.   taken for granted.
           in the dark to meals cooked with love, a   As we mark Mother’s Day, a celebra-
           mother’s presence shapes not just the   tion that honors the sacrifices and love   Loneliness: A growing emotional
           early years but the emotional framework   of mothers, it is equally important to   epidemic
           of a child’s life. Yet, as time unravels   cast light on those who find themselves   In a world that increasingly cele-
           and children grow into adults with lives   forgotten. This article explores the silent   brates youth and independence; aging
           of their own, many mothers are left be-  emotional erosion that many aging   mothers often find themselves isolated.
           hind, not in memory or sentiment, but in   mothers face, their loneliness, loss of   The World Health Organization iden-  ►►

































           10                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[often linked to her reproductive and
                                                                           caregiving roles. Once those functions
                                                                           are perceived as complete, her societal
                                                                           relevance diminishes.
                                                                              In Western cultures, the pressure to
                                                                           remain youthful adds another layer of
                                                                           erasure. Media and advertisements often
                                                                           sideline older women, portraying moth-
         A mother sits quietly by the window                               come later. The narrative rarely includes
                                                                           erhood in soft, glowing tones while ig-
                                                                           noring the wrinkles and weariness that
                                                                           the mother who is no longer needed
                                                                           every day, whose advice is politely ig-
                                                                           nored, or whose health begins to falter
                                                                           in the absence of attentive care.
                                                                              This invisibility is not just metaphor-
                                                                           ical. A study published in The Journals
                                                                           of Gerontology found that older women
                                                                           are more likely to be overlooked in
                                                                           healthcare settings, have their pain un-
                                                                           derestimated and receive less aggressive
                                                                           treatment for serious illnesses. The cu-
                                                                           mulative effect of societal neglect leaves
                                                                           many elderly mothers vulnerable, not
         A generational photo with the elderly mother                      A cross-cultural perspective:
                                                                           just emotionally, but also physically and
                                                                           economically.


                                                                           Varying shades of abandonment
                                                                              Although the experience of aging
                                                                           mothers differs across cultures, certain
                                                                           threads remain consistent. In India, for
                                                                           example, traditional joint family systems
                                                                           once guaranteed that mothers aged with
                                                                           their children and grandchildren under
                                                                           one roof. However, urbanization and
                                                                           migration have rapidly transformed
                                                                           these dynamics. Many elderly women
                                           tired teacher in Taiwan, who raised four   now live alone or in old age homes,
         An older woman holding a framed photo of her children
                                           children. Today, all live abroad. “They   struggling with the emotional betrayal of
                                           love me,” she says, “but their lives are   being left behind.
                                           full. They video call once a week, but   In Scandinavian countries, where in-
                                           the silence in this house is deafening.”   dividual autonomy is prized, elderly
                                           Her words echo those of countless   care is often outsourced to the state.
                                           mothers across India, the United States,   While materially secure, mothers here
                                           Kenya and Brazil, who express similar   may still experience emotional aliena-
                                           feelings of being emotionally sidelined   tion. In Latin America, where familial
                                           after their children have moved on.   bonds are deeply cherished, aging moth-
                                             This emotional abandonment is   ers sometimes face a different kind of
                                           rarely deliberate. Adult children often   neglect, being involved only in practical
                                           juggle demanding careers, parenting   roles like childcare or cooking, without
                                           their own children and geographic dis-  being treated as individuals with emo-
                                           tances. Yet, the result is the same, moth-  tional needs of their own.
                                           ers, once at the heart of the home, are   The variation in practice does not
                                           now on the periphery.           erase the shared truth, most societies
                                                                           lack structured systems to emotionally
                                           The invisibility of age and gender   support aging women transitioning out
        ►  tifies loneliness among older adults as a   Aging brings its own set of chal-  of full-time motherhood.
           major public health concern, affecting   lenges, but when combined with gender
           mental and physical health. For mothers   expectations, it creates a double bind.   The intersection of feminism and
           who once navigated bustling homes, this   Older women, especially mothers, face a   aging
           isolation can feel especially acute.   unique form of social invisibility. In pa-  Feminist discourse has long chal-
             Consider the story of Mei Lin, a re-  triarchal societies, a woman’s value is   lenged the restrictive definitions of   ►►

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[A hallway decorated with family photos




         A single woman present physically but emotionally detached

















                                                                                                           A woman showing a photo of her daughter






        ►  womanhood, but aging remains a rel-
           atively underexplored frontier. While
           younger generations of women are in-
           creasingly asserting independence, the
           elderly cohort, particularly mothers, still
           live within old constructs.
             These mothers often never learned to
           see themselves outside the lens of serv-
           ice to others. For them, the notion of   shops for young mothers. In the Nether-  ship. Instead of seeing mothers solely
           self-care feels indulgent and pursuing   lands, university students live rent-free   through their historical role, we can en-
           new passions in their sixties or seventies   in elder care homes in exchange for   gage with them as evolving individuals
           can seem futile or inappropriate. Fem-  companionship. Such initiatives can be   with stories, wisdom and dreams yet to
           inism must evolve to embrace not just   adapted globally.       be fulfilled. A conversation over coffee,
           the liberation of young women but also   Moreover, mental health support for   a shared book, or learning a hobby to-
           the redefinition of aging womanhood.   aging mothers needs urgent attention.   gether can foster deeper, reciprocal
           Supporting mothers to reclaim agency in   Counseling centers, support groups and   bonds.
           their later years is not just compassion-  helplines specifically tailored to the   Motherhood does not end when chil-
           ate; it is a feminist imperative.   post-parenting phase can help women   dren grow up; it simply shifts in form.
                                           navigate their loss of role and rediscover   What mothers need most in their later
           Policy and community responses   personal identity.             years is not more accolades or tokens of
             Addressing this silent crisis requires                        appreciation, but continued connection,
           more than emotional awareness, it de-  A call to adult children: Love is a   respect and recognition of their person-
           mands structural change. Governments   verb                     hood. As we celebrate Mother’s Day, let
           and social organizations must develop   No policy or organization can replace   us look beyond flowers and phone calls.
           policies that recognize the psychological   the comfort of a child’s voice, a visit, a   Let us confront the uncomfortable truth,
           needs of aging women, particularly   shared laugh. Adult children play a criti-  that many mothers feel abandoned after
           those who spent most of their lives as   cal role in ensuring their mothers don’t   their "usefulness" is over.
           caregivers.                     feel forgotten. While modern life is fast   By acknowledging their silent grief
             Programs such as community circles,   and fragmented, small gestures, consis-  and taking active steps to include them
           elder mentoring networks and intergen-  tent phone calls, video messages, invit-  in the rhythm of life, we honor not just
           erational living models can combat iso-  ing them into your world, carry im-  their role as mothers, but their identity
           lation and restore meaning. In Japan,   mense emotional weight.   as women deserving of joy, dignity and
           elder women lead traditional craft work-  It’s also vital to reframe the relation-  belonging, every day of their lives. ■

           12                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[PROFILE



































           Satyajit Ray



           The global lens





           of Indian cinema                                                structural precision and Akira Kuro-

                                                                           sawa’s universal themes of morality and
                                                                           identity, Ray’s fingerprints are subtly but
                                                                           surely visible. His stories, rooted in
                                                                           Bengali culture, have, paradoxically,
           To understand cinema without understanding Satyajit             achieved global resonance. What makes
           Ray is to read literature without touching Shakespeare or       this possible? And why does Ray still
                                                                           matter in a global cinematic conver-
           to study music without hearing Mozart. By Aarav Sharma          sation?
                                                                           The universality of Ray’s
                                                                           storytelling
             n the vast constellation of global   a humanism so authentic and a style so   At first glance, Ray’s films seem
             cinema, a few names shine with a   singular, that generations of filmmakers   deeply regional, set in rural villages or
           Ibrilliance that transcends not just   across continents have found inspiration   bustling Kolkata, populated with char-
           borders, but time. Satyajit Ray is one   in his work.           acters speaking Bengali, grappling with
           such enduring star. A filmmaker whose   As we commemorate his birth anni-  everyday lives. Yet, therein lies the para-
           quiet frames and lyrical storytelling rev-  versary, it is fitting to revisit not just   dox: his local is universal. In Pather
           olutionized not just Indian cinema, but   Ray’s contributions to Indian cinema,   Panchali, Ray captured the essence of
           altered the cinematic grammar under-  but to examine how his cinematic lan-  childhood curiosity, familial struggle
           stood worldwide. Whether depicting the   guage has profoundly influenced world   and the inexorable passage of time. No
           struggles of rural Bengal or the curios-  cinema. From Martin Scorsese’s emo-  subtitles could dilute the raw, emotional
           ities of a Calcutta detective, Ray brought   tional realism to Christopher Nolan’s   purity of Apu and Durga racing after a   ►►

           14                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[►  train or gazing at a field of white kash
           flowers.
             Ray’s brilliance lay in his ability to
           illuminate the human condition, grief,
           wonder, loss, dignity, with profound em-
           pathy. His characters rarely shout; they
           observe, they endure, they dream. These
           narratives strike chords across cultures.
           A Japanese mother may weep for Apu’s
           loss just as deeply as an Italian father
           may see his own childhood in Apu’s
           wide-eyed gaze.
             His dialogue often deferred to si-                                                            Satyajit Ray reading a script4o
           lence. As Ray himself noted, "The best
           spoken lines are those that are not
           spoken at all." Such quietude, imbued
           with unspoken tension, evokes the sub-
           tlety of Antonioni or the introspective
           beauty of Ozu. Yet Ray was never imi-
           tating; he was, always, distinct.

           Ray’s influence on Kurosawa,
           Scorsese and Nolan
             Perhaps no testament to Ray’s global
           stature is stronger than the reverence he
           commands among his cinematic peers.
             Akira Kurosawa, the titan of Japa-
           nese cinema, once declared, "Not to
           have seen the cinema of Ray means ex-
           isting in the world without seeing the                                                          Satyajit Ray working behind the camera
           sun or the moon." Kurosawa, known for
           his sweeping epics and intense human
           dramas, admired Ray’s restraint, his
           ability to turn the mundane into the pro-
           found. While Kurosawa dramatized
           moral dilemmas, Ray quietly unfolded
           them. Both sought truth, but through dif-  but revelation.         It’s this quiet influence, subtle yet en-
           ferent lenses, yet deeply respected each   Christopher Nolan, the contempo-  during, that shows Ray’s artistry doesn’t
           other's craft.                  rary wizard of cinematic structure, has   just inspire direct emulation, but shifts
             Martin Scorsese, the American au-  cited Ray’s Charulata as a favorite film.   the way filmmakers think.
           teur whose films pulse with urban angst   While Nolan’s layered narratives seem
           and emotional realism, credits Ray as a   far from Ray’s realism, both directors   Crafting a language beyond
           formative influence. Scorsese's Mean   share a fascination with time, memory   language
           Streets and The Irishman may differ in   and human agency. Nolan’s Interstellar   Ray’s genius extended beyond direc-
           setting, but his commitment to character   carries a line, “Love is the one thing   tion. He was a screenwriter, composer,
           over plot, his lingering shots on reflec-  we're capable of perceiving that tran-  editor, illustrator and calligrapher, a
           tive faces and moral complexity, echo   scends dimensions of time and space”,   complete artist. This holistic vision
           Ray’s style. In Scorsese’s hands, we see   that would not feel out of place in Ray’s   meant that his films were cohesive ex-
           Ray’s belief that cinema is not spectacle,   The World of Apu.   pressions of his inner world, refined   ►►



       Left: Filmmaker Christopher Nolan   Right: Martin Scorsese                                          Renowned filmmaker Akira Kurosawa















           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[His themes, social mobility, women’s
                                                                           agency, colonial hangovers, spiritual
                                                                           longing, remain startlingly relevant. In
                                                                           Mahanagar, the tale of a middle-class
                                                                           housewife becoming a working woman,
                                                                           Ray addressed gender roles with sensi-
                                                                           tivity that many contemporary films still
                                                                           struggle to match. In Shatranj ke Khilari,
                                                                           his Urdu-language film set during the
         Satyajit Ray with his family                                      with satire and pathos.
                                                                           British annexation of Oudh, he dissected
                                                                           colonial power not with bombast but

                                                                              Globally, Ray has inspired retrospec-
                                                                           tives, restorations and reverence. The
                                                                           Criterion Collection houses his films,
                                                                           ensuring their preservation and ped-


        ►  through every element of craft. His mu-                         agogy. Film schools from Paris to New
           sical scores, especially in the Apu Tril-
           ogy, blended Indian classical melodies
           with global sensibilities, often drawing
           on the same emotional undercurrents as
           a Chopin or a Debussy.
             Cinematographically, Ray drew from
           Italian neorealism, particularly De Sica’s
           Bicycle Thieves, but did not mimic it.
           He fused neorealist tenets, non-profes-
           sional actors, real locations, natural
           light, with the lyricism of Tagorean po-
           etics. The result was a cinematic lan-
           guage that didn’t require translation.
           You didn’t need to understand Bengali                                                           Still from Charulata (1964)
           to feel the ache in Apur Sansar or the
           yearning in Charulata.
             Such is the power of form. Through
           mise-en-scène, rhythm and restraint,
           Ray communicated beyond language,   gorithm-curated spectacle, Ray’s films   York teach Ray not as “Indian cinema”
           creating what French film critic André   remind us of cinema’s meditative power.   but as cinema, full stop. His name be-
           Bazin might call “pure cinema.”   Where modern blockbusters chase ve-  longs not just in Indian halls of fame but
                                           locity, Ray invites stillness. Where   on the world’s cinematic Mount Olym-
           Why ray still matters: Relevance in   stories now often reduce characters to   pus.
           the global cinematic conversation   tropes, Ray explored their contradic-
             In an age of visual overload and al-  tions, vulnerabilities and silences.   A legacy without borders
                                                                              To understand cinema without under-
                                                                           standing Satyajit Ray is to read literature
                                                                           without touching Shakespeare or to
                                                                           study music without hearing Mozart. He
                                                                           was not just a director of films, but a
                                                                           thinker, a humanist and a seer who saw
                                                                           cinema not as escape, but encounter,
                                                                           with self, with society, with the soul.
                                                                              His lens may have been grounded in
                                                                           Bengal, but its focus was unfailingly
                                                                           global. As long as stories are told with
         A still from Pather Panchali                                      duct, Ray will remain a guiding light.
                                                                           honesty, characters drawn with empathy
                                                                           and cinema revered as art and not pro-

                                                                           Across languages, across generations,
                                                                           across continents, he whispers still,
                                                                           through flickering reels and streaming
                                                                           pixels, the quiet, resonant truths of what
                                                                           it means to be human. ■

           16                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION







































                                           The politics of laughter
             n a world increasingly marred by po-
             larization, censorship and ideolog-
           Iical rigidity, laughter may be the last
           truly subversive act. It sneaks past de-  When comedy
           fenses, exposes hypocrisy and speaks
           truth to power, often while wrapped in
           absurdity or irony. But humor is more
           than a momentary escape; it can be a
           pointed critique, a form of resistance   becomes a weapon
           and occasionally, a perilous occupation.
             While laughter may be celebrated
           universally, its politics are anything but   In an age of disinformation, division and dissent,
           neutral. On World Laughter Day, it’s fit-
           ting to reflect not just on the joy comedy   political comedy is not merely entertainment, it’s
           brings but on its historical and ongoing
           role as a mechanism of protest, social   engagement. By Naina Kapoor
           commentary and survival, especially in
           times and places where dissent is dan-
           gerous.                         but for its clarity, mocking tyranny at a   journalism cannot. A cartoon, a parody
                                           time when many were still hesitant to   sketch, or a stand-up routine may trigger
           Laughter as dissent: From silent   call it out.                 more public engagement than a news-
           films to global satire            Fast forward to today and we find   paper column. In repressive regimes
             Humor has always had a rebellious   that the platforms and mediums have   where media is tightly controlled, humor
           streak. When direct criticism is stifled,   changed, but the essence of protest   becomes a language of survival, subtle,
           comedy steps in to say what cannot be   humor remains. From Trevor Noah’s   symbolic, yet loaded with meaning.
           spoken aloud. Charlie Chaplin, through   sharp monologues dissecting American
           his silent films, delivered some of the   and global politics, to Bassem Youssef,   The global pulse of satire
           earliest cinematic jabs at power. In The   the “Jon Stewart of Egypt,” who used   One of satire’s enduring strengths is
           Great Dictator (1940), Chaplin parodied   satire to challenge military rule, come-  its universality. While cultural refer-
           Adolf Hitler at a time when the world   dians continue to hold mirrors up to the   ences vary, the instinct to laugh at ab-
           teetered on the brink of war. The film’s   powerful.            surdity and call out injustice is shared
           satire was daring not only for its timing   In many cases, satire reaches where   worldwide. In South Africa, comedians   ►►

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Charlie Chaplin in The Great Dictator















                                                                           mune to satire’s sting. In the United
                                                                           States, late-night comedy has taken on
                                                                           the role of the “unofficial opposition,”
                                                                           especially during turbulent political
                                                                           times. Shows like Saturday Night Live,
                                                                           Last Week Tonight with John Oliver and
                                                                           The Daily Show blur the lines between
                                                                           entertainment and commentary, educat-
                                                                           ing while entertaining.
                                                                              Yet, it’s not just TV or mainstream
         Bassem Youssef in Cairo, Egypt                                    online skits and satirical Instagram ac-
                                                                           comedy doing the heavy lifting. Memes,
                                                                           counts have become new-age arsenals of
                                                                           resistance, often wielded by younger,
                                                                           digital-savvy generations. They mock
                                                                           surveillance states, question electoral
                                                                           fraud and challenge religious orthodoxy,
                                                                           sometimes anonymously, always pro-
                                                                           vocatively.

                                                                           Risks and resilience under
                                                                           authoritarianism
                                                                              But humor isn’t always safe, espe-
                                                                           cially when it challenges those who
                                                                           wield unchecked power. The darker side
                                                                           of political comedy is its cost.
                                                                              Bassem Youssef, once hailed as the
                                                                           Arab world’s boldest satirist, was forced
                                                                           to cancel his show and flee Egypt after
         Trevor Noah on The Daily Show                                     In Myanmar, comedian Zarganar was
                                                                           receiving threats and facing legal action.
                                                                           imprisoned for criticizing the military
                                                                           junta. In Turkey, a simple joke against
                                                                           the president can result in prosecution.
                                                                           And in China, social media comedians
                                                                           tread carefully, often using metaphor
                                                                           and visual gags to avoid state retaliation.
                                                                              Comedy in these contexts demands
                                                                           not just creativity, but courage. The risks
        ►  like Trevor Noah reflect on apartheid’s   often at great personal risk. In Iran,   are real, imprisonment, exile, censor-
           legacy and contemporary racial tensions   stand-up comedy is thriving on under-  ship. But the resilience is astonishing.
           with biting wit and empathy. In Russia,   ground stages and online, offering a rare   Underground shows flourish; exiled
           satirists have used coded language to   space for critical dialogue.   comedians continue performing abroad
           critique Vladimir Putin’s government,   Even democratic nations aren’t im-  and fans risk attending shows that speak ►►

           18                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Dr. Popular Meerathi, a renowned literary figure                                                  Kunal Kamra performing stand-up comedy



















        ►  truth under the veil of humor. Their per-
           sistence underscores an old truth: where
           speech is gagged, laughter becomes re-
           bellion.

           A voice of wit and wisdom from
           India: Dr. Popular Meerathi
             Among India’s most celebrated
           voices of satirical poetry is Dr. Syed Ai-
           jazuddin Shah, known by his pen name
           Popular Meerathi, a literary figure who
           requires little introduction in Hindi and
           Urdu poetic circles. For over four dec-
           ades, Dr. Popular Meerathi has crafted a
           distinct brand of humor and satire that                                                         A global comedy audience
           gracefully weaves in themes of patriot-
           ism, social awareness and human good-
           will. What sets him apart is his ability to
           address the burning issues of society
           with biting insight, all without malice.
           His poetry strikes at the heart of societal
           dysfunctions, but instead of leaving
           wounds, it often provides healing,
           through laughter, reflection and hope.
             With a legacy spanning more than
           1,000 public performances across Mus-
           hairas and Kavi Sammelans in India and
           abroad, Dr. Popular Meerathi has be-
           come a cultural ambassador for literary
           satire. His mastery of Tazmeen, a re-
           vered form of Urdu poetry that emo-
           tionally reinterprets classical couplets,                                                       Comedy artist in action
           adds further depth to his work. Through
           his sharp yet compassionate wit, he not
           only holds a mirror to society but also
           inspires emerging poets to use humor as
           a means of expression and resistance.   and satirical take on national politics,   into a battleground of ideas, where lan-
                                           particularly on issues like media bias   guage, timing and tone carry significant
           A closer look: Kunal kamra      and judicial conduct.           political weight.
             India, the world’s largest democracy,   Kamra’s style, acerbic, sharp, unfil-
           has seen its share of political comedians   tered, represents a growing wave of In-  Comedy’s burden: Not just jokes,
           walk the tightrope between freedom and   dian comedians who don’t just make   but justice
           backlash. Among them, Kunal Kamra   people laugh, but make them think. It   Satirists walk a fine line. They’re ex-
           stands out for his candid commentary   also reveals how comedy is evolving   pected to be entertaining, insightful,   ►►

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Live comedy performance







                                                                           is not our medicine. Stories hold our
                                                                           cure.” Comedy, in that sense, is the de-
                                                                           livery system, a clever, often charming
                                                                           disguise for a deeper wound that needs
                                                                           airing.
         Kapil Sharma's Indian television comedy show                      space, where differences momentarily
                                                                           The hope in humor
                                                                              Despite the risks, comedians persist.
                                                                           Why? Because laughter creates a shared

                                                                           blur and ideas sneak in. Because in op-
                                                                           pressive environments, laughter reminds
                                                                           us that we are still human. And because
                                                                           once you’ve made people laugh, you’ve
                                                                           made them listen.
                                                                              In moments of darkness, comedy
                                                                           offers both a torch and a mirror. It lights
                                                                           the way and reflects back what we’ve
                                                                           become. Whether it’s a street perform-
                                                                           ance in Tehran, a late-night monologue
                                                                           in New York, or a YouTube sketch from
                                                                           Mumbai, satire continues to play an in-
                                                                           dispensable role in holding the powerful
                                                                           accountable.

                                                                           The last laugh
                                                                              In an age of disinformation, division
         Street art featuring satirical cartoons                           often, it endures long after the news
                                                                           and dissent, political comedy is not
                                                                           merely entertainment, it’s engagement.
                                                                           It questions, critiques, consoles and
                                                                           cycle fades. From Charlie Chaplin’s
                                                                           mute mockery of fascism to today’s
                                                                           global stand-up rebels, humor has con-
                                                                           sistently proven its might as a peaceful
                                                                           yet potent form of protest.
                                                                              On this World Laughter Day, let’s re-
                                                                           member: comedy is not just about mak-
                                                                           ing us laugh. It's about making us think,
        ►  fearless and at times, sacrificial. But au-  shown us that jokes are often more than   care and, when necessary, stand up.
           diences, too, play a role. For comedy to   punchlines, they are the first signals of   Because when the powerful fear
           thrive as a tool of resistance, it must be   social discomfort, the early warnings of   jokes more than protests, you know
           protected, legally, culturally and so-  authoritarian drift, the whispered truth in   laughter is doing its job.
           cially.                         a room of shouted propaganda.      “The duty of the comedian is to find
             Critics often dismiss political humor   As Hannah Gadsby pointed out in her   out where the line is drawn and cross it
           as trivial or disrespectful. Yet history has   revolutionary special Nanette, “Laughter   deliberately.” - George Carlin  ■

           20                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Filtered hearts, real feelings                                  presenting an idealized self, users aren’t
                                                                           necessarily lying; they’re optimizing.
                                                                           Yet this optimization often leads to dis-  SPECIAL FEATURE
                                                                           illusionment. The version of someone
                                                                           you fall for on-screen may feel funda-
                                                                           mentally different when encountered in
                                                                           person. Sociologist Erving Goffman’s
           The vulnerability  theory of self-presentation comes alive
                                                                           here: just like in physical society, we
                                                                           manage impressions online, but with
           of digital love                                                 more tools and fewer real-time con-
                                                                           sequences.
                                                                              Apps like Tinder and Bumble gamify
                                                                           romance, turning vulnerability into
                                                                           strategy. You reveal just enough to spark
           Online romance asks us to hold two truths at once:              interest, never too much to seem desper-
                                                                           ate. It’s a dance between authenticity
           we are both more and less than our profiles. The                and attractiveness, with many users un-
                                                                           aware when the line blurs.
           digital mirror can distort, but it can also reveal.
                                                                           The catfish and the chameleon:
           Authenticity online isn’t about full exposure, it’s             When performance becomes
                                                                           deception
           about intention. Are we curating to deceive, or to                 On one end of the spectrum, per-
           express? By Pooja Mehta                                         formance is strategic, a tweaked version   ►►



             n the age of curated feeds and algo-
             rithmic attraction, love has found a
           Inew playground, and it’s digital.
           With a few taps, we construct versions
           of ourselves meant to charm strangers
           across a virtual void. But is the image
           we offer truly “us”? Or just a carefully
           filtered projection tailored to get that
           coveted swipe?
             The question of authenticity in online
           dating has become more than a philo-
           sophical musing; it's a social phenome-
           non with deep psychological roots. As
           we observe Online Romance Day, it's
           worth unpacking the nuanced tension
           between self-presentation and sincerity
           in the quest for connection. For young
           adults navigating the labyrinth of dating
           apps and for digital natives who view
           the screen as a second skin, this dy-
           namic is not just relevant, it’s defining.

           Profile vs. Person: The digital self
           as a performance
             Dating profiles have become a mod-
           ern form of self-branding, a résumé not
           for jobs, but for intimacy. Carefully
           chosen photos, witty one-liners and in-
           terests that seem adventurous (but not
           intimidating) create a persona designed
           for appeal. But behind every “sunset
           lover” or “dog dad” lies a real person,
           often much more complex, and some-
           times messier, than the bio suggests.
             This is where the friction begins. In

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Smartphone displaying an open dating app                                                          Symbolizing the heart and the brain





























         A woman talking to her boyfriend                                                                  Two hands reaching toward one another













        ►  of the truth. On the other end lies cat-  This gray zone is where most of us   sations, seeking validation or testing
           fishing: outright deception, where indi-  live, negotiating the fine line between   empathy. Others retreat behind walls of
           viduals pose as someone else entirely,   being desirable and being real. And it   banter and emojis, avoiding anything
           often stealing photos and crafting false   raises an uncomfortable question: are we   that might hint at real emotional needs.
           identities. The motivations vary, insecu-  catfishing ourselves?   Both are reactions to a space that
           rity, loneliness, malicious intent, but the                     doesn’t quite know how to hold human
           result is the same: betrayal.   Vulnerability as a risk and     complexity.
             The 2010 documentary Catfish and   currency                      The paradox? Digital dating is both
           the MTV series it spawned opened the   Authenticity online isn’t just about   more emotionally intimate and more
           world’s eyes to this darker side of digital   accuracy, it’s about vulnerability. To be   emotionally evasive than traditional
           dating. But the problem persists because   real is to be exposed. And in a space   courtship. We can exchange life stories
           catfishing is a symptom, not the disease.   where rejection can be as easy as a   before even hearing someone’s voice,
           It reflects our culture’s obsession with   swipe, exposure feels risky.   but ghost them before things get real.
           perfection and the fear that we are not   Yet ironically, what we crave most is
           enough as we are.               connection, the kind that comes only   Global love, local masks: Culture
             In between the extremes of honest   when people drop the façade. The ten-  and identity in a digital world
           vulnerability and complete fabrication   sion is tangible: to connect, we must be   In a globally connected dating pool,
           lies a murky middle; curated personas.   open; but to survive online spaces, we   cultural identity becomes another filter.
           These are the people who exaggerate   often wear armor. Vulnerability becomes   Users from different backgrounds often
           their travel, downplay their mental   a form of currency, rare, valuable and   adapt or conceal cultural markers to ap-
           health struggles, or pick pictures that are   sometimes weaponized.   peal to broader audiences. A queer
           five years and ten pounds ago. Are they   Consider the trend of "trauma-dump-  woman in a conservative country might
           deceiving others, or just protecting   ing" on dating apps. Some users over-  hide her orientation on mainstream plat-
           themselves?                     share personal struggles early in conver-  forms. A South Asian man might down- ►►

           22                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[►  play his ethnicity to avoid racial bias, a
           known issue on many dating apps where
           algorithms and user preferences mirror
           societal stereotypes.
             Digital spaces, meant to be equal-
           izers, often reflect the same biases found
           in real life, sometimes amplified. Beauty
           standards, class implications and lin-
           guistic preferences all shape who gets
           attention and who is overlooked. This
           invisible sorting reinforces identity ten-
           sion, especially for people of color,                                                           Two people on a date with mismatched expectations
           gender nonconforming individuals, or
           those from marginalized communities.
             But the tide is shifting. Niche dating
           apps, from HER for queer women to
           Muzmatch for Muslims, are creating
           spaces where users can be more authen-
           tic without fear of erasure. They offer a
           glimpse into a future where personaliza-
           tion might finally serve authenticity, not   maintain authenticity and the more   courage, honesty and a little vulnerabil-
           just compatibility.             draining the dating process becomes.   ity.
                                             But understanding this can also em-
           The psychology of the swipe:    power users. By being aware of these   The mirror and the mask
           Seeking connection in a game of   tendencies, we can choose to show up   In the end, online romance asks us to
           appearances                     more honestly, more consciously. The   hold two truths at once: we are both
             Online dating is often described as a   swipe doesn’t have to erase sincerity.   more and less than our profiles. The dig-
           “numbers game,” where more swipes                               ital mirror can distort, but it can also re-
           mean more chances. But psychologi-  A new kind of romance:      veal. Authenticity online isn’t about full
           cally, this abundance has side effects:   Connection beyond the filter   exposure, it’s about intention. Are we
           decision fatigue, disillusionment and re-  Despite its flaws, online dating is not   curating to deceive, or to express?
           duced empathy. The paradox of choice   inherently shallow. It has led to mean-  As we continue to navigate the world
           makes people more likely to seek per-  ingful relationships, marriages and   of filtered feelings, perhaps the best we
           fection, and less likely to settle into im-  cross-cultural unions that would have   can do is to show up with a little more
           perfection, which is, ironically, where   been unlikely in a pre-digital world. It   grace, for ourselves and others. To swipe
           love often lives.               allows introverts, people with disabil-  not just with our thumbs, but with our
             Psychologists suggest that self-pre-  ities and those in remote areas to seek   hearts slightly ajar.
           sentation on dating apps taps into both   love in ways they never could before.   Because whether in pixels or in per-
           our ideal self (who we want to be) and   Technology doesn’t kill romance, it   son, the essence of love remains the
           our ought self (who we think we should   reshapes it. The challenge is not to aban-  same: the desire to be seen, truly seen,
           be). The disconnect between these and   don the screen, but to humanize it. To   and still be chosen. ■
           our real self creates internal tension. The   recognize that behind every profile is a
           greater the gap, the harder it becomes to   person and that connection still requires










         A woman speaking with her psychiatrist                                                            A woman feeling disappointed in her relationship
















           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT





































           Drink different                                                         perfectly crafted cocktail is
                                                                                 more than just a blend of spirits,
                                                                           Amixers and garnishes, it’s a sen-
                                                                           sory symphony. Each sip should delight
           The science of                                                  of aromas and captivate the eye with
                                                                           the palate, tease the nose with a bouquet
                                                                           color and clarity. But as mixology con-
                                                                           tinues to evolve, the bar is no longer
                                                                           merely a counter for pouring drinks; it’s
                                                                           a laboratory of innovation. Today’s bar-
           the perfect                                                     tenders are chemists, artists and technol-
                                                                           ogists, shaking up the industry with mo-
                                                                           lecular gastronomy, AI-powered flavor
                                                                           profiling and immersive experiences.
                                                                              In celebration of World Cocktail Day,
           cocktail                                                        drinks, one where precision meets pa-
                                                                           we raise our glasses to a new era of
                                                                           nache and science gives creativity an
                                                                           extra twist of lime. Whether you're a
                                                                           seasoned bartender, a foodie with flair,
                                                                           or someone who just likes their Old
           The modern cocktail is a celebration of flavor,                 Fashioned with a side of innovation,
                                                                           there’s something here to stir your cu-
           science and spectacle. From nitrogen-smoked                     riosity.

           glasses to AI-curated flavor profiles, we’re                    Molecular mixology: The alchemy
                                                                           of spirits
                                                                              At the heart of the modern cocktail
           witnessing the convergence of craftsmanship                     revolution is molecular gastronomy, a
           and code. This is no fleeting fad, it’s the future of           culinary discipline that manipulates ing-
                                                                           redients on a molecular level to enhance
           flavor. By Ishita Desai                                         flavor, texture and presentation. In the   ►►
                                                                           context of cocktails, this translates into

           24                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[►  spherified margaritas, smoke-infused
           Negronis and foamed mojitos, drinks
           that don’t just taste different, but feel
           different.
             Spherification, a technique popular-
           ized by chefs like Ferran Adrià, allows
           bartenders to encapsulate liquids into
           gel-like orbs. Imagine a burst of es-
           presso martini caviar popping in your
           mouth, intensely flavored, visually strik-                                                      A bartender using spherification to craft a cocktail
           ing and texturally surprising. Then
           there’s emulsification, used to create
           stable foams or airs, often flavored with
           citrus, herbs, or bitters, sitting atop the
           drink like a silky crown.
             These techniques aren’t mere gim-
           micks. They rely on deep knowledge of
           chemical reactions, pH balances and
           temperature thresholds. For instance,
           achieving the perfect foam involves ad-
           justing acidity levels and stabilizing
           agents like lecithin. Achieving clarity in
           a cocktail might require centrifugation, a
           method more often found in labs than in
           lounges.
           The physics of flavor layering
             While chemistry helps construct the
           molecular building blocks, physics plays
           an equally crucial role, especially when
           it comes to flavor layering. A well-lay-
           ered cocktail isn’t just visually stunning;
           it guides the drinker through a journey                                                         Cocktail being garnished
           of taste, one layer at a time.
             This is achieved by understanding
           the specific gravity of different ing-
           redients. Liquids with higher sugar
           content are denser and will settle at the   dome lifted tableside to reveal a rose-
           bottom, while those with higher alcohol   mary-infused bourbon, your brain reg-
           content float on top. Think of the classic   istering the woody scent before the
           B-52 shot, where coffee liqueur, Irish   drink even meets your palate.
           cream and Grand Marnier rest atop each   Fat-washing is another technique
           other like a boozy tricolor flag.   where spirits are infused with flavorful
             Temperature also plays its part. A   fats, like truffle oil, duck fat, or coconut
           chilled glass can preserve aromatic vol-  butter, then chilled and strained to retain
           atility, while shaking versus stirring   the aroma without the grease. The re-
           changes dilution and texture. Every ac-  sult? A richly aromatic drink that lingers
           tion, from the twist of the wrist to the   in memory as much as on the tongue.
           number of ice cubes, is rooted in scien-
           tific intent.                   Tech-Forward Bartending:
                                           Innovation on Tap
           Scent-sory innovation: The power   In an era of smart everything, tech-                         A beautifully crafted cocktail
           of aroma                        forward bartending is transforming
             While the tongue identifies sweet,   cocktail creation into a digital craft. Pre-
           sour, bitter, salty and umami, the nose   cision dispensing systems, digital refrac-
           deciphers thousands of volatile aromatic   tometers and temperature-controlled
           compounds. As such, bartenders are in-  mixing robots are ensuring consistency   printing to craft bespoke garnishes, ed-
           creasingly turning to aroma infusion to   with every pour.      ible art, or ice sculptures on demand.
           craft memorable cocktails.        High-end bars are now equipped with   But it’s not just about spectacle.
             Using tools like vaporizers, atom-  QR-coded menus, allowing guests to   Technology reduces waste, improves ac-
           izers and even liquid nitrogen, aromas   scan and customize drinks based on   curacy and enhances accessibility. For
           can be introduced before the drink ever   mood, dietary preference, or even   instance, AI-driven tools can suggest
           touches the lips. Picture a smoked glass   weather conditions. Some setups use 3D   substitutions for allergens or develop   ►►

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[yuzu foam and dill air. It’s not just ex-
                                                                           perimentation; it’s curated, calculated
                                                                           innovation.
                                                                              AI doesn’t just suggest ingredients. It
         A bartender presenting his crafted cocktail                       Imagine a bar where your past drink or-
                                                                           learns from consumer behavior, trending
                                                                           flavor notes and regional preferences.

                                                                           ders and Spotify playlists help tailor a
                                                                           cocktail just for you. It’s personalization
                                                                           taken to the next (and delicious) level.

                                                                           The ethical and artistic balance
                                                                              Despite the marvels of molecular
                                                                           mixology and AI mixologists, there's a
                                                                           lingering question, how much tech is too
                                                                           much?
                                                                              Purists argue that the soul of bartend-
                                                                           ing lies in the human connection, the
                                                                           flair, the eye contact, the intuitive ad-
                                                                           justments. A perfectly balanced Manhat-
                                                                           tan is more than its ingredients; it’s
         Beautifully presented cocktails, ready to serve                   sation.
                                                                           about knowing the drinker. Machines
                                                                           can’t yet replicate charisma or conver-

                                                                              Yet, proponents of innovation point
                                                                           out that technology amplifies creativity
                                                                           rather than replacing it. Tools like sous
                                                                           vide machines or centrifuges were once
                                                                           exotic; now they’re mainstays in pro-
                                                                           gressive bars. The key is to maintain
                                                                           balance, letting tech elevate, not over-
                                                                           shadow, the experience.
                                                                              In many ways, this mirrors the
                                                                           kitchen revolution; chefs didn’t vanish
                                                                           with the rise of precision cookers or
                                                                           data-driven plating. They evolved.
                                                                           A toast to the future of mixology
                                                                              The modern cocktail is a celebration
                                                                           of flavor, science and spectacle. From
                                                                           nitrogen-smoked glasses to AI-curated
                                                                           flavor profiles, we’re witnessing the
                                                                           convergence of craftsmanship and code.
                                                                           This is no fleeting fad, it’s the future of
                                                                           flavor.
                                                                              World Cocktail Day reminds us that
         A mixology lab setup                                              curiosity. Whether you’re behind the bar
                                                                           every great drink begins with a spark of
                                                                           or at the other end of it, the joy lies in
                                                                           discovery. And now, with science as our
                                                                           shaker and innovation as our bitters, the
                                                                           possibilities are as endless as the drink
                                                                           list.
        ►  low-alcohol alternatives with similar fla-  rithms are being applied to spirits. By   So here’s to the thinkers, the tin-
           vor profiles, an inclusive twist that res-  analyzing thousands of ingredients and   kerers, the tasters. The next time you sip
           onates with modern wellness trends.   flavor profiles, AI can generate new   a cocktail, take a moment to savor the
                                           cocktail recipes based on data, not just   science behind it. You’re not just drink-
           Artificial intelligence in the age of   instinct.               ing a Negroni, you’re experiencing a
           alcohol                           Some bartenders feed the AI sensory   carefully constructed molecular marvel,
             The arrival of AI-designed cocktails   input (flavor wheels, guest feedback,   perhaps with a dash of code and a gar-
           is one of the most fascinating frontiers.   chemical compositions) and it responds   nish of genius.
           Platforms like IBM’s Chef Watson have   with unlikely but balanced combina-  Cheers to the future, it’s already
           dabbled in food, but now similar algo-  tions, say, mezcal and beetroot with   being stirred. ■

           26                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Gone too soon
        ►


           Remembering                                                                                           TRIBUTE






           Javidan’s






           beautiful life







                  By Staff Writer
                                           A trailblazer with vision and   mere acquaintance, they embraced him
                                           courage                         like family. His camaraderie with Ra-
                he loss of a loved one is never   Javidan's life was a portrait of dyna-  kesh Johri, the celebrated music com-
                easy. But when the youngest   mism and innovation. He was not just a   poser and Dr. Johri’s son, further ce-
           Tmember of a family departs, the   dreamer but a doer , the first among his   mented his legacy in the local music
           sorrow runs deeper, striking chords that   siblings to begin earning, charting his   circle. Javidan was ever-present at musi-
           reverberate through the very soul of   own course with confidence and cou-  cal events, handling logistics, singing
           those left behind. Such is the grief that   rage. His journey from Meerut to Mum-  with joy and turning every gathering,
           enveloped the Zuberi family with the   bai, where he pursued a film editing   whether a concert or a family celebra-
           untimely passing of Javidan Zuberi, a   course and worked on well-known tele-  tion , into a memory to cherish.
           beloved son, brother, father and friend ,   vision serials, speaks volumes of his
           a man whose life, though tragically cut   daring spirit. In an era when few ven-  The man who brought people
           short, was full of warmth, brilliance and   tured into media from small towns, Javi-  together
           irreplaceable charm.            dan stood out with grit and talent.   To his friends, he was a companion
                                                                           with a generous heart. To his com-
           A date marked by love and loss   A technological genius ahead of   munity, he was the dependable one, al-
             On May 1, a date once marked by   his time                    ways stepping in to organize, entertain
           celebration, his wedding anniversary, the   His technical flair was exceptional.   and support. To his family, he was the
           air is now heavy with remembrance. Just   When VCRs were in vogue, he could   youngest, the liveliest and the one who
           two days prior, Javidan bid farewell to   mend them with a magician's touch, a   made things whole.
           this world. His decline began on No-  skill he learned under the keen guidance
           vember 13, 2024, following a brain in-  of his father. Later, as CCTV technology   A legacy etched in love and
           jury from a fall. Despite the tireless ef-  gained momentum, Javidan became a   memory
           forts at Meerut Medical College   trusted contractor, securing large-scale   As we reflect on Javidan’s life, a mix
           Hospital, where his son, Aman Zuberi,   projects across Western Uttar Pradesh   of pride and pain rises. Pride in the man
           studies as a first-year MBBS student, Ja-  and Uttarakhand. His leadership and   he became, talented, loving, enterprising
           vidan could not overcome the final bat-  technical prowess enabled him to build   and pain in the loss that time cannot
           tle.                            teams and deliver consistently, winning   mend. Yet, amidst this sorrow lies grat-
                                           respect in a competitive industry.   itude: for having known him, for the
           The cherished youngest son                                      moments he gifted and the legacy he
             Born as the youngest of four sons to   A soul moved by music   leaves behind.
           Dr. F.H. Zuberi, a renowned physicist,   Yet, beyond his professional accom-  The Revoir Magazine family joins in
           Javidan naturally became the heart of   plishments, it was his artistic soul that   mourning this irreplaceable loss and ex-
           the household. Showered with affection   endeared him to many. Javidan inherited   tends heartfelt condolences to the Zuberi
           by his parents and three elder brothers,   a deep love for music, which blossomed   family. May the strength of shared mem-
           his presence brought light and laughter   into treasured relationships with stal-  ories and the love of those around bring
           to every corner of the home. His bond   warts like Dr. Sunita Saxena, head of the   solace in this difficult hour. And may Ja-
           with his family was profound and endur-  Music Department at RG Postgraduate   vidan's soul find eternal peace, his
           ing, a reflection of the love that sur-  College and her mentor, Dr. Prem Pra-  melody echoing in the hearts of all who
           rounded him from his earliest days.   kash Johri. These bonds transcended   loved him. ■

           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                May 01-15, 2025









           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     A burst of energy propels you toward professional   Balance is your keyword now, don’t overcom-
                     progress. It’s a great time to initiate new projects.   mit. Career requires teamwork, while love blos-
                     Relationships thrive if you listen more and react   soms through shared experiences. A surprise ex-
                     less. Be cautious with spending, unexpected     pense could arise, so hold off on luxuries. Music
                     expenses may arise.                             or art can help you unwind.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     With the Sun in your sign, confidence soars. You'll   You’re drawn toward introspection. Workplace
                     feel more in control at work and in personal    harmony improves if you control your intensity.
                     matters. Romance is fulfilling, and your charm is   In love, deep conversations bring closeness.
                     magnetic. A good period for financial planning.   Avoid large financial risks. Focus on hydration
                     Don’t ignore physical fitness.                  and avoid burnout.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     You may feel a bit scattered, so focus on organ-  Adventure beckons, but work demands dis-
                     izing your priorities. Networking brings career   cipline. Time management is crucial. Romantic
                     advantages. In love, clarity beats mixed signals.   connections are spontaneous and light-hearted.
                     Financially, avoid lending money. Meditation    Investments show promise. Add more fruits and
                     helps restore inner balance.                    fiber to your diet.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     A powerful period to set personal goals. Your in-  A productive fortnight where results match your
                     tuition helps you in both work and relationships.   effort. Love life is stable, but don’t take your
                     Emotional bonding strengthens romantic con-     partner for granted. An older financial decision
                     nections. Financially, things improve with con-  could pay off. Rest your joints and take short
                     servative spending.                             breaks if you’re desk-bound.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     You’re in the spotlight professionally, so make   Fresh ideas bring momentum to projects. Col-
                     your voice heard. Romantic sparks may fly with   laboration leads to success. Love feels refreshing
                     someone unexpected. Expenses could rise, track   and intellectually stimulating. A good time to
                     them carefully. Focus on your posture and avoid   clear debts. Practice breathing exercises for
                     overexertion.                                   mental clarity.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Problem-solving is your strength this fortnight.   Your sensitivity is your strength. Creative work
                     Challenges at work can be resolved diplomati-   shines, and intuition guides financial choices.
                     cally. Romance may need more attention, don’t   Love life feels dreamy, ground it with honest
                     let routine dampen love. Your savings plan looks   talks. Don’t skip meals or neglect hydration.
                     stable. Avoid eye strain from screens.          Sleep is your secret superpower.


           28                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 | MAY 01 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           SC's verdict on police misconduct   stance over symbolism. Citizens expect
           a welcome step                  concrete action, not just slogans. If the
             The Supreme Court’s decision to   census is to bring real change, all parties   but as a fracture in our collective mem-
           uphold the ₹2 lakh penalty on a Tamil   must commit to transparency, inclusiv-  ory. I wholeheartedly agree that heritage
           Nadu police inspector for failing to   ity, and genuine empowerment.   is the connective tissue of society, shap-
           register an FIR and using abusive   Kapil Gupta, Delhi, India   ing identity and imparting wisdom to fu-
           language is a significant step toward                           ture generations. All the articles in the
           police accountability. Such misconduct                          magazine are engaging; however, the
           undermines public trust in law   Condemning the pahalgam terror   deliberate destruction of monuments,
           enforcement and denies justice to victims.   attack             whether ancient temples, mosques, or
             This ruling sends a clear message:   I am writing to express deep anguish   statues of figures like Ambedkar and
           abuse of power will not be tolerated. It is   over the recent terror attack in Pahal-  Gandhi, reveals a dangerous urge to re-
           high time police officers are held to higher   gam, which claimed the lives of inno-  write history in pursuit of ideological
           standards of professionalism and duty.   cent civilians. Such heinous acts of vio-  dominance.
           Strict enforcement of legal obligations   lence not only shatter the peace of the   As rightly pointed out, heritage must
           and disciplinary actions can pave the way   region but also threaten the spirit of   evolve through thoughtful reexamina-
           for much-needed reform in the policing   unity and democracy that defines our   tion, not erasure. Vandalism carried out
           system.                         nation.                         in the name of religious or political
           Kavita Sharma, Mumbai,            Pahalgam, known for its natural   agendas is a deeply troubling act, one
           Maharashtra, India              beauty and tourism, must not be allowed   that denies the very pluralism which has
                                           to become a ground for terror. The gov-  defined civilizations across time.
                                           ernment must act swiftly to bring the   Aarav Sharma’s adjacent piece, Her-
           ‘Jhukti Hai Duniya’ Posters     perpetrators to justice and ensure robust   itage Loss: What Happens When History
             The sudden appearance of "Jhukti   security measures to prevent such inci-  Is Erased?, and Prof. Kishan Kant
           Hai Duniya" posters featuring Rahul   dents in the future. Additionally, it's vital   Sharma’s Preserving the Soul of Civili-
           Gandhi, following the Centre’s nod to   to support the affected families and pro-  sation, underscore the irreversible dam-
           caste census, has stirred both curiosity   mote harmony among communities.   age of such actions. The emphasis on in-
           and political debate. While the slogan   Terrorism has no place in a civilized   clusive policies and community
           echoes confidence and political asser-  society. It is our collective responsibil-  engagement is essential. When history is
           tion, it also raises questions about the   ity, as citizens, to remain vigilant and   weaponized, it is often the marginalized,
           timing and intent behind such cam-  support peace-building efforts.   already underrepresented, who bear the
           paigns.                         Ramesh Sehgal, Delhi, India     greatest cost.
             The caste census is a significant                                Let us strive to preserve our heritage
           move toward social justice, aiming to                           not as a site of conflict, but as a shared
           ensure equitable resource distribution.   Heritage must be preserved, not   legacy, one that embraces uncomfortable
           However, using it as a platform for po-  erased                 truths while honouring the rich and di-
           litical one-upmanship risks diverting at-  Dr. Kamran Zuberi’s editorial, Not   verse tapestry of our past.
           tention from the real issue—uplifting   Just the Past, eloquently captures the   Shahid A Siddiqui, I.R.S (Retd.)
           marginalized communities.       profound loss that occurs when heritage   Hamdard Education Society,
             Political leaders must prioritize sub-  is erased, not only as a cultural tragedy,   New Delhi, Inida



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           MAY 01 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.9 www.revoir.in                                    29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[The sea, once it casts its spell, holds one in


                                               its net of wonder forever." – Jacques Cousteau











































































                                                                                                               Photo credit: Leone]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[►










































                                    YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!






































                                                                                                         ►►

                                                                                 ol. 3, No.5 |
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                V
                                                                                  V
                                                                                      |

                                                                                   ol. 3, No.7 |
                                                                                      |
                                                                            .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                            .in
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                              .in
                                                                              ol. 3, No.4 |
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                             V
                                                                              REVOIR

                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                        FEBRUAR
                                                                                        |

                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                   16 2025

                                                                                             APRIL
                                                                                        DECEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024

                                                                                      |
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024



           32
           32
           323232
           32
           32
                                                      www
                                                      .revoir
                                                  www.revoir
                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.6 | MARCH 16 2025MARCH 01 2025
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32
           32                                     wwwwwwwww www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025 01 2025OBER 01 2024
           323232
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
                                                                   www
                                                                    www
                                                                   www
                                                                 REVOIR Magazine
                                                                  REVOIR Magazine REVOIR | AUGUST 01 202432
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in
                                                                     www
                                                           .revoir
                                                           .in
                                                       www.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.1 | JANUARY 01 2025www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | NOVEMBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | OCTOBER 16 2023www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024
                                                         .revoir
                                                            www
                                                                .revoir
                                                                .in
                                                              .in
                                                              REVOIR Magazine
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>