<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="36"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 22  I  DECEMBER 16 2024        ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             25



                                                             8













                                                            20                                        5
















           4-Editorial: The unseen steps to                23-The height of talent
           success                                         25-Christmas around the world

           5-The Power of Failure                          29-How basketball unites the world

           8-A Life in Rhythm (1951–2024)                  32-Horoscopes

           10-The magic behind numbers                     33-Letters
           14-Why books outshine screens

           17-From analog to digital

           20-Height doesn’t measure greatness












           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Failures
     EDITORIAL  The unseen                                                         Dr. Kamran Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           steps to success                                                      zuberi@magazine.revoir.in


                                                                                Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                                                               uzma.naaz@magazine.revoir.in
                                             ailure is often seen as the villain in
                                             our pursuit of success, casting a    Art & Culture Editor
                                        Fshadow of doubt, disappointment,            Navormi Vats
                                        and fear. Yet, if we pause to reflect, failure   navormi.vats@magazine.revoir.in
                                        is not the enemy, it is a disguised mentor,
                                        offering lessons that no triumph can teach.   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        As we observe Unlucky Day, let us shift our   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        perspective on failure, recognizing its   purnima.chauhan@magazine.revoir.in
                                        indispensable role in shaping success.
                                           Great achievers throughout history have   Social Media Editor
                                        turned failures into stepping stones. Thomas   Vikas Babbar
                                        Edison, who endured thousands of failed   vikas.babbar@magazine.revoir.in
                                        attempts before inventing the light bulb,
                                        saw these failures not as defeats but as   Art & Graphics Editor
           lessons. Each mistake brought him closer to the solution. His story, like countless   Vipin Kumar
           others, reminds us that success is not a straight road; it’s a winding path paved with   vipin.kumar@magazine.revoir.in
           missteps, retries, and resilience. Failure doesn’t end dreams, it refines them. It
           teaches us perseverance, the ability to adapt, and a deeper understanding of our goals.   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
             Failure also humbles us. It strips away arrogance, forcing us to acknowledge our
           limitations while helping us grow. More importantly, it builds mental toughness,   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           preparing us to face life’s inevitable challenges. Mistakes are not dead ends; they are   Editor, United News of India, New
           detours, guiding us to approach problems with greater clarity and creativity.   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             In today’s fast-paced, success-driven world, where perfection is often glorified,   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           the fear of failure can be paralyzing. It stifles creativity, curbs risk-taking, and keeps   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           us within the confines of what feels safe. Yet true growth lies beyond our comfort   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           zones. When we embrace failure, we unlock the courage to experiment, innovate, and   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           aim higher. Falling is a part of learning, and rising after a fall is where real success   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           begins.                                                                Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             The journeys of Walt Disney, who faced countless rejections before building his
           entertainment empire, and J.K. Rowling, whose manuscript for Harry Potter was   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           turned down repeatedly, serve as powerful reminders. Their successes were not
           despite their failures but because of them. These stories inspire us to see setbacks not   Phone +91 20 40199102
           as barriers but as part of the process toward greatness.          Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             As individuals, organizations, and societies, we must reframe failure as an   Baner Road,
           opportunity rather than a setback. We should celebrate the lessons it teaches and the   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           resilience it fosters. By creating environments that embrace mistakes as learning   Published by Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           experiences, we encourage innovation and growth.                   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
             On this Unlucky Day, let us embrace the idea that failures, however daunting, are   Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
           temporary. They don’t define us but instead shape us into better versions of   Frequency Fortnightly
           ourselves. Each stumble is a step closer to growth, and every misstep carries the seed   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           of success. After all, the true measure of success is not how often we avoid failure,   Website www.revoir.in
           but how we rise, learn, and move forward in its aftermath.
             Failure, far from being a foe, is the fuel that propels us toward greatness. Let us   Legal Advisor
           embrace it wholeheartedly.                                            Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)

                                                                            Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
         Khzuberil
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi                                                      without permission.
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Fueling Success                                                 ing their breakthroughs. Thomas Edison,

                                                                           who invented the electric light bulb, fa-
                                                                           mously said, "I have not failed. I've just
                                                                           found 10,000 ways that won't work."   PERSPECTIVE
           The Power of                                                    failure is not an endpoint but a part of
                                                                           This perspective highlights the idea that
                                                                           the process that brings you closer to the
                                                                           ultimate goal.
                                                                              Failure serves as a feedback mecha-
                                                                           nism. It reveals what doesn’t work, al-
           Failure                                                         ation and adjust their approach. Whether
                                                                           lowing individuals to analyze the situ-
                                                                           it’s in business, relationships, or per-
                                                                           sonal goals, each mistake provides valu-
                                                                           able data that can guide future actions.
                                                                           Embracing failure as a necessary part of
                                                                           the learning curve allows individuals to
           Mistakes and setbacks are not the end of the road, they         persevere and adapt, ultimately leading
                                                                           them toward success.
           are merely a part of the journey. Each failure provides us
           with invaluable lessons that help us grow, refine our           The psychological impact of failure
                                                                              The psychological effects of failure
           strategies, and build resilience. By Naina Kapoor               are often cited as the main reason people
                                                                           fear making mistakes. Fear of failure



               ailure, often regarded as the anti-
               thesis of success, has long been
           Fmisunderstood as a negative ex-
           perience to be avoided at all costs. In re-
           ality, failure is an essential part of the
           journey to success. The most accom-
           plished people in history have all faced
           setbacks, challenges, and mistakes,
           which ultimately shaped their paths to
           greatness. Rather than viewing failure as
           something to fear, one can embrace it as
           an invaluable tool for personal and pro-
           fessional growth.
             On the occasion of Unlucky Day, a
           day dedicated to reflecting on the chal-
           lenges and obstacles that often make us
           feel unlucky or thwarted, it’s important
           to remember that these very challenges
           can provide the insights and experiences
           necessary for future triumphs. Unlucky
           Day is a reminder that even in the midst
           of apparent misfortune, there is a greater
           opportunity to learn and grow. In this ar-
           ticle, we will explore how mistakes and
           failures are not just roadblocks but step-
           ping stones to eventual success.

           The role of failure in success
             At first glance, failure may seem
           counterproductive to the idea of success.
           It may invoke feelings of discourage-
           ment, self-doubt, and frustration. Ho-
           wever, failure provides essential lessons
           that cannot be learned through success
           alone. Many of the world’s most famous
           inventors, entrepreneurs, and leaders
           have experienced failure before achiev-

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[can cause anxiety, leading to procrasti-
           nation and avoidance. Yet, by facing fai-
           lure head-on, individuals can train their
           minds to view setbacks as temporary
           and solvable challenges. Overcoming
           failure helps build resilience—a crucial
           characteristic for personal and profes-
           sional success.
             People who are willing to take risks
           and face failure head-on are often more
           successful than those who avoid failure
           altogether. Resilience is developed by
           continually picking oneself up after each
           fall, learning from the experience, and                                                         A climber scaling a mountain
           trying again. By re-framing failure as a
           learning opportunity, people can take the
           sting out of mistakes and approach chal-
           lenges with a healthier mindset. This
           shift in perspective helps to create an en-
           vironment where risk-taking and inno-
           vation are celebrated rather than feared.

           Mistakes as stepping stones to
           success
             In every field, failure can serve as a
           powerful teacher. In business, a failed
           venture often leads to a deeper under-
           standing of market dynamics, customer
           needs, and operational challenges. En-
           trepreneurs who have experienced fai-
           lure are often better equipped to pivot,
           make more informed decisions, and ex-
           ecute their next venture with greater
           confidence and insight. For instance,                                                           An athlete reflecting after a loss
           Steve Jobs' journey through failure at
           Apple in the 1980s and his eventual re-
           turn to the company is a testament to the
           value of learning from mistakes. His
           early failure was a crucial step in his
           personal growth, ultimately enabling   ences defeat at some point in their ca-  titude. A basketball player who misses a
           him to lead Apple to unparalleled suc-  reer. These losses are crucial for im-  crucial shot in a game doesn’t just feel
           cess.                           provement, as they help athletes identify   defeated; they analyze their technique,
             In sports, mistakes and losses are   areas for development, refine their   learn to adjust, and come back stronger
           equally important. Every athlete experi-  skills, and strengthen their mental for-  in future matches. The greatest athletes
                                                                           in the world view setbacks as opportuni-
                                                                           ties to evolve, rather than signs to quit.
                                                                              Similarly, in creative fields like writ-
         A person viewing a wall of failures with affirmations             deal, and many famous authors, such as
                                                                           ing, art, and music, rejection or failure
                                                                           can be a catalyst for refinement and
                                                                           growth. Writers often face numerous re-
                                                                           jections before landing a publishing

                                                                           J.K. Rowling, faced multiple setbacks
                                                                           before finding success. Each rejection
                                                                           teaches writers to improve their craft,
                                                                           develop their voice, and become more
                                                                           resilient. Success, then, is not about
                                                                           avoiding mistakes but learning to use
                                                                           them as stepping stones toward achiev-
                                                                           ing one’s goals.

                                                                           Failure in personal development
                                                                              Failure is not limited to the profes-

           6                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[A person crossing the finish line                                                                 A road with hurdles and a clear path ahead

















         Failures are valuable lessons for growth                          cess is built on the foundation of perse-

                                                                           verance through failure. In many cul-
                                                                           tures, failure is stigmatized and seen as
                                                                           something to be avoided at all costs. Yet,
                                                                           the most successful individuals and or-
                                                                           ganizations understand that failure is a
                                                                           natural part of the creative and growth
                                                                           process.
                                                                              By creating environments that en-
                                                                           courage risk-taking and the acceptance
                                                                           of mistakes, businesses and educational
                                                                           institutions can foster innovation and re-
           sional world—it also plays a vital role in   failures. The ability to persist in the face   silience. When failure is normalized as a
           personal growth. In relationships, per-  of adversity is what separates successful   part of the learning process, people are
           sonal goals, or self-improvement, failure   individuals from those who never reach   more likely to take creative risks, chal-
           can offer critical insights into one’s be-  their full potential. Each failure serves to   lenge the status quo, and develop new
           havior, preferences, and desires. Often,   strengthen one's determination and re-  ideas. In fact, failure often leads to
           mistakes reveal parts of ourselves that   solve. This persistence is often what   greater creativity because it forces indi-
           we may not have been aware of, such as   leads to eventual breakthroughs.   viduals to think outside the box and find
           unaddressed fears, insecurities, or areas   One of the most famous examples of   novel solutions to problems.
           that require healing. For instance, a per-  persistence after failure is the story of   On this Unlucky Day, it’s essential to
           son who faces failure in a romantic rela-  Walt Disney. Early in his career, Disney   recognize that failure is not something
           tionship might learn about their own   faced numerous rejections and setbacks.   to fear but something to embrace. Mis-
           emotional needs, boundaries, or com-  He was even told that he lacked creativ-  takes and setbacks are not the end of the
           munication patterns. This awareness al-  ity and vision. However, he didn’t give   road, they are merely a part of the jour-
           lows them to grow and build healthier   up. Instead, he used those rejections to   ney. Each failure provides us with in-
           relationships in the future.    fuel his drive to succeed. His persistence   valuable lessons that help us grow, re-
             Failure can also help individuals re-  eventually led to the creation of Disney,   fine our strategies, and build resilience.
           assess their values and redefine what   one of the world’s most beloved and   Success is not defined by the number of
           success means to them. Sometimes, we   profitable entertainment companies.   times we fall but by the number of times
           set goals based on external pressures or   Disney’s story demonstrates that success   we rise, learn, and continue to strive to-
           societal expectations, only to realize that   often requires years of effort, many fai-  ward our goals. By changing the way we
           they don’t align with our true aspira-  lures, and an unwavering belief in one’s   view failure, we can transform chal-
           tions. By failing in these pursuits, we are   ability to overcome challenges.   lenges into opportunities for growth.
           often forced to reconsider our direction                        Embracing failure as a natural and nec-
           and set new, more meaningful goals.   Embracing failure in modern   essary part of the process will lead to
                                           society                         greater self-awareness, innovation, and
           The importance of persistence     In today’s fast-paced world, where   success. So, next time you encounter a
             Persistence is key to turning failure   instant gratification and overnight suc-  setback, remember that it may just be
           into success. No one achieves greatness   cess stories often dominate the media,   the stepping stone you need to achieve
           by giving up after encountering a few   it’s easy to forget that real, lasting suc-  your dreams. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SPOTLIGHT




































           Ustad Zakir Hussain



           A Life in





           Rhythm (1951–2024)






           Zakir Hussain’s impact on music transcends borders and generations.  By Meera Reddy


                he world of music mourns the   ness as the son of Ustad Alla Rakha, a   forefront of Indian classical music.
                loss of Ustad Zakir Hussain, the   revered tabla maestro. Under the metic-
           Ttabla virtuoso who passed away   ulous guidance of his father, Zakir   A global ambassador for Indian
           on December 16, 2024, at the age of 73.   began his training in the intricacies of   music
           Known for his unmatched artistry and   rhythm at a young age. By the time he   Zakir Hussain’s genius lay in his
           global influence, Zakir succumbed to   was a teenager, his prodigious talent was   ability to seamlessly blend traditional
           complications from idiopathic pul-  evident. His performances were charac-  Indian rhythms with global music forms.
           monary fibrosis at a hospital in San   terized by an exceptional command of   He became a global ambassador for In-
           Francisco. His demise leaves a void in   the tabla, coupled with an infectious   dian music, introducing audiences
           the world of music that will be hard to   passion that captivated audiences.   worldwide to the magic of the tabla. His
           fill, but his legacy remains eternal.   Zakir’s early career saw him working   collaborations with international musi-
                                           with stalwarts like sitar maestro Ravi   cians such as John McLaughlin, Mickey
           Early years: A prodigy in the   Shankar, violinist L. Subramaniam, and   Hart, and George Harrison exemplified
           making                          flute legend Hariprasad Chaurasia. With   his openness to experimentation and in-
             Born on March 9, 1951, in Mumbai,   every performance, he pushed the   novation.
           Zakir Hussain was destined for great-  boundaries of tabla, bringing it to the   Zakir co-founded the fusion band

           8                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Shakti with McLaughlin, which became
           a pioneering act in world music. His
           contributions to Planet Drum, a
           Grammy-winning album, further show-
           cased his versatility. These collabo-
           rations not only enriched his repertoire
           but also cemented his position as a
           global musical icon.
           Honors and recognition                                                                          Ustad Zakir Hussain during a live performance
             Zakir Hussain's artistic excellence
           earned him numerous accolades
           throughout his illustrious career. Do-
           mestically, he was honored with the
           Padma Shri, Padma Bhushan, and
           Padma Vibhushan—the highest civilian
           awards in India. His international rec-
           ognitions included the National Heritage
           Fellowship in the United States and the
           Officier of the Order of Arts and Letters
           in France. He also received four
           Grammy Awards, underscoring his uni-
           versal appeal.
             Beyond awards, Zakir was widely re-
           spected for his contributions to cultural
           diplomacy. His performances at presti-                                                          Ustad Zakir Hussain receives Padma Vibhushan
           gious venues, including Carnegie Hall,
           Lincoln Center, and the Royal Albert                                                              Ustad Ghulam Mustafa Khan Award
           Hall, were testaments to his ability to
           bring people and cultures together
           through music.

           Personal life and influence
             Zakir Hussain was as devoted to his
           family as he was to his craft. His wife,   was not just a profession but a medium   while industrialist Anand Mahindra
           Antonia Minnecola, a Kathak dancer,   to connect with humanity.   aptly remarked, “The rhythm of India
           played an integral role in his personal                         paused today.”
           and professional life. Together, they   The final chapter          Social media was flooded with heart-
           raised two daughters, Anisa and Isa-  In the weeks leading up to his death,   felt tributes, including those from actor
           bella, who often accompanied him on   Zakir Hussain was hospitalized in San   Anupam Kher, who celebrated Zakir’s
           his international tours.        Francisco due to worsening lung-related   infectious smile, and Kareena Kapoor,
             Known for his childlike smile and   complications. His passing sent ripples   who called him a “maestro forever.” His
           warm personality, Zakir inspired count-  of grief across the world, with tributes   funeral, expected to take place in Mum-
           less young musicians. His workshops   pouring in from musicians, actors, and   bai, is anticipated to draw a global au-
           and masterclasses were eagerly attended   politicians alike. Kerala Chief Minister   dience of admirers.
           by aspiring tabla players and percus-  Pinarayi Vijayan described him as “a
           sionists worldwide. For Zakir, music   true custodian of classical traditions,”   A legacy that transcends time
                                                                              Zakir Hussain’s impact on music
                                                                           transcends borders and generations. He
                                                                           revolutionized the way tabla was per-
         Ustad Zakir with his wife Antonia Minnecola                       art form. Through his dedication and
                                                                           ceived, transforming it from an accom-
                                                                           panying instrument to a celebrated solo

                                                                           artistry, he ensured that Indian classical
                                                                           music found its rightful place on the
                                                                           global stage.
                                                                              As the world bids farewell to this
                                                                           legend, his music will continue to in-
                                                                           spire and resonate. In every rhythmic
                                                                           beat and every harmonious note, Zakir
                                                                           Hussain’s spirit will live on, reminding

                                                                           that he so beautifully mastered.

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                us of the universal language of music   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION



































           Mathematics


           The magic



                                                                           a reminder of the elegance and rel-
                                                                           evance of math in our daily lives. Ra-
           behind numbers                                                  manujan, who faced numerous chal-
                                                                           lenges throughout his life, proved that
                                                                           mathematical brilliance does not require
                                                                           a formal education but is a product of
                                                                           passion, perseverance, and an innate un-
           The beauty of mathematics is not just in its applications but   derstanding of patterns that defy con-

           in the sense of wonder it evokes. Whether it's the elegance of   ventional knowledge. Mathematics Day
                                                                           encourages not only appreciation for
           prime numbers, the harmony of geometry, or the endless          Ramanujan’s genius but also a celebra-
                                                                           tion of the timeless allure of math itself.
           mysteries of infinity, mathematics captivates the imagination.
           By Karan Malhotra                                               The magic of numbers
                                                                              Mathematics is often referred to as
                                                                           the "language of the universe." The ele-
                  athematics is often regarded   you're observing the growth patterns of   gance of numbers is immediately appar-
                  as a discipline of numbers,   a sunflower, calculating the trajectory of   ent when one explores their intrinsic
           Mformulas, and equations. But   a rocket, or exploring the infinite uni-  properties. Consider the number pi (π),
           to the curious mind, it reveals itself as a   verse of prime numbers, math has an un-  which appears in everything from the
           treasure trove of patterns, mysteries, and   paralleled way of inspiring awe and   geometry of circles to the study of
           elegant truths that transcend the bound-  wonder.               waves and oscillations in physics. Pi is
           aries of textbooks. From the symmetry   On the occasion of Mathematics Day,   an irrational number, meaning its dec-
           of nature to the complexities of modern   we take a deeper look at the beauty and   imal representation never repeats and
           technology, math is woven into the very   magic of math. Celebrated in honor of   never ends, which makes it a symbol of
           fabric of our world. Its beauty lies not   the renowned Indian mathematician Sri-  the infinite. For centuries, mathemati-
           just in its utility, but in the profound   nivasa Ramanujan, whose contributions   cians have been trying to calculate the
           sense of order and logic it brings to our   to number theory continue to shape the   value of pi with greater precision, and
           understanding of the universe. Whether   world of mathematics, this day serves as   yet the mystery of its infinite sequence

           10                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[continues to captivate and inspire.
             Similarly, the golden ratio, denoted
           by the Greek letter φ (phi), is another re-
           markable mathematical constant that ap-
           pears in nature, architecture, and art.
           This ratio, approximately equal to 1.618,
           is the result of dividing a line into two
           parts such that the longer part divided by
           the shorter part is the same as the whole
           line divided by the longer part. This
           ratio can be found in the branching of
           trees, the arrangement of leaves around
           a stem, and even in the proportions of
           the Parthenon in Greece. The ubiquity of                                                        The Golden Ratio in nature
           the golden ratio across various natural
           and man-made structures reflects the in-
           herent beauty of mathematical relation-
           ships.

           The art of geometry
             Geometry, the branch of mathematics
           concerned with the properties of shapes
           and spaces, is another domain where the
           magic of math is evident. From the sim-
           plicity of a triangle to the complexities
           of a 3D polyhedron, geometry offers
           endless possibilities for discovery. One
           of the most famous geometrical theo-
           rems is Pythagoras’ theorem, which
           states that in a right-angled triangle, the
           square of the hypotenuse is equal to the
           sum of the squares of the other two
           sides. This principle is not only a foun-
           dational concept in geometry but has
           far-reaching applications in fields like
           physics, engineering, and computer
           graphics.                                                                                       The Golden Ratio in nature
             The beauty of geometry extends bey-
           ond its theoretical applications. Archi-
           tects and artists have long been inspired
           by geometric principles to create works
           that are visually striking and structurally   such as x+3=7x + 3 = 7x+3=7, demon-
           sound. The use of symmetry, proportion,   strates how a seemingly trivial problem
           and shape in buildings, paintings, and   can lead to a deeper understanding of
           sculptures can be traced back to the   the relationships between variables.
           study of geometry, where balance and   In more advanced algebra, math-
           harmony are essential. The appeal of   ematicians use complex equations to
           shapes like the circle, hexagon, and spi-  model everything from financial mar-
           ral lies in their simplicity and their prev-  kets to the behavior of subatomic par-
           alence in nature, from the symmetry of a   ticles. One of the most beautiful aspects
           snowflake to the whorls of a seashell.   of algebra is the idea of symmetry. Sym-
                                           metry plays a crucial role in group
           Algebra: Unlocking the secrets of   theory, a branch of abstract algebra that
           equations                       deals with mathematical structures
             Algebra, the branch of mathematics   known as groups. The concept of sym-
           dealing with symbols and the rules for   metry is fundamental in physics, chem-
           manipulating them, might seem more   istry, and biology, where the same prin-                   Srinivasa Ramanujan, Indian mathematician
           abstract than geometry, but it is equally   ciples apply to the behavior of
           full of wonder. At its heart, algebra is   molecules, atoms, and even living or-
           about solving problems and finding un-  ganisms.
           knowns. The beauty of algebra lies in its
           ability to generalize and model real-  The beauty of prime numbers
           world situations. A simple equation,   Among the many wonders of math-

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Mathematical models in architecture                                                               Mathematics in architectural design















           ematics, prime numbers hold a special   domly. The unpredictability and mystery   fields like computer graphics, where
           place. Primes are numbers greater than 1   of primes continue to fascinate math-  these patterns are used to generate real-
           that cannot be divided evenly by any   ematicians, making them a symbol of   istic images of natural landscapes.
           other number except for 1 and them-  the infinite complexity within the realm
           selves. The study of prime numbers is   of mathematics.         The role of mathematics in
           not only a central area of research in                          technology and innovation
           number theory but also a gateway to   Mathematical patterns in nature   The magic of math extends far bey-
           some of the deepest mysteries in math-  Mathematics is not confined to ab-  ond theoretical concepts; it plays a vital
           ematics. The famous Prime Number   stract theories; it is evident in the natural   role in shaping the technological innova-
           Theorem describes the distribution of   world all around us. From the spirals of   tions of our time. Every algorithm used
           primes and gives insight into how they   a sunflower to the branching of trees,   in computers, every encryption method
           become less frequent as numbers grow   math reveals itself in the patterns of na-  safeguarding our digital communica-
           larger. Despite their seeming simplicity,   ture. The Fibonacci sequence, for exam-  tions, and every machine learning model
           primes are like the "building blocks" of   ple, is a series of numbers where each   that powers artificial intelligence is
           all numbers, as any integer can be   number is the sum of the two preceding   based on mathematical principles. The
           uniquely factored into a product of   ones (starting with 0 and 1). This   field of cryptography, which involves
           primes, a concept known as the Funda-  sequence can be seen in the arrangement   the study of codes and ciphers, relies
           mental Theorem of Arithmetic.   of petals on flowers, the pattern of   heavily on number theory, particularly
             One of the most fascinating aspects   leaves on a stem, and even the arrange-  the properties of prime numbers, to se-
           of prime numbers is their unpredictabil-  ment of galaxies in space.   cure data transmission in our increas-
           ity. While mathematicians have been   These patterns, known as fractals, are   ingly digital world.
           able to identify larger and larger primes,   characterized by their self-similarity,   Moreover, advancements in artificial
           the search for the next prime is still an   meaning they look similar at any scale.   intelligence and machine learning are
           unsolved problem. The largest known   Fractals are not only beautiful but also   made possible by the mathematical tools
           prime number, discovered in 2018, has   serve as models for real-world phenom-  of calculus, linear algebra, and probabil-
           over 24 million digits, but mathemati-  ena, such as the structure of coastlines,   ity theory. These technologies, which
           cians are still unsure if there is a pattern   mountain ranges, and clouds. The study   have revolutionized industries from
           to prime numbers or if they appear ran-  of fractals has led to breakthroughs in   healthcare to finance, are built on the
                                                                           foundation of math.
                                                                              The beauty of mathematics is not just
                                                                           in its applications but in the sense of
                                                                           wonder it evokes. Whether it's the ele-
                                                                           gance of prime numbers, the harmony of
                                                                           geometry, or the endless mysteries of in-
                                                                           finity, mathematics captivates the imagi-
                                                                           nation. Mathematics Day serves as an
         Visualization of prime numbers                                    contributions of legendary mathemati-
                                                                           opportunity to appreciate not only the
                                                                           cians like Srinivasa Ramanujan but also
                                                                           the profound role that math plays in our
                                                                           lives. As we continue to uncover the
                                                                           mysteries of the universe, mathematics
                                                                           will remain our guide, revealing new
                                                                           wonders and inspiring future genera-
                                                                           tions to explore its boundless magic. ■

           12                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[INSIGHT
























                                                                           like "One Book, One City" aren’t just
                                                                           about reading a single book, they’re
                                                                           about building a sense of community
           Why books                                                       and sparking intellectual conversations.
                                                                           Compare this to the fleeting nature of
                                                                           online information, where even signifi-
                                                                           cant insights are lost in an endless sea of
           outshine screens                                                Enrich your words, enrich your
                                                                           updates.


                                                                           world
                                                                              Ever struggled to find the right words
                                                                           to express yourself? Reading is your an-
           In an era where fleeting notifications dominate and             swer. Each book you read introduces

           misinformation spreads unchecked, books remain bastions         you to a world of vocabulary and ex-
                                                                           pressions. Personally, I’ve found myself
           of enduring wisdom and authenticity. By Shahid A. Siddiqui*     incorporating phrases I’ve picked up
                                                                           from novels, making conversations more
                                                                           meaningful and engaging. Unlike social
                                                                           media, where communication often feels
             n today’s digital age, where scrolling                        truncated, books nurture your ability to
             through social media feeds often                              articulate and connect deeply.
           Ifeels like second nature, the joy of
           reading a book has become something                             Exercise for your mind
           of a lost art. But as someone who’s spent                          Reading is like a gym session for
           countless hours discovering the magic                           your brain. Imagine the mental workout
           hidden between the pages of a novel or                          involved in remembering plots, char-
           the wisdom locked in a historical ac-                           acters, or arguments presented in non-
           count, I can assure you: books have a                           fiction. Scientific studies suggest that
           value that no digital platform can rep-                         engaging with books strengthens cogni-
           licate.                                                         tive functions and keeps your memory
             Let me take you on a journey to re-                           sharp. I’ve seen this firsthand in older
           discover why reading should be an es-                           relatives who’ve made reading a daily
           sential part of your life.                                      habit, they seem sharper and more artic-
                                                                           ulate than many younger folks glued to
           A treasure trove of knowledge                                   screens.
             Books are like time machines, they
           take us to the past, illuminate the pres-                       Finding solace in stories
           ent, and inspire the future. I recall visit-                       When was the last time you truly es-
           ing Toronto’s public libraries, marveling                       caped the chaos of daily life? For me, it
           at their extensive collections. Programs                        happens every time I open a book.

           14                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Whether it’s a gripping mystery or a   iety that often accompanies excessive   recent travels to Europe, I noticed
           heartfelt memoir, books offer an escape   screen time.          people engrossed in books on public
           that’s far more fulfilling than doom                            transport, fully absorbed in their stories.
           scrolling through endless news updates.   The battle for focus   It was a refreshing sight, a reminder of
           Libraries in North America, like Chi-  We live in a world of distractions,   how books teach us to be present.
           cago’s public spaces, have created   notifications, buzzing phones, and end-
           reading zones where people find com-  less streams of content. Reading de-  Building bridges through
           fort in books, a stark contrast to the anx-  mands and nurtures focus. During my   empathy
                                                                              Have you ever cried for a fictional
                                                                           character or cheered for their victory?
                                                                           Books have a way of pulling us into
                                                                           others’ lives, teaching us empathy in
                                                                           ways no social media post can. Pro-
                                                                           grams like Boston’s community book
                                                                           clubs bring diverse groups together,
                                                                           fostering understanding through shared
         A scholar with books in the library                               misuse of social media often stirs divi-
                                                                           reading experiences. It’s something we
                                                                           could use more of in India, where the
                                                                           sion rather than unity.

                                                                           Creativity’s best friend
                                                                              Ideas breed ideas, and books are fer-
                                                                           tile ground for creativity. Reading
                                                                           sparks your imagination, inspiring you
                                                                           to think differently. I’ve had some of
                                                                           my best ideas after reading something
                                                                           provocative or enlightening. Contrast
                                                                           this with social media’s tendency to
                                                                           present recycled trends, books always
                                                                           offer something fresh.

                                                                           A good night’s sleep
                                                                              Ever swapped scrolling on your
                                                                           phone for a chapter of a good book be-
                                                                           fore bed? The difference is remarkable.
                                                                           Reading calms the mind, helping you
         A scene from the library                                          cantly impact your well-being.
                                                                           wind down and prepare for restful
                                                                           sleep. It’s a small habit that can signifi-


                                                                           The social media dilemma
                                                                              Platforms like TikTok and Instagram
                                                                           have undeniably changed the way we
                                                                           discover books, with trends like #Book-










         A young woman enjoying a book                                                                     A cozy reading nook













           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Tok introducing new audiences to   books, is an antidote to this phenome-  understanding. The Quran, in Surah Al-
           reading. But there’s a flip side. These   non.                  Kahf, offers timeless wisdom: verify
           platforms often emphasize popularity                            information before sharing it. This prin-
           over substance. In India, we’ve seen   Information vs. Knowledge   ciple is more relevant than ever. Shar-
           how misinformation spreads like wild-  Here’s a thought: not all information   ing unchecked information on social
           fire, creating chaos and division. Veri-  is knowledge. In today’s world, it’s   media can lead to harm, while books,
           fied knowledge, like that found in   easy to consume data and mistake it for   with their rigorously researched
                                                                           content, remain trustworthy compan-
                                                                           ions in our quest for truth.

                                                                           A parting thought
                                                                              In an era where fleeting notifications
                                                                           dominate and misinformation spreads
         A girl reading a book on a park bench                             Unlike the shallow dives of social
                                                                           unchecked, books remain bastions of
                                                                           enduring wisdom and authenticity.
                                                                           They don’t just inform, they transform.
                                                                           media, books offer depth, reflection,
                                                                           and clarity. They cultivate empathy, ig-
                                                                           nite creativity, and foster true knowl-
                                                                           edge. During my travels to Canada and
                                                                           Europe, I marveled at bustling libraries,
                                                                           testaments to the irreplaceable value of
                                                                           books in a fast-paced world. India, ho-
                                                                           wever, faces a cultural shift: social
                                                                           media, with its unverified content and
                                                                           divisive narratives, often overshadows
                                                                           the enriching power of books. It’s time
                                                                           to rekindle our love for reading, nurtur-
                                                                           ing a society that values truth and un-
         A variety of books at a stall in an exhibition                    reader lives a thousand lives before
                                                                           derstanding over fleeting trends. As
                                                                           George R.R. Martin aptly said, "A
                                                                           they die; the person who doesn’t read
                                                                           lives only one." So pick up a book
                                                                           today, the next chapter of your life
                                                                           awaits in its pages. ■
                                                                              *The writer, an IRS (Retd.), crafted
                                                                           this article after his visit to Canada.












                                                                                                           A book lover searching for his preferred choice










         A lively book fair







           16                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH
































           Short Films


           From analog to






           digital






           The evolution of short films from analog to digital has
           been a fascinating journey, marked by technological

           advancements, changing storytelling techniques,
           and an ever-expanding audience. By Riya Verma


               hort films have always played an   filmmaking has not only transformed the   global film industry. The evolution of
               important role in the world of   way films are made but also how they   short films reflects a shift in cultural,
           Scinema. These compact, often ex-  are consumed, shaping the future of this   technological, and artistic trends, and it
           perimental films have captured the   beloved genre.             provides a fascinating glimpse into the
           imagination of filmmakers and au-  In recognition of the growing signifi-  history of cinema itself.
           diences alike, offering a unique form of   cance of short films, ‘National Short
           storytelling that differs from feature-  Film Day’ was introduced to celebrate   The early days: Analog filmmaking
           length films. From the early days of   the art form and encourage filmmakers   The story of short films begins in the
           cinema to the digital revolution, short   to experiment with new ideas. It serves   late 19th century, when film was first in-
           films have evolved significantly, both in   as a platform to recognize the creative   vented. Early cinema was predominantly
           terms of technology and artistic expres-  brilliance of short filmmakers and high-  analog, with film stock being the pri-
           sion. This journey from analog to digital   light the impact of short films on the   mary medium for recording and display-

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Filmmakers at work in the 20th century                                                            Vintage celluloid film
















           ing moving images. The first short films
           were made on film reels that were hand-
           cranked and projected using mechanical
           projectors. These films were typically
           short in length, often lasting only a few
           minutes. They were seen as novelties
           and were primarily presented as part of
           vaudeville shows or as standalone at-
           tractions at local theaters.
             Thomas Edison’s invention of the ki-
           netoscope in 1891 is often credited as
           the beginning of the short film era. The
           kinetoscope allowed a single viewer to                                                          Early cinema screening
           watch a short film through a peephole
           viewer, offering a glimpse into the po-
           tential of motion pictures. This early de-
           vice gave birth to short films as a me-
           dium of entertainment and storytelling,   The golden age: Analog innovation   that many filmmakers had to work
           though they were simple in content and   As the film industry developed   within tight budgets. This resulted in the
           often focused on everyday life or nov-  throughout the early 20th century, short   rise of independent filmmakers and un-
           elty acts.                      films gained more prominence, espe-  derground cinema. Directors such as
             The Lumière brothers in France took   cially in the context of educational   Stanley Kubrick and Martin Scorsese
           this concept further by inventing the   films, documentaries, and animated   began their careers making short films
           Cinématographe in 1895, which allowed   shorts. Disney, for example, revolution-  in the 1950s and 1960s, showcasing the
           films to be projected onto a screen for a   ized animation with its short films in the   potential of short-form storytelling and
           wider audience. Their short films, like   1920s and 1930s, producing ground-  the power of creativity in a constrained
           Workers Leaving the Lumière Factory   breaking work such as Steamboat Willie   format.
           and Arrival of a Train at La Ciotat, be-  (1928), which introduced the world to   During this golden age, film festivals
           came iconic examples of early cinema.   Mickey Mouse.           dedicated to short films also began to
           These short films were groundbreaking   Throughout the 1930s to 1950s, short   emerge. The Cannes Film Festival, for
           in their use of real-life events and were   films continued to flourish, often as an   instance, introduced its prestigious Short
           far ahead of their time in terms of cap-  essential part of a film program. They   Film Palme d'Or award in 1952, which
           turing motion in a way that had never   were regularly shown before feature   helped to elevate the status of short
           been seen before.               films in cinemas, with genres ranging   films and encourage emerging film-
             During the early 20th century, short   from newsreels to comedies, cartoons,   makers to pursue the format. Short
           films became a staple in theaters world-  and experimental art films. The Looney   films, though considered a secondary
           wide. They were often paired with fea-  Tunes series, for instance, became in-  form of filmmaking at the time, played a
           ture-length films to provide additional   credibly popular and influential during   key role in the creative growth of the
           entertainment. At this time, short films   this period, cementing short films as a   film industry, offering new ways of tell-
           were shot on 35mm film stock, and the   beloved form of entertainment.   ing stories outside of the commercial
           process of filmmaking involved several   In the analog era, short films were   filmmaking model.
           manual steps: from exposure to devel-  primarily created with 16mm and 35mm
           oping the film, followed by editing and   film stock, which offered good quality   The digital revolution: A new era of
           printing. This was a labor-intensive and   for both professional and amateur film-  filmmaking
           costly process, limiting the number of   makers. Filmmaking tools such as the   With the advent of digital technology
           filmmakers who could afford to create   film camera, editing equipment, and   in the 1990s, the world of filmmaking
           short films.                    projectors were expensive, which meant   experienced a major shift. The arrival of

           18                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[makers to experiment with new formats,
                                                                           such as interactive films or virtual real-
                                                                           ity experiences, further expanding the
                                                                           scope of what short films could achieve.
                                                                              Another significant shift in the digital
                                                                           era was the rise of digital film festivals
                                                                           and online platforms dedicated to short
                                                                           films. Many traditional film festivals
                                                                           now accept digital submissions, and
         Modern digital filmmaking                                         work into multiple festivals globally.
                                                                           platforms like FilmFreeway have made
                                                                           it easier for filmmakers to enter their

                                                                           Online streaming services such as Net-
                                                                           flix and Amazon Prime have even begun
                                                                           to showcase short films, offering a wider
                                                                           audience to this often overlooked genre.
                                                                           The present and future: Short films
                                                                           in the age of streaming
                                                                              Today, short films continue to
                                                                           evolve with advancements in technol-
                                                                           ogy, social media, and digital distribu-
                                                                           tion. The growing popularity of stream-
                                                                           ing platforms has provided short
                                                                           filmmakers with a new way to reach
                                                                           viewers. Services like YouTube and
                                                                           Vimeo remain popular for showcasing
                                                                           independent short films, while larger
                                                                           streaming giants are increasingly in-
                                                                           cluding short film content in their li-
         Outdoor film shoot                                                gained significant recognition on plat-
                                                                           braries. In fact, many short films have
                                                                           forms like YouTube, where millions of
                                                                           people tune in to watch.
                                                                              The future of short films appears to

                                                                           development of digital technology. With
                                           could now shoot and edit their films on   be inextricably linked to the continued
                                           computers using digital software. This   advancements in 4K and 8K resolution,
                                           change had a profound impact on the   virtual reality, and AI-powered film-
                                           creation of short films, as the cost of   making tools, short films are becoming
                                           producing high-quality films signifi-  more immersive and accessible. Film-
                                           cantly decreased.               makers now have access to a broad
                                             The digital revolution opened the   array of tools that were previously un-
                                           door for a new generation of filmmakers   imaginable, allowing them to push cre-
                                           to experiment with storytelling tech-  ative boundaries and engage with au-
                                           niques and genres that had previously   diences in entirely new ways.
                                           been inaccessible. Filmmakers could   The evolution of short films from
                                           now create professional-quality short   analog to digital has been a fascinating
         A modern digital camera in use    of the internet. Websites like YouTube,   niques, and an ever-expanding au-
                                           films with relatively low budgets, and
                                                                           journey, marked by technological ad-
                                           distribution became easier with the rise
                                                                           vancements, changing storytelling tech-
                                           Vimeo, and later social media platforms
                                                                           dience.
                                                                              As we celebrate National Short Film
                                           like Instagram and TikTok, offered a
                                                                           Day, it’s important to reflect on how far
                                           global stage for short films to be seen
                                           and shared by audiences worldwide.
                                                                           the medium has come and the exciting
                                             Digital technology also brought new
                                           possibilities for animation, special ef-
                                                                           Whether it's a touching drama, an ex-
                                           fects, and post-production work. Tools   possibilities it holds for the future.
                                                                           perimental piece, or an animated short,
           digital video (DV) cameras in the late   like Adobe Premiere Pro, Final Cut Pro,   short films remain a vital and essential
           1990s made filmmaking more accessible   and After Effects allowed filmmakers to   part of the cinematic landscape, offer-
           and affordable. Independent filmmakers   add sophisticated editing, sound design,   ing a platform for filmmakers to ex-
           no longer had to rely on expensive film   and visual effects to their films. The dig-  press their creativity and connect with
           stock or manual editing equipment; they   ital medium also made it easier for film-  audiences on a personal level. ■
           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT









































           Height doesn’t







           measure greatness







           It’s a reminder that the true measure of a person lies not in their physical stature but

           in their ability to inspire, lead, and create positive change. By Aarav Sharma



             n a world where physical appearance   celebrate the qualities that truly define a   termination, and skill far outweigh phys-
             often shapes first impressions, it is   person.               ical attributes when it comes to defining
           Ieasy to overlook the traits that truly   On National Short Person Day, ob-  a person's potential and value.
           matter—abilities, talent, and character.   served on December 22, we are re-
           While height may play a role in percep-  minded of the importance of looking   Breaking the chains of stereotypes
           tions and stereotypes, it is neither a limi-  beyond superficial traits like height.   Throughout history, societal norms
           tation nor a measure of a person’s worth.   This day recognizes individuals who   have attached stereotypes to physical
           Society’s undue emphasis on physical   might be considered shorter than aver-  features, including height. Taller indi-
           attributes has marginalized many, par-  age but stand tall in their achievements   viduals are frequently associated with
           ticularly those of shorter stature. Ho-  and contributions to society. It serves as   leadership, dominance, and competence,
           wever, it’s time to shift the focus and   a powerful reminder that character, de-  while shorter people may face assump-

           20                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Chandra Bahadur Dangi, the shortest living Nepali man




                                                                                                           Jyoti Amge (Nagpur, India), just 2 feet tall

















                                                                           narrative that height determines capabil-
                                                                           ity, emphasizing that success is defined
                                                                           by passion, talent, and hard work.
         Afshin Ghaderzadeh, the shortest living man (Iran)                the arts, sciences, sports, or leadership,
                                                                           The power of talent
                                                                              Talent knows no bounds. Whether in

                                                                           talent is the ultimate equalizer. It tran-
                                                                           scends barriers of physical appearance,
                                                                           allowing individuals to shine in their
                                                                           chosen fields.
                                                                              Consider the story of Ludwig van
                                                                           Beethoven, one of the most renowned
                                                                           composers in history. Standing at ap-
                                                                           proximately 5’4”, Beethoven didn’t let
                                                                           his height—or even his eventual loss of
                                                                           hearing—limit his creativity. His com-
                                                                           positions have stood the test of time, in-
                                                                           spiring generations.
           tions of inferiority or lesser capability.   Height is no barrier to greatness   In sports, Lionel Messi, standing at
           These biases, deeply ingrained in culture   History is filled with remarkable in-  5’7”, has proven that height is irrelevant
           and media, fail to account for individual   dividuals who have defied height-based   when it comes to sheer skill and deter-
           merit and achievements.         stereotypes to achieve greatness. These   mination. Despite being considered
             This societal bias often results in sys-  individuals not only excelled but also re-  shorter than most professional football
           temic disadvantages. In workplaces, for   shaped perceptions about the role of   players, Messi has become a legend in
           instance, studies have shown that taller   physical attributes in defining success.   the sport, celebrated for his agility, tech-
           candidates are perceived as more au-  Mahatma Gandhi, standing at 5’5”,   nique, and relentless pursuit of excel-
           thoritative or capable during interviews.   led India’s struggle for independence   lence.
           These perceptions exist even when   and became a global symbol of peace   These stories underscore a universal
           shorter candidates have equal or greater   and non-violence. Similarly, Simone   truth: talent, coupled with perseverance,
           qualifications. Such biases seep into   Biles, an Olympic gymnast who stands   transcends all barriers. Height, or any
           areas like politics, where taller candi-  at 4’8”, is celebrated as one of the great-  other physical attribute, is never an im-
           dates often enjoy an unspoken advan-  est athletes of all time. Her achieve-  pediment to achieving greatness.
           tage in elections, or in social situations,   ments underscore the fact that physical
           where height can influence first impres-  stature is no hindrance to excelling in   Character: The true measure of a
           sions and confidence levels.    fields requiring incredible skill and dis-  person
             Addressing these stereotypes in-  cipline.                       While talent is essential, character re-
           volves unlearning societal prejudices   Actors like Danny DeVito have   mains the ultimate measure of an indi-
           and consciously focusing on intrinsic   proved that charm and talent can break   vidual. Empathy, resilience, honesty, and
           qualities like intelligence, kindness, and   through the barriers of stereotypes. De-  a strong moral compass define a person
           perseverance. It’s crucial to move past   spite standing at 4’10”, DeVito has had   far more than their physical traits ever
           these outdated measures of worth and   a long and illustrious career, bringing   could. Unlike height, which is an inher-
           embrace a more inclusive and equitable   joy to millions through his perform-  ited trait, character is cultivated through
           worldview.                      ances. These examples challenge the   life experiences, decisions, and the abil-

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Well-known Hollywood stars











           ity to overcome challenges.     appearance.                                                     Women of different heights
             Shorter individuals often develop re-  Parents, educators, and mentors have
           silience and adaptability, traits honed   a responsibility to instill confidence in
           through navigating a world that some-  young minds. Encouraging children to
           times marginalizes them. These qual-  pursue their passions, celebrate their tal-
           ities, combined with their inner strength,   ents, and remain resilient in the face of   building stronger teams. Organizations
           make them exceptional leaders, innova-  challenges helps build a foundation of   that prioritize inclusivity not only bene-
           tors, and role models. For example,   self-worth that is immune to societal   fit from diverse ideas but also set an ex-
           James Madison, the fourth President of   judgments. By fostering inclusivity and   ample for others, promoting fairness and
           the United States, stood at 5’4” but is re-  teaching empathy, we can ensure that fu-  equality in society.
           membered for his pivotal role in drafting   ture generations judge themselves and
           the U.S. Constitution and the Bill of   others by character, not by height.   A call to action
           Rights. His intellectual contributions far                         As we celebrate National Short Per-
           outweighed any biases regarding his   Celebrating strength in diversity   son Day, let us commit to breaking
           stature.                          National Short Person Day reminds   down the barriers of stereotypes and fos-
                                           us to reflect on the diverse paths individ-  tering a culture of inclusivity. Whether
           Representation matters          uals take to success. By shifting the   through individual actions, workplace
             Representation is a powerful tool for   focus from height to abilities and   policies, or societal campaigns, every ef-
           changing societal attitudes and dismant-  achievements, we celebrate the resil-  fort counts in creating a world where
           ling stereotypes. When individuals of di-  ience, determination, and talents of   people are valued for their abilities,
           verse statures are celebrated for their ac-  people who prove that physical traits are   character, and contributions.
           complishments, it challenges long-held   inconsequential in the grand scheme of   This day challenges us to redefine the
           biases and inspires others to embrace   life.                   metrics of success and worth. Instead of
           their unique qualities.           This day also highlights the need to   measuring greatness in inches, let us
             The media plays a crucial role in   recognize the strength found in diversity.   measure it in impact, kindness, and re-
           shaping perceptions. Films, television,   Just as diversity in ethnicity, gender, and   silience. Height may shape appearances,
           and literature can promote inclusivity by   culture enriches societies, so too does   but it does not define the boundless po-
           featuring shorter individuals in leading   the inclusion of individuals of all physi-  tential within each individual.
           roles, highlighting their successes, and   cal statures. Every person, regardless of   The essence of National Short Person
           portraying them as dynamic and capable   height, contributes a unique perspective   Day lies in celebrating the strength,
           characters. Campaigns advocating for   and set of experiences that enhance our   achievements, and individuality of
           body positivity and self-acceptance are   collective understanding.   people who demonstrate that height has
           also instrumental in creating a culture                         no bearing on one’s ability to make a
           that values individuals for who they are   Height diversity in the workplace   difference. It’s a reminder that the true
           rather than how they look.        Workplace environments should pri-  measure of a person lies not in their
                                           oritize inclusivity and equity, ensuring   physical stature but in their ability to in-
           Lessons for the next generation   that talent and ability take precedence   spire, lead, and create positive change.
             National Short Person Day is not   over physical traits. Employers who   So, let us stand together in celebrat-
           only about acknowledging the struggles   value skills over appearance create   ing every individual for who they are,
           and triumphs of shorter individuals but   spaces where all employees can thrive,   honoring their unique qualities, and en-
           also about empowering future genera-  irrespective of their height.   suring that no one is judged by super-
           tions to embrace their individuality. It’s   Shorter individuals often bring   ficial measures. After all, greatness isn’t
           an opportunity to teach children that   unique perspectives shaped by their ex-  measured by how tall we stand—it’s de-
           their worth is defined by their actions,   periences. These insights can lead to in-  fined by how high we aim and the last-
           choices, and values—not their physical   novative solutions and contribute to   ing impact we leave on the world. ■

           22                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Jitender Singh Vihan                                            Johri, Jitender’s talent began to flourish.
                                                                           “He taught me like his own child,” Ji-
                                                                           tender shares, his voice filled with grat-
                                                                           itude.
           The height of                                                   Gratitude to his pillars of strength   PROFILE

                                                                              Jitender attributes his success to the
                                                                           selflessness and guidance of key indi-
                                                                           viduals in his life. His elder sister, Usha
                                                                           Singh, a dear friend, Manoj Kumar, and
           talent                                                          played an instrumental role. It was Mr.
                                                                           his first guru, Radhe Lal Sharma, each
                                                                           Sharma who took the then 11-year-old
                                                                           Jitender to school for the first time,
                                                                           shielding him from the ridicule of others
                                                                           and instilling a sense of self-worth.
           Jitender Singh Vihaan’s life is a symphony that celebrates      A unique perspective on life
                                                                              When asked about challenges he
           resilience, gratitude, and passion. His unwavering belief in    faced due to his short height, Jitender
                                                                           radiates positivity. “I never saw my
           himself and his love for music have made him a source of        height as a weakness. God made me
                                                                           special because I am special,” he says
           inspiration for many. By Staff writer                           with a smile. “People spend crores to
                                                                           stand out, but I was born unique. If I
                                                                           meet God, I’ll thank Him for this gift
             n the serene village of Sivaya, nes-  took up a job in a foam mattress com-  and ask to live my life with the same
             tled in Meerut district of Uttar Pra-  pany, which allowed him to fund his   short height again.”
           Idesh, lives a man whose story   dream. Under the mentorship of the re-  Jitender’s perspective is as uplifting
           strikes a chord of inspiration and deter-  nowned musician and composer Rakesh   as his music. “A man works with his
           mination. Jitender Singh Vihan, standing
           at 4 feet 3 inches, may be modest in
           height but towers in spirit. At 49, he is
           not only a successful music teacher but
           a beacon of hope for those who dare to
           dream beyond limitations. His life is a
           melody of perseverance, woven with the
           threads of passion, resilience, and love
           for music.
             As Jitender recalls his childhood, his
           eyes light up with the memory of a fair
           where he first saw a man playing the Ek
           Tara, a simple string instrument. That
           moment sparked an unquenchable thirst
           for music in the young boy. With his
           modest savings, he bought an Ek Tara
           for Rs. 2.50, and though he didn’t know
           how to play it, the spark of curiosity and
           passion had been ignited.

           A mother's support amidst
           challenges
             Born to a farmer, Mr Vishambar
           Singh, Jitender faced initial resistance to
           his passion. His father’s disapproval
           threatened to extinguish his dreams, but
           his mother, Mrs Satyavati, became his
           unwavering pillar of support. Her quiet                                                         Jitender Singh Vihan, music coach
           encouragement helped Jitender keep the
           flame of music alive in his heart, even
           when external circumstances seemed
           discouraging.
             After completing his BA, Jitender

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Jitender with his students in coaching















           mind, not his body. If the mind is strong,   estimate him due to his height, Jitender
           anything is possible,” he asserts.   responds with humility and wit. “No   Highlights:
                                           matter how tall people are, they talk to
           Teaching with passion and       me with their eyes lowered, and I ad-  Early Passion for Music: Jiten-
           empathy                         dress them with my eyes raised. Isn’t   dra’s love for music began in child-
             For the past 12 years, Jitender has   that wonderful?”         hood after seeing a musician play the
           been running a successful music coach-                           ‘Ek Tara’ at a fair.
           ing center, teaching instruments like the   A vision rooted in generosity   Overcoming Family Resistance:
           harmonium, keyboard, guitar, dholak,   Looking ahead, Jitender dreams of   Despite his father’s disapproval, his
           and his favorite, the mandolin. His   providing free music education to un-  mother’s encouragement kept his
           teaching style is distinct, he considers   derprivileged children. “Music is a part   passion alive.
           himself a classmate rather than a guru to   of nature and will remain eternal. I want   Mentorship: Learned music
           his students. This camaraderie fosters a   to dedicate my entire life to spreading   under the guidance of renowned mu-
           comfortable and enthusiastic learning   its joy,” he says with conviction.   sician and mentor Sri Rakesh Johri.
           environment.                                                        Unique Perspective on Height:
             One of the most heart-warming mo-  The crescendo of an inspiring life   Views his short stature as a blessing,
           ments of his career was teaching a 96-  Jitender Singh Vihaan’s life is a sym-  embracing his uniqueness with grat-
           year-old retiree from Modi Tyre Factory.   phony that celebrates resilience, grat-  itude.
           “His hands trembled, and his legs   itude, and passion. His unwavering be-  Teaching Career: Has been
           shook, but his passion for music was un-  lief in himself and his love for music   teaching music for over 12 years, of-
           shaken. He didn’t want to waste a single   have made him a source of inspiration   fering lessons in instruments like the
           moment of his remaining life without   for many. As he continues to teach and   harmonium, keyboard, guitar, dholak,
           learning music,” Jitender recalls with   uplift others through his music, Jitender   and mandolin.
           admiration.                     reminds us that true greatness is meas-  Inclusive Teaching Style: Treats
                                           ured not by physical stature but by the   students as classmates to foster a
           Defying stereotypes with grace   depth of one’s spirit and the harmony   comfortable learning environment.
             When faced with those who under-  they bring to the world. ■      Unforgettable Student: A 96-
                                                                            year-old man with a deep passion for
                                                                            music remains one of his most mem-
                                                                            orable students.
                                                                               Positive Mindset: Believes chal-
                                                                            lenges are opportunities to shine,
         Jitender playing his favorite mandolin                             vide free music education to under-
                                                                            demonstrating resilience and opti-
                                                                            mism.
                                                                               Future Aspirations: Aims to pro-

                                                                            privileged individuals and continue
                                                                            spreading the joy of music.
                                                                               Life Philosophy: Strongly be-
                                                                            lieves in using one’s mind and pas-
                                                                            sion to overcome physical limita-
                                                                            tions.


           24                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[SPECIAL FEATURE














































           A Global Festive Journey



           Christmas around






           the world






           Christmas is a celebration that transcends borders, uniting people from all walks of life.
           Whether through grand feasts, religious observances, or festive customs, the holiday is a

           testament to the shared values of love, kindness, and community. By Pooja Mehta

                hristmas is a time of joy, reflec-  people from every corner of the globe   The birth of Christmas traditions
                tion, and togetherness. While it   come together to share in the spirit of   The history of Christmas as we know
           Coriginated as a Christian holiday   love, generosity, and community. From   it today blends both religious and secu-
           to commemorate the birth of Jesus   the snowy streets of Europe to the sun-  lar influences. The story of Christmas,
           Christ, over centuries, it has become a   soaked beaches of Australia, Christmas   centered around the birth of Jesus in
           global celebration observed in various   is celebrated with vibrant customs, local   Bethlehem, has been passed down
           forms across cultures, each with its own   delicacies, and family-oriented activities   through generations. The Christmas tree,
           unique set of traditions and practices.   that bring people closer regardless of   one of the most iconic symbols, dates
           On Christmas Day, December 25th,   their backgrounds.           back to 16th-century Germany when

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[begins with the Advent period, marked
                                                                           by the lighting of candles on an Advent
                                                                           wreath. The German Christmas markets,
                                                                           or "Weihnachtsmärkte," are world-re-
                                                                           nowned for their festive atmosphere,
                                                                           where people gather to enjoy mulled
                                                                           wine, gingerbread cookies, and hand-
                                                                           crafted ornaments. The tradition of the
         Christmas carolers in Mexico                                      candles, stars, and glass baubles.
                                                                           Christmas tree also has its roots in Ger-
                                                                           many, where it is often decorated with
                                                                              In Scandinavia, Christmas is cele-
                                                                           brated with both religious and folkloric
                                                                           traditions. The Norwegian Christmas in-
                                                                           volves a visit from Julenissen, a Santa-
                                                                           like figure who delivers presents, while
                                                                           in Sweden, families celebrate St. Lucia’s
                                                                           Day on December 13th, honoring the
                                                                           patron saint of light with processions of
                                                                           young girls in white robes holding can-
                                                                           dles. The festive season is filled with
                                                                           warmth, with families enjoying meals
                                                                           such as ham, meatballs, and rice por-
                                                                           ridge, often with a touch of Scandina-
                                                                           vian delicacies like gingerbread and
                                                                           Swedish mulled wine, known as
                                                                           “glögg.”
                                                                              In the United Kingdom, Christmas
         Swedish St. Lucia Festival                                        cance. Christmas Eve is often marked by
                                                                           traditions also carry centuries of signifi-
                                                                           the lighting of candles and attending
                                                                           church services, and Boxing Day, the
                                                                           day after Christmas, is a time for charity,
                                                                           where people traditionally give gifts to
                                                                           the less fortunate. The Christmas Panto-
                                                                           mime, a form of musical comedy, is also
                                                                           a popular holiday tradition, with per-
                                                                           formances taking place across the UK.
                                                                           Christmas crackers, filled with small
                                                                           gifts, jokes, and paper crowns, are a sta-
         Vibrant Christmas market in Düsseldorf                            festivities and pop culture
                                                                           ple of the holiday meal, along with the
                                                                           quintessential Christmas pudding.
                                                                              North America: The influence of

                                                                              In the United States and Canada,
                                                                           Christmas is celebrated with a blend of
                                                                           religious observance and secular fun, in-
                                                                           fluenced by both European traditions
                                                                           and the country’s multicultural heritage.
                                                                           Santa Claus, a jolly, bearded figure who
                                                                           delivers presents to children on Christ-
                                                                           mas Eve, is a central part of the Ameri-
                                                                           can and Canadian holiday experience.
           Christians brought decorated trees into   ways that reflect both historical roots   The modern image of Santa was pop-
           their homes. The practice of gift-giving   and local cultural influences. From the   ularized by Clement Clarke Moore’s
           is also rooted in the story of the Three   Middle East to the Americas, Europe to   poem "A Visit from St. Nicholas", and
           Wise Men, who presented gifts to the in-  Asia, each country has added its unique   Coca-Cola’s advertising in the early
           fant Jesus. Over time, these traditions   flavor to the celebration, making it a   20th century. Families decorate their
           evolved and merged with various local   truly global occasion.   homes with elaborate lights and festive
           customs, creating the diverse ways in                           displays, and the tradition of sending
           which Christmas is celebrated today.   Europe: A blend of ancient   Christmas cards and gifts to loved ones
             In countries around the world, Christ-  customs and modern festivities   is widely practiced.
           mas brings communities together in   In Germany, the Christmas season   In Mexico, Christmas traditions are

           26                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[tians make up a smaller percentage of
                                                                           the population, the holiday is widely
                                                                           celebrated, especially in states like Goa,
                                                                           Kerala, and the northeastern regions.
                                                                           Churches are adorned with lights and
                                                                           flowers, and Midnight Mass on Christ-
                                                                           mas Eve is a cherished tradition. Fam-
                                                                           ilies decorate their homes with colorful
                                                                           lights, nativity scenes, and Christmas
                                                                           trees, often made from banana or mango
                                                                           trees. Traditional Indian sweets like kal-
                                                                           kals and rose cookies are prepared, and
                                                                           communities come together for feasts
         Christmas dinner                                                  and festivities. Street markets in cities
                                                                           such as Mumbai and Kolkata buzz with
                                                                           activity, offering Christmas decorations,
                                                                           gifts, and seasonal treats. Despite being

           vibrant and full of life, heavily in-                           a minority festival, Christmas in India
           fluenced by the country’s deep-rooted
           Catholic heritage. The Las Posadas pro-
           cession, which reenacts Mary and Jo-
           seph’s search for shelter, is a highlight
           of the holiday season. The procession
           moves from house to house, with partic-
           ipants singing carols, asking for shelter,
           and finally celebrating with food and
           festivities. Traditional dishes such as ta-
           males, bacalao (salted cod), and ponche
           (a warm fruit punch) fill the tables, and
           fireworks light up the sky. Piñatas, espe-
           cially in the shape of a star, are also a
           popular part of the celebration.                                                                Christmas Eve in Canada
           South America: A warm and joyous
           Christmas
             In Brazil, where Christmas occurs
           during the summer months, the holiday
           has a distinctly tropical feel. Celebra-
           tions often start with Missa de Galo
           (Midnight Mass), followed by a late-
           night feast of traditional Brazilian foods
           such as farofa, peru de natal (Christmas
           turkey), and panettone, a sweet bread
           filled with dried fruits. Families ex-
           change gifts, often around a beautifully
           decorated natal tree, and enjoy fireworks
           that light up the warm Christmas night.
           The holiday season also marks the start
           of a long summer vacation, which is a
           special time for families to travel, re-                                                        Christmas in South Africa
           unite, and enjoy the outdoors.
             In Argentina and Chile, where
           Christmas is also celebrated in the sum-
           mertime, the holiday festivities often
           center around family gatherings and   children leave their shoes out to be filled   embodies the spirit of unity and joy,
           large outdoor barbecues known as asa-  with gifts.              drawing people from all faiths to join in
           dos. Similar to Brazil, Christmas in                            the celebration.
           these countries combines Catholic tradi-  Asia: Blending new and old   In the Philippines, Christmas is one
           tions with festive outdoor meals, fire-  celebrations           of the longest and most celebrated holi-
           works, and music. Los Reyes Magos   In India, Christmas is a vibrant cele-  days in the world, with festivities start-
           (the Three Wise Men) are an important   bration that reflects the country’s diver-  ing as early as September. The country’s
           part of the Argentine Christmas story, as   sity and cultural richness. While Chris-  Simbang Gabi, or Christmas Eve Mass,

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[decades as a secular celebration. Fam-
                                                                           ilies often decorate their homes with
                                                                           Christmas lights, and a popular tradition
                                                                           is to have a Christmas dinner of fried
                                                                           chicken, with KFC becoming an iconic
                                                                           choice for many Japanese families on
                                                                           Christmas Eve. The emphasis on Christ-
                                                                           mas in Japan is more about sharing the
         Ethiopian Christmas celebration                                   religious observance, making it a unique
                                                                           joy of the season with loved ones than
                                                                           and vibrant celebration.
                                                                           Africa: A blend of tradition and
                                                                           religion
                                                                              In South Africa, Christmas occurs
                                                                           during the summer, making it a time for
                                                                           outdoor celebrations. The holiday is a
                                                                           mix of Christian and local traditions,
                                                                           with families attending church services
                                                                           before gathering for a festive meal of
                                                                           roast meats, braai (barbecue), and malva
                                                                           pudding. Many South Africans also
                                                                           enjoy outdoor activities like picnics and
                                                                           beach outings to celebrate Christmas
                                                                           Day. The bright summer sun and the
                                                                           warm African hospitality make Christ-
                                                                           mas in South Africa a lively and com-
                                                                           munal affair.
                                                                              In Ethiopia, where Christmas is
         Santa Lucia in Sweden                                             holiday is a deeply religious occasion.
                                                                           celebrated on January 7th according to
                                                                           the Orthodox Christian calendar, the

                                                                           Gena, as the holiday is called, is marked
                                                                           by church services, prayer, and fasting,
                                                                           followed by a feast of traditional dishes
                                                                           such as doro wat (spicy chicken stew)
                                                                           and injera (flatbread). Ethiopians dress
                                                                           in traditional white robes and celebrate
                                                                           with family and friends, reflecting the
                                                                           country’s rich Christian heritage.

                                                                           A global celebration
                                                                              Christmas is a celebration that tran-
                                                                           scends borders, uniting people from all
                                                                           walks of life. Whether through grand
                                                                           feasts, religious observances, or festive
         Family gathering at Christmas                                     community. No matter where in the
                                                                           customs, the holiday is a testament to
                                                                           the shared values of love, kindness, and
                                                                           world Christmas is celebrated, its mes-
                                                                           sage remains the same: the joy of giv-
                                                                           ing, the warmth of family, and the spirit
                                                                           of peace that brings people together.
                                                                              As we celebrate Christmas Day each

                                                                           beauty in the diversity of traditions that
                                                                           make this holiday so special. Whether
           is a deeply cherished tradition. Follow-  of Bethlehem. Caroling is also an inte-  year, it is essential to recognize the
           ing the Mass, families gather for a   gral part of the holiday, with groups of   it’s the snow-covered streets of Europe
           hearty meal of lechon (roast pig), bib-  people singing Christmas carols door-to-  or the summer warmth of Brazil, Christ-
           ingka (rice cake), and puto bumbong   door to raise money for charitable   mas is a global celebration that con-
           (purple rice cakes). The parol, a star-  causes.                tinues to unite people in joy, generosity,
           shaped lantern, is a beloved symbol of   In Japan, Christmas is not a public   and togetherness, reminding us of the
           Filipino Christmas, representing the Star   holiday but has been embraced in recent   true spirit of the season. ■

           28                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[IN-FOCUS


































           A Game for All                                                  international influence, and its ability to
                                                                           shape not just athletes, but communities
                                                                           as a whole. The very nature of the
                                                                           game—team-oriented, fast-paced, and
           How basketball                                                  people from different backgrounds come
                                                                           inclusive—has created a platform where
                                                                           together to share a common goal: to play
                                                                           and celebrate basketball.
           unites the world                                                A shared language across
                                                                           continents



           Basketball’s unifying power is a testament to the sport’s
           universal appeal. As it continues to grow and spread

           across borders, it becomes a beacon of hope,
           cooperation, and friendship among people from diverse
           backgrounds.  By Ishita Desai


                asketball, a sport born in the   beyond the court, as the sport acts as a
                United States, has transcended   cultural unifier, fostering connections
           Bits origins and grown into a   across borders, languages, and ethnic-
           global phenomenon. From its humble   ities.
           beginnings in the late 19th century, it   On World Basketball Day, a day ded-
           has captured the hearts and minds of   icated to celebrating the global impact
           millions worldwide. Played in urban   of this beloved sport, we reflect on how
           playgrounds, rural villages, and grand   basketball has become a powerful tool
           arenas alike, basketball’s universal ap-  for social cohesion, bringing together
           peal lies in its simplicity and ability to   people from all walks of life. It is on this
           bridge divides. Its influence extends far   day that we honor the sport’s history, its

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Girls playing basketball                                                                          Giannis Antetokounmpo









                                                                           temporarily set aside.
                                                                              In more recent years, basketball has
                                                                           continued to serve as a tool for inter-
                                                                           national diplomacy. The NBA’s global
                                                                           outreach initiatives and the NBA Global
                                                                           Games, where professional basketball
                                                                           teams travel worldwide to play exhi-
                                                                           bition matches, have introduced the
                                                                           sport to fans in countries where it was
                                                                           once relatively unknown. These events
                                                                           foster cultural exchange, as players and
         Women's basketball team                                           unite in their passion for the game.
                                                                           fans from different parts of the world
                                                                              Moreover, many NBA players use
                                                                           their global platform to speak out on so-
                                                                           cial issues and promote peace. Figures
                                                                           like LeBron James and Steph Curry,
                                                                           through their charitable work and activ-
                                                                           ism, not only contribute to their com-
             One of the most remarkable aspects   China, or Argentina—compete against   munities in the United States but also in-
           of basketball is its ability to break down   one another, yet the respect for the game   spire people globally. They highlight the
           linguistic and cultural barriers. Whether   and for each other remains constant.   unifying force of basketball, where ath-
           in the streets of New York, the parks of   This international exchange fosters   letes use their visibility and influence to
           Paris, or the courts of Cape Town, bas-  friendships, nurtures cultural awareness,   advocate for positive change, encourag-
           ketball speaks a universal language. The   and promotes understanding across bor-  ing individuals from different back-
           game’s rules are straightforward and can   ders.                grounds to unite for causes greater than
           be understood regardless of one’s native                        the game itself.
           tongue. Dribbling, passing, shooting,   Diplomacy through sports
           and defending are actions that need no   Basketball has also played an impor-  Empowering youth and building
           translation. These shared practices   tant role in diplomacy, particularly in   communities
           create an immediate sense of connection   bridging divides during times of con-  Perhaps one of basketball’s most sig-
           among players, whether they are com-  flict. One of the most iconic examples of   nificant impacts is on youth across the
           municating through words or gestures.   basketball serving as a diplomatic tool   globe. The sport provides opportunities
             In international tournaments, such as   occurred during the Cold War. In 1972,   for young people to engage in healthy,
           the FIBA World Cup and the Olympic   the United States and the Soviet Union   team-oriented activities that can help
           Games, basketball becomes a stage   faced off in the Munich Olympic Games   foster personal growth and development.
           where different cultures and nations   in a tense basketball final. Although the   It teaches discipline, teamwork, perse-
           come together to showcase their skills.   game itself was heated, the competition   verance, and leadership. For children
           The global nature of these events not   illustrated the ability of sports to serve   from diverse cultural backgrounds, bas-
           only emphasizes the sport’s widespread   as a peaceful arena for international en-  ketball can be a means of empowerment
           reach but also highlights the mutual re-  gagement. Both sides respected the   and self-expression. Whether in the
           spect and camaraderie that basketball   game’s integrity, and despite the politi-  slums of Nairobi or the suburbs of Los
           promotes. Countries from every con-  cal tensions, basketball provided a   Angeles, the sport offers an escape from
           tinent—be it the United States, Spain,   shared space where animosities could be   socio-economic hardships and gives

           30                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Street basketball culture









           youth the chance to rise above their cir-  continent. The rise of African talent in
           cumstances.                     the NBA is helping to reshape percep-
             Organizations like the Jr. NBA pro-  tions of the sport and foster even greater
           gram aim to teach young athletes not   interest in basketball at a grassroots
           only the fundamentals of basketball but   level across the continent.
           also important life lessons. By promot-  Asia, too, has seen basketball’s pop-
           ing basketball in underserved com-  ularity skyrocket, particularly in China,
           munities around the world, these initia-  where the sport is a cultural phenome-
           tives create positive environments where   non. The country has produced world-                 A woman playing basketball
           kids can form lifelong friendships, build   class basketball players like Yao Ming,
           confidence, and develop valuable skills   who has gone on to influence genera-
           both on and off the court. Through these   tions of young athletes in China. The
           programs, basketball serves as a tool for   NBA’s partnership with Chinese televi-
           social mobility, particularly in margin-  sion networks and digital platforms has   cludes the lifestyles and values that
           alized communities where resources   brought the game to millions of new   players represent.
           may be limited.                 fans in the region. As a result, basketball   The rise of streetball culture, where
             Furthermore, the sport’s inclusivity   has become one of the most-watched   players take the game to the streets and
           makes it particularly appealing to   sports in China, creating a unique fusion   playgrounds, has given basketball a re-
           women and girls, especially in societies   of American and Chinese culture   bellious, grassroots appeal. In many
           where access to physical activities may   through the love of the game.   urban areas, basketball courts are where
           be limited for gender-specific reasons.   In Latin America, countries such as   young people learn not just how to play
           Internationally, there has been a signifi-  Argentina, Brazil, and the Dominican   the game, but also how to express them-
           cant increase in the participation of   Republic boast rich basketball traditions.   selves creatively and socially. Through
           women in basketball, with countries   The sport is deeply embedded in the fab-  music, art, and fashion, basketball has
           such as the United States, Spain, Turkey,   ric of these nations, and their basketball   woven itself into the cultural fabric of
           and Australia investing heavily in   leagues have become integral parts of   cities around the world, turning it into a
           women’s basketball leagues. The em-  their local cultures. Latin American   global movement rather than just a
           powerment of female athletes helps to   players such as Manu Ginóbili and Car-  sport.
           challenge societal norms and promotes   los Boozer have helped to elevate the   Basketball’s unifying power is a tes-
           gender equality in the sporting world   sport’s profile, while also highlighting   tament to the sport’s universal appeal.
           and beyond. Women’s participation in   the diverse cultural influences that shape   As it continues to grow and spread ac-
           basketball also strengthens the sport’s   the way basketball is played and enjoyed   ross borders, it becomes a beacon of
           ability to unite cultures, as female ath-  in the region.       hope, cooperation, and friendship among
           letes represent their countries and their                       people from diverse backgrounds. On
           communities on the world stage.   The cultural impact of basketball   World Basketball Day, we celebrate
                                             Basketball’s influence extends far   more than just the game itself; we cele-
           Basketball’s global reach       beyond the court, infiltrating music,   brate the ways in which basketball
             As basketball spreads to new corners   fashion, and media. The sport has be-  brings people together, transcends differ-
           of the world, it continues to take on new   come a key part of global pop culture,   ences, and builds stronger, more inclu-
           cultural significance. In Africa, the sport   with NBA players often serving as   sive communities. From the professional
           has gained tremendous popularity, par-  trendsetters in fashion and style. The   level to streetball courts in small towns,
           ticularly in countries like Nigeria, Sene-  popularity of sneaker culture, where bas-  basketball’s ability to unite cultures and
           gal, and Angola. African players, such   ketball shoes become coveted commod-  promote peace continues to shape the
           as Giannis Antetokounmpo of Greece   ities, has further cemented the sport’s   world for the better. As long as the ball
           and Joel Embiid of the Philadelphia   place in modern society. The cultural ex-  bounces and the game is played, the
           76ers, have become international stars,   change through basketball goes beyond   spirit of unity that basketball fosters will
           bringing attention to basketball on the   what happens on the court—it also in-  continue to thrive across the globe. ■

           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                             December 16-31, 2024










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Aries, the year wraps up with a focus on        Libra, relationships thrive as you reconnect with
                     relationships. A heartfelt conversation around   loved ones. December 21 brings an opportunity
                     December 20 can bring clarity. Use the last days of   for meaningful conversations or mending old
                     December to plan your goals for 2025. Avoid     misunderstandings. Focus on creating balance
                     impulsive decisions during the festive season.   between social events and personal relaxation.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Taurus, the holiday season encourages rest and   Scorpio, the stars highlight transformation and
                     connection. Financial matters may require       renewal. Let go of past burdens and embrace
                     attention around December 22. Focus on practical   fresh beginnings around December 28. The New
                     decisions and cherish time with family and friends   Year sparks motivation to pursue long-term
                     to recharge your spirits.                       goals with determination.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Gemini, your social calendar is full as the year   Sagittarius, the holiday season brings joy and
                     winds down! December 18 is a great time for     spontaneity. A creative idea or project may
                     networking or strengthening bonds with loved    bloom around December 27. Use the final days
                     ones. Be mindful of overextending yourself, set   of the year to reflect on your achievements and
                     aside time to reflect on your personal growth.   set intentions for 2025.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Cancer, career advancements or creative projects   Capricorn, this is your time to shine! December
                     take center stage this month. Around December   23 brings career opportunities or recognition for
                     24, you may receive recognition for your efforts.   your efforts. Balance work with festive cheer
                     Spend the New Year’s Eve focusing on self-care   and take a moment to celebrate your accom-
                     and setting intentions for the year ahead.      plishments as the year closes.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, the last two weeks of December bring joy   Aquarius, the year ends with inspiration and
                     and excitement. Travel or a new adventure may   growth. December 25 highlights exciting oppor-
                     unfold around December 23. The New Year in-     tunities in learning or travel. Use the New Year’s
                     spires you to dream big, embrace the possibil-  energy to map out bold plans and step into 2025
                     ities and take bold steps toward your goals.    with confidence.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, reflect on your accomplishments as the   Pisces, December 29 brings emotional clarity
                     year ends. December 26 is perfect for organizing   and helps you leave behind any lingering doubts.
                     your finances or setting personal resolutions.   The holiday season encourages creativity and
                     Family and close relationships bring comfort and   bonding with loved ones. Use the New Year’s
                     joy during the festive season.                  Eve energy to envision a brighter path forward.


           32                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Tragic loss: Arrests in Bengaluru   tional values over the past decade.
           techie suicide case               Her calm yet assertive delivery res-
             The recent arrest of Nikita Singhania,   onated as she called for a nationwide   upheld regardless of celebrity status.
           her mother, and brother in connection with   caste census and highlighted the govern-  This incident serves as a crucial re-
           the tragic suicide of Bengaluru techie Atul   ment's failure to address rising violence   minder for event organizers and au-
           Subhash has sparked widespread outrage   and social injustice. Drawing parallels   thorities to prioritize safety measures to
           and concern. Atul's death, which he   with her grandfather, she underscored   prevent such tragedies in the future. Im-
           attributed to harassment and extortion by   the importance of accountability and   mediate action is essential to protect
           his estranged wife and her family, raises   urged the ruling party to reflect on its   lives and ensure that entertainment does
           serious questions about domestic violence   actions.            not come at such a high cost.
           and mental health support in our society.   Priyanka's articulate arguments not   Venkateswara Rao, Hyderabad, Te-
             In a heart-breaking 24-page suicide   only showcased her commitment to   langana, India
           note and an 80-minute video, Atul detailed   democratic principles but also re-
           the emotional turmoil he faced, including   affirmed the Congress party's stance on
           allegations of legal harassment and   safeguarding the Constitution. Her   A noble gift: Organ donation saves
           financial demands that ultimately   speech marks a promising start to her   lives
           overwhelmed him. The police have   parliamentary journey, echoing a legacy   The organ donation by Vishnu Pra-
           charged Nikita and her family with   of strong leadership.      sad, a brain-dead man, marks a mile-
           abetment to suicide, emphasizing the need   Sweta Sharma, Delhi, India   stone in Rajasthan's healthcare. His or-
           for accountability in such cases.                               gans were airlifted from Jhalawar to
             This incident highlights a critical need                      Jaipur and Jodhpur, saving six lives
           for systemic changes to protect   Allu Arjun's arrest: A wake-up call   through an extraordinary act of generos-
           individuals from domestic abuse and   for safety                ity.This first use of helicopters for organ
           ensure mental health resources are readily   The recent arrest of Telugu actor Allu   transplants showcases the potential for
           available. It is imperative that we address   Arjun in connection with a tragic stam-  swift action in critical cases.
           these issues to prevent further tragedies in   pede during the premiere of his film   Vishnu’s family showed immense
           our community.                  Pushpa 2: The Rule has raised signifi-  courage by donating his organs, turning
           Ravi Kant Singh, Delhi, India   cant concerns about crowd management   their grief into compassion. The success-
                                           at public events. The stampede, which   ful transplant emphasizes the life-saving
                                           resulted in the death of a 35-year-old   power of organ donation and inspires
           Priyanka Gandhi's maiden speech   woman and left her son critically in-  others to consider this noble act.
             Congress MP Priyanka Gandhi Vadra   jured, highlights the urgent need for   Such selflessness transforms loss into
           made a significant impact with her first   better safety protocols in large gath-  hope, proving the profound impact one
           speech in Parliament during the debate   erings.                individual can make. Promoting aware-
           on the Constitution. She passionately   Arjun was charged with culpable   ness about organ donation is vital to en-
           addressed key issues, emphasizing that   homicide not amounting to murder, re-  courage more families to follow their
           the Constitution serves as a protective   flecting the severity of the situation. Fol-  example and make a difference in count-
           shield for justice and unity. Priyanka   lowing his arrest, he was granted bail by   less lives.
           urged the BJP-led government to   the Telangana High Court, which em-  Krishan Kumar Gupta, Jaipur, Rajas-
           strengthen its commitment to constitu-  phasized that accountability must be   than, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           DECEMBER 16 2024 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!










































                                                                                      |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                      |
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024

                                                                                      |
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                              .in
                                                                              .in
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                .in
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                         OCT

                                                                                         |
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                          AUGUST




                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                        |
                                                                                        |
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 01 2024OBER 16 2023
           36
           3636
                                                                   wwwwww.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 01 202436
                                                                    www
                                                                    www
                                                                   www
           3636
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           36                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024OBER 01 2024
           36
           36
           36
           36
                                                                     www
                                                                            .in
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                            .in
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                             .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       www
                                                                     www
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>