<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents







                      VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 05  I  MARCH 01 2024       ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL




             15




                                                             5













                                                            10                                       25















           4-Editorial: Women's day rings with             15-The rise of green fashion

           inclusion                                       18-Facing the Silence

           5-The glamour of women's minds                  22-The hidden drawback of school
           8-“Behno aur Bhaiyo”                            uniforms

           10-Can We Finally Reverse Male Pattern          25-Essence of Vietnam

           Balding?                                        28-Horoscopes
           13-The velvet voice stilled                     29-Letters














           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Building Bridges
     EDITORIAL  Women's day rings                                                  Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           with inclusion                                                         Art & Culture Editor

                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                              s March unfolds, so does the      Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                              resonance of International Women's
                                        ADay, observed globally on March            Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        8th. This annual celebration is not merely a
                                        date on the calendar but a resounding call to   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        action, urging us to reflect on the strides   Sushil Kumar
                                        made and recommit to the ongoing pursuit
                                        of gender equality.                       Social Media Editor
                                           This year's theme, "Inspire Inclusion,"   Vishakha Sharma
                                        encapsulates the essence of our collective
                                        endeavor. It beckons us to not only     Art & Graphics Director
                                        recognize women's achievements but to        Vipin Agarwal
                                        actively break bias, challenge stereotypes,
                                        and foster an environment where every
           woman is empowered to thrive.
             International Women's Day is a testament to the transformative power of women   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           across various fields. From science and technology to politics and the arts, women
           have left an indelible mark, shaping societies and inspiring future generations.   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           However, amid celebration, we must confront the persistent challenges of gender-  Editor, United News of India, New
           based discrimination, pay inequities, and limited access to education.   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
             "Inspire Inclusion" calls for more than dismantling stereotypes; it encourages the   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           creation of inclusive spaces where diversity flourishes. This theme underscores the   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           importance of respecting and embracing the unique strengths and perspectives that   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           women bring to all facets of life, be it the workplace, laboratories, or communities.   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
             As we commemorate International Women's Day, let us stand united in our
           commitment to fostering environments that amplify women's voices and provide   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Er. Rifat
           pathways for their success. The theme beckons us to break biases at their roots,   Jamali (Architect)
           advocating for an end to gender-based discrimination and the promotion of diversity
           in its entirety.                                                        SUBSCRIPTIONS
             Celebrating International Women's Day is not only about acknowledging the
           achievements of women but also honoring the trailblazers who have paved the way   Phone +91 20 40199102
           for progress. From suffragettes fighting for voting rights to modern-day activists   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           advocating for equality, these women embody resilience and determination,   Baner Road,
           illustrating that change is possible.                               Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
             This International Women's Day, let's use "Inspire Inclusion" as a catalyst for   Email revoir@post.com
           tangible change. It is a day to amplify women's voices, recognize their achievements,   Website www.revoir.in
           and commit to creating a world where equality is not an aspiration but an undeniable
           reality. By breaking bias, we pave the way for a future where every woman can
           contribute, lead, and thrive without constraints.                        Legal Advisor
             In this pursuit of inclusion, we honor the incredible strength, intelligence, and   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           resilience of women globally. Let International Women's Day 2024 serve as a
           reminder that together, we can build a world that celebrates and uplifts the diversity   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           and potential of women in every sphere of life.                  all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



           Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL


































           Beyond Beauty




           The glamour of








           women's minds









             nternational Women's Day, a global                            search has consistently debunked this
             celebration observed annually on                              myth. While there may be subtle differ-
           IMarch 8th, is a momentous occasion                             ences in the size of certain brain struc-
           that transcends borders, cultures, and                          tures, these variances do not translate to
           ideologies. It serves as a platform to ac-                      variations in intelligence.
           knowledge and honor the achievements,
           contributions, and progress made by                             The human brain: Quality over
           women throughout history. This day is                           quantity
           not only a celebration of womanhood                                The human brain, a marvel of com-
           but also a call to action to address                            plexity and intricacy, is an organ whose
           gender disparities, challenge stereo-                           intellectual capabilities are not solely
           types, and foster an environment of in-                         determined by its weight. Although, on
           clusivity and equality.                                         average, the male brain may be larger,
                                                                           the emphasis should be on the quality
           Dispelling myths about brain    differences is the belief that the male   and efficiency of neural connections
           weight                          brain is larger and heavier than the fe-  rather than sheer size. Numerous studies
             One persistent misconception that   male brain, implying a correlation with   highlight that cognitive abilities and in-
           has permeated discussions on gender   intelligence. However, scientific re-  telligence are influenced by a combina-

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[tion of genetic, environmental, and
           socio-cultural factors, underscoring the
           fallacy of correlating intelligence with
           brain size.

           Historical biases and scientific
           clarifications
             Historically, the erroneous belief in
           the inferiority of the female intellect has
           perpetuated gender biases and inequal-
           ities. It is essential to confront and dis-
           pel such myths that have impeded
           women's progress and contributed to so-
           cietal stereotypes. Research indicates                                                          Female doctor breaking gender barriers
           that the brains of men and women ex-


             Famous

             women leaders                 hibit remarkable similarities in structure   woman to win a Nobel Prize and re-

                                           and function, debunking any notion of   mains an inspiration for her relentless
             and scientists                inherent intellectual disparities based on   pursuit of knowledge. Today, women
                                                                           like Jane Goodall, a renowned primatol-
                                           gender.
               1. Marie Curie (Poland/France)                              ogist, and Dr. Mae Jemison, the first Af-
             - Renowned physicist and chemist   Celebrating female achievements   rican-American woman astronaut, con-
             who conducted pioneering re-    International Women's Day stands as   tinue to break barriers, contributing to
             search on radioactivity and be-  a testament to the resilience, accom-  scientific progress and inspiring future
             came the first woman to win a   plishments, and potential of women   generations.
             Nobel Prize.                  worldwide. It is a day to celebrate the
               2. Indira Gandhi (India) - The   triumphs of women who have broken   Empowering women as
             first and only female Prime Minis-  barriers, defied expectations, and left an   inspirations
             ter of India, serving from 1966 to   indelible mark on society. Women   International Women's Day is not
             1977 and again from 1980 until   leaders, scientists, artists, activists, and   merely a retrospective celebration of ac-
             her assassination in 1984.    entrepreneurs have demonstrated time   complished women; it is also a platform
               3. Angela Merkel (Germany) -   and again that intelligence knows no   to inspire and empower future genera-
             Former Chancellor of Germany,   gender.                       tions. Malala Yousafzai, a Nobel laure-
             serving from 2005 to 2021. Mer-                               ate and advocate for girls' education, ex-
             kel is known for her leadership in   Inspiring women leaders   emplifies the power of courage and
             navigating through various global   In the realm of leadership, women   resilience in the face of adversity. Her
             crises and her contributions to Eu-  have risen to prominent positions, show-  unwavering commitment to education,
             ropean politics.              casing intelligence, resilience, and com-  even in the face of grave danger, high-
               4. Ada Lovelace (United King-  passion. Angela Merkel, the first female   lights the transformative impact that one
             dom) - Often considered the   Chancellor of Germany, exemplifies   individual, regardless of gender, can
             world's first computer pro-   strong and effective leadership. Her ten-  have on society.
             grammer, Lovelace worked with   ure has been marked by decisive ac-  Gitanjali Rao, a teenage inventor and
             Charles Babbage and made signif-  tions, principled governance, and an un-  TIME's Kid of the Year in 2020, repre-
             icant contributions to the devel-  wavering commitment to the well-being   sents the potential of young women to
             opment of the Analytical Engine.   of her nation. Similarly, Jacinda Ardern,   drive change and innovation. Her work
               5. Malala Yousafzai (Pakistan)   the Prime Minister of New Zealand, has   in developing solutions to address
             - A prominent advocate for girls'   garnered international acclaim for her   global issues, such as water contamina-
             education and the youngest recip-  empathetic and inclusive leadership   tion and opioid addiction, showcases the
             ient of the Nobel Peace Prize.   style, proving that women are equally   power of young minds in shaping the fu-
             Yousafzai survived an assassina-  capable of steering nations with wisdom   ture. By celebrating and amplifying the
             tion attempt and continues to fight   and strength.           achievements of these inspiring women,
             for educational equality.                                     we pave the way for a future where
               There are countless other re-  Trailblazing women in science   gender equality is not only a societal as-
             markable women leaders and      In the field of science, women have   piration but a lived reality.
             scientists from different countries   played pivotal roles in groundbreaking
             who have made significant con-  discoveries and advancements. Marie   Challenges and progress
             tributions to society in various do-  Curie, a pioneering physicist and chem-  While celebrating the accomplish-
             mains.                        ist, stands as an iconic figure in the sci-  ments of women, it is essential to ac-
                                           entific community. She was the first   knowledge that gender disparities persist

           6                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[A female leader






           in various aspects of life. Disparities in   ongoing, requiring collective efforts to   Education plays a pivotal role in
           pay, representation in leadership roles,   dismantle barriers and foster an environ-  challenging stereotypes, dismantling bi-
           and access to education are just a few   ment where every individual, regardless   ases, and fostering a culture of equality.
           examples of the challenges women con-  of gender, can thrive.   By promoting education that is inclusive
           tinue to face globally. International                           and devoid of gender-based prejudices,
           Women's Day serves as a reminder that   The role of education and   societies can nurture the talents and po-
           the journey towards gender equality is   awareness              tential of all individuals. Awareness
                                                                           campaigns and initiatives that highlight
                                                                           the achievements of women across di-
                                                                           verse fields contribute to changing per-
                                                                           ceptions and inspiring future genera-
                                                                           tions.
                                                                              In conclusion, International Women's
                                                                           Day is a powerful and significant occa-
                                                                           sion that goes beyond a mere celebra-
                                                                           tion of women. It is a global movement,
                                                                           a call to action, and a reminder of the
                                                                           collective responsibility to create a
                                                                           world where gender equality is not ne-
                                                                           gotiable. By dispelling myths about the
                                                                           female brain and celebrating the
                                                                           achievements of women in leadership,
                                                                           science, and inspiration, we contribute
                                                                           to a narrative that recognizes and appre-
                                                                           ciates the diverse talents and capacities
                                                                           of individuals, irrespective of gender. As
                                                                           we celebrate International Women's
                                                                           Day, let it be a catalyst for positive
                                                                           change, driving us toward a future
                                                                           where gender equality is not just an
         An entrepreneur who is female                                          GENDER EQUALITY IS
                                                                           ideal but a reality.




                                                                                NOT JUST AN IDEAL
                                                                                BUT A REALITY



           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                         7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[ENTERTAINMENT






































           Ameen Sayani's Legacy




          “Behno aur Bhaiyo”










                 n February 20, 2024, the world   The magic of Ameen Sayani's voice   Geetmala family.
                 bid farewell to a true icon of In-  Ameen Sayani's voice was un-  The influence of Binaca Geetmala
           Odian radio broadcasting, Ameen   doubtedly the heart and soul of Binaca   Binaca Geetmala played a pivotal
           Sayani. Over the years, Sayani had be-  Geetmala. With his unique intonation   role in shaping the Indian music indus-
           come synonymous with the immensely   and powerful yet soothing voice, he had   try. Apart from showcasing the most
           popular show "Binaca Geetmala" and   the ability to transport his listeners into a   popular songs of the time, the show also
           had captivated millions of listeners with   world filled with melodies and emo-  introduced new talent and promoted
           his velvety voice and impeccable style.   tions. Sayani's warm and friendly de-  emerging artists. Sayani's careful cura-
           Today, we pay tribute to Ameen Sayani   meanor ensured that he struck a chord   tion of the songs, his insightful com-
           and the remarkable legacy he leaves be-  with people of all ages, creating an inti-  mentary, and his deep knowledge of In-
           hind.                           mate connection with his audience.   dian music garnered immense respect
           The rise of Binaca Geetmala     The iconic catchphrase          from musicians and music enthusiasts
             In the 1950s, radio was the primary   No tribute to Ameen Sayani and Bi-  alike.
           source of entertainment in India, and   naca Geetmala would be complete with-  Binaca Geetmala's lasting impact
           Ameen Sayani saw the opportunity to   out mentioning the legendary catch-  Ameen Sayani's Binaca Geetmala
           create a platform that would showcase   phrase, "Behno aur Bhaiyo" (Sisters and   had a profound impact on the Indian
           the most popular Bollywood songs of   Brothers). Sayani's use of this endearing   music industry beyond simply promot-
           the time. Thus, "Binaca Geetmala" was   greeting at the start of every episode be-  ing popular songs. Let's delve into some
           born. The show quickly gained a mas-  came his trademark and endeared him to   of the ways this iconic radio show in-
           sive following, becoming the go-to des-  listeners even more. It brought a sense   fluenced and shaped the industry:
           tination for music lovers across the   of familiarity and unity, making every   Discovering New Talent: Binaca
           country.                        listener feel like a part of the Binaca   Geetmala served as a platform for dis-

           8                                                            www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[tributed to the preservation and appreci-
                                                                           ation of Indian film music history.
                                                                              Setting Trends and Influencing Taste:
                                                                           Binaca Geetmala had the power to make
         Ameen Sayani in a recording session                               the show influenced the taste of the In-
                                                                           or break songs in terms of popularity.
                                                                           With Ameen Sayani's astute curation,

                                                                           dian audience and shaped music trends.
                                                                           A song's inclusion in Binaca Geetmala
                                                                           often translated to its success and rec-
                                                                           ognition in the wider music industry.
                                                                              Engaging the Audience: Ameen Say-
                                                                           ani's magnetic personality and engaging
                                                                           style of hosting made Binaca Geetmala
                                                                           more than just a radio show. He con-
                                                                           nected with listeners on a personal level,
           covering and promoting emerging talent   place in the show, promoting a rich tap-  taking song requests, sharing stories,
           in the Indian music industry. Ameen   estry of languages, cultures, and musical   and providing insightful commentary on
           Sayani's keen ear for talent allowed him   styles. This helped bridge the gap be-  the music. This interaction fostered a
           to spot promising artists and introduce   tween different parts of India and fos-  sense of community and made listeners
           them to a wider audience. Many musi-  tered a sense of unity through music.   feel part of the Binaca Geetmala family.
           cians and singers owe their break-  Preserving Musical Heritage: Ameen   Motivating Musician-Listener Bond:
           throughs to the exposure they received   Sayani took pride in preserving the rich   Sayani's love for music and deep under-
           through the show.               heritage of Indian film music. His metic-  standing of the craft resonated with both
             Encouraging Regional Diversity: Bi-  ulous research and deep knowledge of   musicians and audiences. His genuine
           naca Geetmala played a significant role   the industry ensured that vintage songs   appreciation for the art form inspired
           in showcasing the diversity of Indian   from films of yesteryears were not for-  budding musicians and nurtured a strong
           music across different regions. Sayani   gotten. By featuring these timeless clas-  bond between artists and listeners.
           ensured that regional songs found a   sics on Binaca Geetmala, Sayani con-  Sayani's contribution to music
                                                                           preservation
                                                                              One of Ameen Sayani's remarkable
                                                                           contributions was his efforts in preserv-
                                                                           ing Indian film music. Through his me-
                                                                           ticulous research and extensive knowl-
                                                                           edge of the industry, he ensured that
                                                                           countless vintage songs were archived
                                                                           and cherished for future generations. His
                                                                           dedication to preserving the rich musical
                                                                           heritage of India will forever be remem-
                                                                           bered.
                                                                           A legacy that lives on
                                                                              Though Ameen Sayani may no
                                                                           longer be with us, his legacy will con-
                                                                           tinue to live on through the countless
                                                                           memories he created and the impact he
                                                                           had on the world of Indian music. Bi-
                                                                           naca Geetmala will forever be etched in
                                                                           the hearts of millions, and Sayani's in-
                                                                           fluence will continue to inspire future
                                                                           generations of broadcasters.
                                                                              Ameen Sayani's contribution to the
                                                                           Indian radio industry, particularly
                                                                           through his iconic show Binaca Geet-
                                                                           mala, will always be remembered as a
                                                                           monumental achievement. His marvel-
                                                                           ous voice, engaging style, and genuine
                                                                           connection with his audience left an in-
         Presenting a program                                              As we bid farewell to this legend, we
                                                                           delible mark on the hearts of millions.
                                                                           celebrate his life, his passion for music,
                                                                           and the joy he brought to the lives of so
                                                                           many. Behno aur Bhaiyo, Ameen Sayani


           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            will forever be cherished and missed.   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[MEDICAL TECHNOLOGY













































           Bidding Farewell to Baldness



           Can we reverse male







           pattern balding?







                  ale pattern balding, also   hope for a solution to this age-old prob-  ducing new hair, leading to baldness.
                  known as androgenetic alope-  lem.
           Mcia, is a common condition                                     Traditional treatments
           that affects a large number of men   Understanding male pattern    Historically, there have been various
           worldwide. It is characterized by pro-  balding                 methods for managing male pattern bald-
           gressive hair loss, typically starting at   Male pattern balding is primarily   ing, including medications, topical solu-
           the temples and crown of the head, and   caused by a combination of genetic and   tions, and hair transplant surgeries. Med-
           eventually leading to partial or complete   hormonal factors. The main culprit is a   ications like finasteride and minoxidil
           baldness. Over the years, extensive re-  hormone called dihydrotestosterone   have shown some effectiveness in slow-
           search has been conducted to find effec-  (DHT), which is derived from testoste-  ing down hair loss and promoting hair
           tive treatments for reversing male pattern   rone. DHT binds to hair follicles, caus-  growth, but they are not always success-
           balding. In this article, we will explore   ing them to shrink and produce thinner,   ful in restoring a full head of hair. Hair
           the current state of research and discuss   shorter hair strands. Eventually, the af-  transplants, on the other hand, involve
           the potential breakthroughs that offer   fected follicles become incapable of pro-  surgically moving hair follicles from one

           10                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[part of the body to the balding areas, but   to create an unlimited supply of hair fol-
           they can be expensive and may not al-  licles, providing a potentially permanent  Is baldness
           ways provide satisfactory results.   solution to balding.
                                                                            found in women?
           Recent advances                 Potential risks or side effects
             In recent years, there have been sig-  The new advancements in hair restor-  es, baldness can occur in
           nificant advancements in the field of hair   ation techniques, such as stem cell ther- Ywomen. While it is more com-
           restoration, offering hope for a more ef-  apy and gene therapy, are still in the ex-  monly associated with men, female
           fective and permanent solution to male   perimental stages and undergoing   pattern hair loss, also known as fe-
           pattern balding. Here are a few notable   clinical trials. While these techniques   male pattern baldness, is a condition
           breakthroughs:                  show promise, it is essential to consider   that affects women as well. It is esti-
             Stem Cell Therapy: Researchers are   the potential risks and side effects associ-  mated that around 40% of women ex-
           exploring the potential of using stem   ated with them. Here are some possible   perience some degree of hair loss by
           cells to regenerate hair follicles. Stem   considerations:       the age of 50.
           cells have the ability to differentiate into                       Female pattern hair loss typically
           various cell types, including hair follicle   Stem Cell Therapy   manifests as a gradual thinning of the
           cells. By injecting stem cells into the   Infection: Any medical procedure in-  hair, primarily on the top and crown
           scalp, scientists hope to stimulate the   volving injections or surgical interven-  of the scalp. Unlike male pattern
           growth of new hair follicles and reverse   tions carries a risk of infection. Sterile   baldness, which often results in com-
           balding.                        techniques and proper precautions   plete bald patches, female pattern hair
             Gene Therapy: Genetic research has   should be followed to minimize this risk.   loss tends to cause a more diffuse
           identified specific genes that play a role   Rejection or Allergic Reactions:   thinning of the hair.
           in male pattern balding. Gene therapy   There is a possibility of the body reject-  The exact cause of female pattern
           aims to modify these genes to prevent or   ing the stem cells or experiencing aller-  hair loss is not fully understood, but it
           reverse hair loss. By targeting the under-  gic reactions to the injected cells or ac-  is believed to involve a combination
           lying genetic factors, scientists believe   companying substances. Pre-screening   of genetic factors, hormonal changes
           they can address the root cause of bald-  and compatibility testing can help miti-  (such as fluctuations in estrogen and
           ing and restore hair growth.    gate these risks.                androgen levels), and aging. Other
             Platelet-Rich Plasma (PRP) Therapy:   Tumor Formation: As with any ther-  factors that can contribute to hair loss
           PRP therapy involves extracting a pa-  apy involving cell manipulation, there is   in women include certain medical
           tient's blood, separating the platelets, and   a theoretical risk of tumor formation or   conditions, hormonal imbalances,
           injecting the concentrated platelet-rich   uncontrolled cell growth. Rigorous   medications, stress, and hairstyling
           plasma into the scalp. Platelets contain   safety measures and careful monitoring   practices that put excessive tension
           growth factors that can stimulate hair fol-  are necessary to minimize this risk.   on the hair.
           licle activity and promote hair growth.                            If you are experiencing hair loss as
           While the effectiveness of PRP therapy is  Gene Therapy          a woman, it is advisable to consult
           still being studied, preliminary results   Immune Response: Gene therapy   with a dermatologist or a healthcare
           have shown promising outcomes.   involves modifying the genetic material   professional who specializes in hair
             Hair Cloning: Another exciting area   of cells, which can trigger an immune   disorders. They can evaluate your
           of research is hair cloning, which in-  response. This response may result in   specific situation, identify any under-
           volves multiplying hair follicle cells in a   inflammation or other adverse effects.   lying causes, and recommend appro-
           laboratory and then implanting them   Close monitoring and appropriate   priate treatment options or manage-
           back into the scalp. This approach aims   immune-suppressive measures may be   ment strategies to address the hair
                                                                            loss.

                                                                           required.
                                                                             Off-Target Effects: Gene therapy aims
                                                                           to modify specific genes, but there is a
                                                                           possibility of unintended modifications
                                                                           in other genes. This could potentially
                                                                           lead to unforeseen consequences or un-
                                                                           wanted side effects.
                                                                             Ethical Considerations: Gene therapy
                                                                           raises ethical concerns due to the poten-
                                                                           tial for altering inheritable traits. Thor-
                                                                           ough evaluation of the ethical implica-
                                                                           tions and adherence to strict guidelines
                                                                           are crucial.
         Stem Cell Therapy                                                 risks and side effects can vary depending
                                                                             It is important to note that the specific
                                                                           on the individual, the technique used, and
                                                                           the expertise of the medical professionals
                                                                           involved. These advancements require

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Antibiotic Prophylaxis: In some
                                                                           cases, patients may be prescribed antibi-
                                                                           otics before the procedure as a preven-
                                                                           tive measure to reduce the risk of infec-
                                                                           tion. This is particularly common for
                                                                           individuals who may have a higher sus-
                                                                           ceptibility to infections or those under-
                                                                           going certain types of stem cell ther-
                                                                           apies.
                                                                              Post-treatment Monitoring: After the
                                                                           stem cell therapy, patients are closely
                                                                           monitored for any signs of infection,
                                                                           such as fever, redness, swelling, or dis-
                                                                           charge at the injection site. Prompt de-
                                                                           tection and management of any potential
         Gene Therapy                                                      complications.
                                                                           infections are crucial to prevent further
                                                                              It is important to note that these
                                                                           measures are general guidelines, and
           further research, extensive clinical trials,   Pre-treatment Screening: Patients un-  specific protocols may vary depending
                                                                           on the healthcare facility, the type of
           and regulatory approval to ensure safety   dergoing stem cell therapy are typically   stem cell therapy, and the patient's indi-
           and efficacy.                   screened for any existing infections,   vidual circumstances. Each case should
             Before considering any new hair re-  such as bacterial, viral, or fungal infec-  be evaluated by qualified healthcare pro-
           storation technique, it is essential to con-  tions. If an active infection is detected,   fessionals who will determine the appro-
           sult with a qualified healthcare provider   the procedure may be postponed until   priate precautions to minimize the risk
           who can provide personalized advice   the infection is treated and resolved.   of infection during stem cell therapy.
           based on the most up-to-date information   Donor Screening: In cases where   While the prospect of reversing male
           and individual circumstances.   stem cells are obtained from a donor,   pattern balding is still a work in pro-
                                           thorough screening is conducted to en-  gress, the advancements in research and
           How to minimize the risk of     sure the donor is free from infectious   technology provide hope for a future
           infection                       diseases. Donors undergo rigorous test-  where baldness could be effectively re-
             During stem cell therapy, several   ing to detect any potential pathogens   versed. Stem cell therapy, gene therapy,
           measures are taken to minimize the risk   that could be transmitted during the ther-  PRP therapy, and hair cloning are just a
           of infection. Here are some common   apy.                       few examples of the innovative ap-
           precautions and protocols:        Proper Hygiene Practices: Healthcare   proaches being explored. As scientists
             Sterile Techniques: The entire proce-  providers involved in the procedure fol-  continue to unravel the complexities of
           dure is performed in a sterile environ-  low strict hygiene practices, including   male pattern balding, it is conceivable
           ment, such as an operating room or a   hand washing, wearing sterile gloves,   that we may witness breakthrough treat-
           specialized clinical setting. This helps to   masks, and gowns. This helps to prevent   ments in the coming years. Until then, it
           minimize the presence of harmful micro-  the introduction of any microorganisms   is important to consult with medical pro-
           organisms that could potentially cause   from the healthcare providers them-  fessionals and explore the available op-
           an infection.                   selves.                         tions for managing and treating hair loss.



















         Sterile Techniques







           12                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[MUSIC





































           Pankaj Udhas's iconic ghazal journey



           The velvet voice









           stilled









             n a heart-wrenching turn of events,   ditions captivated audiences for over   over the ghazal genre. Songs like
             the music world bids farewell to   four decades. The 1980s and 1990s   "Chhupana Bhi Nahin Aata," "Aur Aa-
           Ithe legendary ghazal maestro,   marked the pinnacle of his career,   hista Kijiye Baatein," and "Jeeye To
           Pankaj Udhas, who passed away at the   especially with the release of the chart-  Jeeye Kaise" resonated deeply with lis-
           age of 72 on February 26, 2024, after a   topping album "Chitthi Aayi Hai,"   teners, creating timeless classics.
           prolonged illness.              which solidified his status as a preemi-  Udhas's contributions to the ghazal
             Pankaj Udhas, born on May 17,   nent ghazal singer.           genre earned him prestigious accolades,
           1951, in Jetpur, Gujarat, was an iconic   Throughout his illustrious career,   including the Padma Shri in 2006 and
           figure in Indian ghazal music. His   Udhas released numerous albums   the Government of Maharashtra's Life-
           soul-stirring voice and emotive ren-  showcasing his versatility and mastery   time Achievement Award. Beyond

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[emotions.
                                                                              What set Udhas apart was not just
                                                                           his vocal prowess but also his impec-
                                                                           cable diction and pronunciation of
                                                                           Urdu words. His nuanced approach,
                                                                           characterized by delicate phrasing and
         Pankaj Udhas in a Ghazal performance                              scended performance boundaries. Lis-
                                                                           subtle nuances, showcased not just
                                                                           singing ability but also a deep under-
                                                                           standing of the genre.
                                                                              Udhas created an intimacy that tran-

                                                                           tening to him was a personal experi-
                                                                           ence, as if he were whispering verses
                                                                           directly into the ears of his audience.
                                                                           This ability to create an emotional con-
                                                                           nection set him apart, making each lis-
                                                                           tener feel like a part of a shared jour-
                                                                           ney through love and longing.
                                                                              Live performances stood out as
                                                                           jewels, each a testament to Udhas's
                                                                           mesmerizing aura and captivating stage
                                                                           presence. Whether in concerts in India
                                                                           or abroad, he established an emotional
                                                                           communion with the audience. His live
                                                                           renditions were not mere musical per-
                                                                           formances but emotional journeys.
         With her wife Farida Udhas                                        and "Aahat" stand out. The title track
                                                                              As we celebrate Udhas's legacy,
                                                                           iconic albums like "Chitthi Aayi Hai"

                                                                           of the former etched itself into the an-
                                                                           nals of musical history. "Aahat" fea-
                                                                           tured memorable ghazals like "Aur Aa-
                                                                           hista Kijiye Baatein," "Mahiya Teri
                                                                           showcasing his remarkable vocal range
           music, his philanthropic endeavors re-  Aayi Hai" in the 1980s catapulted him   Kasam," and "Chale Aao Saiyan,"
                                                                           and emotional depth.
           flected a compassionate soul dedicated   to unparalleled fame, making him syn-  "Musafir" was another gem, unveil-
           to education, healthcare, and empower-  onymous with the ghazal genre.   ing Udhas's ability to evoke deep emo-
           ing underprivileged children.     Pankaj Udhas was not merely a   tions with soul-stirring ghazals. Tracks
             As we reflect on Pankaj Udhas's   singer but a storyteller, painting emo-  like "Niklo Na Benaqab" and "Abhi
           life, we mourn the loss of a mesmeriz-  tions with the brushstrokes of his   Kuch Dino Se" became anthems, en-
           ing ghazal maestro whose legacy,   voice. Each album was a journey into   chanting audiences with melodious
           marked by enchanting melodies and   the human soul, exploring facets of   tunes and heartfelt lyrics.
           benevolent contributions, will endure   love and life. The music industry ac-  While these albums represent mile-
           eternally. Though his physical presence   knowledged his brilliance with the   stones, they are a glimpse into Udhas's
           may have departed, his timeless artistry   Padma Shri in 2006, a testament to his   vast body of work. Each album, from
           and benevolence will forever echo in   unparalleled contributions.   early hits to later releases, encapsulates
           the hearts of those touched by his   Beyond accolades, Udhas was a phi-  his talent and dedication to ghazal
           music and generosity.           lanthropist. His commitment to social   singing.
             Pankaj Udhas's journey in the realm   causes showcased a man whose gener-  In conclusion, Pankaj Udhas's leg-
           of ghazals was extraordinary, leaving   osity mirrored the richness of his   acy is a testament to the transcendental
           an indelible mark on the hearts and   voice. The Government of Maharashtra   power of music. His voice, with its
           souls of his listeners. Born in Jetpur,   honored him with the Lifetime   captivating and emotive qualities, has
           Gujarat, on May 17, 1951, Udhas dis-  Achievement Award, recognizing his   left an indelible imprint on the hearts
           covered his musical passion early in   humanitarian endeavors.   of millions. His contributions to the
           life, becoming one of the foremost   Delving into the unique aspects of   world of ghazals go beyond entertain-
           ghazal singers of his era.      Pankaj Udhas's singing style reveals a   ment; they are a cultural and emotional
             In college, Udhas began his musical   revered figure in the world of ghazals.   heritage that will continue to resonate
           expedition, performing at various gath-  His voice, like a mellifluous river, car-  through the ages. As we remember
           erings and cultural events. His velvety   ried a range of emotions with unparal-  him, we celebrate not just a singer but
           voice and impeccable control over gha-  leled grace. Seamless control over vo-  a storyteller who wove emotions into
           zal nuances drew the attention of music   cals allowed him to navigate ghazal   the fabric of our lives, leaving behind a
           aficionados. The iconic album "Chitthi   poetry, weaving a tapestry of authentic   timeless legacy.

           14                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[ENVIRONMENT & LIFE STYLE













































           ECO ELEGANCE




           The rise of green







           fashion








             n recent years, the fashion industry   choices. In this comprehensive explora-  tive alternatives, such as organic cotton,
             has undergone a transformative shift,   tion, we will delve deeper into the var-  Tencel, hemp, and recycled polyester.
           Iwith sustainability emerging as a key   ious eco-friendly trends shaping the   These materials not only require fewer
           focus. As global awareness of climate   fashion industry and examine their pro-  pesticides and chemicals but also signif-
           change and environmental issues has   found impact on the environment.   icantly reduce water consumption dur-
           risen, consumers are increasingly mind-  Sustainable materials   ing production. Furthermore, the in-
           ful of the ecological impact of their   A cornerstone of the eco-friendly   tegration of recycled materials into
           choices, extending their concern to the   fashion movement is the adoption of   fashion contributes to the creation of a
           clothes they wear. This shift has given   sustainable materials. Traditional fash-  circular economy by diverting waste
           rise to a wave of eco-friendly trends   ion heavily relies on resource-intensive   away from landfills.
           within the fashion industry, as designers,   materials, such as conventional cotton   Organic cotton, for instance, is grown
           brands, and consumers strive to make   and polyester. However, eco-conscious   without synthetic pesticides and fertil-
           more environmentally responsible   designers are actively seeking innova-  izers, reducing the environmental impact

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[cheap, short-lived garments contribute
                                                                           to excessive waste.
                                                                              Slow fashion emphasizes the signifi-
                                                                           cance of a curated wardrobe comprised
                                                                           of versatile and enduring pieces. This
                                                                           approach not only reduces the frequency
                                                                           of purchases but also encourages con-
                                                                           sumers to invest in high-quality, sustain-
                                                                           able garments that withstand the test of
                                                                           time. As a result, the slow fashion move-
                                                                           ment is gaining traction as an antidote to
         Organic Clothing                                                  fast fashion.
                                                                           the wasteful practices associated with
                                                                           Circular fashion
                                                                              Circular fashion is a holistic ap-
                                                                           proach that envisions a closed-loop sys-
                                                                           tem within the fashion industry. This
           associated with conventional cotton   Slow fashion              system aims to minimize waste by de-
           farming. Tencel, a fabric made from sus-  The detrimental effects of fast fash-  signing products with recycling and up-
           tainably sourced wood pulp, boasts a   ion, characterized by rapid production   cycling in mind. Brands are increasingly
           closed-loop production process, where   cycles and disposable clothing, have   adopting circular practices by creating
           water and solvents are continually   prompted a growing interest in the slow   garments that are easily recyclable or re-
           reused. Hemp, known for its resilience,   fashion movement. Slow fashion en-  purposable. Some companies have even
           requires minimal water and pesticides,   courages consumers to make mindful   introduced take-back programs, allow-
           making it an eco-friendly alternative.   choices, emphasizing the importance of   ing customers to return old clothing for
           The incorporation of these sustainable   quality over quantity and promoting   recycling or upcycling, thereby extend-
           materials reflects a commitment to mini-  timeless, durable designs. This shift to-  ing the life cycle of garments and con-
           mizing the environmental footprint of   wards longevity in fashion addresses the   tributing to a more sustainable fashion
           clothing production.            issue of planned obsolescence, wherein   ecosystem.
                                                                              Circular fashion challenges the linear
                                                                           model of "take, make, dispose" that
                                                                           dominates traditional fashion produc-
                                                                           tion. Instead, it advocates for a circular
                                                                           economy where resources are continu-
                                                                           ously reused, promoting environmental
                                                                           sustainability. By embracing circular
                                                                           fashion principles, the fashion industry
                                                                           can make significant strides in reducing
                                                                           its ecological impact and addressing the
         Eco-friendly clothes                                              Ethical and fair trade practices
                                                                           challenges posed by textile waste.
                                                                              Eco-friendly fashion extends beyond
                                                                           materials and production processes to
                                                                           encompass ethical and fair trade prac-
                                                                           tices. Consumers are becoming increas-
                                                                           ingly conscientious about the conditions
                                                                           in which their clothes are made and are
                                                                           demanding transparency from fashion
                                                                           brands. Ethical practices include ensur-
                                                                           ing fair wages, providing safe working
                                                                           conditions, and prohibiting the use of
                                                                           child labor.
                                                                              Brands that prioritize ethical produc-
                                                                           tion are gaining favor among consumers
         Fashion designer at a factory                                     ethical and fair trade practices not only
                                                                           who seek to align their values with their
                                                                           purchasing decisions. The shift towards
                                                                           addresses social justice concerns but
                                                                           also contributes to the overall sustain-
                                                                           ability of the fashion industry. By foster-
                                                                           ing positive working conditions and fair
                                                                           compensation, fashion brands can build
                                                                           stronger relationships with both their

           16                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Recycled Clothing







           workers and consumers.          This shift towards more sustainable   This shift towards cruelty-free fash-
           Eco-friendly dyeing and printing   practices in the dyeing and printing pro-  ion aligns with the growing awareness
             Traditional dyeing and printing pro-  cesses aligns with the broader goal of   of animal rights and the environmental
           cesses in the fashion industry often in-  minimizing the environmental footprint   consequences of animal agriculture.
           volve the use of harmful chemicals, con-  of the fashion industry.   Vegan and cruelty-free options provide
           tributing to water pollution and   Vegan and cruelty-free fashion   consumers with ethically sound choices,
           environmental degradation. In response,   An emerging trend in the fashion in-  allowing them to express their style
           eco-friendly alternatives are gaining   dustry is the increased demand for   without compromising their values.
           prominence. Natural dyes derived from   vegan and cruelty-free alternatives, par-  As the fashion industry undergoes a
           plants, minerals, and insects are being   ticularly in accessories such as shoes,   paradigm shift towards sustainability,
           explored as a sustainable option. Water-  bags, and belts. Designers are exploring   eco-friendly trends are becoming imper-
           based inks and digital printing technol-  innovative materials as substitutes for   ative for its continued evolution. The in-
           ogies are also being adopted to mini-  traditional animal-derived products.   tersection of environmental conscious-
           mize the environmental impact of   Pineapple leather, commercially known   ness, ethical practices, and consumer
           traditional printing methods.   as Piñatex, is one such example, made   demand is reshaping the landscape of
             Eco-friendly dyeing and printing   from the fibers of pineapple leaves.   fashion. By embracing sustainable mate-
           methods not only reduce the use of   Mushroom leather, derived from myce-  rials, slow fashion principles, circular
           harmful chemicals but also produce vi-  lium, and synthetic alternatives are also   practices, ethical production, and
           brant and unique designs on clothing.   gaining popularity.     cruelty-free alternatives, the fashion in-
                                                                           dustry can lead the way toward a more
                                                                           environmentally conscious and socially
                                                                           responsible future.
                                                                              Consumers play a crucial role in this
                                                                           transformation by making informed
                                                                           choices and supporting brands that pri-
                                                                           oritize eco-friendly practices. As the
                                                                           fashion industry progresses on its sus-
                                                                           tainable journey, it is essential for stake-
                                                                           holders to collaborate, innovate, and im-
                                                                           plement eco-friendly solutions. By
                                                                           collectively addressing the environmen-
                                                                           tal and social impact of fashion, we can
                                                                           pave the way for a more sustainable and
         slow fashion                                                      ethical industry that not only meets the
                                                                           needs of the present but also ensures a
                                                                           thriving and resilient future.

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[TECHNOLOGY




































           Digital dominance over Real instruments




          Facing the









          Silence











             n recent decades, the landscape of                            Reduced budgets and cost
             the music industry has undergone a                            considerations
           Itransformative shift with the wide-                               One of the significant factors contrib-
           spread adoption and integration of elec-                        uting to the dominance of electronic
           tronic music. The evolution of technol-                         music in the industry is the economic ef-
           ogy has given rise to a new era where                           ficiency it offers. Hiring skilled musi-
           electronic beats and synthesized sounds                         cians to play real instruments can be a
           have become the driving force behind                            costly affair, involving expenses related
           modern music. This shift has not only                           to recording studios, session musicians,
           influenced the way music is produced                            and equipment maintenance. In contrast,
           but has also had far-reaching con-                              electronic music production requires
           sequences on the traditional world of                           fewer resources, enabling artists and
           real musical instruments.                                       producers to create music with reduced

           18                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[overall budgets.
           The rise of electronic music in the
           modern industry
             As a consequence of cost-effective-
           ness, electronic music has become the
           preferred choice in the modern music in-
           dustry. The ease of digital production,
           the availability of a vast array of virtual
           instruments, and the ability to manipu-
           late sound electronically have all con-
           tributed to the widespread adoption of
           this genre. From pop and hip-hop to
           EDM (Electronic Dance Music), elec-                                                             Indian classical music instruments
           tronic elements have become ubiquitous
           in contemporary music.
           Impact on real musical instrument
           makers
             While the shift towards electronic
           music has benefited some sectors of the
           industry, it has created challenges for   Global impact on Indian musical   vibrant market for these instruments in
           traditional musical instrument makers.   instruments            European countries has diminished,
           The demand for real instruments has   The impact of electronic music ex-  leaving exporters with excess inventory
           dwindled, leading to financial hardships   tends beyond regional boundaries, af-  and a shrinking customer base.
           for artisans and craftsmen who have   fecting the global demand for specific   The evolution of electronic music
           been crafting these instruments for gen-  types of instruments. In the case of   technology
           erations. Many skilled instrument   India, renowned for its rich musical her-  To understand the impact of elec-
           makers find themselves grappling with a   itage and diverse instruments such as   tronic music on traditional instruments,
           decline in orders, forcing them to ex-  Tabla, Flute, Sitar, Sarangi, Veena,   it's crucial to delve into the evolution of
           plore alternative sources of income.   Sarod, and Harmonium, the worldwide   technology that has facilitated this shift.
           Career transitions and financial   shift towards electronic music has had   The advent of synthesizers, drum ma-
           hardships                       profound consequences. The demand for   chines, and digital audio workstations
             In response to the changing musical   these traditional Indian instruments in   (DAWs) has empowered musicians to
           landscape, some traditional instrument   European countries, which was once ro-  create entire compositions without the
           makers have been compelled to make   bust, has reached negligible levels.   need for physical instruments or live
           significant career transitions. The de-  Exporters struggling in a business-less   musicians.
           cline in demand for real instruments has   environment             The versatility and convenience of
           led to a scarcity of jobs and financial in-  The decline in demand for Indian   electronic music production tools have
           stability for those dedicated to the craft.   musical instruments has left exporters in   democratized music creation, allowing
           Some artisans have been forced to   a challenging position. Businesses that   aspiring artists to produce high-quality
           switch to other businesses or seek alter-  once thrived on international sales of   tracks from the comfort of their homes.
           native employment, abandoning the   Tablas, Sitars, and other instruments are   This accessibility has further accelerated
           skills and traditions that have been   now facing a stark reality of dwindling   the rise of electronic music, attracting a
           passed down through generations.   orders and financial struggle. The once-  diverse range of creators who may not
                                                                           have had access to traditional instru-
                                                                           ments or expensive recording studios.
                                                                           The economic efficiency of electronic
                                                                           music production
                                                                              Beyond artistic expression, economic
                                                                           considerations have played a pivotal role
                                                                           in the ascendancy of electronic music.
                                                                           The costs associated with hiring skilled
         Digital music synthesizer with a keyboard                         struments are significant contributors to
                                                                           instrumentalists, renting recording
                                                                           spaces, and maintaining traditional in-
                                                                           the financial burden faced by musicians
                                                                           and producers. Electronic music, with its
                                                                           reliance on digital interfaces and virtual
                                                                           instruments, offers a more cost-effective
                                                                           alternative.
                                                                              Additionally, electronic music allows
                                                                           for easier collaboration across geograph-

                                                                           digital files and collaborate remotely, re-

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                            ical boundaries. Artists can exchange   19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[ducing the need for expensive travel and   tion techniques. Their exposure to a   centuries.
           studio time. This has facilitated a more   wide range of electronic subgenres has   To adapt to the changing market dy-
           globalized and interconnected music in-  shaped their musical tastes, contributing   namics, some instrument makers have
           dustry, where artists from different parts   to a cultural shift away from traditional   explored incorporating electronic ele-
           of the world can seamlessly contribute   forms of instrumentation. This change   ments into their designs. Hybrid instru-
           to a project without the logistical chal-  in preference has further fueled the de-  ments that combine traditional crafts-
           lenges associated with traditional   mand for electronic music and dimin-  manship with electronic components
           recording methods.              ished the appeal of live instrumental   aim to bridge the gap between the old
           The cultural impact of electronic music   performances.         and the new. However, the success of
             As electronic music continues to   The challenges faced by traditional   such innovations depends on whether
           shape the musical landscape, it has also   instrument makers    they resonate with contemporary musi-
           influenced cultural perceptions and pref-  As the demand for real musical in-  cians and audiences.
           erences. The sonic palette of electronic   struments diminishes, traditional instru-  The human touch vs. digital precision
           genres, characterized by synthesizers,   ment makers find themselves at a cross-  One of the debates within the music
           drum machines, and computer-generated   roads. These artisans, often carrying the   industry centers around the perceived
           sounds, has become synonymous with   legacy of generations, face the daunting   trade-off between the human touch of
           modernity and innovation. This associa-  task of preserving ancient craftsmanship   live instruments and the precision of
           tion has, in turn, influenced the way au-  in a rapidly changing musical landscape.   electronic production. Advocates for tra-
           diences perceive and consume music.   The decline in orders not only affects   ditional instruments argue that the nu-
             The younger generation, in particu-  their livelihoods but also endangers the   ances, emotions, and imperfections in
           lar, has grown up in an era dominated   survival of cultural and artistic traditions   live performances create a unique and
           by electronic beats and digital produc-  that have been passed down through   authentic listening experience. On the
                                                                           other hand, proponents of electronic
                                                                           music emphasize the precision, repeat-
                                                                           ability, and unlimited creative possibil-
                                                                           ities afforded by digital tools.
                                                                              The dichotomy between the human
                                                                           touch and digital precision highlights
                                                                           the evolving nature of musical expres-
                                                                           sion. While some artists continue to
                                                                           champion the warmth and expressive-
                                                                           ness of real instruments, others embrace
                                                                           the boundless creative potential offered
                                                                           by electronic production.
                                                                           The changing dynamics of music
                                                                           education
                                                                              The shift towards electronic music
                                                                           has also influenced the way music is
         Digital controls                                                  taught and learned. Traditional music
                                                                           education, which often focuses on mas-
                                                                           tering specific instruments and sheet
                                                                           music, is facing competition from
                                                                           courses that emphasize digital produc-
                                                                           tion techniques and software profi-
                                                                           ciency. Aspiring musicians are increas-
                                                                           ingly drawn to programs that equip
                                                                           them with the skills to navigate the digi-
                                                                           tal landscape of the modern music in-
                                                                           dustry.
                                                                              This shift in educational priorities
                                                                           poses a challenge to institutions and
                                                                           teachers dedicated to preserving tradi-
                                                                           tional musical knowledge. The decline
                                                                           in enrollment for traditional instrument
                                                                           classes may lead to a diminishing pool
                                                                           of skilled instrumentalists, further con-
                                                                           tributing to the erosion of real instru-
                                                                           ment culture.
                                                                           Preserving cultural heritage in the
                                                                           digital age
         Harmonium                                                         traditional instruments extends beyond
                                                                              The impact of electronic music on
                                                                           economic and technological considera-

           20                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[could result in innovative fusions that
                                                                           appeal to a broader audience. Experi-
                                                                           mentation with incorporating traditional
                                                                           instruments into electronic compositions
                                                                           may open new avenues for artists and
                                                                           instrument makers alike.
                                                                              Educational initiatives that highlight
                                                                           the cultural significance of traditional
                                                                           instruments and their unique sonic qual-
                                                                           ities can contribute to a renewed interest
                                                                           among audiences. Public awareness
                                                                           campaigns, music festivals, and collabo-
                                                                           rative projects that showcase the beauty
                                                                           of live instrumental performances may
         Digital recording control room                                    organizations can play a pivotal role in
                                                                           help bridge the gap between electronic
                                                                           and traditional music enthusiasts.
                                                                              Moreover, governments and cultural

                                                                           supporting and preserving traditional
                                                                           music. Financial incentives, grants, and
                                                                           programs that encourage the production
                                                                           and promotion of traditional instruments
                                                                           can provide a lifeline for struggling arti-
                                                                           sans and exporters.
           tions—it raises questions about cultural   once thrived on a vibrant international   The impact of electronic music on
           preservation. Instruments like the Tabla,   market for instruments like Tablas,   the existence of real musical instruments
           Sitar, and Sarangi are not merely tools   Flutes, and Harmoniums now find them-  is a complex and multifaceted phenome-
           for creating music; they carry the cul-  selves grappling with reduced orders   non that goes beyond economic consid-
           tural heritage, stories, and traditions of   and financial uncertainty.   erations. While the rise of electronic
           their respective regions.         The challenges faced by exporters   music has undoubtedly transformed the
             Efforts to preserve and promote tra-  are exacerbated by factors such as   music industry, offering new possibil-
           ditional instruments in the digital age   changing import regulations, fluctuating   ities for creativity and accessibility, it
           are crucial for maintaining cultural di-  exchange rates, and the emergence of al-  has also posed challenges to traditional
           versity within the global music land-  ternative musical trends. The once-thriv-  instrument makers and exporters.
           scape. Collaborative initiatives between   ing export market for Indian musical in-  Finding a harmonious balance be-
           electronic and traditional musicians, cul-  struments, particularly in European   tween electronic and traditional musical
           tural institutions, and policymakers can   countries, has contracted significantly,   expressions is crucial for preserving cul-
           help strike a balance between embracing   leaving exporters with surplus inventory   tural heritage, fostering artistic diversity,
           technological advancements and safe-  and financial strain.     and supporting those whose livelihoods
           guarding cultural legacies.     Revitalizing the market: Exploring   are intertwined with the craftsmanship
           The economic ripple effect on exporters   opportunities         of real instruments. As the music indus-
             The decline in demand for traditional   While the challenges are undeniable,   try continues to evolve, it is imperative
           Indian instruments has created a ripple   there are opportunities to revitalize the   to recognize and address the broader im-
           effect throughout the supply chain, im-  market for traditional instruments in the   plications of these changes to ensure a
           pacting exporters and businesses associ-  context of the electronic music-dom-  thriving and inclusive musical ecosys-
           ated with the production and distribution   inated landscape. Collaboration between   tem that embraces both the digital and
           of these instruments. Exporters who   electronic and traditional musicians   the analog.

                                                                                                           Real instruments are visible in live performances




















           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[EDUCATION





































           Exercise Hindered




           The hidden drawback






           of school uniforms







               chool uniforms have long been a   attend schools with mandatory uniforms   nents of school uniforms, which may
               topic of debate among educators,   may participate in less physical activity   limit movements like running, jumping,
           Sparents, and experts. While they   compared to their peers in schools with-  and playing sports. This restriction re-
           are often praised for promoting dis-  out such dress codes. The primary rea-  duces the overall levels of physical ex-
           cipline and a sense of belonging, some   son behind this observation stems from   ertion and can result in lower overall
           concerns have been raised regarding   the restrictive nature of the clothing it-  activity levels.
           their impact on children's physical ac-  self.
           tivity levels. This article aims to explore                     Psychological impact and
           the potential relationship between   Limitations on movement    reduced motivation
           school uniforms and reduced exercise in   School uniforms typically consist of   Uniforms can also have a psycholog-
           children, and whether the clothing's re-  formal attire that imposes certain re-  ical impact on children, affecting their
           strictions could be a contributing factor.   strictions on children's movement.   motivation to engage in physical activ-
                                           These restrictions can hinder their abil-  ities. The association of uniforms with a
           The impact of school uniforms on   ity to engage in physical activities   more formal and disciplined setting may
           physical activity               freely. For instance, trousers, blazers,   create a mindset that physical activity is
             Research suggests that children who   and dress shoes are common compo-  not a priority during school hours.

           22                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[signs that prioritize comfort and flex-
                                                                           ibility, allowing for a wider range of
                                                                           movement.
                                                                              Encouraging Extracurricular Activ-
                                                                           ities: Schools can actively promote and
                                                                           endorse extracurricular activities such
                                                                           as sports clubs, dance groups, and other
                                                                           physically engaging options, providing
                                                                           children with opportunities to be active
                                                                           outside of regular school hours.
                                                                              Recess and Break Time: Allowing
                                                                           longer and more frequent recess or
                                                                           break periods can give students more
                                                                           time for physical activity within the
                                                                           school day, compensating for any limi-
                                                                           tations imposed by uniforms.

                                                                           Potential solutions or alternatives
                                                                              There are several potential solutions
                                                                           or alternatives to school uniforms that
                                                                           can encourage children to engage in
                                                                           physical activity while maintaining a
                                                                           sense of discipline and identity. Here
                                                                           are a few examples:
                                                                              Dress Code Guidelines: Instead of
                                                                           mandating a specific uniform, schools
                                                                           can implement dress code guidelines
         School uniform: Limitations on movement                           ment. This approach will not only en-
                                                                           that prioritize comfort and flexibility,
                                                                           allowing for a wider range of move-
                                                                           courage physical activity but also help
                                                                           to eliminate any concerns surrounding
                                                                           the psychological impact of formal uni-
                                                                           forms.
                                                                              Sportswear Options: Schools can
                                                                           provide students with the option of wea-
                                                                           ring sportswear as part of their uniform,
                                                                           such as tracksuits, shorts, or sweatpants.
                                                                           This approach will help students partici-
                                                                           pate in physical activity more comfort-
                                           Moreover, the desire to keep uniforms   ably and easily during school hours.
                                           clean and presentable can discourage   Active Wear Days: Schools can im-
                                           children from participating in activities   plement "active wear days," where stu-
                                           that may result in their clothing getting   dents can wear clothes that are con-
                                           dirty or damaged.               ducive to physical activity, such as gym
                                                                           clothes or sports gear. This approach
                                           Options for addressing this issue   will promote physical activity, and stu-
                                             While the link between school uni-  dents will have more flexibility to
                                           forms and reduced physical activity ex-  choose clothing that allows them to
                                           ists, it's essential to note that uniforms   move around freely, without the need to
                                           alone may not be solely responsible for   worry about uniform restrictions.
                                                                              Emphasis on Extracurricular Activ-
                                           developmentally inadequate exercise   ities: Instead of relying solely on physi-
         Physical activity in a school uniform  tivity within the constraints of a school   courage students to participate in
                                           levels in children. Several strategies can
                                                                           cal education classes, schools can en-
                                           be implemented to promote physical ac-
                                                                           extracurricular activities that promote
                                           uniform policy:
                                                                           physical activity, such as sports teams,
                                             Emphasis on Physical Education:
                                           Schools can prioritize physical educa-
                                                                           dance groups, or fitness clubs. By pro-
                                           tion classes and ensure that students re-
                                                                           viding opportunities to engage in physi-
                                           ceive adequate time for active play and
                                                                           cal activity outside of the traditional
                                           exercise during school hours.
                                                                           classroom setting, students will be more
                                             Choosing Uniform Designs for Flex-
                                                                           tivity while maintaining their sense of
           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in ibility: Schools can opt for uniform de-  motivated to participate in physical ac- 23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[tion classes or adopting flexible dress
                                                                           code policies, can have a positive im-
                                                                           pact on students' physical activity levels
                                                                           and engagement.
                                                                              It is important to note that the re-
                                                                           search in this area is still evolving, and
                                                                           more studies specifically examining the
                                                                           effectiveness of alternative uniform op-
                                                                           tions in promoting physical activity
                                                                           among students are needed to establish
                                                                           a stronger evidence base. Nonetheless,
                                                                           the existing research provides some
                                                                           support for the potential benefits of al-
                                                                           ternative uniform options in encourag-
                                                                           ing physical activity among students.
                                                                              School uniforms have their benefits
                                                                           in terms of instilling discipline and a
           identity.                       form policies on physical activity en-  sense of identity. However, it is crucial
             In summary, adopting dress code   gagement in children. While the review   to recognize the potential impact they
           guidelines, sportswear options, active   did not specifically focus on alternative   can have on children's physical activity
           wear days or emphasizing extracurricu-  uniform options, it concluded that   levels. Schools should search for ways
           lar activities are some potential solu-  school clothing policies that prioritize   to strike a balance between uniformity
           tions or alternatives to traditional school   comfort and flexibility are more likely   and physical activity promotion. By im-
           uniforms that can encourage children to   to promote physical activity and overall   plementing strategies to prioritize
           engage in physical activity while still   well-being among students.   movement and providing opportunities
           maintaining a sense of discipline and   These studies suggest that alternative   for physical activity, schools can help
           identity.                       options in school uniform policies, such   ensure that children maintain healthy
                                           as allowing activewear or more com-  activity levels while observing dress
           Research and studies            fortable clothing during physical educa-  code policies.
             While the concept of alternative uni-
           form options in promoting physical ac-
           tivity among students is relatively new,
           there are some studies and research that
           shed light on their potential effective-
           ness. Although the specific focus on al-
           ternative uniform options may be lim-
           ited, studies examining various related
           factors can provide valuable insights.
           Here are a few examples:
             A study published in the Journal of                                                           Children perform better without uniforms
           Public Health Management and Practice
           in 2017 explored the impact of chang-
           ing school clothing policies to allow
           students to wear athletic shoes instead
           of formal shoes during physical educa-
           tion classes. The study found that this
           simple change resulted in increased
           physical activity participation and im-
           proved student engagement during
           physical education classes.
             Another study published in the Jour-
           nal of School Health in 2018 examined
           the impact of school dress codes on
           physical activity behavior among high
           school students. It found that flexible
           dress code policies that allowed stu-                                                           Uniform upkeep hampers girls' activity engagement
           dents to wear activewear or comfortable
           clothing were associated with increased
           physical activity levels among students.
             A comprehensive review published
           in the International Journal of Environ-
           mental Research and Public Health in
           2020 examined the role of school uni-

           24                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[TRAVEL





































           Essence of Vietnam



           History, culture









           & beauty









                 ietnam, a land steeped in history   nam, exploring its historic sites, breath-  French colonialism and the indelible
                 and adorned with diverse land-  taking natural beauty, bustling cities, cu-  marks of the Vietnam War. History en-
           Vscapes, has established itself as   linary delights, and the warm embrace   thusiasts will find themselves captivated
           a premier destination for travelers seek-  of its people.       by the Imperial City of Hue, a UNESCO
           ing an authentic and immersive experi-  History and Heritage: Vietnam's his-  World Heritage site that served as the
           ence. This Southeast Asian gem, with its   torical journey is a testament to resil-  seat of the Nguyen emperors during the
           rich cultural tapestry, mesmerizing scen-  ience, endurance, and the triumph of the   19th century. The intricate architecture
           ery, and delectable cuisine, beckons ex-  human spirit. The country bears the im-  and serene surroundings provide a
           plorers to uncover its secrets. In this   prints of ancient civilizations, with rem-  glimpse into Vietnam's imperial past.
           comprehensive travel guide, we will   nants of the Cham and Khmer civiliza-  Journeying further, visitors can ex-
           delve deeper into the wonders of Viet-  tions coexisting alongside the echoes of   plore the Cu Chi Tunnels near Ho Chi

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Minh City, a vast underground network   Breathtaking Landscapes: Vietnam's   seascape. A cruise through these mysti-
           that played a crucial role during the   diverse topography ranges from the em-  cal waters provides an opportunity to
           Vietnam War. These tunnels, a symbol   erald waters of Ha Long Bay to the ter-  marvel at the sheer magnificence of na-
           of Vietnamese ingenuity and resilience,   raced rice fields of Sapa, captivating   ture.
           offer a firsthand look at the challenges   travelers with its natural beauty. Ha   For those seeking a mountainous es-
           faced by the Vietnamese people and the   Long Bay, a UNESCO World Heritage   cape, the misty landscapes of Sapa in
           lengths to which they went to protect   site, boasts thousands of limestone   the northern highlands offer a serene re-
           their land.                     karsts and islets, creating a breathtaking   treat. Trekking through terraced rice
                                                                           fields and encountering ethnic minority
                                                                           villages provide a glimpse into the tradi-
                                                                           tional way of life in the mountains. The
                                                                           vibrant markets and the warmth of the
                                                                           local communities make Sapa a must-
                                                                           visit destination for nature lovers and
                                                                           cultural enthusiasts alike.
                                                                              The country's coastline is adorned
                                                                           with pristine beaches, and the island of
         Cruise in Halong Bay, Vietnam                                     dise. With its white sandy beaches, lush
                                                                           Phu Quoc stands out as a tropical para-
                                                                           jungles, and vibrant coral reefs, Phu
                                                                           Quoc is an idyllic destination for relaxa-
                                                                           tion and water-based activities.
                                                                              Vibrant Cities: Vietnam's cities are a
                                                                           captivating blend of old-world charm
                                                                           and modern vibrancy. Hanoi, the capital,
                                                                           reflects the country's rich history and
                                                                           cultural heritage. The Old Quarter, with
                                                                           its narrow streets and ancient architec-
                                                                           ture, invites visitors to wander through a
                                                                           maze of markets, temples, and tradi-
                                                                           tional shops. The Ho Chi Minh Mauso-
                                                                           leum pays homage to the revolutionary
                                                                           leader, while the One Pillar Pagoda and
                                                                           Temple of Literature provide glimpses
                                                                           into Vietnam's spiritual and intellectual
         Availability of homestays                                         as Saigon, stands as a testament to the
                                                                           history.
                                                                              Ho Chi Minh City, formerly known

                                                                           country's resilience and progress. The
                                                                           War Remnants Museum offers a sober-
                                                                           ing portrayal of the Vietnam War, dis-
                                                                           playing artifacts and photographs that
                                                                           tell the story of the conflict and its im-
                                                                           pact on the people. The Notre-Dame Ca-
                                                                           thedral Basilica of Saigon, a remnant of
                                                                           French colonial influence, stands in
                                                                           stark contrast to the bustling street mar-
                                                                           kets and modern skyscrapers, creating a
                                                                           unique cityscape.
                                                                              Culinary Delights: Vietnamese cui-
         Beautiful scene from a Halong Bay Cruise                          the iconic banh mi, a French-inspired
                                                                           sine is renowned for its freshness, com-
                                                                           plexity, and balance of flavors. From the
                                                                           ubiquitous pho, a savory noodle soup, to
                                                                           baguette filled with flavorful ing-
                                                                           redients, the country's culinary offerings
                                                                           are a delight for the taste buds. Explor-
                                                                           ing local street food stalls is a culinary
                                                                           adventure in itself, with specialties like
                                                                           banh xeo (crispy Vietnamese pancake)
                                                                           and goi cuon (fresh spring rolls) entic-
                                                                           ing passersby.
                                                                              To truly immerse yourself in the

           26                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[world of Vietnamese cuisine, consider
           taking a cooking class. Expert chefs will
           guide you through the preparation of
           traditional dishes, providing insights
           into the use of fresh herbs, spices, and
           regional ingredients. These classes often
           include visits to local markets, where
           you can witness the vibrant colors and
           fragrances of Vietnamese produce.
             Cultural Experiences: Beyond his-
           torical sites and natural wonders, Viet-
           nam offers a plethora of cultural experi-
           ences that allow travelers to connect                                                           Ho Chi Minh Mausoleum
           with the local way of life. Timing your
           visit to coincide with Tet, the Lunar
           New Year celebration, provides a unique
           opportunity to witness traditional cus-
           toms, dragon dances, and fireworks   nipulate the puppets in water, creating a   brant and interconnected communities
           lighting up the night sky. Tet is a time of   mesmerizing and culturally rich experi-  that thrive along the delta.
           family gatherings, festive decorations,   ence.                    Engaging with local communities in
           and a collective spirit of hope for the   For a more immersive cultural en-  the Mekong Delta provides a deeper un-
           coming year.                    counter, venture into the Mekong Delta,   derstanding of traditional crafts, such as
             Water puppetry is an ancient Viet-  often referred to as the "Rice Bowl" of   coconut candy making and rice noodle
           namese art form that combines puppetry,   Vietnam. This fertile region is criss-  production. Homestay experiences allow
           music, and storytelling. Attend a water   crossed by a network of rivers and ca-  travelers to stay with local families,
           puppet show, particularly in Hanoi, to   nals, and life revolves around the water.   sharing meals and stories, creating
           witness the intricate performances that   Floating markets, where vendors sell   bonds that transcend cultural differ-
           depict scenes from daily life, folklore,   fruits, vegetables, and local specialties   ences.
           and legends. The skillful puppeteers ma-  from boats, offer a glimpse into the vi-  The warm hospitality of the Viet-
                                                                           namese people adds an extra layer of
                                                                           richness to the cultural experience.
                                                                           Whether interacting with street vendors,
                                                                           chatting with locals in markets, or par-
                                                                           ticipating in community events, visitors
                                                                           often find themselves welcomed with
                                                                           open arms.
                                                                              Conclusion: In conclusion, Vietnam's
                                                                           allure lies in its ability to seamlessly
                                                                           weave together a tapestry of history,
                                                                           landscapes, cuisine, and culture. A jour-
         Water Puppet Show                                                 ney through this captivating country
                                                                           promises to be an odyssey of discovery,
                                                                           offering a profound connection to the
                                                                           past and an appreciation for the resil-
                                                                           ience of its people. From the ancient
                                                                           wonders of Hue to the modern vibrancy
                                                                           of Ho Chi Minh City, from the tranquil
                                                                           beauty of Ha Long Bay to the mountain-
                                                                           ous landscapes of Sapa, every corner of
                                                                           Vietnam beckons with a unique story to
                                                                           tell.
                                                                              Embark on this voyage through time
                                                                           and culture, allowing the enchantment
                                                                           of Vietnam to unfold before your eyes.
                                                                           Taste the flavors, feel the rhythm, and
                                                                           embrace the warmth of a nation that
                                                                           welcomes travelers with open arms.
         New year activities                                               scapes, rich history, and vibrant culture,
                                                                           Vietnam, with its breathtaking land-
                                                                           invites you to explore the depths of its
                                                                           soul, leaving you with memories that
                                                                           will linger long after your journey has
                                                                           ended.

           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                  March 1-15, 2024







           ARIES
                                                           Sept. 23 - October 22
           March 21 - April 19                             LIBRA

                     During this period, you may feel a burst of energy   This period is all about partnerships and rela-
                     and enthusiasm, Aries. Use this motivation wisely   tionships, Libra. Nurture your connections with
                     and channel it into accomplishing your goals. Pay   others and seek harmony in your interactions.
                     attention to your health and well-being and     Find a balance between your own needs and
                     maintain a healthy work-life balance.           those of your loved ones.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     This bi-weekly period brings an opportunity for   During this bi-weekly period, you may feel a
                     self-reflection, Taurus. Take some time to evaluate   strong desire for personal transformation, Scor-
                     your priorities and make any necessary          pio. Embrace this inner growth and let go of any
                     adjustments. Focus on building strong foundations   old patterns or beliefs that no longer serve you.
                     in your personal and professional life.         Trust your intuition.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Communication is key during this bi-weekly      Adventure awaits you during this period, Sagit-
                     period, Gemini. Express yourself clearly and ef-  tarius. Take the opportunity to explore new
                     fectively, as this will help you navigate any chal-  places, ideas, and experiences. Broaden your ho-
                     lenges that come your way. Stay open to new     rizons and embrace the unknown. Keep an open
                     ideas and collaborations.                       mind.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Emotional intelligence plays a significant role in   Focus on your ambitions and long-term goals
                     your interactions during this period, Cancer. Be   during this bi-weekly period, Capricorn. Take
                     sensitive to the needs and feelings of others.   practical steps to achieve your dreams and main-
                     Take time for self-care and nourish your emo-   tain a disciplined approach. Cultivate patience
                     tional well-being.                              and resilience.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Creativity and self-expression are emphasized   This period encourages you to connect with your
                     during this bi-weekly period, Leo. Embrace your   social circle and community, Aquarius. Embrace
                     unique talents and share them with the world.   collaboration and work towards collective goals.
                     Take bold steps toward your dreams and aspira-  Stay true to your authentic self and be open to
                     tions.                                          innovative ideas.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Focus on building a solid foundation in your per-  Listen to your intuition and trust your instincts
                     sonal and professional life, Virgo. Pay attention   during this bi-weekly period, Pisces. Take some
                     to the details and take a practical approach to   time for introspection and self-reflection. Pay at-
                     problem-solving. Maintain a harmonious bal-     tention to your dreams and inner guidance.
                     ance between work and personal life.





           28                                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR | MARCH 01 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS







           Thought-provoking insights        The horror cinema brief was chilling,   Salman Ahmad, Hyderabad,
                                           while Sydney-Australia's plus points   Telangana, India
             It's becoming more enriching with   were visually appealing. Overall, the
           each passing issue; this one I liked best   magazine's presentation was commend-
           because it evokes thoughts, such as   able.                     Saluting the timeless legacy of
           extramarital relations. There is so much   Vilas Pathak, Pune, Maharashtra,   Shivaji Maharaj
           happening on the socio-political platforms   India
           that our generation, which is witnessing                           I write to express admiration for the
           the transition, is caught unawares in this                      enduring legacy of Chhatrapati Shivaji
           tsunami of change. It's difficult to digest   Illuminating sustainability   Maharaj and his visionary Maratha Em-
           this fast-changing scenario, and at the                         pire. His commitment to justice, reli-
           same time, we need to, or at least feign the   I commend Revoir Magazine for   gious tolerance, and strategic brilliance
           acceptance to stay relevant. It’s certainly a   consistently delivering insightful content   set a precedent that shaped India's his-
           changed world. Then comes the desert   that captivates readers. The recent article   tory. Shivaji's military prowess and ad-
           expansion; it's alarming. I didn't know 9   on environmental sustainability was par-  ministrative reforms stand as a testament
           km per year is being gobbled up by the   ticularly enlightening. The meticulous   to his leadership. As we commemorate
           sand. Time is not far when whole   research and engaging narrative show-  his birth anniversary, let us celebrate the
           continents will be covered. Loved the   cased the magazine's commitment to   indomitable spirit that forged a united
           Time article too.               high-quality journalism. Revoir's ability   and prosperous Maratha state. Shivaji
           Sandeep Rai, Asst. Editor, The Times of   to tackle pressing issues with depth and   Maharaj remains an inspiration, his em-
           India, Meerut, Uttar Pradesh, India   clarity is commendable. It's a beacon in   pire a beacon of valor and resilience.
                                           the sea of publications. Keep up the ex-  Naresh Patil, Pune, Maharashtra, India
                                           cellent work!
           Magazine’s presentation was     Ramesh Sehgal, New Delhi, India
           commendable                                                     Uniting for awareness

             Kudos to Revoir Magazine for the   The Surge of Digital Infidelity   Rare Disease Day amplifies the
           captivating Issue 16, Feb 2024! The                             voices of those facing uncommon health
           coverage on Extra Marital Affairs was   The pervasive rise of digital infidel-  challenges. This year's theme, "Unite for
           articulate, supported by impactful pho-  ity warrants our collective scrutiny. The   change! Unite for equity!," emphasizes
           tos. The feature on combating the 'In-  allure of secret online rendezvous has   global collaboration. Let's spotlight the
           visible Enemy' shed light on radiation   significantly altered the landscape of re-  resilience, advocate for research, and
           hazards, offering practical solutions. The   lationships, challenging traditional   strengthen support networks. Together,
           comprehensive article on Shivaji Maha-  boundaries. This phenomenon isn't   we can make strides toward a more in-
           raj, spanning from birth to admin-  merely a matter of personal choices; it   clusive and informed healthcare land-
           istrative reforms, was commendable.   reflects a broader societal shift worth   scape.
             Sahara-Africa Desert's relentless ex-  discussing openly. From the shadows of   Sunil Sethi, Florence, Alabama, United
           pansion was vividly portrayed with con-  cyberspace, emotional and physical con-  States
           sequences and impacts, accompanied by   nections are being forged discreetly, im-
           detailed photos. The piece on the evolu-  pacting the fabric of fidelity in unsus-
           tion of time clocks/watches was intrigu-  pecting ways. Shedding light on these   Letters (limited to one hundred words)
           ing, emphasizing luxury watches' unaf-  digital complexities encourages open   are welcome and should be addressed
           fordable prices. Rare diseases were   discourse, fostering understanding in an   to the Editor at Email:
           presented in layman's terms, fostering   era where relationships navigate un-  revoir@post.com
           awareness.                      charted waters.



             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           MARCH 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                        29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>