<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                       VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 10 I  MAY 16 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: MAHDI CHAGHARI





               5



                                                            11













                                                            21                                        8
















           4-Editorial: Humanity at its most honest  23-Should horses still perform?
           5-Will we all eat differently by 2050?          26-Is wine losing its charm?

           8-Life in a world that never switches off  28-Horoscopes

           11-The force that built civilization            29-Letters

           15-If the world ended tomorrow…                 31-Frame of thought
           18-The new beauty revolution

           21-The most beautiful woman in the

           world?












           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                  3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[The Last Sunrise
     EDITORIAL  Humanity                                                            Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           at its most honest                                                   Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                hat would you do if tomorrow      Art & Culture Editor
                                                never came?  It sounds like one    Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Wof those late-night questions
                                        people ask half-jokingly over coffee or dur-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        ing long train rides. Yet every few years, the   Vishakha Sharma
                                        world seems to brush against that fear for
                                        real. A pandemic empties streets. A war
                                        flashes across television screens. Wildfires   Social Media Editor
                                        turn entire skies orange. Suddenly, the im-  Sushil Kumar
                                        possible no longer feels distant.
                                           And strangely, when people think the   Art & Graphics Director
                                        end may be near, they don’t rush toward      Vipin Agarwal
                                        ambition. They move toward each other.
                                           During the early months of COVID-19,
           there were stories from almost every country that felt deeply human. Neighbours left   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           groceries outside doors for elderly strangers. Families rediscovered dinner tables.
           Friends called each other without needing a reason. In cities usually obsessed with   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           speed, life slowed down just enough for people to ask themselves a difficult question:   Editor, United News of India, New
           What actually matters?
             If the world ended tomorrow, most of us probably wouldn’t spend today checking   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           unread emails or arguing online with people we’ll never meet. We’d call our parents.   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           We’d apologise to someone. We’d sit quietly with our children, or our partners, or   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           maybe just ourselves. Some would pray. Some would write. Others would walk out-  Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           side and look carefully at the sky, perhaps for the first time in months.   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Shahid
             Modern life rarely gives us room to think this way. We’re trained to plan endlessly   A Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           for the future. Better jobs, bigger homes, longer savings plans. There’s nothing wrong
           with that, of course. Progress matters. Stability matters. But somewhere along the
           way, many people have started postponing joy itself. We save conversations for later.   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           Vacations for later. Forgiveness for later. Living, oddly enough, also gets pushed to
           later.
             Maybe that’s why the idea of “the end” unsettles us so much. Not because life   Phone +91 20 40199102
           would stop, but because we realise how much of it we haven’t fully lived.   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             There’s also another uncomfortable truth. If tomorrow were truly the last day, the   Baner Road,
           world would not end equally for everyone. Some people would face it from safe   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           homes with loved ones around them. Others, even now, are already living through   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           conditions that feel apocalyptic: war zones, refugee camps, hunger, displacement,   Website www.revoir.in
           loneliness. For them, the question isn’t philosophical. It’s painfully real.
             And yet humanity continues in small acts of stubborn hope. A teacher still enters a   Legal Advisor
           classroom. Doctors work exhausting shifts. Young people still fall in love, plant trees,   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           make music and dream about futures they may never completely control.
             Maybe that’s the point. If the world ended tomorrow, what would survive until the
           final moment would not be wealth or status. It would be kindness. Memory. Connec-
           tion. The simple proof that we were here and that, despite everything, we tried to care   Copyright © 2026 REVOIR (eZine),
           for one another. Perhaps we shouldn’t wait for the end of the world to start living like   all rights reserved. This publication
           that.                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



        Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH

































           The future diet

                                                                              Food has always been deeply emo-
                                                                           tional. A recipe can carry memories of
           Will we all eat                                                 grandparents, childhood summers or dif-
                                                                           ficult times survived together. People
                                                                           don’t just eat nutrients. They eat com-
                                                                           fort, identity and culture. That’s why
                                                                           conversations about changing diets
           differently                                                     world eats is becoming impossible to ig-
                                                                           quickly become personal.
                                                                              Still, the pressure to rethink how the

                                                                           nore.
                                                                              By 2050, the global population is ex-
                                                                           pected to approach 10 billion. Climate
           by 2050?                                                        change is already affecting harvests,
                                                                           water supplies and food prices. Heat-
                                                                           waves damage crops. Droughts shrink
                                                                           farmland. Meanwhile, millions still
                                                                           struggle to afford healthy meals while
           By 2050, dinner tables could look very different from           food waste continues on a massive scale.
                                                                              The question is no longer whether
           those of today. By Naina Kapoor                                 diets will change. It’s how far they’ll
                                                                           change and whether people are truly
                                                                           ready for it.
                  hat’s for dinner? sounds like   beef. A teenager mixes cricket powder
                  such an ordinary question.   into a breakfast smoothie because it’s   Why food systems are under strain
           WYet for scientists, farmers and   cheap, high in protein and environmen-  Modern agriculture feeds billions,
           families across the world, it’s becoming   tally friendly. In another apartment, cul-  but it comes at a cost.
           one of the biggest questions of the cen-  tivated chicken grown from animal cells   Livestock farming contributes signif-
           tury.                           heats inside a microwave. It sounds fu-  icantly to greenhouse gas emissions and
             Picture a kitchen a few decades from   turistic, maybe even slightly uncomfort-  uses enormous amounts of land and
           now. Someone grills a plant-based steak   able. But pieces of that future already   water. Producing beef, for example, re-
           that looks and smells almost identical to   exist.              quires far more resources than growing

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                  5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[more     regularly test meat alternatives because
                                                                  compli-  demand continues to grow.
                                                                  cated.      Part of the success comes from famil-
                                                                    Food   iarity. Plant-based eating isn’t entirely
                                                                  disgust is   new. Many traditional diets already rely
                                                                  power-   heavily on vegetables, lentils and grains.
                                                                  ful. A   In India, for example, generations have
                                                                  person   grown up eating protein-rich vegetarian
                                                                  may un-  meals without considering them un-
                                                                  derstand   usual.
                                                                  the envi-   What has changed is the technology.
                                                                  ronmen-     Food companies can now create
                                                                  tal bene-  plant-based products that imitate the tex-
                                                                  fits of   ture, smell and appearance of meat sur-
                                                                  eating   prisingly well. Some alternatives even
                                                                  insects   “bleed” like beef. For younger urban
           beans or lentils. As cities expand and
           natural resources become more limited,
           governments and researchers are search-
           ing for alternatives that are both sustain-
           able and affordable.
             At the same time, younger genera-
           tions are already changing their eating
           habits.
             Many Gen Z consumers are more cli-
           mate-conscious than previous genera-
           tions. Some are reducing meat consump-
           tion for environmental reasons. Others
           are motivated by health concerns, ani-
           mal welfare or curiosity. Vegan milk,
           meatless burgers and high-protein plant
           snacks have moved from specialty stores
           into everyday supermarkets.
             But changing food habits is never
           simple.                         and still feel uncomfortable taking a
             People grow attached to familiar   bite. That reaction isn’t always rational,
           meals. Traditions matter. In many cul-  but it’s real.           “
           tures, food represents celebration,   Companies trying to popularize in-  People don’t
           family and even national identity. Ask-  sect protein have noticed this barrier. In-
           ing people to replace those foods can   stead of selling whole insects, many
           feel less like a health recommendation   now use cricket flour in protein bars,   just eat
           and more like a challenge to their way   pasta or baked foods where consumers
           of life.                        barely notice the source.         nutrients, they
                                             Even then, resistance remains.
           The rise of insect protein        There’s also an uncomfortable social   eat memory,
             For many people, the idea of eating   question beneath the debate. Some
           insects still feels strange.    critics worry that sustainable diets may   comfort and
             Yet insects are already part of tradi-  become divided by class. Will wealthy
           tional diets in many regions of the   consumers continue enjoying expensive
           world. In countries such as Thailand and   traditional meats while ordinary people   identity.”
           Mexico, crickets and grasshoppers are   are encouraged to eat insects in the
           commonly eaten as snacks or ing-  name of sustainability? The concern
           redients. What seems unusual in one   may sound cynical, but it reflects gen-  consumers, these foods feel less experi-
           culture may be perfectly normal in   uine anxiety about inequality.   mental than they might have a decade
           another.                                                        ago.
             Scientists often point to insects as   Plant-based eating goes   Still, not everyone is convinced.
           one possible solution to future food   mainstream                  Some nutrition experts argue that
           shortages. Crickets require far less water   Compared to insects, plant-based   heavily processed plant-based foods
           and land than cattle, while also produc-  proteins have found acceptance much   shouldn’t automatically be considered
           ing fewer emissions. They’re rich in   faster.                  healthy. Others feel uncomfortable with
           protein, iron and vitamins.       Restaurants now serve mushroom   long ingredient lists and artificial flavor-
             On paper, the logic is convincing.   burgers, soy kebabs and oat-milk coffees   ing.
             Emotionally, however, the situation is   almost everywhere. Fast-food chains   And honestly, some products simply

           6                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[and health data could become common.
                                                                           Vertical farms inside cities may grow
                                                                           vegetables year-round. Smart kitchens
                                                                           may help reduce food waste automati-
                                                                           cally.
                                                                              Yet even with all these changes,
                                                                           people will probably remain emotionally
                                                                           attached to comfort food.
                                                                              Someone somewhere will still crave
                                                                           homemade soup, fresh bread or street
                                                                           food prepared the old-fashioned way.
                                                                           Technology may transform ingredients,
                                                                           but the emotional role of meals will
                                                                           likely remain unchanged.
                                                                              That’s why conversations about fu-
                                                                           ture diets feel so emotional. They touch
                                                                           something deeply human.
                                                                              Nobody wants culture reduced to sta-
                                                                           tistics and carbon calculations. Yet ig-
                                                                           noring environmental realities also
                                                                           carries consequences.

                                                                           Learning to eat differently
                                                                              The future of food may depend less
                                                                           on science alone and more on storytell-
                                                                           ing.
                                                                              People rarely change habits because
                                                                           of facts and charts. They change when
                                                                           new behaviors begin to feel normal. A
                                                                           child raised on plant-based school
                                                                           lunches may never see them as unusual.
                                                                           A teenager watching athletes promote
                                                                           alternative proteins may become curious
           don’t taste convincing yet.     synthetic food production? Entire rural   enough to try them.
             That matters more than people admit.   communities depend on livestock farm-  History shows how quickly food cul-
           Consumers may care about sustainabil-  ing. Food transitions don’t only change   tures can evolve. Tomatoes were once
           ity, but they also want food that feels   diets. They change jobs, economies and   feared in parts of Europe. Sushi was
           satisfying after a long day.    identities.                     considered strange in many Western
                                             In some countries, debates around   countries only a few decades ago.
           Meat without the farm           cultivated meat have already become   What feels unfamiliar today may
             Perhaps the most controversial idea   political. Food carries symbolism. A   eventually become ordinary.
           is cultivated meat, sometimes called lab-  steak isn’t just protein. It can represent   By 2050, dinner tables could look
           grown meat.                     tradition, masculinity, celebration or   very different from those of today. There
             Unlike plant-based substitutes, culti-  family history.       may be more sustainable ingredients,
           vated meat is real animal meat produced   Changing those emotional connec-  fewer assumptions about where protein
           from animal cells rather than slaugh-  tions may take generations.   comes from and greater awareness about
           tered animals. Scientists grow the cells                        the environmental cost of food choices.
           in controlled environments until edible   Will the future diet be the same   But there will also be resistance, nos-
           tissue forms.                   everywhere?                     talgia and debate. Probably plenty of it.
             Supporters believe this technology   Despite predictions of dramatic food   After all, eating has never been just
           could dramatically reduce animal suffer-  revolutions, the future diet may not be-  about survival. It’s about memory, ritual
           ing and environmental damage while al-  come completely uniform.   and connection.
           lowing people to continue eating famil-  Different regions will likely adapt in   And perhaps the future diet won’t be
           iar foods.                      different ways. Wealthier cities may em-  defined by one revolutionary invention
             But public reactions remain mixed.   brace cultivated foods more quickly,   at all. Maybe it will simply reflect a qui-
             For many consumers, laboratory-pro-  while rural communities continue rely-  eter shift in mindset, an understanding
           duced meat sounds unnatural. Even if   ing on traditional farming. Climate con-  that every meal connects people not
           scientists insist it’s safe, people often   ditions will also shape eating habits.   only to culture and family, but also to
           hesitate when food feels too engineered   Areas facing severe drought may adopt   the future of the planet itself.
           or unfamiliar. Trust becomes essential.   resource-efficient foods out of necessity   The next time someone asks,
             There are also economic concerns.   rather than preference.   “What’s for dinner?”, the answer may
             What happens to traditional farmers   Technology will influence diets too.   reveal far more about the world than we
           if large corporations begin dominating   Personalized nutrition based on genetics   realize. ■

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                  7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SPECIAL REPORT







































           The digital trap


           Life in a world                                                 being unreachable almost feels irrespon-
                                                                           sible. We wake up to alarms on our
                                                                           phones and fall asleep beside them.
                                                                           Work follows us home. Friends expect
                                                                           instant replies. News alerts interrupt
                                                                           dinner. Social media fills the tiny pauses
           that never                                                      tion, or simply looking out of a window.
                                                                           that once belonged to boredom, reflec-
                                                                              Technology promised connection and
                                                                           in many ways, it delivered. Families
                                                                           separated by oceans can now talk every
                                                                           day. Remote work has opened opportu-
           switches off                                                    nities for people who once had none.
                                                                           Students can learn almost anything on-
                                                                           line. Emergencies can be handled faster.
                                                                           The digital world has made life more ef-
                                                                           ficient, more informed and sometimes
           We were promised a world more connected than ever               more compassionate.
                                                                              But somewhere along the way, con-
           before. So why do so many people feel mentally                  stant connectivity stopped feeling like
           exhausted and emotionally distant? By Riya Verma                freedom. For many people, it started
                                                                           feeling like pressure.
                                                                           When the brain never truly rests
              ust one more notification. That’s   friend’s meme, then opening a work chat   Human beings were never designed
              what Maya told herself at 1:17 in   again because the green dot beside her   to process this much information all the
           Jthe morning while staring at the   manager’s name made her anxious. By   time.
           blue light of her phone. She had planned   the time she finally put the phone down,   A generation ago, most people had
           to sleep early after another draining   her mind was racing.    natural boundaries in their day. Work
           workday, but one unread message turned   The strange thing is, Maya isn’t un-  ended when they left the office. News
           into checking emails, then scrolling   usual. Millions of people now live in a   arrived in newspapers or on television at
           through headlines, then replying to a   world where silence feels unfamiliar and   fixed hours. If someone wasn’t home,

           8                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[sages has become surprisingly challeng-
                                                                           ing for many.
                                                                              Some teachers now speak openly
                                                                           about students struggling to sustain at-
                                                                           tention in classrooms. Employers com-
                                                                           plain about declining focus while simul-
                                                                           taneously expecting workers to remain
                                                                           constantly available online. It’s a contra-
                                                                           diction that modern professionals know
                                                                           too well.
                                                                              You’re expected to be productive,
                                                                           creative, emotionally balanced and al-
                                                                           ways reachable. That’s exhausting.
                                                                           Burnout doesn’t always look
                                                                           dramatic
























                                           thing urgent might happen the moment   Burnout is often imagined as a com-
                                           they stop checking their devices. And   plete breakdown, but in reality, it can
                                           honestly, sometimes something does.   look painfully ordinary.
                                           That’s part of the trap.           It’s the employee answering emails
           you simply waited.                                              from bed before sunrise. The freelancer
             Now there’s no real “off” switch.   The attention economy and the   who feels guilty taking a Sunday after-
             A marketing executive in Mumbai   exhaustion behind it        noon off. The young professional who
           checks campaign updates during dinner.   Most digital platforms are designed   keeps saying “I’m fine” while secretly
           A university student in London revises   to keep people engaged for as long as   feeling emotionally numb.
           for exams while responding to group   possible. Notifications are carefully   Remote work blurred the line be-
           chats every few minutes. A father in To-  timed. Infinite scrolling removes natural   tween professional and personal life
           ronto sits beside his child at the play-  stopping points. Algorithms learn emo-  even further. During the global shift to-
           ground while mentally drafting replies   tional triggers with remarkable preci-  ward working from home, many people
           to Slack notifications.         sion.                           initially celebrated the flexibility. No
             The body may be resting, but the   Attention has become a business   commute. More comfort. More freedom.
           mind often isn’t.               model.                             Yet over time, living rooms became
             Psychologists have increasingly   There’s a reason people often pick up   offices and office hours stretched end-
           linked excessive screen exposure and   their phones without even realizing it.   lessly.
           digital overload to anxiety, sleep disrup-  The habit is deeply conditioned. Tiny   For some workers, especially
           tion, burnout and reduced attention span.   bursts of information, likes, messages   younger employees trying to prove
           What makes it difficult is that the stress   and updates create short moments of   themselves, online visibility became a
           rarely arrives dramatically. It builds   stimulation that the brain begins to   form of performance. If they responded
           slowly, quietly. A person becomes more   crave. But constant stimulation comes   quickly, they appeared committed. If
           irritable. Sleep gets lighter. Concentra-  with a hidden cost.   they disconnected, they worried about
           tion weakens. Small breaks disappear.   People are finding it harder to focus   seeming lazy or unavailable. The pres-
           Even moments of relaxation start feeling   deeply on one thing. Reading long ar-  sure isn’t always spoken aloud, but it
           oddly restless.                 ticles feels difficult. Conversations are   lingers.
             Many people describe an almost con-  interrupted by glances at screens. Even   In hyper-connected workplaces,
           stant sense of anticipation, as if some-  watching a film without checking mes-  people often carry the emotional weight

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                  9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[sing something important. Others worry
                                                                           that stepping back from online spaces
                                                                           could damage their careers or social
                                                                           lives. And to be fair, those fears aren’t
                                                                           completely irrational.
                                                                              Modern systems reward responsive-
                                                                           ness. Fast replies are praised. Visibility
                                                                           creates opportunities. Online networking
                                                                           shapes careers.
                                                                              Technology itself isn’t the villain
                                                                           here. Most people aren’t asking to aban-
                                                                           don modern life or throw away their de-
                                                                           vices. The issue is balance and balance
                                                                           becomes difficult when entire industries
                                                                           profit from keeping human attention
                                                                           permanently occupied.
                                                                           Relearning how to be unavailable
                                                                              There are small signs that people are
                                                                           beginning to push back.
                                                                              Some companies now encourage em-
                                                                           ployees to avoid after-hours communi-
                                                                           cation. Schools in certain countries are
                                                                           experimenting with phone-free class-
                                                                           rooms. Families create screen-free
                                                                           dinner rules. Young adults increasingly
                                                                           speak about protecting mental health in
                                                                           ways previous generations rarely did.
                                                                              Even tiny habits can matter. Turning
                                                                           off non-essential notifications. Taking
                                                                           walks without a phone. Reading without
                                                                           multitasking. Allowing boredom to exist
                                                                           again.
                                                                              These actions sound simple, maybe
                                                                           even trivial, but they restore something
           of being “on call” even when nobody   Children are growing up observing   important: uninterrupted human atten-
           explicitly asks them to. That invisible   adults who rarely disconnect. Teachers   tion. Because attention is more than pro-
           stress accumulates.             and child psychologists increasingly   ductivity. It shapes relationships, mem-
                                           worry about how this shapes emotional   ory, creativity and emotional stability.
           Relationships are changing too   development, patience, empathy and   And perhaps that’s the real question
             Connectivity has transformed human   communication habits.    modern society must confront. If every
           relationships in complicated ways.   A child trying to speak to a parent   spare moment is occupied, when do
             On one hand, digital communication   who keeps glancing at notifications no-  people actually process their lives?
           helps people maintain contact across   tices more than adults realize. So does a   Late one evening, Maya finally
           continents and time zones. Long-dis-  partner.                  began leaving her phone outside the
           tance friendships survive because of                            bedroom. At first, she hated it. She kept
           video calls and messaging apps. Parents   The strange guilt of slowing down   imagining missed messages and unfin-
           can see their children instantly. Support   Perhaps one of the saddest con-  ished conversations. But after a few
           networks exist online for people who   sequences of constant connectivity is   weeks, she noticed something unex-
           once felt isolated.             that rest itself now feels uncomfortable   pected. Her thoughts became quieter.
             Still, many people quietly admit they   for many people.         She slept longer. She started reading
           feel lonelier than ever.          Moments that once allowed mental   again. Some mornings, she simply sat
             A group of friends may sit together at   recovery are quickly filled with scroll-  near the window with coffee before
           a café while each person scrolls through   ing. Waiting in a queue, sitting on a   opening a screen.
           separate feeds. Couples share homes but   train, even walking alone often becomes   Nothing about her life became per-
           compete with screens for attention. Par-  another opportunity to consume infor-  fect. The world remained noisy. Work
           ents document childhood moments on-  mation. People say they’re over-  still demanded attention. Notifications
           line while occasionally missing the mo-  whelmed, yet silence can feel strangely   still waited. But she no longer felt
           ment itself.                    unsettling.                     owned by them.
             There’s a subtle emotional difference   Some individuals who attempt digital   Maybe that’s what people are really
           between being connected and being   detoxes describe withdrawal-like symp-  searching for now. Not complete discon-
           present. One offers access. The other   toms during the first few days. They feel   nection, but permission to breathe inside
           offers attention.               anxious, disconnected, or afraid of mis-  a world that rarely stops talking. ■

           10                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY






































                                                                           fire. Historians often describe the con-
           Light                                                           trol of fire as one of humanity’s greatest
                                                                           turning points. It changed far more than
                                                                           cooking habits. Fire extended the day
                                                                           beyond sunset, allowing people to com-
           The force that                                                  municate, plan and tell stories after dark.
                                                                           Communities formed around its warmth.
                                                                              Imagine that moment thousands of
                                                                           years ago. Beyond the fire lay darkness,
                                                                           cold and danger. Inside the circle of or-
           built civilization                                              safety. That glow did more than protect
                                                                           ange light, there was conversation and
                                                                           people. It connected them.
                                                                              Over time, civilizations learned to
                                                                           shape light in more sophisticated ways.
           Different moments. Same force. Perhaps that’s why               Oil lamps illuminated ancient streets.
                                                                           Temples in Egypt were designed so sun-
           light remains one of humanity’s most enduring                   light entered sacred chambers only at
                                                                           particular times of the year. In India and
           symbols. By Karan Malhotra                                      China, lamps became woven into rituals
                                                                           and festivals. Light slowly became a
                                                                           symbol of hope, wisdom and spirituality.
                                                                              Humans are visual creatures. We un-
                  hat would happen if the   It has always been emotional too. For   derstand the world largely through what
                  world suddenly went dark? It   ancient humans, light meant safety. For   we see. In many ways, light gave civ-
           Wsounds dramatic, almost cine-  sailors, it meant direction. For artists, in-  ilization not just survival, but meaning.
           matic, but the question reveals some-  spiration. For scientists, discovery. Even
           thing important about human history.   today, in cities glowing with billboards   Light and the rise of knowledge
           Nearly every stage of civilization, from   and phone screens, people still light can-  For centuries, the study of light trans-
           the first cave fires to modern fiber optic   dles during grief, prayer and celebration.   formed science itself. One of the earliest
           networks, has been shaped by light. We   Somehow, light continues to feel deeply   breakthroughs came from
           wake with it, work beneath it, celebrate   human.               entity["people","Ibn al-
           around it and depend on it in ways we                           Haytham","Islamic scholar and pioneer
           rarely notice.                  The first flame                 of optics"], whose work on vision and
             Light has never been only scientific.   Long before electricity, there was   optics challenged long-held assumptions

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[“


                                                                             Civilization may

                                                                             have begun the

                                                                             moment humans

                                                                             learned how to
                                                                             keep a small flame

                                                                             alive through the

                                                                             night.”
































           about how humans see. His experiments   doctors use lasers for delicate surgeries.   But artificial light also changed
           helped establish principles that later in-  Knowledge still travels through illumina-  human behavior in complicated ways.
           fluenced modern scientific methods.   tion.                     People became less connected to natural
             Then came telescopes. When en-                               rhythms. Today, millions of children
           tity["people","Galileo Galilei","Ital-  The glow that changed cities   growing up in large cities rarely see a
           ian astronomer and physicist"] ob-  For most of history, night limited   sky filled with stars because of light
           served the night sky through a telescope,   human activity. Cities grew quieter after   pollution. The same invention that ex-
           humanity’s understanding of the universe   sunset because darkness carried risk.   panded human possibilities also dis-
           changed forever. Suddenly, the heavens   Then electric lighting transformed urban   tanced people from the night sky that
           no longer appeared perfect and unchang-  life.                  inspired poets, philosophers and ex-
           ing. There were moons orbiting Jupiter   When streetlights appeared in the 19th   plorers for centuries. There’s something
           and mountains on the Moon.      century, factories could operate longer   slightly sad about that.
             Microscopes brought another rev-  hours, businesses stayed open later and
           olution. Tiny organisms invisible to the   public spaces became safer. Nightlife,   Capturing light, creating culture
           naked eye suddenly became visible   modern entertainment and late-working   Light shaped culture as deeply as it
           through manipulated light. Diseases once   cities emerged because darkness no   shaped science. Photography is essen-
           blamed on mystery or superstition slowly   longer controlled daily routines. The in-  tially the art of capturing light. Early
           became understandable.          candescent bulb, often associated with   photographs were blurry and difficult to
             In a way, scientific progress has al-  entity["people","Thomas   produce, yet they changed human mem-
           ways depended on learning how to see   Edison","American inventor"] though   ory forever. Suddenly, ordinary mo-
           more clearly.                   developed through the work of many in-  ments could survive time.
             Even today, observatories search for   ventors, became a unique symbol of pro-  A grandparent’s portrait. A child
           faint light from distant galaxies, while   gress itself.        running through rain. A soldier writing

           12                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             The same light that
                                                                             once guided sailors

                                                                             across oceans now
                                                                             carries billions of

                                                                             digital conversations
                                                                             through glass fibers.”



           home during war. Such memories en-
           dure because someone learned how to
           preserve light on paper.
             Cinema took the relationship even
           further. Moving images projected
           through beams of light became power-
           ful enough to shape public imagination,
           politics and culture across the world.
             Painters and architects also became
           fascinated with light. The Impression-
           ists studied how sunlight transformed
           landscapes through the day, while mod-
           ern architects learned that natural light
           affects mood and mental well-being.
             Even now, people instinctively seek
           bright rooms and open windows. Per-
           haps humans still carry an ancient mem-
           ory of gathering around fire.   tricity, offering cleaner energy in a   has shaped how humans live, communi-
                                           warming world.                  cate, worship, create and dream. And its
           The invisible light powering      Yet technology has complicated hu-  influence continues quietly every day.
           modern life                     manity’s relationship with light too.   Tonight, somewhere, a student will
             Much of today’s civilization depends   People now spend hours staring at   study under a desk lamp. A surgeon
           on forms of light people never actually   glowing screens late into the night. Ar-  will rely on laser precision in an operat-
           see. Fiber optic cables carry enormous   tificial brightness surrounds modern   ing room. An astronomer will watch an-
           amounts of information through pulses   life, but many individuals feel mentally   cient starlight arrive through a tele-
           of light. Every video call, online pay-  exhausted and disconnected from na-  scope. A family facing a power cut will
           ment and streamed film travels this   ture.                     light candles and sit together talking.
           way.                              Perhaps civilization has reached a   Different moments. Same force. Per-
             It’s remarkable when you think   stage where it must rediscover balance.   haps that’s why light remains one of hu-
           about it. The same force that once illu-                        manity’s most enduring symbols. Not
           minated caves now powers global com-  A civilization written in light   because it solves every problem, but be-
           munication.                       Human history could almost be re-  cause it keeps guiding people forward.
             Medicine also relies heavily on light.   told through the ways people learned to   Civilization is often explained through
           Infrared imaging helps detect disease.   create, study and control light. From   wars, empires and inventions. But
           Ultraviolet light sterilizes equipment.   campfires to lighthouses, stained glass   maybe its real story is simpler than that.
           Solar panels convert sunlight into elec-  windows to smartphone screens, light   A small flame pushing back the dark. ■

















           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[EXCLUSIVE






























                                                                          The Last Day



                                           If the world ended



                  hat would you do if you knew
                  you had only one day left?
           WIt’s the kind of question                            tomorrow…
           people usually avoid. Too uncomfort-
           able. Too dramatic. Yet it slips into the
           mind after a tragedy, a frightening head-
           line or the sudden loss of someone we   The thought of the world ending tomorrow sounds
           love. For a moment, the future no longer
           feels guaranteed. And then another   terrifying, until it forces us to ask what truly matters
           thought follows: if the world truly ended
           tomorrow, how would people spend                                   today. By Aarav Sharma
           today?
             Not as nations or political groups.
           Simply as human beings. The answer   dark humor and conspiracy theories.   Airports would fill with people trying
           might reveal more about humanity than   Memes would appear within minutes be-  to go home. Not for business meetings
           history books ever could.       cause humor is often how people handle   or holidays. Home.
                                           fear.                              A son working abroad would call his
           The first reaction: disbelief     But beneath the noise, something   mother repeatedly. A student living over-
             Human beings are remarkably skilled   quieter would begin. People would start   seas would want to hear her father’s
           at denial. During disasters and crises, re-  reaching for each other.   voice again. Divorced couples might sit
           searchers have often noticed that many                          together for dinner because resentment
           people continue ordinary routines at   Home would suddenly matter   suddenly feels too small.
           first. They check their phones, make tea,   again                  Across cultures, the details would
           answer emails. Routine feels safer than   Modern life has trained people to live   differ, but the instinct would remain
           fear.                           at a distance. Families are scattered ac-  similar. In Italy, families might gather
             If the world had exactly twenty-four   ross countries. Friends communicate   around long meals. In Japan, some could
           hours left, disbelief would arrive before   through hurried messages. Parents are   seek silence in temples or gardens. In
           panic.                          distracted by work, children by screens.   India, prayers would rise from homes,
             People would refresh news websites,   But if time became painfully limited,   mosques, churches, temples and gurud-
           hoping the warning was wrong. Social   priorities would rearrange themselves   waras.
           media would explode with arguments,   quickly.                     And somewhere, millions of people

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[“


            In humanity’s final

            hours, people

            would probably

            search for each
            other long before

            they searched for

            answers.”



                                                                              For years, doctors and caregivers
                                                                           working with terminally ill patients have
                                                                           noticed a pattern. Near the end of life,
                                                                           people rarely talk about status or posses-
                                                                           sions. They talk about relationships, un-
                                                                           finished conversations, forgiveness and
                                                                           simple moments that once seemed ordi-
                                                                           nary.
                                                                              Maybe that’s why end-of-the-world
                                                                           stories fascinate us so deeply. They are
                                                                           not really about destruction. They are
                                                                           mirrors.
                                                                              They expose what matters when dis-
                                                                           traction disappears. Religious com-
                                                                           munities would gather. Young people
                                                                           might organize concerts or candlelight
                                                                           vigils. In crowded cities, strangers could
                                                                           become unexpectedly kind.
                                                                              Something similar happened during
                                           would fade. Stock markets, office pol-  the pandemic years. Even while fear
                                           itics, luxury brands and follower counts   spread, there were stories of neighbors
                                           would suddenly seem fragile, even ab-  helping each other, healthcare workers
                                           surd.                           comforting isolated patients and musi-
                                             Would anyone care about quarterly   cians performing from balconies.
                                           targets if the sky itself was collapsing?   Human beings are imperfect. Selfish
                                           Probably not.                   sometimes, cruel sometimes. But history
                                             A final day would force people into   also shows that people often become
                                           the present tense. The vacation post-  deeply compassionate when faced with
                                           poned for years.                shared vulnerability.
                                             The apology never made. The guitar
                                           left untouched in the corner. The child   The digital world would feel
                                           asking a parent to look up from a laptop.   strangely empty
                                             Modern culture encourages endless   There’s another uncomfortable truth
                                           preparation for the future. Work harder.   about modern life. Many people spend
                                           Save more. Plan constantly. There’s   more time documenting experiences
                                           logic in that, of course. But many people   than fully living them. Meals are photo-
                                           become so busy building life that they   graphed before they’re tasted. Vacations
                                           forget to experience it.        become content. Even grief sometimes
           would quietly think the same thing: “I                          turns into public performance online.
           wish we had spent more time together.”   Some people would seek meaning   If humanity truly faced its final day,
                                             Not everyone would spend the last   that habit might suddenly feel meaning-
           The things we chase would lose   day the same way. Some would pray.   less.
           meaning                         Others would celebrate loudly. Some   No one would care about perfect cap-
             Money would still exist tomorrow   would sit quietly near the sea or walk   tions or carefully edited images. People
           morning, technically. But its power   through familiar streets.   would want reality instead. Real voices.

           16                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[“


            The end of the

            world would not

            create meaning, it

            would simply
            expose what

            mattered all along.”


































                                           from a balcony. Sharing tea with some-  confuses productivity with purpose.
                                           one you love.                      Maybe that’s the uncomfortable les-
                                             The digital age has connected hu-  son hidden inside the question itself.
                                           manity in extraordinary ways, but it has   People do not need the end of the world
                                           also left many people emotionally ex-  to start living differently. Deep down,
                                           hausted. Constantly informed, rarely   they already know what matters most.
                                           present.                           They just assume there will always
                                             A final day might remind the world   be more time. Hopefully there will be.
           Real touch. Real presence.      that attention is one of the purest forms   Still, the question is worth asking once
             And perhaps that realization would   of love. To truly listen. To truly sit with   in a while. Who would we call first?
           be both heartbreaking and strangely   someone. To stop rushing. These things   Where would we go? What would sud-
           freeing. Imagine opening social media   sound small until time runs out.   denly stop mattering?
           on humanity’s final day.                                           Because in the end, life has always
             At first there would be chaos. End-  What the last day would reveal   been uncertain. We simply became very
           less livestreams, emotional confessions   about us              good at pretending otherwise.
           and frantic reactions. Politicians promis-  Perhaps the most surprising thing is   So maybe tonight someone will close
           ing calm. Influencers trying to process   this: the world ending tomorrow would   their laptop a little earlier. Maybe a
           fear in real time.              not suddenly create love, grief or mean-  daughter will phone her parents. Maybe
             But eventually, something unusual   ing. Those things already exist. The   an exhausted worker will step outside
           might happen. People could start putting   deadline would simply strip away illu-  and notice the evening sky for the first
           their phones down. Because no screen   sion.                    time in weeks.
           can replace physical presence.    It would reveal how deeply people   Not because the world is ending to-
             A hug from a parent. Sitting beside a   need connection. How fragile modern   morrow. But because one day, for each
           friend without speaking. Watching rain   life really is. And how often humanity   of us, time quietly runs out. ■

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[INSIGHT




































           WELLNESS OVER APPEARANCE


           The new beauty                                                  comfortable in one’s own body. Not per-

                                                                           fect. Just real.
                                                                              And honestly, that change may be
                                                                           one of the most important cultural shifts
                                                                           of this generation.
           revolution                                                      From beauty routines to emotional

                                                                           survival
                                                                              For many people, beauty routines
                                                                           once promised control. A new cream,
           People are realizing that wellness is not separate from         diet, fitness trend, or makeup technique
           beauty. It shapes it. By Pooja Mehta                            offered hope that confidence could
                                                                           somehow be purchased or applied.
                                                                              Sometimes those routines were en-
                                                                           joyable and creative. There’s nothing in-
                  hat if the healthiest person in   being observed, rated and compared.   herently wrong with makeup, skincare,
                  the room isn’t the one with   But something has shifted. Slowly at   or wanting to look good. The problem
           Wperfect skin, a tiny waist, or a   first, then all at once.    began when appearance became tied too
           carefully filtered Instagram feed?   Today, more people are asking differ-  closely to self-worth.
             A few years ago, beauty conver-  ent questions. Am I sleeping enough?   College students now speak openly
           sations often began with appearance and   Why am I anxious all the time? Why   about “pretty pressure,” the constant
           ended there too. Better hair. Flatter   does self-care feel like another competi-  feeling that they must look camera-
           stomach. Sharper jawline. Fewer wrin-  tion? Why do I look “fine” online but   ready even during ordinary moments.
           kles. Social media amplified it all, turn-  feel emotionally drained offline?   Office workers describe editing photos
           ing ordinary faces into polished digital   The modern beauty conversation is   before posting them because unfiltered
           performances. Many people, especially   no longer only about appearance. In-  images feel risky. Teenagers compare
           young adults, quietly carried the ex-  creasingly, it’s about wellness, balance,   themselves to influencers whose images
           hausting feeling that they were always   mental health, confidence and feeling   are often altered beyond recognition.

           18                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[“


                                                                             The new beauty

                                                                             ideal isn’t

                                                                             perfection

                                                                             anymore, it’s peace
                                                                             of mind.”



                                                                           this moment. Wellness is not always dra-
                                                                           matic transformation. Sometimes it’s
                                                                           simply the end of constant self-criticism.

                                                                           Men are entering the conversation
                                                                           too
                                                                              Beauty pressure has long affected
                                                                           women more visibly, but men are in-
                                                                           creasingly confronting similar struggles.
                                                                              Fitness culture, grooming standards
                                                                           and social media trends have created un-
                                                                           realistic expectations for male bodies as
                                                                           well. Lean muscles, flawless skin, lux-
                                                                           ury lifestyles, emotional control. The
                                                                           modern masculine image can be just as
                                                                           restrictive.
                                                                              Many young men now openly dis-
                                                                           cuss burnout from trying to maintain im-
                                                                           possible standards online. Some speak
                                                                           about steroid use in gym culture. Others
                                                                           admit they feel uncomfortable express-
             The emotional cost has been signifi-  bracing softer, more realistic goals. Get-  ing insecurity because vulnerability still
           cant.                           ting enough sleep. Drinking water.   carries stigma.
             Studies across several countries have   Walking without obsessing over calo-  Interestingly, wellness culture has
           linked excessive social media compari-  ries. Taking breaks from social media.   opened space for broader emotional con-
           son with anxiety, body dissatisfaction,   Going to therapy. Learning boundaries.   versations among men too. Meditation
           low self-esteem and loneliness, espe-  Saying no without guilt.   apps, therapy platforms, support groups
           cially among young users. Mental health   These habits rarely create viral   and mental health podcasts are drawing
           professionals say many patients no   content, but they improve lives in qui-  audiences that would have seemed un-
           longer separate appearance from iden-  eter ways.               likely a decade ago.
           tity. If they don’t feel attractive, they as-  Take the growing popularity of   The idea that caring for emotional
           sume they are failing socially too.   phrases like “body neutrality.” Unlike   well-being is “weak” is gradually losing
             That’s where the newer wellness   body positivity, which encourages lov-  ground.
           movement enters the picture.    ing one’s appearance, body neutrality   And perhaps that’s part of the new
             Instead of asking, “How do I look?”   focuses less on appearance altogether.   beauty revolution as well. Not looking
           more people are beginning to ask, “How   The body becomes something to care for   invincible all the time.
           do I feel?” It sounds simple, but cul-  rather than constantly evaluate.
           turally, it changes everything.   For someone recovering from years   Brands are adapting, though not
                                           of insecurity, that idea can feel surpris-  always perfectly
           The rise of softer goals        ingly liberating.                  The beauty and wellness industries
             Not long ago, wellness itself became   A 24-year-old marketing executive in   have noticed the shift. Advertisements
           commercialized. Social feeds filled with   Mumbai described deleting beauty   increasingly feature diverse skin tones,
           green juices, expensive yoga retreats   filters from her phone after realizing she   body types, ages and disabilities. Cam-
           and impossible morning routines begin-  no longer recognized her own face in   paigns now speak about authenticity,
           ning at 5 a.m. Even “healthy living”   photographs. “I didn’t suddenly become   confidence and self-acceptance.
           started to look like a performance.   confident,” she admitted in an online   Some of these changes are meaning-
             Now there’s growing resistance to   discussion forum. “But I stopped pun-  ful. Others feel carefully calculated.
           that pressure too.              ishing myself every day.”          Consumers today are quick to rec-
             Young people are increasingly em-  That sentence captures the mood of   ognize performative messaging. A com-

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[pany cannot realistically preach self-
           love while heavily editing every cam-
           paign image. Young audiences, espe-
           cially Gen Z consumers, tend to value
           transparency more than polished perfec-
           tion.
             Several brands have responded by re-
           ducing retouching, featuring real cus-
           tomer stories, or supporting mental
           health initiatives. Even fashion cam-
           paigns are becoming slightly less rigid
           about idealized beauty.
             Still, contradictions remain.
             The same platforms promoting well-
           ness often continue rewarding unattain-
           able aesthetics through algorithms and
           advertising. Influencer culture still
           thrives on aspiration. Cosmetic proce-
           dures are increasingly normalized
           among younger age groups.
             So the shift toward wellness is real,
           but it isn’t complete. Society is still ne-
           gotiating what healthy beauty standards
           actually look like.

           Digital life and the exhaustion of
           being visible
             Part of the reason this conversation
           feels urgent is because modern life
           rarely allows people to disappear.
             Previous generations could leave
           school or work and largely escape social
           judgment for the day. Today, visibility
           follows people home through phones,
           group chats, stories, video calls and end-
           less scrolling.
             There’s pressure to look attractive
           during workouts, vacations, casual out-  may not be external at all. It’s internal.   now sit beside conversations about skin-
           ings and even moments of vulnerability.   People are beginning to understand   care and style.
           Ordinary life has become strangely per-  that wellness is deeply connected to   People are realizing that wellness is
           formative.                      beauty in ways older conversations often   not separate from beauty. It shapes it.
             Psychologists often describe this as   ignored. Chronic stress shows up physi-
           “continuous self-presentation.” People   cally. Loneliness affects sleep. Anxiety   A quieter kind of confidence
           are not just living experiences anymore.   changes posture, energy, concentration   Not every revolution arrives loudly.
           They are also documenting, editing and   and confidence.           Some begin in ordinary moments. A
           presenting them.                  Meanwhile, emotionally healthy   teenager posting an unfiltered photo-
             That can become exhausting.   people often radiate qualities no cos-  graph for the first time. A mother choos-
             In response, many users are inten-  metic product can manufacture fully:   ing rest over relentless productivity. A
           tionally pulling back. Some keep private   warmth, calmness, humor, kindness,   young man finally admitting he’s strug-
           accounts with close friends only. Others   presence.            gling emotionally. A friend deciding not
           post less frequently or take social media   That doesn’t mean appearance no   to apologize for gaining weight.
           breaks altogether. A growing number of   longer matters. Humans will probably   These moments rarely make head-
           people are rediscovering offline hobbies   always care about aesthetics to some de-  lines, but together they reveal something
           that have nothing to do with appearance   gree. Fashion, grooming and self-ex-  important. Many people are tired of per-
           at all.                         pression can be joyful parts of identity.   forming perfection.
             Reading. Gardening. Painting. Run-  But increasingly, beauty is being   Maybe the future of beauty is not
           ning slowly without tracking every sta-  viewed less as perfection and more as   about becoming someone else at all.
           tistic.                         alignment. Looking like yourself. Feel-  Maybe it’s about feeling whole enough
             Tiny rebellions, maybe. But mean-  ing emotionally stable. Having energy.   to stop hiding.
           ingful ones.                    Feeling safe in your own skin.     That idea feels less glamorous than
                                             Perhaps that explains why conver-  old beauty myths. But it also feels more
           Redefining what beauty means    sations about therapy, burnout, bound-  human. And perhaps that’s why it’s last-
             The most powerful aspect of this shift   aries, nutrition, sleep and mindfulness   ing. ■

           20                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[PROFILE































           Remembering Gayatri Devi                                        A face the world wanted to frame

                                                                              In the 1960s, Western fashion maga-
           The most                                                        women from beyond Europe. Gayatri
                                                                           zines became fascinated with royal
                                                                           Devi arrived at precisely the right mo-
                                                                           ment for global media hungry for exotic
                                                                           sophistication. Her photographs ap-
           beautiful woman                                                 and America, often accompanied by lan-
                                                                           peared in publications across Europe
                                                                           guage that now feels revealing in itself.
                                                                           She was presented as mysterious yet
                                                                           modern, regal yet approachable. The
           in the world?                                                   shaped her into an idea.
                                                                           world admired her beauty, but it also
                                                                              That idea reflected the beauty stan-
                                                                           dards of the time. Slim figure. Fair skin.
                                                                           Delicate features. Controlled poise.
           Perhaps her greatest charm was that she never                   Even today, many of the surviving mag-
                                                                           azine covers show how beauty was
           seemed to be performing for attention. By Ishita Desai          frequently tied to aristocracy and privi-
                                                                           lege. Gayatri Devi fit that visual vocabu-
                                                                           lary perfectly, though perhaps uninten-
                  hat makes a woman unforget-  the third Maharani consort of Jaipur, be-  tionally. She became less a person in
                  table? Is it the symmetry of a   came one of the most photographed In-  those narratives and more a symbol of
           Wface, the elegance of a photo-  dian royals of the twentieth century. To   refinement. Still, reducing her to beauty
           graph, or something quieter that lingers   many outside India, she represented an   alone misses something important.
           long after the camera flash fades? For   image that felt almost cinematic. Pearl
           decades, the name of Gayatri Devi car-  necklaces, chiffon saris, calm eyes, im-  Beyond the photographs
           ried that strange magnetism. She was   peccable posture. The kind of elegance   People who encountered Gayatri
           often described by international maga-  that seemed untouched by time. Yet be-  Devi often spoke not only about her ap-
           zines as one of the most beautiful   hind those famous portraits was a far   pearance but about her presence. There
           women in the world, a title that sounded   more layered woman, one who moved   was confidence in the way she carried
           glamorous on the surface but also re-  through politics, social reform, royal ex-  herself and intelligence in the way she
           vealed much about the era that created it.   pectation and public scrutiny with un-  spoke. She studied in London and
             Born on May 23, 1919, Gayatri Devi,   usual grace.            Switzerland, rode horses, played sports

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[and moved comfortably in diplomatic   vived changing
           circles. In newly independent India,   decades. She
           where princely identities were rapidly   seemed authentic
           changing, she adapted with remarkable   in a world increas-
           composure.                      ingly obsessed
             She also entered politics at a time   with performance.
           when few royal women did so publicly.   Her style also
           In 1962, she won a parliamentary elec-  continues to influence fashion conver-
           tion by a record margin, representing the   sations today. Designers still reference
           Swatantra Party. It surprised many who   her chiffon saris and understated jew-  “
           assumed royal women belonged only in   elry. Jaipur tourism campaigns regularly   The world admired
           palaces and charity events. Her political   invoke her era of royal elegance.
           success hinted at another kind of beauty   Younger audiences discovering her pho-
           altogether, one rooted in clarity, courage   tographs online often react with dis-  Gayatri Devi’s
           and discipline.                 belief. How could someone from
             And yet, public memory often circles   another century look so contemporary?   beauty, but history
           back to her face first.           But maybe the real fascination lies
             Maybe that's the contradiction at the   elsewhere. Gayatri Devi represented bal-  remembers her
           heart of celebrity culture, then and now.   ance. Tradition without rigidity. Glam-
           Women admired for their intelligence   our without loudness. Privilege com-  composure.”
           are still frequently introduced through   bined with public responsibility. That
           appearance. Gayatri Devi lived decades   combination feels rare now.
           before Instagram filters and viral trends,                         That may explain why Gayatri Devi
           but the mechanism feels oddly familiar.   A beauty larger than appearance   still resonates more than two decades
                                             Looking back at Gayatri Devi today   after her passing. Her photographs are
           The burden of being iconic      invites a more thoughtful question than   beautiful, certainly. But the lasting im-
             There is something slightly melan-  whether she was truly the world's most   pression comes from something harder
           cholic about being remembered prima-  beautiful woman. Perhaps the better   to capture. A calm intelligence. A meas-
           rily as beautiful. Beauty attracts atten-  question is why the world needed such   ured voice. A refusal to become merely
           tion, but it can also flatten identity. Old   titles in the first place.   ornamental.
           interviews with Gayatri Devi suggest   Beauty changes with generations.   And perhaps that's the quiet lesson
           she understood this quietly. She rarely   Standards evolve, sometimes dramati-  hidden beneath all those glamorous
           appeared eager to dramatize her image.   cally. What once defined perfection can   headlines. Real elegance is never only
           Even in formal portraits, there was re-  later feel narrow or exclusionary. Yet   about how someone looked. It's about
           straint. No excessive ornamentation. No   certain individuals remain admired be-  how they moved through the world and
           theatricality. Just stillness.   cause they carried more than outward   how the world remembered them after-
             Perhaps that's why her appeal sur-  charm. They carried dignity.   ward. ■

           22                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[ANALYSIS


































           Entertainment vs ethics

                                                                           parades. In some places, they are sym-
                                                                           bols of prestige. In others, they’re tied to
                                                                           cultural identity and livelihoods. Yet ani-
                                                                           mal welfare advocates increasingly ar-
           Should horses  gue that many of these practices survive
                                                                           not because horses need them, but be-
                                                                           cause humans are reluctant to let go.
           still perform?                                                  tivism versus tradition. It has become
                                                                              The debate is no longer emotional ac-
                                                                           more complicated than that.

                                                                           A partnership shaped by history
                                                                              Humans and horses have shared a re-
           The larger issue may not be about horses alone. It’s            lationship for thousands of years. Long

           about how modern societies define acceptable                    before engines and highways, horses
                                                                           carried people across continents, worked
           entertainment. By Rohan Kapoor                                  farms, delivered supplies and fought
                                                                           wars. Entire civilizations depended on
                                                                           them.
                                                                              That history matters because it
                 o they enjoy this? It’s a simple   ist photographs, another conversation   shapes how many people still view
                 question, the kind a child might   has quietly grown louder. Not about   horses today. For some communities,
           Dask while watching a horse pull   whether horses are beautiful or intelli-  horse processions at weddings or festi-
           a decorated carriage through crowded   gent, because almost everyone agrees   vals are not casual entertainment. They
           streets or trot in circles beneath circus   they are, but about whether human en-  are cultural memory. A white horse car-
           lights. Adults rarely answer it honestly.   tertainment still justifies the demands   rying a groom through crowded streets
           Tradition usually speaks first. Horses   placed on them.        may symbolize status, celebration and
           have always done this, people say.   Across the world, horses remain part   continuity with older generations.
           They’re trained for it. They’re strong   of public celebrations and leisure indus-  Tourist carriage rides operate in a
           animals. They’re treated well.   tries. They carry tourists through historic   similar emotional space. Visitors often
             But somewhere between the ap-  cities, pull grooms to wedding venues,   describe them as romantic or nostalgic.
           plause, the wedding music and the tour-  perform in shows, races and ceremonial   A slow ride through old city streets feels

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[“



            A horse may obey

            commands while

            still experiencing

            fear.”



           more personal than sitting in a taxi. In
           cities like New York, Vienna or Marra-
           kech, horse-drawn carriages have long
           been part of the urban image itself.
             And then there’s the equestrian
           world. Competitive riding communities
           often argue that trained horses enjoy
           structured activity, bonding and stimula-
           tion. Many riders genuinely love and
           care for their animals. Some spend more
           on veterinary care than they do on them-
           selves.
             This is what makes the debate diffi-
           cult. Not every horse involved in enter-
           tainment is abused. Not every owner is
           careless.
             Still, affection alone doesn’t erase
           ethical questions.

           When tradition becomes strain
             On a humid evening in South Asia,
           wedding bands play loudly while fire-
           works explode nearby. The groom sits   lapsing on a Manhattan street from ap-  dience. If a horse followed instructions
           upright on a decorated horse that inches   parent exhaustion. Images spread online,   calmly, people assumed it was comfort-
           nervously through traffic. Motorbikes   reigniting calls to ban horse-drawn car-  able. Modern animal behavior research
           weave past. Children scream excitedly.   riages altogether. Supporters of the in-  suggests the reality can be more com-
           Music blasts from portable speakers.   dustry argued the incident did not repre-  plex. Animals can become conditioned
             To spectators, it looks festive.   sent the entire profession. Critics said   to stressful environments without nec-
             To the horse, it may feel terrifying.   one collapse was enough to expose a   essarily thriving in them.
             Animal rescue groups across India,   deeper problem.             Circuses have faced this criticism
           Pakistan and parts of the Middle East   And perhaps that’s the uncomfortable   sharply. While elephants and wild cats
           have repeatedly documented injuries,   truth. Ethical questions rarely begin with   drew most public attention in earlier ani-
           dehydration and stress among horses   the best examples. They begin with the   mal rights campaigns, horses also re-
           used in weddings and street processions.   worst ones.          mained common performers in travel-
           Some animals work long hours in heat                            ling shows and staged spectacles. Critics
           with little water. Others are transported   The hidden cost of performance   argue that repetitive routines, transporta-
           poorly or controlled with painful equip-  Horses are prey animals by nature.   tion schedules and confinement prior-
           ment.                           Their instincts are built around alertness   itize entertainment over welfare.
             The same concerns appear in tourist   and escape. Loud noise, flashing lights   Some countries have already re-
           industries. In heavily visited cities, car-  and unpredictable crowds can create in-  sponded. Several European nations have
           riage horses often work on hard pave-  tense stress, even in trained animals.   introduced tighter regulations on ani-
           ment for hours each day, inhaling pollu-  Veterinarians and equine behavior   mals in circuses, while others have
           tion and navigating chaotic traffic.   specialists increasingly emphasize that   banned certain performances altogether.
           Welfare organizations have pointed to   physical injury is only part of the issue.   Public attitudes are changing too.
           cases of collapse, untreated wounds and   Chronic stress matters too.   A generation raised on wildlife doc-
           exhaustion.                       A horse may obey commands while   umentaries and social media rescue vi-
             Even where regulations exist, en-  still experiencing fear.   deos tends to ask different questions
           forcement can be inconsistent.    That distinction changes the conver-  than previous generations did. Young
             A horse named Ryder became a sym-  sation. For decades, humans often   audiences are more likely to see animals
           bol of this debate in New York after col-  judged animal welfare by visible obe-  as sentient companions rather than tools

           24                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[many spectacles that later generations
                                                                           questioned. Public animal fights, captive
                                                                           dolphin shows and certain zoo practices
                                                                           once attracted huge crowds. Over time,
                                                                           ethical awareness shifted.
                                                                              That shift often begins with discom-
                                                                           fort. A small moment. A horse flinching
                                                                           at fireworks. A tired animal breathing
                                                                           heavily in traffic. A child asking a diffi-
                                                                           cult question.
                                                                              And honestly, people are conflicted
                                                                           because they still love horses. Perhaps
                                                                           that’s exactly why the debate feels per-
                                                                           sonal.
                                                                              There’s something undeniably mov-
           for spectacle. For them, a horse dancing   ding horse owner may take pride in   ing about these animals. Their size, sen-
           beneath bright lights may not appear   keeping animals groomed and healthy.   sitivity and quiet intelligence create
           magical. It may look uneasy.      The problem is that good intentions   emotional connection almost instantly.
                                           don’t always guarantee humane con-  Watching a horse run freely across open
           The people behind the reins     ditions.                        land carries a very different feeling from
             Yet removing horses from entertain-  That’s why many welfare advocates   watching one perform for noise and
           ment industries is not a simple moral   now focus less on outrage and more on   profit.
           equation.                       standards. They argue for mandatory   Maybe the future lies somewhere be-
             Many families depend financially on   rest periods, veterinary inspections,   tween abolition and blind tradition. Not
           these traditions. Carriage drivers, horse   weight limits, bans on extreme weather   every interaction between humans and
           trainers, stable workers and ceremonial   work and stricter licensing. Others push   horses is cruel. Riding schools, therapy
           suppliers often have few alternative   for gradual replacement with mechani-  programs and ethical equestrian sports
           sources of income. In tourist cities,   cal or symbolic alternatives rather than   can provide meaningful relationships
           horse rides can support entire local   immediate bans.          when welfare genuinely comes first.
           economies.                        Some wedding planners have already   But entertainment built primarily on
             There is also genuine emotional con-  started offering vintage cars or electric   stress, overwork or fear deserves scru-
           nection involved. Speak to experienced   carriages instead of live horses. In parts   tiny, no matter how old the tradition may
           handlers and many will describe their   of Europe, virtual and theatrical per-  be.
           horses almost like relatives. They know   formances are increasingly replacing   In the end, the question isn’t whether
           their moods, habits and fears. Some res-  live animal acts. Cultural traditions, it   horses can perform.
           cue retired animals at personal cost.   turns out, can evolve.     They can.
             This complexity matters because                                  The harder question is whether they
           sweeping judgments can alienate the   What kind of entertainment do we   still should.
           very people needed for reform.   want?                             And perhaps the answer depends on
             A carriage driver in an old city may   The larger issue may not be about   what humans value more: preserving fa-
           not see himself as exploiting animals.   horses alone. It’s about how modern so-  miliar spectacles, or learning how to ad-
           He may believe he is preserving heritage   cieties define acceptable entertainment.   mire animals without demanding a per-
           while earning an honest living. A wed-  Historically, humans normalized   formance in return. ■

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  Sobriety movement                                        cape, is increasingly being examined
                                                                           through the lens of wellness. People are
                                                                           asking practical questions. How does
                                                                           drinking affect productivity? Mood? Re-
                                                                           lationships? Even skin health?
                                                                              And honestly, some don’t like the an-
                                                                           swers they’re finding.
                                                                              A growing number are embracing
                                                                           what’s often called “mindful drinking”
                                                                           or the “sober curious” lifestyle. It
           Is wine losing  doesn’t always mean complete absti-
                                                                           nence. Often, it simply means drinking
                                                                           less, choosing carefully, or deciding al-
           its charm?                                                      piece of social life.
                                                                           cohol no longer needs to be the centre-
                                                                              That shift has opened the door for an
                                                                           industry many once dismissed as impos-
                                                                           sible: non-alcoholic wine.

           For a growing generation, saying no to alcohol is no            Wine without the buzz
                                                                              Not long ago, alcohol-free wine car-
           longer an act of rebellion, but an act of self-                 ried a bad reputation. Enthusiasts com-

           awareness. By Anaya Gupta                                       plained it tasted flat, overly sweet or
                                                                           strangely artificial. Even restaurants
                                                                           treated it like an afterthought.



                  ould you like the wine list, or
                  our zero-proof pairings
           Wmenu? A few years ago, that
           question might have sounded odd in an
           upscale restaurant. Today, it feels sur-
           prisingly normal. In cities from London
           to Mumbai, New York to Melbourne, a
           quiet cultural shift is unfolding at dinner
           tables, rooftop parties and wedding re-
           ceptions. People are still gathering,
           laughing and celebrating. They’re just
           drinking differently.
             Wine, long associated with sophisti-
           cation, romance and social ritual, seems
           to be facing an uncomfortable question:
           does it still hold the same emotional grip
           on younger generations?
           The rise of mindful drinking
             For decades, wine carried a certain
           aura. A glass of red at the end of a
           stressful day symbolized maturity. Shar-
           ing a bottle over dinner meant intimacy,
           conversation, slowing down. Entire
           travel industries were built around vine-
           yards and tasting tours. It wasn’t just al-
           cohol. It was lifestyle.
             But attitudes are changing, especially
           among millennials and Gen Z con-
           sumers.
             Many young professionals now speak
           openly about anxiety, sleep quality,
           mental clarity and emotional balance in
           ways previous generations rarely did.
           Alcohol, once marketed as a form of es-

           26                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[tional weight. In countries like Italy,
                                                                           France and Argentina, wine remains tied
                                                                           to family traditions, regional identity
                                                                           and everyday meals. That kind of her-
                                                                           itage doesn’t vanish overnight.
                                                                              And many wine lovers argue, fairly,
                                                                           that moderation was always part of wine
                                                                           culture at its best. The idea wasn’t ex-
                                                                           cess, but appreciation. Taste. Conver-
                                                                           sation. Slowness.
                                                                              Some also believe the sobriety move-
                                                                           ment risks becoming performative in its
                                                                           own way, another lifestyle identity
                                                                           shaped by wellness marketing and social
                                                                           media aesthetics. There’s probably some
                                                                           truth there too. Trends have a habit of
                                                                           turning personal choices into public
                                                                           branding.
                                                                              Still, something deeper seems to be
             Now, producers are investing heavily   Younger adults are navigating burn-  happening beneath the hashtags and cu-
           in improving quality. Vineyards in   out, expensive cities and constant digital   rated wellness routines.
           France, Spain, Australia and California   overstimulation. Many don’t want hang-  People are rethinking what comfort
           are experimenting with sophisticated de-  overs consuming the little free time they   means. They’re searching for connection
           alcoholisation techniques that preserve   have. Others grew up watching older   without dependency, celebration without
           aroma and texture. Some bottles even   generations struggle quietly with alcohol   regret, relaxation without escape. That
           mimic the complexity of traditional   dependency and are consciously choos-  emotional recalibration is bigger than
           wines surprisingly well.        ing another path.               wine alone.
             The market is responding.       There’s also the visibility factor.
             In many urban bars, zero-proof   Every dinner, party and late-night mis-  The future of the social glass
           menus now sit proudly beside cocktail   take can potentially end up online. That   Maybe wine isn’t losing its charm so
           lists. Boutique stores dedicate shelves to   awareness shapes behaviour more than   much as losing its unquestioned status.
           alcohol-free sparkling rosé and botanical   people admit.          For centuries, alcohol occupied a
           wine alternatives. Social media in-  Interestingly, the hospitality industry   near-permanent seat at human gath-
           fluencers casually post photos of elegant   isn’t resisting entirely. Many restaurants   erings. Today, that seat is being shared.
           stemware filled with non-alcoholic   and luxury hotels are adapting quickly   Kombucha, botanical spirits, alcohol-
           blends and nobody seems particularly   because they understand something im-  free wines and simple sparkling water
           defensive about it anymore.     portant: people still crave experience   are entering spaces once dominated by
             What’s changed isn’t only the pro-  and ritual. They still want beautiful   Cabernet and Champagne.
           duct. It’s the social meaning attached to   glasses, thoughtful pairings and cele-  And perhaps that’s not a cultural loss.
           sobriety.                       bratory moments. They just may not   Perhaps it’s just a broader definition of
             There was a time when refusing wine   want intoxication attached to them every   belonging.
           at a gathering invited awkward ques-  time.                        A friend raising a glass of non-alco-
           tions. “Are you okay?” “Driving?” “On   So the wine culture itself is evolving   holic rosé at dinner is still participating
           medication?” Now, declining alcohol   rather than disappearing.   in the ritual. The conversation still
           can signal discipline, self-awareness or                        flows. The laughter still arrives in
           simply preference. That’s a major cul-  Is wine really losing relevance?   waves. The evening still matters.
           tural transformation.             Not exactly.                     In the end, maybe the real story isn’t
                                             Global wine consumption has soft-  whether people are drinking wine less.
           A generational reset            ened in several regions, particularly   It’s whether society is finally learning
             Part of this movement comes from   among younger consumers, but wine   that connection was never inside the
           economics and lifestyle realities too.   still carries enormous cultural and emo-  bottle to begin with. ■

           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                May 16-31, 2026










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Communication becomes important as discussions   New experiences inspire optimism and growth.
                     and negotiations increase. Stay patient while   Travel, learning, or future planning may attract
                     expressing ideas. Financial matters improve     attention. Relationships feel supportive. Finan-
                     gradually. Relationships benefit from honest    cial matters remain balanced when practical
                     conversations.                                  decisions guide important commitments.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Financial awareness strengthens this fortnight.   Shared responsibilities require patience and
                     Practical decisions improve stability and       careful communication. Emotional honesty
                     confidence. Career progress continues steadily.   strengthens important relationships. Financial
                     Relationships feel supportive when expectations   planning becomes necessary. Avoid unnecessary
                     remain realistic.                               stress by focusing on steady progress.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Your season begins with renewed confidence      Partnerships demand attention and cooperation.
                     and energy. New opportunities emerge through    Professional collaborations move forward suc-
                     networking and communication. Relationships     cessfully when expectations remain clear. Rela-
                     improve with openness. Financial matters re-    tionships improve through patience and under-
                     main balanced.                                  standing.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     A reflective mood encourages rest and emotional   Daily routines require better organization.
                     balance. Avoid overthinking situations beyond   Health and productivity improve through consis-
                     your control. Work progresses quietly. Financial   tent habits. Work responsibilities increase
                     stability remains steady, while trusted relation-  steadily. Relationships remain stable when emo-
                     ships provide comfort and reassurance.          tional needs are expressed openly and calmly.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Social connections bring encouragement and      Creativity and personal interests bring satisfac-
                     fresh opportunities. Teamwork supports profes-  tion and renewed motivation. Romantic energy
                     sional progress. Relationships improve through   improves through meaningful conversations. Fi-
                     shared activities and understanding. Financial   nancial matters remain secure when practical
                     matters remain stable with disciplined planning.   decisions guide long-term planning.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Career responsibilities increase, demanding     Home and family matters become priorities.
                     focus and organization. Recognition follows     Emotional balance improves through supportive
                     consistent effort. Emotional balance improves   conversations and patience. Career remains
                     with practical thinking. Financial stability grows   steady. Financial stability strengthens when un-
                     gradually through disciplined choices.          necessary expenses are avoided.


           28                                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Changing spending habits and the   The new Chief Minister must now
           economy                         prove his administrative ability through
             The growing advice to avoid buying   transparent policies and people-oriented   parties managed to retain power, several
           gold, reduce foreign travel and adopt   decisions. Tamil Nadu has long been   governments faced public anger over
           work-from-home culture may help   known for strong governance and social   unemployment, rising prices, poor in-
           individuals save money, but it could also   welfare, and citizens expect the same   frastructure and unfulfilled promises.
           create mixed effects on the economy.   commitment from the new government.   The elections also highlighted the grow-
           Lower gold imports may reduce pressure   Politics should rise above cinema-style   ing influence of regional parties and
           on foreign exchange reserves, while fewer   hero worship, focusing instead on edu-  young voters, who are now demanding
           overseas trips can help retain money   cation and healthcare, rural development   transparency, development and better
           within the country. Work-from-home   and employment opportunities for the   governance instead of emotional slogans
           practices may save fuel and reduce   common people.             alone.
           pollution.                      Shruti Pillai, Chennai, Tamil Nadu,   Political leaders should understand
             However, these changes could   India                          that citizens are becoming more aware
           negatively affect sectors such as tourism,                      and expect accountability after every
           aviation, hotels, jewellery and urban                           election. Victory should not lead to arro-
           transport, which employ millions of   Hantavirus cases raise health   gance, and defeat should become an op-
           people. Economic growth depends not   concerns                  portunity for self-examination. The true
           only on savings but also on spending and   The recent reports of Hantavirus   winners of these elections should be the
           business activity. Policymakers must   cases in India have created concern   people of India, provided the elected
           therefore strike a balance between   among citizens and health experts alike.   representatives work honestly for public
           financial discipline and economic   Though the number of infections re-  welfare rather than focusing only on po-
           expansion. Instead of discouraging   mains limited, the development reminds   litical rivalries and ambitions.
           consumption completely, the focus should   us that emerging diseases can spread   Navneet Khanna, Delhi, India
           be on promoting responsible spending,   quickly if ignored. Hantavirus, com-
           domestic tourism and sustainable   monly linked to rodents and contami-
           lifestyles that support both citizens and   nated surroundings, highlights the ur-  Cyber slavery and rising online
           national economic development in the   gent need for better sanitation, waste   fraud
           long run.                       management and public awareness.   The shocking case of three Indian
           Susheel Kumar Gupta, New Delhi,   Health authorities must increase surveil-  men, rescued from cyber slavery abroad
           India                           lance in vulnerable regions and ensure   only to regroup and run online fraud op-
                                           early diagnosis facilities in hospitals.    erations in Pune, India, exposes the dan-
                                             Citizens should also maintain clean-  gerous spread of cybercrime and the fai-
           Tamil Nadu welcomes new         liness in homes, storage areas and mar-  lure of rehabilitation systems.
           leadership                      ketplaces to reduce the risk of infection.   In cities like Pune, where digital
             The oath-taking ceremony of actor-  India learned valuable lessons during the   transactions and IT-related activities are
           turned-politician Vijay as the Chief Min-  COVID-19 pandemic, and those lessons   rapidly growing, such crimes create se-
           ister of Tamil Nadu marks a new chapter   should not be forgotten.   rious concern among citizens.
           in the state’s political history. His re-  Dr. Rakesh Sharma, New Delhi, India   Sunanda Patil, Pune, Maharashtra,
           markable popularity among youth and                             India
           first-time voters reflects the growing de-
           sire for fresh leadership and clean gov-  Assembly elections 2026: A
           ernance. However, public admiration   message for leaders          Letters (limited to one hundred
           alone cannot solve the real challenges   The recent Assembly Election results   words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           facing the state, including unemploy-  across India have once again shown the   Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           ment, rising prices, water scarcity and   strength of democracy and the changing
           infrastructure development.     mood of voters. While some ruling


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           MAY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                                 29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Climb the mountains and get their good

           tidings. Nature’s peace will flow into you                                                          Photo credit: Nikita

           as sunshine flows into trees. - John Muir]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                   .revoir
                                                                        .in
                                                                                           |
                                                                          REVOIR Magazine
                                                                  www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | MAY 16 2026MARCH 16 2026
           3232
           32                                                  www .revoir .in  REVOIR Magazine  |     MARCH 01 2026
                                                               www
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>