<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="34"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                      VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 02  I  JANUARY 16 2025     ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





             19



                                                             8













                                                            27                                        5
















           4-Editorial: Empowering every citizen           25-Reviving tradition with modern
           equally                                         creativity

           5-The next wave of education                    27-Snow as a canvas of human

           8-Ensuring equality, justice, and liberty  emotions

           11-An era truly comes to an end                 30-Horoscopes
           12-Religion in the age of technology            31-Letters

           16-From pollution to solution

           19-Empowering voices through art

           22-A tradition fading in the digital
           storm







           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                 3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[We the People
     EDITORIAL  Empowering every                                                  Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                             MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           citizen equally                                                      Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                              he phrase “We the People” in the       Navormi Vats
                                              Preamble of the Indian Constitution
                                        Tencapsulates the very essence of
                                        democracy,  a nation built by its citizens, for   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        its citizens, and with its citizens at its core.   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        The Constitution of India is not just a legal
                                        framework but a profound social contract   Social Media Editor
                                        that guarantees equal rights and             Vikas Babbar
                                        opportunities to every individual,
                                        irrespective of their socioeconomic status,   Art & Graphics Editor
                                        caste, gender, or religion.                  Vipin Kumar
                                           One of the Constitution’s greatest
                                        triumphs is its emphasis on equality. The
                                        Right to Equality, enshrined in Articles 14   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           to 18, ensures that every individual is equal before the law. Whether one is a daily
           wage laborer or a business magnate, the Constitution provides equal protection,   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           guaranteeing that justice is blind to wealth, power, or privilege. By abolishing   Editor, United News of India, New
           untouchability and discriminatory practices, it lays the foundation for a society free   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           from oppression.                                                  Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
             The Indian Constitution is a guardian of the underprivileged. Through its   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           provisions for affirmative action, such as reservations in education, employment, and   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           political representation for Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, and Other Backward   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           Classes, it addresses historical inequalities. This ensures that those who have been   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           marginalized for centuries can reclaim their rightful place in society.   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             Democracy is meaningless without freedom, and the Constitution ensures this
           through the Right to Freedom (Articles 19 to 22). These freedoms empower every   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           individual to express their thoughts, move freely, and pursue their aspirations without
           fear. For the poorest laborer or the richest industrialist, these freedoms create a level   Phone +91 20 40199102
           playing field where merit and determination can flourish.         Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
             Moreover, the Constitution safeguards the dignity of labor. It guarantees fair   Baner Road,
           wages, the prohibition of exploitation, and the right to form unions. Every worker,   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           irrespective of their status, is protected under the law. This recognition of labor’s   Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
           dignity underscores that every contribution, no matter how small, is vital to the   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
           nation’s progress.                                                   Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
             Above all, the Constitution’s most empowering feature is the Right to   Founding year 2023
           Constitutional Remedies (Article 32). This provision ensures that every citizen,   Subject Multidisciplinary
           regardless of their resources, can seek justice if their rights are violated. It places the   Frequency Fortnightly
           power of the judiciary in the hands of the people, making the courts accessible to   Format Online
           everyone, from the poorest laborer to the wealthiest industrialist.     Language English
             As India celebrates Republic Day, it is a reminder that our Constitution is a living   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           document, evolving with the needs of its people. It promises that every citizen, from   Website www.revoir.in
           the most affluent to the humblest, is an equal stakeholder in the nation’s destiny. By
           upholding its principles, we can truly realize the vision of “We the People.”   Legal Advisor
                                                                                 Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH





































           From chalkboards to chatbots


           The next wave




                                                                           the evolving role of educators in a tech-
                                                                           driven world.
           of education                                                    AI: Personalizing the learning

                                                                           experience
                                                                              Artificial Intelligence is revolutioniz-
                                                                           ing education by tailoring learning ex-
                                                                           periences to individual needs. AI-pow-
           AI, VR, and robotics are more than just tools; they are         ered platforms such as adaptive learning
           catalysts for reimagining education. By Aarav Sharma            systems analyze student performance
                                                                           and adjust content delivery accordingly.
                                                                           For instance, tools like Khan Academy’s
                                                                           AI-driven learning assistants can iden-
                ducation has long been the foun-  On the occasion of the International   tify gaps in a student’s understanding
                dation of societal progress,   Day of Education, observed annually on   and recommend specific resources to ad-
           Eevolving in response to cultural   January 24th, it is crucial to reflect on   dress them.
           shifts, economic demands, and techno-  these profound changes. This day em-  Moreover, AI is enhancing admin-
           logical advancements. In recent years,   phasizes the role of education in achiev-  istrative efficiency. Tasks like grading
           the rapid pace of technological innova-  ing global peace and sustainable devel-  assignments, scheduling classes, and
           tion has ushered in a transformative era   opment. Emerging technologies, while   managing student records can now be
           for education. Artificial Intelligence   still in their nascent stages, offer un-  automated, freeing educators to focus on
           (AI), Virtual Reality (VR), and robotics   precedented opportunities to make   teaching and mentorship. AI-driven
           are not only reshaping how we learn but   learning more personalized, accessible,   chatbots provide 24/7 academic support,
           also redefining what it means to be edu-  and engaging. However, they also raise   answering queries, and guiding students
           cated in the 21st century.      questions about equity, ethical use, and   through complex topics.

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                 5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[In higher education and professional
           training, AI is enabling skills-based
           learning. Platforms like Coursera and
           edX leverage AI to match learners with
           courses that align with their career
           goals. Additionally, Natural Language
           Processing (NLP) technologies facilitate
           language learning, with apps like Duol-
           ingo adapting exercises to individual
           progress.
             However, the integration of AI in
           education is not without challenges. Is-
           sues like data privacy, algorithmic bias,                                                       Students engaging with smart devices
           and the digital divide must be addressed
           to ensure that AI benefits all learners
           equitably. Governments, educators, and
           tech developers must collaborate to es-
           tablish ethical guidelines and policies
           that prioritize student well-being.
           VR: Immersive and experiential
           learning
             Virtual Reality is transforming edu-
           cation by creating immersive and inter-
           active learning environments. Unlike
           traditional methods, VR enables stu-
           dents to experience concepts firsthand,
           making abstract ideas tangible and en-
           gaging.
             For instance, in science education,                                                           Students interacting with an AI-powered chatbot
           VR simulations allow students to ex-
           plore the human body in 3D or conduct
           virtual chemistry experiments without
           safety concerns. History lessons come
           alive as students virtually visit ancient
           civilizations, walking through the streets
           of Rome or exploring the pyramids of
           Egypt. These experiences enhance reten-
           tion and foster a deeper understanding   in STEM (Science, Technology, Engi-
           of complex topics.              neering, and Mathematics) fields. Edu-
             VR is also proving invaluable in vo-  cational robots like LEGO Mindstorms
           cational training. Medical students use   and VEX Robotics teach programming
           VR to practice surgeries in a risk-free   and engineering concepts through
           environment, while aspiring pilots train   hands-on activities. These tools encour-
           in virtual cockpits. This experiential   age problem-solving, creativity, and
           learning not only improves skill acqui-  teamwork, preparing students for the
           sition but also builds confidence by al-  jobs of the future.
           lowing learners to make mistakes and   Robots are also enhancing inclusivity
           learn from them in a controlled setting.   in education. For example, telepresence
             Accessibility remains a key challenge   robots enable students with mobility                  A learning experience in the classroom
           for VR adoption. High costs of VR   challenges to attend classes remotely,
           equipment and the need for robust inter-  fostering a sense of belonging and par-
           net infrastructure can limit its reach, par-  ticipation. Humanoid robots, such as
           ticularly in developing regions. Ho-  SoftBank’s Pepper, are being used as
           wever, as technology becomes more   teaching assistants, helping to engage
           affordable and widespread, the potential   students in subjects ranging from lan-
           for VR to democratize education is im-  guage learning to mathematics.   While robotics offers exciting possi-
           mense.                            In early childhood education, robots   bilities, its integration into classrooms
                                           like Cozmo and Dash introduce young   requires careful planning. Educators
           Robotics: Redefining interactivity   learners to coding through play. By   need training to effectively incorporate
           and collaboration               making complex concepts approachable   robots into their teaching methods. Ad-
             Robotics is playing an increasingly   and fun, these robots ignite curiosity and   ditionally, there is a need for curricula
           significant role in education, particularly   a lifelong love for learning.   that balance technological skills with

           6                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Kids participating in a robotics class









                                                                                                           A telepresence robot in action












                                                                           Google’s Chromebooks for Education
         Students exploring with VR headsets                               accessible. Governments must also pri-
                                                                           and Microsoft’s global skills programs
                                                                           are examples of how corporations can
                                                                           contribute to making technology more

                                                                           oritize digital inclusion in their educa-
                                                                           tion policies, ensuring that no student is
                                                                           left behind in the transition to tech-en-
                                                                           abled learning.

                                                                           The road ahead
                                                                              As we celebrate the International
                                                                           Day of Education, it is clear that AI, VR,
           critical thinking, ethics, and interper-  in education also necessitates a focus on   and robotics are more than just tools;
           sonal communication.            digital literacy. Students must learn to   they are catalysts for reimagining educa-
                                           critically evaluate online information,   tion. By harnessing their potential re-
           Impact on teaching and learning   safeguard their privacy, and use technol-  sponsibly, we can create a future where
             The convergence of AI, VR, and ro-  ogy responsibly. Equally important is   learning is not only more effective but
           botics is fundamentally altering the roles   addressing the social-emotional aspect   also more equitable and inclusive.
           of teachers and students. Educators are   of learning, ensuring that technology   The road ahead requires collabo-
           transitioning from knowledge dispensers   complements rather than replaces   ration among educators, technologists,
           to facilitators of learning, guiding stu-  human interaction.   policymakers, and communities. To-
           dents as they navigate digital tools and                        gether, we must address the challenges
           resources. Professional development is   Bridging the digital divide   of accessibility, ethical use, and teacher
           becoming essential, with teachers need-  While the potential of AI, VR, and   training while embracing the opportuni-
           ing training in emerging technologies to   robotics in education is undeniable, their   ties that technology offers. Education
           stay relevant and effective.    benefits are not yet universally acces-  has always been a powerful force for
             For students, learning is becoming   sible. The digital divide—disparities in   change, and with the aid of emerging
           more collaborative and self-directed.   access to technology and the internet—  technologies, it can continue to shape a
           Gamified platforms and virtual class-  remains a significant barrier, particularly   better future for all.
           rooms encourage active participation,   in low-income and rural communities.   In this transformative era, the ques-
           fostering skills like teamwork, critical   Bridging this gap requires investment in   tion is not whether technology will
           thinking, and adaptability. These compe-  infrastructure, affordable devices, and   change education but how we will adapt
           tencies are crucial in a world where   inclusive policies that prioritize margin-  and innovate to ensure it serves the
           knowledge is readily accessible, and   alized groups.           greater good. By doing so, we can em-
           problem-solving abilities are in high de-  Public-private partnerships can play a   power learners worldwide to reach their
           mand.                           pivotal role in expanding access to edu-  full potential and contribute meaning-
             However, the reliance on technology   cational technologies. Initiatives like   fully to a rapidly evolving world. ■

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                 7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY





































           We the People



           Ensuring





           equality, justice,





           and liberty                                                                                     Dr. Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar





                                                                           nation. On Republic Day, celebrated
           The Constitution empowers citizens with rights and              every year on January 26, Indians com-
                                                                           memorate the day when the Constitution
           responsibilities, envisioning an India that is just,            came into effect. This day symbolizes
                                                                           the culmination of India’s struggle for
           inclusive, and progressive. By Naina Kapoor                     independence and the beginning of its
                                                                           journey as a sovereign democratic re-
                                                                           public.
                he opening words of the Indian   vember 26, 1949, and enforced on Janu-
                Constitution, “We the people,”   ary 26, 1950, is the supreme law of the   Fundamental rights: The core of
           Tresonate deeply with the ideals of   land. It not only provides a legal frame-  citizen empowerment
           democracy, equality, and justice. These   work for governance but also safeguards   At the heart of the Constitution lie
           three words symbolize the essence of   the rights and freedoms of its citizens.   the Fundamental Rights, enshrined in
           the Indian Republic, a nation where   More than just a legal document, the   Part III, which ensure that every individ-
           power emanates from its citizens. The   Constitution is a visionary framework   ual enjoys basic freedoms. These rights
           Constitution of India, adopted on No-  that reflects the aspirations of a diverse   are not mere privileges; they are guaran-

           8                                        www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[guards, protecting citizens from any
                                                                           abuse of power by the state. They form
                                                                           the foundation of a free and just society.

                                                                           Directive principles: A roadmap
         Supreme Court of India, New Delhi                                 enforceable, the Directive Principles of
                                                                           for welfare
                                                                              While the Fundamental Rights are
                                                                           State Policy (Part IV) serve as guiding
                                                                           principles for governance. These princi-
                                                                           ples reflect the aspirations of the framers
                                                                           of the Constitution to create an equitable
                                                                           society.
                                                                              Promotion of social and economic
                                                                           welfare, including adequate means of
                                                                           livelihood for all citizens.
                                                                              Equal pay for equal work, irrespec-
                                                                           tive of gender.
                                                                              Protection of children from exploita-
                                                                           tion and opportunities for their healthy
                                                                           development.
         Citizens casting their votes in an election                       strengthen grassroots democracy.
                                                                              Improvement of public health and the
                                                                           prohibition of intoxicating substances.
                                                                              Organization of village panchayats to

                                                                              Promotion of education, especially
                                                                           free and compulsory education for chil-
                                                                           dren up to 14 years of age.
                                                                              These principles aim to reduce in-
                                                                           equalities and promote social justice, en-
                                                                           suring that the benefits of economic
                                                                           progress reach all sections of society.

                                                                           Affirmative action: Bridging his-
                                             Right to freedom (Articles 19-22):   torical gaps
                                           Citizens have the freedom of speech and   To address centuries of social and
                                           expression, assembly, association,   economic oppression, the Constitution
                                           movement, and residence, along with   incorporates provisions for affirmative
                                           the right to practice any profession or   action. Articles 15(4) and 16(4) em-
                                           trade. These freedoms are essential for   power the state to implement reserva-
                                           the growth of democracy and individual   tions for Scheduled Castes (SC),
                                           dignity.                        Scheduled Tribes (ST), and Other Back-
                                             Right against exploitation (Articles   ward Classes (OBC) in education, pub-
                                           23-24): This right safeguards individuals   lic employment, and legislatures.
         Rashtrapati Bhavan in New Delhi   ardous work environments.       ensuring that the intended beneficiaries
                                                                              While such measures have led to sig-
                                           from human trafficking, bonded labor,
                                                                           nificant progress, challenges remain in
                                           and the exploitation of children in haz-
                                                                           fully access these opportunities. Never-
                                             Right to freedom of religion (Articles
                                           25-28): Citizens are free to profess,
                                                                           theless, these provisions reflect the Con-
                                           practice, and propagate any religion, en-
                                                                           stitution’s commitment to creating an
                                                                           inclusive society.
                                           suring India’s secular ethos.
                                             Cultural and educational rights (Ar-
                                           cultural and educational rights of minor-
                                                                           chayati raj
                                           ities, allowing them to preserve their
                                                                              The Constitution’s vision of democ-
                                           heritage and establish institutions.
           teed by the Constitution and enforceable   ticles 29-30): These rights protect the   Grassroots empowerment: Pan-
                                                                           racy is not limited to the national and
           in a court of law.                Right to constitutional remedies (Ar-  state levels; it extends to the grassroots
             Right to equality (Articles 14-18):   ticle 32): Often referred to as the “heart   through the 73rd and 74th Amendments.
           This guarantees equality before the law   and soul” of the Constitution, this right   These amendments established Panchay-
           and equal protection of the laws. It also   empowers citizens to approach the Su-  ati Raj Institutions and Urban Local
           abolishes practices like untouchability   preme Court or High Courts to enforce   Bodies, which empower citizens to par-
           and titles, which were instruments of so-  their Fundamental Rights.   ticipate directly in decision-making at
           cial discrimination.              The Fundamental Rights act as safe-  the local level.
           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                 9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Everyone deserves equal rights                                                                    Schoolchildren in uniform












             Through Gram Sabhas and local
           governance bodies, citizens have a say
           in resource allocation, developmental
           initiatives, and welfare schemes. This
           decentralization fosters a sense of own-
           ership and accountability in govern-
           ance.                                                                                           The Indian Constitution ensures equal rights

           Empowering women: A constitu-
           tional mandate
             The Constitution is a strong advo-
           cate for gender equality. Articles 14, 15,
           and 16 ensure equal rights for women
           and prohibit discrimination. Over the
           decades, laws like the Hindu Succes-
           sion Act (2005), which grants daughters   the Constitution’s promise of dignity   Challenges and responsibilities
           equal rights in ancestral property, and   for all individuals.     Despite its robust framework, the
           the Protection of Women from Domes-  Through its interventions, the judici-  Constitution’s ideals face challenges.
           tic violence act (2005) have reinforced   ary ensures that the Constitution   Socio-economic inequalities, caste-
           women’s rights.                 evolves to meet the needs of contempo-  based discrimination, and lack of aware-
             The 73rd Amendment reserves one-  rary society.               ness about rights hinder empowerment.
           third of seats in Panchayati Raj Institu-                       Furthermore, delays in justice delivery
           tions for women, enabling them to play   The power of voting    and misuse of freedoms sometimes di-
           a significant role in grassroots govern-  Article 326 of the Constitution   lute the Constitution’s intent.
           ance. These measures have empowered   grants the right to vote to every citizen   As citizens, it is our duty to uphold
           women to become active participants in   aged 18 and above. By exercising their   constitutional values. Awareness cam-
           the nation’s development.       franchise, citizens play an active role in   paigns, civic education, and proactive
                                           shaping the nation’s future. The Elec-  participation in democratic processes are
           Judiciary: The sentinel of democ-  tion Commission of India, established   crucial for bridging these gaps.
           racy                            under Article 324, ensures free and fair
             The judiciary plays a crucial role in   elections, preserving the sanctity of   Republic day: A reminder of re-
           upholding the Constitution. Landmark   India’s democracy.       sponsibility
           judgments have continuously reinforced                             Republic Day is not just a celebration
           the document’s relevance. For instance:   Unity in diversity: A constitu-  of the Constitution’s adoption; it is a day
             The Kesavananda Bharati case   tional strength                to reflect on its enduring relevance. The
           (1973) established the doctrine of the   India’s diversity is its strength, and   Constitution empowers citizens with
           basic structure, ensuring that Parliament   the Constitution ensures that this diver-  rights and responsibilities, envisioning
           cannot amend the Constitution’s core   sity thrives. Through provisions in   an India that is just, inclusive, and pro-
           principles.                     Schedules VIII and IX, the Constitution   gressive.
             The Vishaka guidelines (1997) laid   protects linguistic and cultural rights   By embracing the principles en-
           the groundwork for combating work-  while promoting national integration. It   shrined in the Constitution, Indians can
           place harassment.               accommodates various religious, cul-  ensure that democracy thrives, and the
             The Navtej Singh Johar case (2018)   tural, and regional identities, creating a   aspirations of “We the people” become a
           decriminalized homosexuality, affirming   harmonious coexistence.   reality for all. ■

           10                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Uttar Pradesh Export Corporation
                                                                           (2004-2006) with the status of Minister
                                                                           of State. His active involvement in na-
                                                                           tional politics saw him as a member of
                                                                           the All India Congress Committee      SPOTLIGHT
                                                                           (AICC), an observer for elections in
         Dr. Mairajuddin Ahmad (File Photo: M. Usman)                      in the Rashtriya Lok Dal and the Sa-
                                                                           multiple states, and a delegate on the
                                                                           Prime Minister’s Haj Delegation.
                                                                              Dr. Mairaj also played pivotal roles

                                                                           majwadi Party, holding leadership posi-
                                                                           tions that demonstrated his commitment
                                                                           to democratic values and inclusive gov-
                                                                           ernance.
                                                                           A cultural and literary luminary
                                                                              Beyond politics, Dr. Mairaj’s deep-
                                                                           rooted love for culture and literature
                                                                           shone brightly. Coming from a family
                                                                           that cherished tradition, he actively or-
                                                                           ganized All India Mushairas and educa-
           Dr. Mairajuddin’s Demise                                        tional conferences, making Meerut a
                                                                           hub of intellectual and artistic gath-
                                                                           erings.
                                                                              His charm and eloquence endeared
          An era truly                                                     him to people from all walks of life. Be
                                                                           it literary icons like Majrooh Sultanpuri,
                                                                           film personalities such as Farooq
                                                                           Sheikh, or political dignitaries like
                                                                           former Governor Aziz Qureshi, Dr. Mai-
          comes to an end                                                  raj’s residence was a melting pot of
                                                                           ideas, culture, and camaraderie.

                                                                           A life loved and celebrated
                                                                              The outpouring of love and concern
           Dr. Mairaj’s passing is not just a loss to his family and       during his ailment bore testimony to the
                                                                           profound impact he had on countless
           loved ones but to society at large. He exemplified              lives. Crowds gathered outside the hos-
                                                                           pital, fervently praying for his recovery,
           elegance, humility, and a profound sense of                     and videos of his admirers flooded so-
                                                                           cial media, reflecting the deep affection
           responsibility that is rare to find. By Staff writer            and respect he commanded.

                                                                           A void that cannot be filled
                 r. Mairajuddin Ahmad, a promi-  A life rooted in service and   Dr. Mairaj’s passing is not just a loss
                 nent political figure, cultural en-  dedication           to his family and loved ones but to soci-
           Dthusiast, and a beacon of humil-  Dr. Mairaj’s illustrious career began   ety at large. He exemplified elegance,
           ity and grace, passed away on January   with his academic journey at Aligarh   humility, and a profound sense of re-
           11, 2025, at the All India Institute of   Muslim University, where he completed   sponsibility that is rare to find.
           Medical Sciences (AIIMS), New Delhi.   his B.Sc. and M.A. BUMMS. He later   His legacy will continue to inspire
           He breathed his last at 4 PM on a   embarked on his political journey in   generations, reminding us of the power
           somber Saturday evening, leaving be-  Meerut, joining the Youth Congress in   of grace and dedication in public serv-
           hind a legacy that epitomizes the values   1988. His leadership and vision were   ice.
           of tradition, elegance, and service.   soon recognized as he contested the   As we bid farewell to this extraordi-
             With his demise, an era has come to   Sardhana Assembly Constituency elec-  nary personality, we celebrate a life that
           an end, a legacy nurtured by his father,   tions in 1993 and twice contested Lok   truly embodied the spirit of service, cul-
           Padma Shri Hakim Saifuddin Ahmed, a   Sabha elections from Baghpat in 1998   ture, and humanity. Dr. Mairaj will
           distinguished physician who served   and 1999.                  forever remain etched in our memories
           three Presidents of India. Dr. Mairaj in-  He held several key positions during   as a towering figure whose contributions
           herited not just the cultural richness of   his career, including serving as the Cabi-  transcended politics and touched the
           his lineage but also the values of service   net Minister for Irrigation and Flood   very soul of society. May his soul find
           and dignity, which he upheld throughout   Control in the Uttar Pradesh Govern-  eternal peace and tranquility in the em-
           his life.                       ment (2006) and as the Chairman of the   brace of the divine. ■

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Rituals Reinvented


     INSIGHT  Religion in the





           age of technology





           As humanity navigates unprecedented technological                                               A person using a spiritual app on a smartphone

           and cultural transformations, faith systems worldwide
           are evolving to remain relevant, inclusive, and
           impactful. By Pooja Mehta



                eligion has always been a cor-
                nerstone of human civilization,
           Rguiding ethical frameworks, fos-
           tering communities, and offering solace
           in times of uncertainty. Across millen-
           nia, it has influenced societies globally,
           shaping cultural identities and historical
           narratives. Yet, as humanity evolves, re-
           ligion finds itself at the crossroads of
           tradition and modernity. Technological
           advancements, social transformations,
           and cultural shifts compel religions to
           adapt to stay relevant, inclusive, and                                                          A sadhvi wearing headphones within temple premises
           meaningful to their followers.
             Celebrated annually on the third Sun-
           day of January, World Religion Day re-
           minds us of the universal values of love,
           understanding, and unity that connect
           different faiths. Established in 1950 by
           the Bahá’í community, this day encour-
           ages interfaith dialogue and highlights
           the shared principles of compassion and
           humanity. In today’s context, the obser-  have allowed faith leaders to extend   health, or logistical constraints. Virtual
           vance of this day is more pertinent than   their reach far beyond their immediate   reality technology now offers immersive
           ever, as it reflects how religions world-  communities. Whether it’s attending Fri-  experiences of sacred spaces like
           wide are evolving to address contempo-  day prayers, Sunday services, or Sat-  Mecca, the Vatican, Jerusalem, and the
           rary challenges and opportunities while   urday Shabbat, worshippers from differ-  Ganges River, allowing individuals to
           preserving their spiritual essence.   ent corners of the globe can now come   connect spiritually in innovative ways.
                                           together virtually.               These advancements have democra-
           Adapting to technology: Digital   Faith-based apps: Apps have rev-  tized access to spiritual experiences,
           worship and beyond              olutionized access to religious texts,   breaking barriers of geography and
             The digital revolution has trans-  practices, and guidance. Tools like Mus-  physical limitations, while also posing
           formed nearly every aspect of modern   lim Pro for prayer schedules, Bible   questions about the sanctity of certain
           life, including how people practice and   Gateway for scripture access, and In-  rituals when performed in virtual for-
           experience faith. The COVID-19 pan-  sight Timer for spiritual meditation have   mats.
           demic further accelerated this transfor-  brought faith closer to individuals, mak-
           mation, making virtual worship and on-  ing spiritual resources accessible any-  Inclusivity and interfaith dialogue
           line religious engagement the norm for   time, anywhere.          Modern religion is increasingly em-
           many communities.                 Virtual reality pilgrimages: For   bracing inclusivity and interfaith har-
             Virtual congregations: Platforms like   many, a pilgrimage to sacred sites re-  mony, reflecting a more interconnected
           YouTube, Zoom, and Facebook Live   mains a distant dream due to financial,   and diverse world. These shifts align

           12                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Medical advancements and ethics:
                                                                           Religious leaders increasingly engage in
                                                                           discussions about medical ethics, ad-
                                                                           dressing topics such as organ donation,
                                                                           genetic engineering, and artificial intelli-
                                                                           gence in healthcare. This collaboration
                                                                           ensures that advancements align with
         The evolution of worship spaces                                   exploration and astrophysics advance,
                                                                           ethical and spiritual values.
                                                                              Exploration of the cosmos: As space

                                                                           some religious thinkers interpret discov-
                                                                           eries as enhancing spiritual understand-
                                                                           ing. For instance, Hinduism and Bud-
                                                                           dhism often view cosmic discoveries as
                                                                           affirmations of their metaphysical prin-
                                                                           ciples. Similarly, Christian theologians
                                                                           have explored the theological implica-
                                                                           tions of extraterrestrial life.

                                                                           Youth engagement in faith
                                                                              Engaging younger generations has
                                                                           become a crucial priority for many reli-
                                                                           gious institutions. Millennials and Gen
                                                                           Z often view traditional practices as
                                                                           rigid or irrelevant, prompting faith
                                                                           groups to find innovative ways to res-
                                                                           onate with them.
                                                                              Social media evangelism: Social plat-
         The Church of God                                                 forms like Instagram, TikTok, and
                                                                           Twitter are used to share sermons, inspi-
                                                                           rational quotes, and short videos that ad-
                                                                           dress contemporary issues through a
                                                                           spiritual lens. Young influencers within
                                                                           religious communities are becoming key
           with the growing recognition that faith   promote collaboration across faiths, ad-  voices in shaping modern narratives of
           must accommodate the complexities of   dressing issues like poverty, climate   faith.
           contemporary society.           change, and humanitarian crises collec-  Cultural relevance: Many congrega-
             Women in leadership roles: Many re-  tively. Shared spaces for worship and   tions incorporate modern music, art, and
           ligious traditions are reexamining tradi-  dialogue emphasize the commonalities   popular culture into services to create an
           tional gender roles and embracing   among religions rather than the differ-  environment that feels relatable to
           women in leadership. In Christianity, de-  ences.               young audiences. For instance, Christian
           nominations like the Anglican Church                            rock bands, Islamic spoken word poetry,
           have ordained women bishops, while in   Reconciling science and   and Hindu devotional rap resonate with
           Judaism, progressive synagogues have   spirituality             younger believers.
           seen a rise in female rabbis. Similarly,   Historically, religion and science   Volunteer and Activism Opportuni-
           women-led congregations are emerging   have often been seen as opposing forces.   ties: Youth are drawn to social action.
           in Islam, signaling a gradual shift to-  However, the modern era has witnessed   Faith-based initiatives addressing issues
           ward gender equality.           significant efforts to reconcile these do-  like homelessness, food insecurity, and
             Acceptance of LGBTQ+ com-     mains, fostering a dialogue that respects   disaster relief provide meaningful ways
           munities: The inclusion of LGBTQ+ in-  both empirical evidence and spiritual   for young people to engage with their
           dividuals within religious spaces is   wisdom.                  spirituality.
           another marker of progress. Faith com-  Climate action: Many religions have
           munities such as the United Church of   positioned themselves as advocates for   Redefining morality and ethics
           Christ, Reform Judaism, and progressive   environmental stewardship. The Hindu   Modernity has brought ethical dilem-
           Hindu organizations openly welcome   principle of reverence for nature, Is-  mas that challenge traditional religious
           LGBTQ+ individuals, creating safe   lamic teachings on the balance of crea-  frameworks. Faith communities are
           spaces where they can worship without   tion, and Pope Francis’s encyclical Lau-  navigating complex issues such as artifi-
           judgment or exclusion.          dato Si’ underscore the moral imperative   cial intelligence, genetic engineering,
             Interfaith collaborations: In an in-  of addressing climate change. Faith-  and social justice while reinterpreting
           creasingly globalized world, interfaith   based environmental movements like   ancient doctrines to provide moral clar-
           initiatives are flourishing. Organizations   Green Muslims and EcoSikh exemplify   ity.
           such as the Parliament of the World’s   how spiritual teachings inspire ecologi-  AI and ethical guidelines: With the
           Religions and grassroots movements   cal responsibility.        advent of artificial intelligence in deci-

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[sion-making, surveillance, and automa-
           tion, religious leaders are exploring how
           faith-based ethics can guide its respon-
           sible use. Questions about human dig-
           nity, free will, and accountability are
           central to these discussions.
             Championing social justice: Move-
           ments addressing systemic injustice,
           such as Black Lives Matter, climate
           strikes, and gender equality campaigns,
           have found support from faith leaders.
           The concept of liberation theology in                                                           Young people at a vibrant religious event
           Christianity, for example, integrates so-
           cial justice with spiritual activism.
             Economic equity: Faith groups con-
           tinue to address wealth disparities, em-
           phasizing charity, fair trade, and com-
           munity-based economic models. The
           Islamic practice of zakat and Christian
           concepts of tithing exemplify how tradi-
           tions advocate economic justice.

           Challenges to tradition
             While adaptation is necessary, it
           often generates resistance within reli-
           gious communities. Striking a balance
           between embracing modernity and pre-
           serving sacred traditions remains a sig-
           nificant challenge.
             Tensions over reforms: Debates
           around gender equality, LGBTQ+ rights,
           and interfaith marriages sometimes lead
           to divisions within religious com-                                                              Women leading religious rituals
           munities. Conservative factions may re-
           sist reforms, fearing the loss of authen-
           ticity and spiritual depth.
             Secularization: The rise of secularism
           and atheism, especially in developed
           countries, challenges religions to prove   forces in a divided world.
           their relevance in societies increasingly   Encouraging education: Open-
           focused on science, technology, and in-  minded theological study allows adher-
           dividualism.                    ents to navigate modern complexities
             Commercialization: The integration   while staying rooted in spiritual truths.
           of religion into modern consumer cul-  Interfaith dialogues, courses on compar-
           ture risks commodifying sacred prac-  ative religion, and community discus-
           tices. For instance, the commercializa-  sions can bridge gaps in understanding.
           tion of yoga as fitness rather than   Engaging communities: Active par-
           spiritual practice raises concerns about   ticipation by congregants strengthens
           authenticity.                   faith communities. From volunteering to                         A Muslim woman reading the holy Quran on a tablet
                                           creative contributions like writing or
           The way forward: Embracing      performing, diverse forms of engage-
           change with wisdom              ment keep religious traditions vibrant
             The evolution of faith is not about   and relevant.
           abandoning traditions but about adapt-  Religion, at its core, remains a dy-
           ing them in ways that maintain their es-  namic force capable of adapting to the
           sence while addressing contemporary   needs of its time. As humanity navigates
           realities.                      unprecedented technological and cul-
             Fostering unity: Observances like   tural transformations, faith systems   On this World Religion Day, let us
           World Religion Day remind us of the   worldwide are evolving to remain rel-  celebrate the resilience and adaptability
           shared human values that transcend reli-  evant, inclusive, and impactful. By em-  of faith, recognizing it as a bridge be-
           gious boundaries. By focusing on com-  bracing change while honoring tradition,   tween past and present, tradition and in-
           mon goals—such as peace, compassion,   religions continue to inspire hope, foster   novation, and humanity’s collective
           and justice—faiths can act as unifying   compassion, and guide ethical living.   quest for meaning and purpose. ■

           14                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Clean energy’s promise                                          ture. Observed globally, this day high-

                                                                           lights the importance of clean energy in
     DEEP DIVE   From pollution                                            reducing our carbon footprint and com-
                                                                           bating climate change. It also calls for
                                                                           collective action to accelerate the shift
                                                                           from fossil fuels to renewable energy
                                                                           sources, which include solar, wind,
                                                                           hydro, geothermal, and biomass energy.
                                                                           As we mark this day, it is essential to ex-
           to solution                                                     our planet into a cooler, healthier, and
                                                                           plore how clean energy can transform
                                                                           more resilient place to live.

                                                                           The carbon conundrum: Why clean
                                                                           energy matters
           By harnessing the power of the sun, wind, water, and               At the core of climate change is the
           Earth, we can drastically reduce greenhouse gas                 accumulation of greenhouse gases
                                                                           (GHGs) in the atmosphere, primarily
           emissions, mitigate the impacts of climate change, and          carbon dioxide (CO2), methane (CH4),
                                                                           and nitrous oxide (N2O). These gases
           pave the way for a healthier planet. By Karan Malhotra          trap heat, leading to a phenomenon
                                                                           known as the greenhouse effect. The
                                                                           burning of fossil fuels—coal, oil, and
                 s the world grapples with the es-  ety, underscoring the critical importance   natural gas—for electricity, heat, and
                 calating effects of climate   of reducing greenhouse gas emissions.   transportation is the largest single source
           Achange, the need for sustainable   Transitioning to renewable energy lies at   of global GHG emissions. According to
           and clean energy solutions has never   the heart of this mission, offering a path   the International Energy Agency (IEA),
           been more urgent. From devastating   to mitigate climate change while foster-  the energy sector accounts for nearly
           wildfires and catastrophic hurricanes to   ing economic growth and energy secu-  three-quarters of all anthropogenic emis-
           melting glaciers and rising sea levels,   rity.                 sions.
           the signs of a warming planet are stark   The International Day of Clean   Switching to renewable energy can
           and unavoidable. These climate events   Energy serves as a timely reminder of   drastically reduce these emissions. Un-
           not only jeopardize ecosystems but also   the indispensable role that renewable   like fossil fuels, renewable energy
           threaten the very fabric of human soci-  energy plays in creating a sustainable fu-  sources generate power without releas-






















         A scenic view of a wind farm at sunset
















           16                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[ing significant amounts of GHGs. For
           instance, solar panels convert sunlight
           into electricity without emitting CO2,
           while wind turbines harness the kinetic
           energy of the wind in a completely
           emission-free manner. By replacing fos-
           sil fuel-based energy systems with re-
           newable ones, we can achieve signifi-
           cant reductions in global emissions and
           curb the trajectory of global warming.

           Renewable energy’s role in                                                                      A coal power plant emitting smoke
           emission reductions

           Solar power
             Solar energy is one of the most prom-
           ising renewable sources for reducing
           emissions. By capturing sunlight and
           converting it into electricity, solar panels
           eliminate the need for burning fossil
           fuels. The deployment of solar energy
           has seen exponential growth in recent
           years, with solar photovoltaic (PV) sys-
           tems now being more affordable and ef-
           ficient than ever. A single megawatt-
           hour (MWh) of solar electricity can                                                             Energy storage solution: large-scale battery farm
           offset approximately one ton of CO2
           emissions, making it a powerful tool in
           the fight against climate change.
             Wind energy
             Wind power is another key player in
           the clean energy revolution. Modern
           wind turbines are capable of producing
           vast amounts of electricity without emit-
           ting any pollutants. In 2021, wind
           energy helped avoid over 1.5 billion
           tons of CO2 emissions globally. More-
           over, offshore wind farms, which are be-
           coming increasingly popular, have the
           potential to generate even more energy
           due to higher wind speeds and consis-
           tency over the ocean.
           Hydropower
             Hydropower has long been a corner-                                                            The city illuminated with electric lights
           stone of renewable energy, accounting
           for nearly 60% of the world's renewable
           electricity generation. By using flowing
           water to generate power, hydropower
           projects can supply consistent and large-
           scale energy while avoiding the emis-
           sions associated with fossil fuel-based   produce energy around the clock, mak-  those of coal or oil, as the carbon re-
           power plants. However, it is essential to   ing it a valuable complement to inter-  leased is roughly equal to the amount
           ensure that hydropower projects are de-  mittent renewable sources like solar and   absorbed by the plants during their
           signed sustainably to minimize ecologi-  wind.                  growth.
           cal disruption.
                                           Biomass energy                  Beyond emissions: Additional
           Geothermal energy                 Biomass energy, derived from or-  benefits of clean energy
             Geothermal energy taps into the   ganic materials like wood, crop residues,   The benefits of renewable energy ex-
           Earth’s internal heat to generate electric-  and animal waste, can serve as a renew-  tend far beyond reducing GHG emis-
           ity or provide direct heating. It is a   able alternative to fossil fuels. While it   sions. These include:
           highly reliable and low-emission energy   does release CO2 when burned, the net   Improved air quality: The combus-
           source. A geothermal power plant can   emissions are significantly lower than   tion of fossil fuels releases harmful pol-

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[A vibrant solar panel field reflecting the sky



















         Hydropower: Flowing water generating electricity                  Agreement and the United Nations’ Sus- A windmill in operation









                                                                           tainable Development Goal 7 (Afford-
                                                                           able and Clean Energy) have catalyzed
                                                                           global efforts to scale up renewable
                                                                           energy deployment.
                                                                              Looking ahead, the transition to

                                                                           multi-faceted approach:
                                                                              Scaling up investments: Increased in-
           lutants such as sulfur dioxide (SO2), ni-  it is not without challenges. The inter-  100% renewable energy will require a
                                                                           vestment in renewable energy infrastruc-
           trogen oxides (NOx), and particulate   mittency of solar and wind energy, high   ture and research is essential to accel-
           matter, which contribute to smog and   initial capital costs, and the need for ad-  erate the transition.
           respiratory illnesses. Clean energy elim-  vanced energy storage solutions are sig-  Grid modernization: Upgrading
           inates these emissions, leading to health-  nificant hurdles. However, ongoing ad-  energy grids to handle the integration of
           ier communities.                vancements in technology are    diverse renewable sources is crucial.
             Energy security: Renewable energy   addressing these issues. For instance, in-  Public awareness: Educating com-
           reduces dependence on imported fuels,   novations in battery storage are making   munities about the benefits of renewable
           enhancing national energy security and   it possible to store excess energy gener-  energy can drive grassroots support and
           protecting economies from volatile fos-  ated during peak production periods for   adoption.
           sil fuel prices.                use during low production times.   Equitable access: Ensuring that clean
             Job creation: The renewable energy   Moreover, supportive policies and in-  energy technologies are accessible to all,
           sector is a significant source of employ-  ternational cooperation are critical to   including marginalized and underserved
           ment, from manufacturing and installa-  overcoming these challenges. Govern-  populations, will be vital for a just tran-
           tion to maintenance and innovation. Ac-  ments can incentivize renewable energy   sition.
           cording to the International Renewable   adoption through subsidies, tax credits,   On this International Day of Clean
           Energy Agency (IRENA), the sector em-  and feed-in tariffs, while global partner-  Energy, the message is clear: renewable
           ployed over 12 million people globally   ships can facilitate technology transfer   energy is not just an option but an im-
           in 2020.                        and capacity building in developing   perative for a sustainable future. By har-
             Resilience to climate impacts: De-  countries.                nessing the power of the sun, wind,
           centralized renewable energy systems,                           water, and Earth, we can drastically re-
           such as rooftop solar panels and com-  Global momentum: Progress and   duce greenhouse gas emissions, mitigate
           munity wind projects, enhance energy   future outlook           the impacts of climate change, and pave
           resilience by reducing vulnerability to   The world has already made signifi-  the way for a healthier planet. The jour-
           natural disasters and grid failures.   cant strides in adopting clean energy. As   ney to a cooler planet requires bold ac-
                                           of 2023, renewable energy accounts for   tion, innovative solutions, and collective
           Challenges and opportunities    nearly 30% of global electricity genera-  resolve. Together, we can ensure that
             While the transition to renewable   tion, a figure that continues to rise.   clean energy powers our present and
           energy presents immense opportunities,   Landmark initiatives like the Paris   safeguards our future. ■

           18                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[HIGHLIGHT



































           Creativity



           Empowering





           voices through art





           Creativity is a gift that has the power to transform                                            A woman painting on a canvas

           not only individual lives but also the fabric of
           society. By Riya Verma                                          found impact of artistic expression, ex-
                                                                           ploring its role in personal growth, so-
                                                                           cial change, and community devel-
                 rt has always been a profound   Every January, we celebrate Inter-  opment. Through real-life examples and
                 way of communicating the inex-  national Creativity Month, a time to re-  insights, we uncover why creativity is
           Apressible, connecting people ac-  flect on the transformative power of cre-  essential and how it can inspire positive
           ross cultures, and fostering a sense of   ativity in our lives and society. This   transformations in the world around us.
           shared humanity. Whether through   observance reminds us of the impor-
           music, painting, dance, or storytelling,   tance of nurturing our creative instincts   Creativity and personal growth
           creative expression has the ability to   and leveraging them to address the chal-  Artistic expression provides an outlet
           transcend barriers, inspire emotions, and   lenges we face as individuals and com-  for individuals to process their emo-
           spark change. Artistic endeavors not   munities. Creativity is not limited to   tions, tell their stories, and make sense
           only serve as a means of self-expression   professional artists; it is a universal trait   of the world. Engaging in creative activ-
           but also act as a powerful tool for per-  that lies dormant within everyone, wait-  ities can lead to profound personal
           sonal transformation, community cohe-  ing to be ignited.       growth by enhancing self-awareness, re-
           sion, and social progress.        In this article, we delve into the pro-  ducing stress, and improving mental

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[well-being.                       Encouraging innovation: Creativity   horrors of war. Today, digital media
             Mental health benefits: Numerous   stimulates critical thinking and problem-  platforms amplify the reach of such
           studies highlight the therapeutic effects   solving skills, qualities that are invalu-  works, enabling artists to connect with
           of creative practices. Painting, journal-  able in both personal and professional   global audiences and drive conver-
           ing, or playing an instrument can help   life. By challenging conventional norms   sations on pressing topics like climate
           individuals release pent-up emotions, re-  and exploring new perspectives, individ-  change, racial inequality, and gender
           duce anxiety, and foster a sense of calm.   uals can unlock innovative solutions to   rights.
           Art therapy, for instance, has become a   everyday problems, enhancing their   Fostering empathy and understand-
           recognized method for helping people   adaptability and resilience.   ing: By immersing audiences in differ-
           cope with trauma, grief, and mental                             ent perspectives, art can break down
           health challenges. Creating art allows   Art as a catalyst for social change   prejudices and build bridges of under-
           individuals to externalize their struggles,   Art has long been a driving force for   standing. A powerful documentary, a
           giving them a sense of control and em-  social movements, challenging injus-  heartfelt poem, or a compelling theater
           powerment.                      tices, raising awareness, and inspiring   performance can evoke empathy, en-
             Building confidence and identity:   action. Throughout history, creative ex-  couraging viewers to see the world
           Creative expression encourages individ-  pression has been instrumental in shap-  through someone else’s eyes. This emo-
           uals to embrace their uniqueness and   ing public opinion and advocating for a   tional connection often leads to greater
           celebrate their identities. When someone   better world.        solidarity and collective action.
           pours their heart into a painting or writes   Raising awareness: Artistic works   Inspiring activism: Artistic expres-
           a song about their experiences, they val-  have the power to shine a light on socie-  sion can galvanize communities to de-
           idate their feelings and discover their   tal issues that might otherwise be over-  mand change. Murals in public spaces,
           voice. This process can be especially   looked. For example, protest songs like   for instance, often serve as bold state-
           empowering for marginalized groups,   Bob Dylan’s “Blowin' in the Wind” be-  ments of resistance or hope, inspiring
           offering them a platform to share their   came anthems for the civil rights move-  residents to take pride in their neighbor-
           narratives and assert their place in soci-  ment, while visual art like Pablo Pi-  hoods and advocate for their rights. Art-
           ety.                            casso’s "Guernica" highlighted the   ists like Banksy and Ai Weiwei use their
                                                                           work to provoke thought and challenge
                                                                           oppressive systems, demonstrating how
                                                                           creativity can be a formidable tool for
                                                                           activism.
                                                                           Strengthening communities
         A woman painting a mural on a city wall                           tary pursuit; it thrives in collaboration
                                                                           through creativity
                                                                              Artistic expression is not just a soli-

                                                                           and shared experiences. By fostering a
                                                                           sense of belonging and collective pur-
                                                                           pose, creativity can bring communities
                                                                           together and drive meaningful devel-
                                                                           opment.
                                                                              Creating shared spaces: Community
                                                                           art projects, such as murals, sculptures,
                                                                           or music festivals, transform public







         People participating in a community art project                                                   A person playing a shehnai-like instrument



















           20                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[A man shaping pots from raw clay                                                                  An artist in their creative workspace














                                                                           inequality—artistic expression offers
                                                                           hope, inspiration, and solutions. By fos-
                                                                           tering creativity, we empower individ-
                                                                           uals to grow, communities to thrive, and
                                                                           societies to evolve.

                                                                           To harness the transformative
         A group of people at a cultural event                             arts programs in schools and com-
                                                                           power of creativity, consider these
                                                                           steps:
                                                                              Support arts education: Advocate for

                                                                           munities, ensuring that everyone has ac-
                                                                           cess to creative opportunities.
                                                                              Celebrate local artists: Attend exhi-
                                                                           bitions, performances, and cultural
                                                                           events to support local talent and enrich

                                                                           tives.
                                                                              Engage in creative practices:
           spaces into hubs of interaction and cul-  but also provide artists with sustainable   your understanding of diverse perspec-
                                                                           Whether it’s painting, writing, or gar-
           tural celebration. These initiatives en-  livelihoods. For instance, in many devel-  dening, find a creative outlet that res-
           courage people to work together, foster-  oping regions, women’s cooperatives   onates with you and make it a part of
           ing a sense of unity and pride. For   centered around crafts have become   your routine.
           example, the Philadelphia Mural Arts   vital sources of income and empower-  Collaborate and share: Join com-
           Program has turned hundreds of blank   ment.                    munity art projects or workshops to con-
           walls into vibrant canvases, revitalizing   Healing and rebuilding: In com-  nect with others and contribute to col-
           neighborhoods and sparking economic   munities affected by conflict or disaster,   lective creativity.
           growth.                         art plays a crucial role in healing and re-  Use art for advocacy: Leverage cre-
             Preserving cultural heritage: Art   construction. Collaborative art projects   ative expression to raise awareness
           serves as a repository of history and tra-  can help individuals process collective   about issues you care about and inspire
           dition, helping communities preserve   trauma, rebuild trust, and envision a   others to take action.
           their cultural identity. Festivals, folk art,   brighter future. Organizations like “Ar-  Creativity is a gift that has the power
           and traditional performances keep her-  tolution” work with refugees and under-  to transform not only individual lives
           itage alive while educating younger gen-  served communities, using participatory   but also the fabric of society. As we
           erations about their roots. This cultural   art to promote resilience and social   honor International Creativity Month, let
           continuity strengthens community bonds   cohesion.              us embrace this gift and recognize its
           and instills a sense of pride in shared                         potential to make the world a more vi-
           history.                        Embracing creativity for a brighter   brant, inclusive, and compassionate
             Economic empowerment: Creative   future                       place.
           industries contribute significantly to   As we celebrate International Crea-  Through the lens of art and imagina-
           local economies by generating jobs, at-  tivity Month, let us remember that crea-  tion, we can build bridges where there
           tracting tourism, and fostering entrepre-  tivity is not a luxury but a necessity. In a   are divides, find hope in times of de-
           neurship. Artisan markets, art fairs, and   world grappling with complex chal-  spair, and create a future that celebrates
           local galleries not only showcase talent   lenges—from climate change to social   the richness of human expression. ■

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[THE HAND THAT WRITES                                            evolved to include calligraphy and cur-
                                                                           sive writing, forms of writing that were
     ANALYSIS  A tradition fading                                          way into the classroom and into every-
                                                                           not just functional but also artistic.
                                                                              However, as technology has made its
                                                                           day life, the reliance on handwritten
                                                                           communication has diminished. Com-
           in the digital storm                                            puters, smartphones, and tablets allow
                                                                           people to type their thoughts more
                                                                           quickly and with fewer physical de-
                                                                           mands than writing by hand. The instant
                                                                           accessibility and efficiency of digital
                                                                           tools have led to the widespread use of
           While technology has undoubtedly changed the way we             keyboards and touchscreens, both in
                                                                           educational settings and personal life.
           write, it is essential to recognize the value of handwriting    Even formal correspondence, which
           as both a functional skill and an art form. By Anaya Gupta      once required a handwritten letter, is
                                                                           now primarily typed and sent via email
                                                                           or social media. The handwritten word,
                                                                           once so ubiquitous, has given way to the
                                                                           digital script.
                                                                              On National Handwriting Day, it's
                                                                           important to consider how these changes
                                                                           are affecting our relationship with writ-
                                                                           ing. The rise of digital communication
                                                                           tools has certainly made life more con-
                                                                           venient, allowing people to write and
                                                                           send messages instantaneously, regard-
         A woman writing in her diary with a pen                           suming, deliberate practice of handwrit-
                                                                           less of location. But in the process,
                                                                           we’ve moved away from the time-con-
                                                                           ing, a skill that encouraged mindfulness,
                                                                           focus, and connection to one's thoughts.
                                                                           The impact on handwriting skills
                                                                           and cognitive development
                                                                              The consequences of moving away
                                                                           from handwriting are more profound

                                                                           Research has shown that handwriting

             n recent decades, technological ad-  write, communicate, and process infor-  than simply the loss of a manual skill.
             vancements have drastically re-  mation. This shift is not only about the
           Ishaped nearly every aspect of our   tools we use but also the skills that ac-
           lives, from how we communicate to how   company them, with handwriting being
           we entertain ourselves and even how we   gradually sidelined in favor of faster,
           work. The shift from physical to digital   more efficient alternatives. But what
           tools in the realm of communication and   does this shift mean for the future of
           writing is undeniable, and nowhere is   handwriting, and are we losing more
           this change more apparent than in the   than just a physical act? Are we losing
           decline of handwriting. Handwriting,   an essential link to culture, memory, and
           once a skill honed over years of practice   creativity?
           and a core aspect of personal expression,
           is now in danger of becoming a lost art.   The technological shift:
             National Handwriting Day, observed   Convenience vs. tradition                                Digital fonts replacing traditional handwritten calligraphy
           every year on January 23, serves as a re-  Handwriting was once a crucial as-
           minder of the importance of handwriting   pect of education and personal com-
           in our lives. It offers an opportunity to   munication. In classrooms around the
           reflect on the evolution of writing, par-  world, children learned the basics of
           ticularly how technology has influenced   writing with a pencil or pen, developing
           its decline. The advent of digital de-  fine motor skills and the cognitive abil-
           vices, from smartphones to laptops, has   ities that come with the act of writing by
           fundamentally altered the way people   hand. Over the years, this process

           22                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Good handwriting for every job                                                                    A Handwriting Artist at Work












           plays a crucial role in cognitive devel-
           opment, particularly in children. When
           children write by hand, they engage
           multiple areas of the brain that are in-
           volved in memory, motor skills, and lan-
           guage processing. Studies have sug-
           gested that writing by hand helps
           reinforce learning in ways that typing on
           a keyboard does not.
             In addition, handwriting has been
           linked to improved creativity and critical
           thinking. The physical act of forming                                                           An ancient Sanskrit manuscript
           letters and words by hand slows down
           the writing process, allowing individuals
           to think more deeply about their words
           and ideas. This stands in stark contrast
           to the rapidity of typing, where the em-
           phasis is on speed and efficiency rather   cline of handwriting in many respects, it
           than on reflective thought.     has also introduced new opportunities
             One of the most significant draw-  for innovation in the field. For example,
           backs of the digital age is that many   digital writing tools such as stylus pens,
           children and young adults today are not   tablets, and touchscreen devices allow
           being given the opportunity to develop   users to simulate the experience of writ-
           strong handwriting skills. With an in-  ing by hand while still benefiting from
           creasing emphasis on typing and using   the convenience of digital technology.
           digital devices in the classroom, stu-  Apps like GoodNotes and Notability
           dents are spending less time practicing   allow people to handwrite notes and
           handwriting. As a result, many students   draw directly on their devices, offering a
           struggle with legibility, and some even   hybrid experience that combines the best
           abandon handwriting altogether in favor   of both worlds.
           of typing. This shift is especially notice-  Additionally, the rise of digital fonts
           able in high school and college settings,   and handwriting recognition technology
           where handwritten notes and assign-  has enabled people to recreate their own                   A calligraphy artist at work
           ments are becoming rarer.       handwriting on computers. This has led
             The decline of handwriting skills has   to a resurgence of interest in personal-
           raised concerns among educators and   ized handwriting styles and digital cal-
           cognitive scientists. Some argue that the   ligraphy, with some users seeking to
           loss of this skill could have long-term   preserve their unique handwriting for   calligraphy and artistic writing. In many
           implications for the development of   use in digital communications. In this   cultures, the art of handwriting was once
           memory and comprehension. Handwrit-  way, technology has not only contrib-  deeply intertwined with cultural and
           ing experts often emphasize the impor-  uted to the decline of handwriting but   spiritual practices. One of the most no-
           tance of writing by hand in helping stu-  has also allowed it to evolve and adapt   table examples of this is the work of
           dents retain information and think   in the digital age.        Kaatib, the traditional Urdu calligrapher.
           critically about what they are learning.   Despite these advancements, the
                                           rapid growth of digital tools has over-  The Kaatib: Preserving the art of
           The role of technology in       shadowed more traditional forms of   handwritten Urdu
           preserving and evolving         writing, such as calligraphy, cursive, and   In the world of Urdu writing, the
           handwriting                     handwritten script. This trend is particu-  Kaatib played a central role in preserv-
             While technology has led to the de-  larly evident in the world of professional   ing and advancing the art of handwrit-

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[easier to produce written material
                                                                           quickly, it has also resulted in the loss of
                                                                           the artistry that characterized traditional
                                                                           handwriting. The work of the Kaatib,
                                                                           which once required years of practice
                                                                           and mastery, has been replaced by digi-
                                                                           tal fonts, which, while functional, lack
                                                                           the unique personal touch of hand-
                                                                           written script.
         Traditional calligraphy tools                                     example of the broader shift away from
                                                                              The decline of traditional calligraphy
                                                                           in the face of technology is a poignant

                                                                           handwritten communication. While digi-
                                                                           tal tools have brought convenience and
                                                                           efficiency, they have also led to the ero-
                                                                           sion of cultural practices that relied on
                                                                           the human touch. The art of the Kaatib,
                                                                           like other forms of handwritten artistry,
                                                                           risks being forgotten in a world increas-
                                                                           ingly dominated by digital fonts and
                                                                           typefaces.

                                                                           The future of handwriting: A digital
                                                                           renaissance or extinction?
                                                                              As we move further into the digital
                                                                           age, the question arises: Will handwrit-
                                                                           ing survive in the future, or will it be-
                                                                           come a forgotten skill? The answer is
                                                                           likely to be somewhere in between.
                                                                           While it is unlikely that handwriting will
         Arabic calligraphy art                                            role in society is changing. The rise of
                                                                           ever fully disappear, it is clear that its
                                                                           digital technology has already trans-
                                                                           formed the way we communicate, and
                                                                           handwriting, like many traditional skills,
                                                                           is being relegated to a secondary role.
                                                                              However, there is also a growing
                                                                           movement to preserve handwriting as an
                                                                           art form and a cultural practice. Callig-
                                                                           raphy and other forms of artistic hand-
                                                                           writing continue to thrive in niche com-
                                                                           munities, with artists and enthusiasts
                                                                           working to keep the tradition alive. In
                                                                           addition, educators and parents are in-
                                                                           creasingly recognizing the value of
                                                                           handwriting in cognitive development
                                                                           and are making efforts to ensure that
                                                                           children continue to learn and practice
         Chinese calligraphy art                                           Day serves as an important reminder of
                                                                           this skill.
                                                                              In conclusion, National Handwriting
                                                                           the role handwriting has played in shap-
                                                                           ing human communication and culture.
                                                                           While technology has undoubtedly
                                                                           changed the way we write, it is essential
                                                                           to recognize the value of handwriting as
           ing. These calligraphers, with their intri-  However, with the advent of modern   both a functional skill and an art form.
           cate and expressive strokes, were re-  technology, the role of the Kaatib has   Whether through digital tools or tradi-
           sponsible for transcribing sacred texts,   been significantly diminished. Today,   tional pen and paper, the future of hand-
           poetry, and other important works. The   desktop publishing software and word   writing will likely continue to evolve,
           beauty and precision of their work made   processors allow anyone to type in   but it is up to all of us to ensure that its
           handwritten Urdu manuscripts highly   Urdu, with elegant fonts available at the   legacy is preserved for future genera-
           valued and cherished.           click of a button. While this has made it   tions. ■

           24                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[PROFILE









                                                                                                           Arabic calligraphy art by Iqbal Raza

         Accomplished graphic designer and calligrapher, Iqbal Raza


























           Iqbal Raza Naqvi                                                                                Calligraphy in vibrant colors


           Reviving tradition




                                                                           my father create mesmerizing Arabic
           with modern                                                     calligraphy on paintings with a brush.
                                                                           His strokes brought the Arabic letters to
                                                                           life, turning them into beautiful Islamic
                                                                           art. Those moments are etched in my
                                                                           memory and became my source of inspi-
           creativity                                                      ration,” reminisces Iqbal Raza. Growing
                                                                           up surrounded by art, Iqbal found him-
                                                                           self drawn to his father’s legacy. Today,
                                                                           he carries forward the torch as a re-
                                                                           nowned graphic designer, calligrapher,
           Iqbal Raza’s story is a testament to the enduring power         and creative head of Raja Art Studio in
                                                                           Meerut, Uttar Pradesh.
           of art, a bridge between generations, cultures, and the            His father, the late H. R. Raja, was
           timeless beauty of human expression. By staff writer            internationally celebrated for his fine art
                                                                           paintings, which ranged from freedom
                                                                           fighter depictions to Hindu religious and
                  eerut-based accomplished   while inspiring a new generation to em-  Islamic paintings. “To continue his leg-
                  graphic designer and callig-  brace creativity and preserve their roots.   acy, my wife, Noor Alassaba, recipient
           Mrapher Iqbal Raza Naqvi                                        of the Yash Bharti Award from the U.P.
           weaves tradition and innovation into art,   A legacy of inspiration   Government, and I work together on
           breathing life into cultural heritage   “When I was small, I used to watch   graphic designing, portraits, paintings,

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Iqbal Raza with his wife, Noor Alassaba (portrait artist)


                                                                                                           A stunning calligraphy artwork by Iqbal Raza


















                                           he shares. His designs have been show-  models for printing presses. “They
                                           cased at prestigious events like the Lon-  maintained the beauty and legibility of
                                           don Book Fair, Frankfurt Book Fair, and   Urdu scripts for centuries,” he explains.
                                           Bologna Book Fair through a tie-up with
                                           a Berlin-based platform, FILU.   A blend of tradition and technology
         A captivating portrait masterpiece by Noor Alassaba
                                                                              With the rise of digital technology,
                                           The art of calligraphy          traditional calligraphy has transitioned
                                             For Iqbal, calligraphy is more than   into digital fonts. “Today, many Urdu
                                           just writing. “It’s an art that transforms   fonts replicate the aesthetics of hand-
                                           letters into beautiful, creative designs.   written calligraphy, allowing designers
                                           Practicing calligraphy connects me to   to use elegant calligraphy styles in digi-
                                           my cultural roots and traditions. It’s a   tal formats,” says Iqbal. Social media
                                           way of preserving our heritage,” he ex-  platforms have also given a new lease of
                                           plains. After years of digital art, Iqbal   life to Urdu calligraphy, helping artists
                                           found immense joy in returning to cal-  reach global audiences.
                                           ligraphy with brushes and Bamboo Qa-
                                           lams (pens made from bamboo).   The emotional connection
                                             Calligraphy has deep cultural signifi-  Beyond the technical skill, calligra-
                                           cance. Different styles, such as Arabic   phy holds an emotional and cultural res-
                                           calligraphy or Chinese brush writing, re-  onance. “Writing by hand, especially in
                                           flect the histories and values of their re-  calligraphy, helps people connect with
                                           spective cultures. “Learning calligraphy   their heritage. It’s a way to remember
           and educational book designs,” says   helps us understand the history and   and practice traditions passed down
           Iqbal. The family’s artistic journey   meaning behind these styles. It’s a way   through generations,” says Iqbal.
           began in the 1950s, and Iqbal has kept   to keep our traditions alive,” Iqbal adds.   Whether it’s crafting wedding invita-
           the flame burning bright.                                       tions or preserving historical manu-
                                           Preserving history through      scripts, calligraphy remains a cherished
           A journey of artistic growth    handwriting                     art form.
             Iqbal completed his master’s in Eng-  Historically, calligraphy has played a
           lish Literature from CCS University,   vital role in documenting religious texts,   Looking ahead
           Meerut, and a diploma in Applied Arts   ancient manuscripts, and literary works.   As Iqbal continues to balance tradi-
           from Aligarh Muslim University   In the Urdu language, traditional callig-  tion with innovation, his journey serves
           (AMU). His professional journey began   raphers, or Kaatibs, have shaped its de-  as an inspiration for budding artists and
           in New Delhi as a creative director at a   velopment and ensured the preservation   calligraphers. “Art has the power to pre-
           renowned advertising agency. However,   of scripts like Nastaliq. “Nastaliq’s   serve our past and shape our future. By
           his heart was in his hometown, and in   flowing, graceful curves are a testament   embracing both traditional and digital
           1994, after marriage, he returned to   to the artistry of Kaatibs who created   techniques, we can ensure that our cul-
           Meerut to join the family studio.   handwritten manuscripts that later be-  tural heritage continues to thrive,” he
             “Meerut is famous as an educational   came the foundation for printed texts,”   concludes with a smile.
           and publishing hub. I started designing   says Iqbal.              Iqbal Raza Naqvi’s story is a testa-
           book covers, which quickly gained ap-  Before the advent of digital printing,   ment to the enduring power of art, a
           preciation in the market. Within a few   calligraphy was indispensable in Urdu   bridge between generations, cultures,
           years, I established myself as a specialist   publishing. Kaatibs meticulously created   and the timeless beauty of human ex-
           in creative book cover design in India,”   handwritten manuscripts that served as   pression. ■

           26                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE







































               now has fascinated humankind for
               centuries, captivating artists,   THE SILENT LANGUAGE OF WINTER
           Swriters, and musicians with its
           pristine beauty and enigmatic qualities.
           This natural phenomenon, with its tran-
           sient and transformative character,   Snow
           evokes powerful imagery and emotions.
           In its gentle descent and inevitable melt-
           ing, snow symbolizes a spectrum of
           human experiences, from purity and
           peace to desolation and impermanence.   as a canvas of
             On World Snow Day, celebrated an-
           nually to honor the joys and challenges
           of winter sports and snowy landscapes,
           it is fitting to reflect on how snow has
           transcended its physical form to become   human emotions
           a profound symbol in art, literature,
           music, and cinema. Snow connects the
           external environment to the inner work-
           ings of the human spirit, creating a rich   Snow's symbolic richness in creative expression. It is more
           tapestry of meanings across cultures and   than just a natural phenomenon; it is a mirror of our emotions,
           creative expressions.
                                           a symbol of life's beauty and fragility. By Ishita Desai
           Snow in visual arts
             Snow has long been a subject in vi-
           sual arts, often symbolizing serenity,   Province, where snow-covered land-  the quiet beauty of a snowy scene,
           solitude, and renewal. Its unblemished   scapes contrast with the vitality of   where snow becomes a canvas reflecting
           whiteness is an emblem of purity, but its   human activity, highlighting harmony   sunlight, creating subtle shifts in tone
           vast expanse can also evoke feelings of   between nature and humanity.   and color. This play of light not only
           isolation or insignificance. Japanese   In Western art, the French Impres-  showcases Monet's technical mastery
           ukiyo-e artist Katsushika Hokusai fa-  sionists, notably Claude Monet, often   but also conveys an emotional stillness,
           mously depicted snow in his woodblock   painted snow as a study of light and   a moment suspended in time.
           prints, such as The Kajikazawa in Kai   shadow. Monet’s The Magpie captures   Modern art continues to use snow as

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[A quiet area after the snow                                                                       A cold city night following a snowfall










                                                                           tions. In classical music, composers like
                                                                           Claude Debussy and Pyotr Ilyich Tchai-
                                                                           kovsky translated the imagery of snow
                                                                           into soundscapes. Debussy's Des pas sur
                                                                           la neige (Footsteps in the Snow) is a
         A beautiful residential area covered in snow                      mirror the stillness of a winter land-
                                                                           haunting piano prelude that evokes the
                                                                           quiet melancholy of walking alone in
                                                                           the snow. The sparse, repetitive notes
                                                                           scape, conveying solitude and introspec-
                                                                           tion.
                                                                              Tchaikovsky’s The Nutcracker fea-
                                                                           tures the iconic "Waltz of the Snow-
                                                                           flakes," a piece that captures the magic
                                                                           and grace of falling snow through its
                                                                           sweeping orchestration and delicate
                                                                           melodies. This music brings snow to life
                                                                           as a symbol of beauty and wonder, tran-
                                                                           scending its physical form to become a
           a metaphor. Contemporary artists blend   tion, while the repeated refrain "miles to   medium for storytelling.
           traditional aesthetics with social com-  go before I sleep" hints at the inevitabil-  In popular music, snow often carries
           mentary, using snow to symbolize cli-  ity of life's journey.   emotional weight. Songs like Simon &
           mate change or the fragility of ecosys-  Russian literature often portrays   Garfunkel's "A Hazy Shade of Winter"
           tems. The ephemeral nature of snow   snow as a symbol of harshness and en-  or Fleet Foxes’ "White Winter Hymnal"
           reminds viewers of the transient beauty   durance. In Leo Tolstoy's War and   use snow to reflect themes of nostalgia,
           of the environment, urging them to pro-  Peace, the unforgiving Russian winter   change, and impermanence. Snow is not
           tect it.                        becomes a character in its own right,   merely a backdrop but a central image
                                           shaping the course of Napoleon's retreat   that shapes the mood and narrative of
           Snow in literature              and symbolizing the resilience of the   the music.
             Snow is a recurring motif in litera-  Russian people.
           ture, serving as both a setting and a sym-  In modern literature, snow frequently   Snow in Indian cinema and music
           bol. In Western literature, it often sig-  serves as a canvas for psychological   In Indian cinema, particularly Bolly-
           nifies both the start and end of cycles,   depth. Orhan Pamuk's novel Snow uses   wood, snow has played a dramatic and
           birth and death, hope and despair.   the setting of a snowbound Turkish town   aesthetic role, with snow-capped peaks
             In James Joyce's short story "The   to explore themes of identity, politics,   and icy landscapes becoming popular
           Dead," snow acts as a unifying meta-  and isolation. Here, snow reflects the   backdrops for romance and drama. The
           phor, blanketing Ireland and symboliz-  inner turmoil of the characters, blurring   pristine whiteness of snow is often used
           ing the universality of human mortality.   the line between clarity and obscurity,   to symbolize purity, eternal love, or mo-
           The snow's all-encompassing nature re-  order and chaos.        ments of profound emotional impact.
           flects the interconnectedness of life and                          Several Hindi film songs have been
           death, past and present. Similarly, in   Snow in music          filmed in snowy locales, blending visu-
           Robert Frost's poem "Stopping by   Snow has inspired countless musical   als of frosty landscapes with heartfelt
           Woods on a Snowy Evening," the snowy   compositions, often capturing its   lyrics. For instance:
           woods evoke tranquility and introspec-  ethereal beauty or its ability to stir emo-  "Tere Chehre Se Nazar Nahin Hatati"

           28                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[(Kabhi Na Kabhi, 1998): This romantic
           track, set against the snowy landscapes
           of Switzerland, showcases love bloom-
           ing amidst the icy peaks, using snow as
           a metaphor for unblemished emotions.
             "Gerua" (Dilwale, 2015): With Shah
           Rukh Khan and Kajol, this song com-
           bines snowy vistas with vivid imagery,
           evoking the idea of timeless love and                                                           A cultural scene of people in a snowy setting
           passion set against the serene whiteness
           of snow.
             "Yeh Haseen Wadiyan" (Roja, 1992):
           This iconic song captures the beauty of
           Kashmir's snow-covered landscapes,
           amplifying the romantic undertones with
           its soulful melody.
             "Zindagi Bhar Nahin Bhoolegi" (Bar-
           saat Ki Raat, 1960): The snow is a cen-
           tral element of the song, heightening the
           poignancy of the lyrics.
             Snow is also referenced in the lyrics
           of some classic Bollywood songs, with
           words like barf (snow) or hima (ice)
           used as poetic devices. The song "Barf
           Si Thandi Hai" from Judaai (1997) uses
           snow as a metaphor for emotional de-                                                            A Bollywood-style romance in the snow
           tachment and the coldness of strained
           relationships.

           The dual symbolism of snow
             What makes snow such a powerful
           symbol in creative expression is its dual-
           ity. On one hand, snow represents purity,   between the natural world and human
           renewal, and peace. Its pristine whiten-  existence. It is seen as a gift that blan-
           ess evokes innocence and simplicity,   kets the earth, protecting and nurturing it
           often associated with childhood mem-  during the harsh winter months. This in-
           ories of playful winters. On the other   terpretation underscores a sense of grat-
           hand, snow's coldness and silence can   itude and reverence for nature.
           signify desolation, death, and isolation.   In Indian culture, snow-capped Hi-
           This duality allows snow to resonate   malayan peaks are revered as sacred,
           with diverse emotional states, making it   embodying purity and divine energy.
           a versatile motif in art forms.   This reverence finds its way into
             For example, in films like Ingmar   cinema, music, and even literature,
           Bergman’s The Virgin Spring or Stanley   where snow becomes a symbol of spiri-
           Kubrick's The Shining, snow becomes   tual elevation and the sublime.                           Playing with snow is a common activity
           an oppressive force, underscoring
           themes of alienation and dread. In con-  Snow as an emotional mirror
           trast, animations like Disney's Frozen   The emotional resonance of snow
           portray snow as a magical element, sig-  lies in its ability to reflect human
           nifying empowerment and self-discov-  moods. For artists and audiences alike,
           ery.                            snow's quiet presence can evoke intro-
                                           spection, nostalgia, or even catharsis.   ability to inspire across art forms speaks
           Cultural interpretations        Whether it symbolizes a clean slate or   to its enduring allure and its capacity to
             Cultural perspectives also shape the   an impending end, snow invites viewers,   connect humanity with the profound
           symbolism of snow. In Japanese culture,   readers, and listeners to explore their   rhythms of nature.
           snow is closely tied to the concept of   inner worlds.             By exploring snow’s multifaceted
           "wabi-sabi," the beauty of imperfection   On World Snow Day, as we celebrate   symbolism in arts, literature, music, and
           and impermanence. The fleeting nature   the joys of winter and its snowy land-  Indian cinema, we not only deepen our
           of snowflakes, each unique yet short-  scapes, we are reminded of snow's sym-  appreciation for creativity but also gain
           lived, mirrors the transient nature of life   bolic richness in creative expression. It   insight into our shared human experi-
           itself.                         is more than just a natural phenomenon;   ence. Snow, in its silent descent, teaches
             In Native American traditions, snow   it is a mirror of our emotions, a symbol   us to pause, reflect, and find meaning in
           often represents the spiritual connection   of life's beauty and fragility. Snow’s   the ephemeral moments of life.

           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                              January 16-31, 2025









           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     Aries, this period brings renewed energy for    Libra, relationships are in focus. January 21
                     personal projects. Around January 20, you’ll feel   brings opportunities to strengthen bonds with
                     inspired to take bold steps toward your goals.   loved ones. Stay open to compromise, and avoid
                     Avoid rushing decisions, especially in financial   overthinking minor conflicts. Avoid dwelling on
                     matters.                                        minor disagreements.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Taurus, patience is your ally in late January. A   Scorpio, productivity soars as the month pro-
                     career opportunity may arise around January 24, so   gresses. Around January 27, tackle tasks you’ve
                     stay prepared. Balance your focus between       been postponing. Take time to rest and recharge
                     professional goals and personal relationships to   to avoid burnout. Remember to balance your
                     maintain harmony.                               hard work with relaxation.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Gemini, your social circle expands during this   Sagittarius, creativity and joy fill the second half
                     time. Networking around January 22 could lead   of January. A passion project or hobby may
                     to exciting possibilities. Be mindful of overcom-  flourish around January 23. Share your enthusi-
                     mitting, prioritize what truly matters. This is a   asm with others, and let your optimism inspire.
                     good time to revisit personal goals.            Stay optimistic.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Cancer, focus shifts to career and long-term    Capricorn, focus on home and family matters.
                     goals. Around January 25, you may receive rec-  January 26 may bring an opportunity to resolve
                     ognition for your hard work. Spend time reflect-  lingering issues. Use this time to nurture your
                     ing on personal growth and setting future inten-  connections and prioritize your well-being. Your
                     tions. Strengthen family bonds.                 steady approach will bring lasting results.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, adventure and learning take center stage.   Aquarius, communication is key in late January.
                     Travel or a new educational pursuit around Janu-  Around January 29, an idea or discussion could
                     ary 26 could broaden your horizons. Stay opti-  lead to exciting opportunities. Stay open to col-
                     mistic but avoid taking unnecessary risks. Take   laboration and embrace your innovative spirit.
                     calculated risks, but stay grounded.            Trust your innovative instincts.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, late January emphasizes personal growth   Pisces, finances and self-worth are highlighted.
                     and financial planning. Around January 28, a    Use January 30 to assess your resources and set
                     meaningful conversation may help you clarify    realistic goals. Trust your intuition to guide you
                     your priorities. Trust your instincts and remain   toward stability and success. A creative project
                     practical in your choices.                      may bring inspiration and peace.


           30                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Los Angeles wildfires and safety   occurring every 144 years, draws pil-
           measures                        grims to the Triveni Sangam for ritual
             The recent wildfires in Los Angeles   bathing, believed to cleanse sins and   stake, including governance and com-
           have devastated communities, claiming at   grant moksha.        munity welfare, voters must critically
           least 24 lives and destroying over 12,000   The significance of this event cannot   evaluate candidates' promises and inte-
           structures. As we confront these   be overstated; it symbolizes unity and   grity. This election is pivotal for shaping
           catastrophic events, it is imperative to   faith among diverse communities. With   Delhi's future; citizens must ensure their
           prioritize safety measures for residents.   key bathing dates like Makar Sankranti   voices are heard and counted.
                                           on January 14 and Mauni Amavasya on   The responsibility of safeguarding
             Authorities must enhance public   January 29, preparations must ensure   democracy lies with the voters. Let us
           awareness regarding evacuation routes   safety and accessibility for all attendees.   ensure this election reflects the true
           and emergency preparedness. The poten-  Local authorities should enhance in-  spirit of democracy by participating ac-
           tial for strong Santa Ana winds exacer-  frastructure, provide adequate sanitation,   tively and making informed choices.
           bates fire risks, necessitating timely   and ensure effective crowd manage-  Sunil Sharma, New Delhi, India
           alerts and community drills.    ment. As we embrace this momentous
             Moreover, improving infrastructure,   occasion, let us celebrate our shared her-
           such as ensuring functional hydrants and   itage and foster an environment of peace   A tribute to Dr. Mairajuddin Ahmad
           water supply systems during emer-  and devotion during this spiritual odys-  The passing of Dr. Mairajuddin
           gencies, is crucial. Local governments   sey.                   Ahmad is an irreplaceable loss, marking
           should also collaborate with environ-  Navneet Singh Ahluwalia, Prayagraj,   the conclusion of a remarkable chapter
           mental agencies to address the underly-  Uttar Pradesh, India   in our collective history. A stalwart in
           ing causes of these fires, including                            public service, he upheld the legacy of
           drought conditions and vegetation man-                          his father, Padma Shri Hakim Saifuddin
           agement.                        Delhi Assembly elections 2025   Ahmad, with grace and determination.
             As we navigate this crisis, a united   As the Delhi Assembly elections ap-  Known for his unwavering politeness
           effort is essential to protect lives and   proach on February 5, 2025, the political   and eloquence, Dr. Ahmad left an indeli-
           property. Let us advocate for proactive   landscape is charged with anticipation.   ble mark on politics, culture, and com-
           measures that can mitigate the impact of   The Aam Aadmi Party (AAP), led by   munity welfare.
           future wildfires.               Arvind Kejriwal, aims for a third con-  His leadership, whether as a minister
           Sushil Kumar, Bakersfield, Kern   secutive term, while the Bharatiya Ja-  or a cultural ambassador organizing lit-
           County, California              nata Party (BJP) seeks to break its long-  erary events, reflected his deep commit-
                                           standing drought in the capital.   ment to progress and harmony. The im-
                                           Allegations of electoral malpractices, in-  mense love and prayers during his final
           Maha Kumbh 2025 - A spiritual   cluding vote manipulation and distribu-  days at AIIMS showcased the profound
           odyssey                         tion of goods, have marred the campaign   respect he commanded. Dr. Ahmad’s de-
             As the Maha Kumbh Mela unfolds in   atmosphere, raising concerns about fair   mise leaves a void not just in Meerut but
           Prayagraj from January 13 to February   play in the electoral process26.   in the hearts of countless admirers. May
           26, 2025, it presents a unique opportu-  Moreover, Congress attempts to re-  his legacy continue to inspire future
           nity for millions of devotees seeking   gain relevance after its dismal perform-  leaders.
           spiritual renewal. This sacred gathering,   ance in 2020. With significant issues at   Rajeev Agarwal, New Delhi, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           JANUARY 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 www.revoir.in                                31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                  REVOIR
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                                ol. 3, No.1 |

                                                                                       |
                                                                                      |
                                                                              .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                           .revoir
                                                                                .in
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                               V

                                                                                         |
                                                                                         JANUAR
                                                                                          | AUGUST 01 202434
                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                          AUGUST

                                                                                        DECEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                                   16 2024
                                                                                         OCT

                                                                                        |
           34
           34
           34
                                                    www
           3434
           34
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           34
           3434                                     www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025 01 2025OBER 16 2023
           34
           34
           34
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                     www
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in REVOIR
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                       www
                                                                    www
                                                            www
                                                        .revoir www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | NOVEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | OCTOBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 16 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                             .in
                                                                .revoir
                                                               REVOIR Magazine
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>