<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="36"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 02, ISSUE: 15  I  SEPTEMBER 01 2024    ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL





              22



                                                             5













                                                            18                                        27
















           4-Editorial: Literacy—A cornerstone of          27-Bye-bye memory cards
           progress                                        31-The divine birth that changed the

           5-Bridging gaps with education                  world

           9-One day, every life matters                   33-Horoscopes

           13-The architects of tomorrow                   34-Letters
           18-Building a better world

           22-Steering into an electric future















           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Literacy
     EDITORIAL  A cornerstone of                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi



                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief
           progress                                                               Art & Culture Editor


                                                                                      Aishwarya
                                                                                     Natasha Goel

                                              s the world observes International   Social & Lifestyle Editor
                                              Literacy Day on September 8th, we
                                        Aare reminded that literacy is not          Dr. Uzma Naaz
                                        merely a fundamental skill but the
                                        cornerstone of personal empowerment and   Digital Strategy Editor
                                        societal progress. The ability to read and   Sushil Kumar
                                        write opens doors to education, opportunity,
                                        and a better quality of life. Yet, despite   Social Media Editor
                                        global advancements, the journey toward    Vishakha Sharma
                                        universal literacy is far from complete.
                                           In India, literacy has been a central focus   Art & Graphics Director
                                        of national development efforts for decades.   Vipin Agarwal
                                        Significant strides have been made, with the
                                        literacy rate increasing from just 18% at the
           time of independence to over 77% today. Government initiatives such as the Sarva
           Shiksha Abhiyan and the National Literacy Mission have played pivotal roles in   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           driving this progress. However, challenges remain. The literacy gap between urban
           and rural areas, and between men and women, persists. In many parts of the country,   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           especially in rural and remote regions, access to quality education is still limited.   Editor, United News of India, New
             The gender gap in literacy rates is particularly concerning. Despite progress,   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           women continue to lag behind men in literacy, reflecting broader societal   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           inequalities. This disparity is more pronounced in rural areas, where traditional   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           gender roles and limited access to educational resources often prevent girls from   Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           completing their education. Addressing this issue requires not only improving access   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           to schools but also changing societal attitudes towards the education of girls and
           women.                                                            N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
             The COVID-19 pandemic has further exacerbated these challenges, widening the   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           educational divide. School closures and the shift to online learning have left many
           students, particularly those from disadvantaged backgrounds, struggling to keep up.   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           The digital divide has highlighted the disparities in access to education, with millions
           of children in India lacking the resources to continue their studies remotely. As we   Phone +91 20 40199102
           move forward, it is essential to address these inequities and ensure that education is   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           accessible to all, regardless of gender, geography, or economic status.   Baner Road,
             Governments, educators, and communities must renew their commitment to   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           literacy. This includes investing in education, supporting teachers, and creating   Email revoir@post.com
           inclusive learning environments. It also means embracing innovative approaches,   Website www.revoir.in
           such as digital learning platforms and community-based programs, to reach those
           who have been left behind.
             As we celebrate International Literacy Day, let us recognize that literacy is more   Legal Advisor
           than a skill; it is a fundamental human right and a critical driver of sustainable   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
           development. By ensuring that everyone has the opportunity to become literate, we
           lay the groundwork for a more just, equitable, and prosperous world. The pursuit of   Copyright © 2024 REVOIR (eZine),
           literacy for all must remain at the forefront of our collective efforts.   all rights reserved. This publication
                                                                            may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.



         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief

           4                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[International literacy day



           Bridging gaps with                                                                                    COVER STORY




           education





           Literacy is more than just a skill—it is a gateway to opportunity,
           empowerment, and a better quality of life. By Naina Kapoor












































              nternational Literacy Day (ILD),   Historical context and significance   of literacy for individuals, communities,
              celebrated annually on September   The concept of International Literacy   and societies.
              8th, is a powerful reminder of the   Day emerged during the World Confer-  The significance of International Lit-
           Iimportance of literacy as a matter   ence of Ministers of Education on the   eracy Day has only grown over the dec-
           of dignity and human rights. Established   Eradication of Illiteracy, which took   ades. In a world where knowledge and
           by UNESCO in 1966, this day aims to   place in Tehran in 1965. The idea was to   information are pivotal to personal and
           promote literacy as a tool for individual   create a day that would draw attention to   societal advancement, literacy is the
           empowerment and societal devel-  the global literacy crisis and the need for   foundation upon which other skills are
           opment. Literacy is not just the ability to   concerted efforts to improve education   built. The ability to read and write en-
           read and write; it encompasses a broader   and literacy worldwide. The following   ables individuals to access information,
           understanding of communication, infor-  year, UNESCO declared September 8th   make informed decisions, and partici-
           mation, and knowledge acquisition that   as International Literacy Day, with the   pate fully in their communities. It is a
           is essential for personal and community   primary goal of reminding the inter-  critical factor in reducing poverty, im-
           growth.                         national community of the importance   proving health, promoting gender equal-

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Tools that make literacy possible                                                                 Women empowered through education













           ity, and ensuring sustainable devel-
           opment.

           Literacy as a fundamental human
           right
             Literacy is a basic human right, rec-
           ognized in various international conven-
           tions and declarations, including the
           Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
           Article 26 of this declaration states that
           everyone has the right to education. Lit-
           eracy is a key component of education
           and is essential for the exercise of other
           human rights. Without literacy, individ-                                                        A teacher interacting with a student
           uals are often excluded from the oppor-
           tunities and benefits of society, leading
           to a cycle of poverty and marginaliza-
           tion.
             Furthermore, literacy is not just about
           acquiring the skills to read and write. It
           is also about empowering individuals to   Sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia have   ganizations play a crucial role in ad-
           interpret and critically engage with the   some of the lowest literacy rates, with   dressing the global literacy crisis. Na-
           world around them. Literacy enables   millions of children out of school and   tional governments are responsible for
           people to access information, express   adults unable to read or write. In con-  creating and implementing education
           themselves, and advocate for their   flict-affected areas, the situation is even   policies that prioritize literacy and en-
           rights. It is a powerful tool for social and   more dire, as educational infrastructure   sure that all citizens have access to qual-
           economic mobility, allowing individuals   is often destroyed, and displaced pop-  ity education. This includes investing in
           to improve their circumstances and con-  ulations struggle to access basic serv-  teacher training, providing adequate
           tribute meaningfully to society.   ices, including education.   educational resources, and creating in-
                                             The COVID-19 pandemic further ex-  clusive educational environments that
           Global literacy challenges      acerbated these challenges. School clo-  cater to the needs of all learners.
             Despite significant progress over the   sures, disruptions in education, and the   International organizations like
           past few decades, literacy remains a crit-  shift to online learning have widened the   UNESCO, UNICEF, and the World
           ical challenge in many parts of the   educational divide, particularly for those   Bank work with governments to support
           world. According to UNESCO, there are   without access to digital technologies.   literacy initiatives and provide technical
           still 773 million adults globally who   Many children, especially those from   and financial assistance. These organiza-
           lack basic literacy skills, two-thirds of   disadvantaged backgrounds, have fallen   tions also help to monitor global pro-
           whom are women. This gender disparity   behind in their learning, with long-term   gress on literacy and advocate for the in-
           highlights the broader issue of gender   implications for their literacy and over-  clusion of literacy as a key component
           inequality in education, where girls and   all educational outcomes.   of sustainable development goals.
           women often face barriers to accessing                             One of the most significant inter-
           and completing their education.   The role of governments and   national efforts to promote literacy is the
             The literacy gap is also starkly ev-  international organizations   United Nations’ Sustainable Devel-
           ident in different regions of the world.   Governments and international or-  opment Goal 4 (SDG 4), which aims to

           6                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[ensure inclusive and equitable quality
           education and promote lifelong learning
           opportunities for all. Literacy is a central
           part of this goal, and achieving universal
           literacy is seen as essential for the real-
           ization of other SDGs, such as ending
           poverty (SDG 1), achieving gender
           equality (SDG 5), and promoting decent
           work and economic growth (SDG 8).

           Innovative approaches to
           promoting literacy
             To address the complex challenges of
           global literacy, innovative approaches
           and strategies are necessary. These in-
           clude leveraging technology, com-
           munity-based initiatives, and targeted
           programs for vulnerable populations.
             Technology and digital literacy:
           The rise of digital technology offers new
           opportunities to promote literacy. Mo-
           bile phones, tablets, and other digital de-
           vices can be used to deliver educational
           content to remote and underserved com-
           munities. For example, digital learning
           platforms and apps can provide inter-                           Global Literacy Success Stories
           active and engaging literacy lessons, al-                          Several successful literacy programs
           lowing learners to study at their own                           around the world have made significant
           pace. However, the digital divide re-                           strides in improving literacy rates and
           mains a significant challenge, with                             access to education. Here are some no-
           many people lacking access to these                             table initiatives:
           technologies. Bridging this divide is es-
           sential for ensuring that everyone can                          World Reader
           benefit from digital literacy initiatives.                         World Reader focuses on providing
             Community-based literacy pro-                                 digital books to children and families in
           grams: Community-based programs are                             developing countries. Operating in 69
           critical in promoting literacy at the                           countries, the program has delivered
           grassroots level. These programs often                          over 28,000 titles in 43 languages, lever-
           involve local organizations, volunteers,                        aging mobile technology to enhance ac-
           and educators working together to pro-                          cess to reading materials in areas with
           vide literacy classes, reading materials,                       limited resources.
           and support for learners. Community li-
           braries, adult education centers, and                           Book Aid
           reading clubs are examples of initiatives                          Established in 1954, Book Aid aims
           that can help promote literacy in local                         to create vibrant libraries and inspire
           communities. Such programs are par-  A library – Grassroots literacy efforts  readers in Africa, Palestine, and South
           ticularly effective in reaching margin-                         Sudan. The organization has distributed
           alized populations, such as women, rural   ticipate more fully in their communities   over 31 million books and has also in-
           communities, and indigenous peoples,   and the economy.         vested in training librarians and estab-
           who may not have access to formal edu-  Literacy in emergencies: In conflict   lishing children's corners in libraries, en-
           cation.                         and crisis situations, access to education   hancing community engagement with
             Literacy for all ages: Promoting lit-  and literacy programs is often disrupted.   reading.
           eracy is not limited to children and   Literacy in emergencies programs aim
           young people. Adult literacy programs   to provide learning opportunities for   World Literacy Foundation
           are essential for providing older individ-  children and adults in these challenging   The World Literacy Foundation
           uals with the skills they need to improve   circumstances. These programs may in-  works to eradicate illiteracy by provid-
           their lives. These programs often focus   clude setting up temporary learning   ing educational resources and support to
           on functional literacy, which includes   spaces, providing learning materials,   marginalized youth. Their programs are
           skills related to everyday tasks, such as   and training teachers to work in emer-  designed to foster literacy skills that are
           reading signs, filling out forms, and un-  gency contexts. Ensuring continuity of   essential for personal and professional
           derstanding health information. Adult   education during crises is vital for main-  development, with operations in various
           literacy initiatives also play a crucial   taining literacy levels and preventing   countries including Australia, the USA,
           role in empowering individuals to par-  further educational disparities.   and the UK.

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[826 National
             This nonprofit organization operates
           writing and tutoring centers across the
           United States, providing free support to
           under-resourced students aged 6 to 18.
           Through creative writing programs and
           tutoring, 826 National aims to enhance
           students' writing skills and boost their
           confidence.

           Indigenous Literacy Foundation
             Based in Australia, this foundation
           focuses on improving literacy among in-
           digenous populations. They supply
           books to remote communities and sup-
           port literacy initiatives like story times,
           reaching speakers of 26 different lan-
           guages and publishing books by indige-
           nous authors.
           Vamos Ler! (Let's Read!)
             This program in Mozambique aims
           to improve literacy among primary
           school students. By focusing on fluency
           and comprehension in local languages
           for Grades 1 to 3, Vamos Ler! addresses
           educational challenges in a country
           where enrollment has increased but out-
           comes remain inadequate.

           Teacher Citizen Participation
           Project
             Funded by USAID, this initiative in
           Honduras aims to enhance child literacy
           rates through community involvement
           in education, professional development
           for teachers, and increased access to
           reading materials. The project has suc-
           cessfully improved educational quality
           in local schools.

           The future of literacy: Moving
           forward                                                                                         Left: Critical role of teachers in promoting literacy
             As we look to the future, it is clear                                                           Top: A research scholar selecting a book
           that promoting literacy will require con-
           tinued commitment, innovation, and
           collaboration. The challenges are signif-
           icant, but so are the opportunities. By
           harnessing the power of technology, em-
           powering communities, and prioritizing
           education in policy and practice, we can
           make strides toward a more literate   sectors of society.
           world.                            International Literacy Day reminds
             International Literacy Day serves as   us that literacy is more than just a
           a call to action for governments, organi-  skill—it is a gateway to opportunity,
           zations, and individuals to renew their   empowerment, and a better quality of
           commitment to literacy and education. It   life. It is the foundation upon which we
           is a day to celebrate the progress made,   build our futures, both individually and             Girl child education in rural areas
           but also to recognize the work that re-  collectively. As we celebrate this day, let
           mains to be done. Achieving universal   us reaffirm our commitment to making
           literacy is not just a goal for educators   literacy a reality for all, ensuring that no
           or policymakers; it is a shared respon-  one is left behind in the journey towards
           sibility that requires the efforts of all   a more educated and equitable world. ■

           8                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Prevent Suicide                                                 The highest rates of suicide are often
                                                                           found in low- and middle-income coun-
                                                                           tries, where mental health resources are
           One day, every                                                  income countries remain significant,   IN FOCUS
                                                                           limited. However, suicide rates in high-
                                                                           with contributing factors including lone-
                                                                           liness, substance abuse, and chronic
                                                                           mental health conditions.
           life matters                                                    Risk factors for suicide

                                                                              While there is no single cause for
                                                                           suicide, several risk factors increase the
                                                                           likelihood of an individual contemplat-
           By raising awareness, promoting understanding, and              ing or attempting suicide:
                                                                              Mental health disorders: Depres-
           encouraging both individual and collective efforts, we can      sion, bipolar disorder, schizophrenia,
                                                                           and other psychiatric conditions are
           make a significant impact in reducing suicide rates globally.   strongly associated with suicide. Indi-



           By Rajeev Khanna



                  orld Suicide Prevention Day
                  (WSPD) is observed every
           Wyear on September 10th. Es-
           tablished in 2003 by the International
           Association for Suicide Prevention
           (IASP) and endorsed by the World
           Health Organization (WHO), the day
           serves as a global platform to raise
           awareness about suicide, its risk factors,
           and preventive measures. Suicide is a
           profound public health issue, claiming
           the lives of nearly 700,000 people an-
           nually, with millions more attempting it.
           The observance of WSPD provides an
           opportunity to highlight the importance
           of mental health, foster discussions, and
           implement actions that can save lives.

           Understanding suicide
             Suicide is the act of intentionally
           causing one’s own death. It is a complex
           issue influenced by a myriad of factors,
           including psychological, environmental,
           social, and cultural dynamics. Contrary
           to common belief, suicide is not an act
           of cowardice or selfishness; rather, it is
           often a response to overwhelming pain,
           hopelessness, and a perceived lack of
           options. Individuals who contemplate
           suicide are usually struggling with se-
           vere emotional distress, mental health
           disorders, or traumatic experiences.
           Global statistics and trends
             Suicide affects individuals across all
           age groups, socioeconomic statuses, and
           cultural backgrounds. According to the
           WHO, it is the fourth leading cause of
           death among 15-29-year-olds globally.

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                     9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[viduals with untreated or inadequately
                                                                           managed mental health issues are par-
                                                                           ticularly vulnerable.
                                                                              Substance abuse: Alcohol and drug
                                                                           misuse can exacerbate suicidal thoughts
                                                                           and impair judgment, increasing the risk
                                                                           of impulsive actions.
                                                                              Chronic illness and pain: Persistent
                                                                           physical health problems, especially
                                                                           those that cause chronic pain or disabil-
                                                                           ity, can lead to feelings of despair and
                                                                           suicidal ideation.
                                                                              History of trauma and abuse: Indi-
                                                                           viduals who have experienced physical,
                                                                           emotional, or sexual abuse, particularly
         A hanging noose                                                   suicide.
                                                                           in childhood, are at a heightened risk of
                                                                              Social isolation: Loneliness and so-
                                                                           cial disconnection are significant risk
                                                                           factors, particularly in older adults. The
                                                                           absence of a supportive social network
                                                                           can lead to a sense of hopelessness.
                                                                              Economic stress: Financial diffi-
                                                                           culties, unemployment, and job-related
                                                                           stress can contribute to suicidal
                                                                           thoughts, especially when compounded
                                                                           by other risk factors.
                                                                              Family history of suicide: A family
                                                                           history of suicide or suicidal behavior
                                                                           can increase the likelihood of similar be-
                                                                           havior in individuals, potentially due to
         A depressed woman in need of help                                 Warning signs of suicide
                                                                           genetic and environmental influences.

                                                                              Recognizing the warning signs of
                                                                           suicide is crucial for prevention. While
                                                                           not everyone will exhibit clear indi-
                                                                           cators, some common warning signs in-
                                                                           clude:
                                                                              Talking about suicide: Expressing a
                                                                           desire to die, talking about being a bur-
                                                                           den to others, or discussing methods of











         An attempt at suicide can be prevented                                                            Falling from the roof
















           10                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[suicide should be taken seriously.   tigue, changes in sleep patterns, and un-
                                             Behavioral changes: Significant   explained physical pain can also be as-
                                           changes in behavior, such as withdrawal   sociated with suicidal thoughts.
                                           from social activities, increased sub-
                                           stance use, or reckless behavior, may   Prevention strategies
                                           signal distress.                   Preventing suicide requires a multi-
                                             Mood changes: Severe mood     faceted approach that involves individ-
                                           swings, increased anxiety, agitation, or a   uals, communities, and governments.
                                           sudden sense of calm after a period of   Effective prevention strategies include:
                                           depression could be red flags.     Improving mental health care: Ac-
                                             Giving away possessions: Individ-  cess to quality mental health services is
                                           uals contemplating suicide may begin   crucial for those at risk of suicide. This
         A person’s body after suicide     for their death.                viduals with mental health disorders.
                                                                           includes timely diagnosis, effective
                                           giving away their belongings, making
                                                                           treatment, and ongoing support for indi-
                                           wills, or settling affairs as they prepare
                                                                              Reducing stigma: Stigma surround-
                                             Feeling trapped or hopeless: Ex-
                                           pressing feelings of hopelessness, being
                                                                           ing mental health and suicide often pre-
                                                                           vents individuals from seeking help.
                                           trapped, or seeing no way out of a diffi-
                                                                           Public awareness campaigns, education,
                                           cult situation can indicate suicidal ide-
                                                                           and open conversations can help reduce
                                           ation.
                                             Physical symptoms: Chronic fa-
                                                                           stigma and encourage people to seek the
                                                                           support they need.
                                                                              Promoting social connections:
                                                                           Strong social networks and community
                                                                           connections can act as protective factors
                                                                           against suicide. Initiatives that foster
                                                                           community engagement, peer support,
                                                                           and social inclusion are essential.
                                                                              Responsible Media reporting:
         Depression can lead to thoughts of suicide                        sible reporting that avoids sensational-
                                                                           Media plays a significant role in shaping
                                                                           public perception of suicide. Respon-
                                                                           ism, provides information on support re-
                                                                           sources, and respects the privacy of
                                                                           those affected can help prevent suicide
                                                                           contagion.
                                                                              Restricting access to means: Reduc-
                                                                           ing access to common methods of sui-
                                                                           cide, such as firearms, pesticides, and
                                                                           certain medications, has been shown to
                                                                           decrease suicide rates. Policy measures
                                                                           and safety protocols can play a critical
                                                                           role in this regard.
                                                                              Crisis intervention services: Hot-
                                                                           lines, chat services, and other crisis in-
                                                                           tervention resources provide immediate
                                                                           support for individuals in distress. These
                                                                           services can offer counseling, safety
                                                                           planning, and referrals to appropriate
                                                                           care.
                                                                              Training gatekeepers: Training pro-
                                                                           grams for teachers, healthcare providers,
         Many factors can cause depression                                 signs of suicide and intervene effec-
                                                                           law enforcement, and community
                                                                           leaders can equip them to recognize the

                                                                           tively.
                                                                              Supporting survivors: Individuals
                                                                           who have lost someone to suicide are at
                                                                           an increased risk of mental health issues
                                                                           and suicide themselves. Providing sup-
                                                                           port to these survivors through counsel-

                                                                           is essential.

                                                                                                       11
           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                        ing, support groups, and other resources]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[The role of world suicide
           prevention day
             World Suicide Prevention Day plays
           a pivotal role in the global effort to re-
           duce suicide rates. The day serves as a
           reminder that suicide is preventable, and
           that everyone has a role to play in sav-
           ing lives. The themes for WSPD often
           focus on fostering hope, connecting in-
           dividuals to support systems, and em-
           powering communities to take action.                                                            Candles lit in memory of those lost to suicide
           Awareness campaigns
             On WSPD, awareness campaigns are
           launched globally to educate the public
           about suicide prevention. These cam-
           paigns use various platforms, including
           social media, public events, and educa-
           tional workshops, to spread key mes-
           sages about the importance of mental
           health, the availability of resources, and
           the need to reach out for help.
           Community engagement
             Communities around the world or-
           ganize events such as candlelight vigils,
           walks, and memorial services to honor
           those who have lost their lives to suicide
           and to support the bereaved. These
           events provide a space for individuals to                                                       Moral support is crucial during depression
           share their stories, connect with others
           who have been affected, and raise
           awareness about the importance of men-
           tal health.

           Policy advocacy
             WSPD is also a time for advocacy,
           where mental health organizations and   The importance of hope and   fostering hope through connection,
           advocates call on governments to imple-  connection             whether it be through professional sup-
           ment policies that prioritize suicide pre-  At the heart of suicide prevention is   port, community networks, or personal
           vention. This includes increasing fund-  the concept of hope. Hope can be a pow-  relationships.
           ing for mental health services, enacting   erful antidote to despair, offering indi-  World Suicide Prevention Day is
           legislation to restrict access to means of   viduals a reason to keep going even in   more than just a day of remembrance; it
           suicide, and promoting research into ef-  the face of overwhelming challenges.   is a call to action. By raising awareness,
           fective prevention strategies.   WSPD emphasizes the importance of   promoting understanding, and encourag-
                                                                           ing both individual and collective ef-
                                                                           forts, we can make a significant impact
                                                                           in reducing suicide rates globally. The
                                                                           road to prevention is paved with empa-
                                                                           thy, education, and proactive interven-
         A march for collective action and awareness                       unwavering commitment to preserving
                                                                           tion. Every life saved is a testament to
                                                                           the power of hope, connection, and the

                                                                           the sanctity of life.
                                                                              As we observe WSPD each year, let
                                                                           us remember that preventing suicide is
                                                                           everyone’s responsibility.
                                                                              Whether through small acts of kind-
                                                                           ness, offering a listening ear, or advocat-
                                                                           ing for better mental health services,
                                                                           each of us can contribute to making the
                                                                           world a safer, more compassionate
                                                                           place. ■

           12                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[The                                                             appreciation. For example, in India,
                                                                           Teachers' Day is observed on September
                                                                           5th, the birth anniversary of Dr. Sarve-
                                                                           palli Radhakrishnan, a renowned philos-
                                                                           opher, scholar, and the second President
                                                                           of India. Dr. Radhakrishnan was an em-  INSIGHT
           architects of                                                   utions to education were so profound
                                                                           inent teacher himself, and his contrib-
                                                                           that when he became President, his stu-
                                                                           dents requested that his birthday be cele-
                                                                           brated as Teachers' Day.
                                                                              In the United States, National
           tomorrow                                                        day of the first full week of May. This
                                                                           Teachers' Day is celebrated on the Tues-
                                                                           date was chosen by the National Educa-
                                                                           tion Association (NEA) in 1980 to honor
                                                                           teachers for their dedication and hard
                                                                           work. Similarly, in many other coun-
           Teachers' Day is a day to honor the tireless                    tries, Teachers' Day is observed on dates
                                                                           that have historical or cultural signifi-
           efforts of teachers who shape the future by                     cance related to education and teaching.
                                                                           The role of teachers in society
           inspiring and guiding their students.                              Teachers are the bedrock of any edu-
                                                                           cational system. They not only impart
                                                                           knowledge but also inspire, guide, and
                                                                           mentor students. The impact of a teacher














                                                                                                           A teacher using a blackboard in class















                                           cance, and celebration of Teachers' Day,   extends beyond the classroom, influenc-
           By Aarav Sharma                 shedding light on why this day is so im-  ing students' personal and professional
                                           portant and how it is observed globally.   lives. Effective teaching fosters critical
                eachers' Day is a special occasion                         thinking, creativity, and emotional intel-
                dedicated to honoring the ex-  Origins and significance of   ligence, helping students become well-
           Ttraordinary contributions of edu-  teachers' day: Historical roots   rounded individuals.
           cators around the world. It is a day when   Teachers' Day is celebrated on var-  Teachers play a pivotal role in shap-
           students, parents, and communities   ious dates across the world, often re-  ing the future by nurturing the next gen-
           come together to recognize the invalu-  flecting the country's own historical and   eration of leaders, thinkers, and innova-
           able role that teachers play in shaping   cultural context. In many countries, the   tors. They create an environment where
           the future of individuals and society.   day is marked by a combination of for-  students feel valued, encouraged, and
           This article explores the origins, signifi-  mal ceremonies and informal gestures of   motivated to achieve their best. Through

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan, former President                                                    A teacher engaging with students



















           their dedication, teachers contribute to   cational institutions often hold special   cates are given to those who have shown
           the overall progress of society, making   events and activities to celebrate their   exceptional dedication and innovation in
           their role indispensable.       teachers. These may include:    their teaching methods.
                                             Ceremonies and awards: Many      Student performances: Students
           Celebrating Teachers' Day:      schools organize ceremonies where out-  often prepare performances, such as
           Traditional observances         standing teachers are recognized for   songs, dances, or skits, to show their ap-
             On Teachers' Day, schools and edu-  their contributions. Awards and certifi-  preciation for their teachers. These per-
                                                                           formances are usually held during
                                                                           school assemblies or special gatherings.
                                                                              Gift giving: Students and parents
                                                                           may present teachers with gifts, cards,
                                                                           or flowers as tokens of appreciation.
                                                                           These gestures, though simple, are a
                                                                           heartfelt way of acknowledging the
                                                                           teachers' hard work and dedication.
                                                                              Special activities: Schools may or-
                                                                           ganize special activities or events, such
                                                                           as workshops, seminars, or cultural pro-
                                                                           grams, to celebrate the day. These activ-
                                                                           ities are designed to provide teachers
                                                                           with a sense of recognition and appreci-
                                                                           ation.
                                                                           Global Variations
                                                                              The way Teachers' Day is celebrated
                                                                           can vary widely across different cultures
                                                                           and countries. For instance:
                                                                              In China, Teachers' Day is celebrated
                                                                           on September 10th. The day is marked
                                                                           by various activities, including student
                                                                           performances and thank-you notes. The
                                                                           government also uses this day to pro-
                                                                           mote educational reforms and policies.
         A teacher overjoyed by gifts from students                        school-wide activities and events to
                                                                              In Japan, Teachers' Day is celebrated
                                                                           on October 5th, aligning with World
                                                                           Teachers' Day. The celebration includes
                                                                           honor teachers and acknowledge their
                                                                           contributions to education.
                                                                              In South Korea, Teachers' Day is ob-
                                                                           served on May 15th. Students typically
                                                                           give carnations and handwritten letters
                                                                           to their teachers, expressing their grat-
                                                                           itude and appreciation.
                                                                              In Brazil, Teachers' Day is celebrated
                                                                           on October 15th. The day is marked by

           14                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[various activities in schools and educa-
           tional institutions, with a focus on rec-
           ognizing the hard work and dedication
           of teachers.

           The Importance of Teachers' Day
             Teachers' Day serves multiple impor-
           tant functions:
             Acknowledgment and apprecia-
           tion: The day provides an opportunity to
           formally recognize and appreciate the
           efforts of teachers. It serves as a re-
           minder of the critical role they play in
           shaping the future and the impact they
           have on students' lives.
             Encouragement and motivation:
           Celebrating Teachers' Day can boost the
           morale of educators. It reinforces their
           commitment to their profession and mo-
           tivates them to continue their valuable
           work.
             Public awareness: Teachers' Day                                                               The student-teacher bond is crucia
           helps raise public awareness about the
           challenges and rewards of the teaching
           profession. It highlights the need for
           support and investment in education to
           ensure that teachers have the resources
           they need to succeed.
             Strengthening community bonds:   often face numerous challenges in their   sources, such as outdated textbooks, in-
           The day fosters a sense of community   profession. These challenges can in-  adequate classroom materials, and insuf-
           by bringing together students, parents,   clude:                ficient funding.
           and educators in celebration. It   Workload and stress: Teachers   Low salaries: In some regions,
           strengthens the bond between these   frequently deal with heavy workloads,   teachers are not adequately compensated
           groups and promotes a collaborative ap-  including lesson planning, grading, and   for their work. This can impact their job
           proach to education.            administrative tasks. This can lead to   satisfaction and the overall quality of
                                           significant stress and burnout.   education.
           Challenges faced by teachers      Limited resources: Many educators   Societal expectations: Teachers are
             Despite the celebrations, teachers   work in environments with limited re-  often expected to address a wide range
















                                                                                                           Active teaching and student involvement

















           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[collaboration and sharing of best prac-
                                                                           tices in education. Teachers' Day could
                                                                           serve as a platform for fostering inter-
                                                                           national cooperation and learning.
                                                                              Advocacy for education: Teachers'
                                                                           Day could also become a focal point for
                                                                           advocating for educational reforms and
                                                                           policies that support teachers and im-
                                                                           prove the quality of education.
                                                                              Teachers' Day is a meaningful occa-
                                                                           sion that celebrates the dedication and
                                                                           impact of educators around the world. It
                                                                           is a day to honor the tireless efforts of
                                                                           teachers who shape the future by inspir-
                                                                           ing and guiding their students. While the
                                                                           ways in which Teachers' Day is cele-
                                                                           brated may vary, the underlying message
                                                                           remains the same: a deep appreciation
                                                                           for the vital role that teachers play in our
           of issues beyond academics, including   show appreciation.      lives and our society.
           social and emotional support for stu-  Focus on well-being: There is an in-  As we observe Teachers' Day, let us
           dents. Balancing these expectations with   creasing recognition of the need to sup-  take a moment to reflect on the chal-
           their teaching responsibilities can be   port teachers' well-being. Future cele-  lenges faced by educators and the im-
           challenging.                    brations may include a greater emphasis   portance of supporting them. By rec-
             Addressing these challenges requires   on addressing mental health and provid-  ognizing their contributions and
           a concerted effort from governments,   ing resources to help teachers manage   advocating for improvements in the edu-
           educational institutions, and com-  stress and burnout.         cation system, we can help ensure that
           munities. By investing in education and   Global collaboration: As the world   teachers continue to thrive and make a
           supporting teachers, we can ensure that   becomes more interconnected, there   positive difference in the lives of their
           they are better equipped to provide high-  may be more opportunities for global   students. ■
           quality education and contribute to the
           development of future generations.

           The future of Teachers' Day
             As we look to the future, the signifi-
           cance of Teachers' Day is likely to con-
           tinue evolving. Advances in technology,
           changes in educational practices, and
           shifting societal expectations will all im-
           pact how we celebrate and support
           teachers.
             Digital recognition: With the rise of                                                           Top: University students interacting
           digital platforms, there are new ways to                                                        Left: Parent-teacher meeting
           celebrate Teachers' Day. Virtual events,
           online messages, and social media cam-
           paigns can help reach a broader au-
           dience and provide innovative ways to








                                                                                                           Teacher development workshop













           16                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Building a


     FEATURE  better world









           Engineers Day is a time to celebrate the

           achievements of engineers and recognize their
           contributions to society. By Ishita Desai









                                                                                ngineers Day is celebrated in
                                                                                many countries around the world
                                                                           Eto honor the contribution of engi-
                                                                           neers to society. These professionals
                                                                           play a vital role in shaping the world we
                                                                           live in by applying their knowledge and
                                                                           skills to create innovative solutions to
                                                                           complex problems. The day serves as an
                                                                           opportunity to recognize the hard work,
                                                                           creativity, and dedication of engineers,
                                                                           and to inspire future generations to pur-
                                                                           sue careers in engineering.

                                                                           The origin of engineers day
                                                                              The celebration of Engineers Day
                                                                           varies by country, with each nation
                                                                           choosing a date significant to its history
                                                                           or to honor a renowned engineer. In
                                                                           India, for example, Engineers Day is ob-
                                                                           served on September 15th in memory of
                                                                           Sir Mokshagundam Visvesvaraya, a dis-
                                                                           tinguished engineer and statesman. Born
                                                                           in 1861, Sir Visvesvaraya made substan-
                                                                           tial contributions to the field of engi-
                                                                           neering, particularly in the areas of irri-
                                                                           gation, flood control, and water supply
                                                                           systems. He was awarded the Bharat
                                                                           Ratna, India's highest civilian honor, in
                                                                           1955.
                                                                              In the United States, Engineers Week
                                                                           is celebrated in February, typically dur-
                                                                           ing the week of George Washington’s
                                                                           birthday. Washington is considered
                                                                           America’s first engineer due to his work  Benjamin Franklin Bridge, Philadelphia
                                                                           in surveying and his role in the design
                                                                           and construction of numerous public
                                                                           works. The event, which started in 1951,
                                                                           aims to increase public awareness of
                                                                           engineers' work and the impact it has on
                                                                           society.

           18                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Top: Golden Gate Bridge, California
                                                                           Bottom: Burj Khalifa, Dubai




























         A church with stained glass windows















             In other countries, Engineers Day is   in nearly every aspect of modern life,   structures not only facilitate transporta-
           celebrated on different dates. In Argen-  from designing buildings and infrastruc-  tion and commerce but also provide es-
           tina, it is observed on June 16th to com-  ture to developing new technologies and   sential services such as clean water and
           memorate the first graduation of an   products. Their work is essential in var-  electricity. The work of civil engineers
           engineer in the country. In Italy, it is   ious fields, including civil, mechanical,   has a direct impact on the quality of life
           celebrated on March 13th, the anniver-  electrical, chemical, and software engi-  of millions of people around the world.
           sary of the first meeting of the National   neering.               Mechanical engineers, on the other
           Council of Engineers in 1923.     One of the most significant contrib-  hand, are responsible for designing and
                                           utions of engineers is in the field of in-  manufacturing machines and equipment
           The role of engineers in society   frastructure. Civil engineers, for exam-  used in various industries. From auto-
             Engineering is often described as the   ple, design and build the roads, bridges,   mobiles and airplanes to manufacturing
           application of scientific principles to   tunnels, and dams that are crucial to the   equipment and household appliances,
           solve problems. Engineers are involved   functioning of modern society. These   the work of mechanical engineers is ev-
                                                                           ident in nearly every aspect of daily life.
                                                                           Their innovations have helped increase
                                                                           productivity, improve safety, and en-
                                                                           hance the quality of products.
                                                                              Electrical engineers play a critical
                                                                           role in the development and mainte-
                                                                           nance of electrical systems. They design
                                                                           and develop the power grids that supply
                                                                           electricity to homes and businesses, as
                                                                           well as the electronic devices that are
                                                                           now an integral part of modern life. The
                                                                           work of electrical engineers has been in-
         Eiffel Tower, Paris                                               strumental in the development of new
                                                                           technologies, such as renewable energy
                                                                           systems and smart grids, which are es-
                                                                           sential for a sustainable future.
                                                                              Chemical engineers, meanwhile,

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[A mechanical engineer working on machinery                                                        International engineering projects


















                                                                           neers are developing innovative solu-
                                                                           tions to address this issue, such as desa-
                                                                           lination plants, water recycling systems,
                                                                           and low-cost sanitation technologies.
                                                                           Their work is essential in improving
                                                                           public health and reducing poverty in
                                                                           developing countries.
                                                                              In addition to environmental and so-
         Software engineer coding in the office                            The rapid pace of technological change
                                                                           cial challenges, engineers are also work-
                                                                           ing to address technological challenges.
                                                                           is creating new opportunities but also
                                                                           new risks. Engineers are developing cy-
                                                                           bersecurity systems to protect critical in-
                                                                           frastructure and data from cyberattacks,
                                                                           as well as working on ethical issues re-
                                                                           lated to the use of artificial intelligence
                                                                           and automation.

                                                                           The impact of engineering on the
           work in industries such as pharmaceuti-  solvers because they apply their techni-  economy
           cals, petrochemicals, and food process-  cal knowledge and creativity to find so-  Engineering is a key driver of eco-
           ing. They develop processes to convert   lutions to complex challenges. Whether   nomic growth. The innovations and effi-
           raw materials into useful products, such   it’s developing a new product, designing   ciencies created by engineers lead to the
           as medicines, fuels, and food items. The   a system, or improving an existing pro-  development of new industries, the crea-
           work of chemical engineers is vital to   cess, engineers are constantly working   tion of jobs, and the improvement of liv-
           the development of new materials and   to make things better, more efficient,   ing standards. The economic impact of
           products that improve the quality of life   and more sustainable.   engineering can be seen in various sec-
           and drive economic growth.        One of the most significant chal-  tors, from manufacturing and construc-
             Software engineers are responsible   lenges engineers face today is address-  tion to healthcare and information tech-
           for designing and developing the soft-  ing the impact of climate change. Engi-  nology.
           ware that powers computers, smart-  neers are at the forefront of efforts to   In the manufacturing sector, engi-
           phones, and other electronic devices.   develop renewable energy technologies,   neers have played a crucial role in in-
           Their work has revolutionized the way   such as solar and wind power, to reduce   creasing productivity and reducing costs
           we live and work, enabling the devel-  reliance on fossil fuels. They are also   through the development of new materi-
           opment of new technologies such as ar-  working on ways to make buildings and   als, processes, and technologies. The in-
           tificial intelligence, the Internet of   infrastructure more energy-efficient and   troduction of automation and robotics
           Things, and cloud computing. Software   resilient to the effects of climate change,   has revolutionized manufacturing, al-
           engineers play a crucial role in the digi-  such as rising sea levels and extreme   lowing companies to produce goods
           tal transformation of industries and the   weather events.      faster and with higher precision. This
           creation of new business models.   Another major challenge is the need   has led to the growth of industries such
                                           to provide clean water and sanitation to   as automotive, aerospace, and elec-
           Engineers as problem solvers    millions of people around the world who   tronics, which are major contributors to
             Engineers are often called problem   lack access to these basic services. Engi-  the global economy.

           20                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[oping solutions to manage and mitigate
                                                                           the effects of climate change, such as
                                                                           flood control systems and resilient in-
                                                                           frastructure.
                                                                              Another area of focus will be the dig-
                                                                           ital transformation of industries. As
                                                                           more companies adopt digital technol-
         Wind turbines: A marvel of engineering                            transformation. This includes the devel-
                                                                           ogies, engineers will be needed to de-
                                                                           sign and develop the systems and infras-
                                                                           tructure required to support this
                                                                           opment of new software, hardware, and
                                                                           communication networks, as well as the
                                                                           integration of technologies such as arti-
                                                                           ficial intelligence, the Internet of
                                                                           Things, and blockchain. The work of
                                                                           engineers will be essential in ensuring
                                                                           that the digital transformation is secure,
                                                                           efficient, and accessible to all.
                                                                              In the healthcare sector, engineers
             In the construction sector, the work                          will continue to play a crucial role in de-
           of civil and structural engineers has en-                       veloping new medical technologies and
           abled the development of modern cities                          treatments. Advances in biotechnology,
           and infrastructure. The construction of                         nanotechnology, and materials science
           high-rise buildings, bridges, and trans-                        will enable the development of new
           portation networks has not only im-                             medical devices and therapies that im-
           proved the quality of life for millions of                      prove patient care and outcomes. Engi-
           people but also created jobs and stimu-                         neers will also be involved in devel-
           lated economic growth. The real estate                          oping systems to manage and analyze
           and construction industries are signifi-                        the vast amounts of data generated by
           cant contributors to the economy, pro-                          healthcare providers, enabling more per-
           viding employment and investment op-                            sonalized and effective treatments.
           portunities.                                                       The future of engineering will also
             The healthcare sector has also bene-                          see a greater emphasis on collaboration
           fited greatly from engineering innova-                          and interdisciplinary work. As the chal-
           tions. Biomedical engineers have devel-                         lenges facing society become more com-
           oped new medical devices, such as                               plex, engineers will need to work
           prosthetics, implants, and diagnostic                           closely with professionals from other
           equipment, that have improved patient                           fields, such as scientists, economists,
           care and outcomes. The development of                           and policymakers, to develop compre-
           new materials and technologies has also                         hensive solutions. This collaborative ap-
           enabled the production of pharmaceuti-  with numerous opportunities for growth   proach will be essential in addressing
           cals and medical treatments that save   and innovation. As technology continues   global challenges, such as climate
           lives and improve health. The healthcare   to evolve, engineers will be at the fore-  change, poverty, and inequality, and en-
           industry is a major contributor to the   front of developing new solutions to ad-  suring that the benefits of engineering
           economy, and the work of engineers is   dress the challenges of the 21st century.   are shared by all.
           essential in ensuring its continued   From renewable energy and sustainable   Engineers Day is a time to celebrate
           growth and innovation.          infrastructure to artificial intelligence   the achievements of engineers and rec-
             The information technology sector is   and biotechnology, the work of engi-  ognize their contributions to society.
           another area where engineering has had   neers will be essential in shaping the fu-  From building infrastructure and devel-
           a significant economic impact. Software   ture of our world.    oping new technologies to solving com-
           engineers, in particular, have driven the   One of the key areas of focus for   plex challenges and driving economic
           digital transformation of industries, en-  engineers in the coming years will be   growth, engineers play a vital role in
           abling companies to operate more effi-  sustainability. With the growing concern   shaping the world we live in. As we look
           ciently and reach new markets. The   over climate change and environmental   to the future, the work of engineers will
           growth of the IT sector has created mil-  degradation, engineers will need to de-  be essential in addressing the challenges
           lions of jobs and generated billions of   velop new technologies and processes   of the 21st century and ensuring a sus-
           dollars in revenue, making it one of the   that reduce the impact of human activ-  tainable, prosperous, and equitable
           most important contributors to the   ities on the planet. This includes the de-  world for all. Whether through innova-
           global economy.                 velopment of renewable energy sources,   tion, problem-solving, or collaboration,
                                           energy-efficient buildings, and sustain-  engineers will continue to be the archi-
           The future of engineering       able transportation systems. Engineers   tects of progress and the drivers of
             The future of engineering is bright,   will also play a crucial role in devel-  change. ■

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH





















                                                                                                           A new electric car ready to drive










           Steering into


                                                                           urbanization increases and more ve-
                                                                           hicles hit the roads, the need for cleaner,
           an electric future                                              more sustainable transportation solu-
                                                                           tions becomes imperative.
                                                                              World EV Day addresses this chal-
                                                                           lenge by promoting the benefits of elec-
                                                                           tric vehicles, which produce zero tail-
           World EV Day serves as a powerful reminder of the               pipe emissions, reduce dependence on
                                                                           fossil fuels, and contribute to cleaner air
           urgent need to transition to a more sustainable and             and quieter cities. By dedicating a day to
                                                                           celebrate and advocate for EVs, World
           environmentally friendly transportation system.                 EV Day fosters global collaboration and
                                                                           drives awareness about the environmen-
                                                                           tal and economic advantages of tran-
           By Anaya Gupta                                                  sitioning to electric mobility.
                                                                           The evolution of electric vehicles
                  orld EV Day, celebrated an-  need for cleaner energy, World EV Day   The concept of electric vehicles is
                  nually on September 9th,   serves as a reminder of the importance   not new; in fact, EVs have been around
           Wmarks a global movement to-    of electric vehicles in achieving a   since the 19th century. The first practical
           ward embracing electric vehicles (EVs)   greener and more sustainable planet.   electric car was built by Thomas Parker
           as a critical solution to reducing carbon                       in 1884 in London, using non-recharge-
           emissions, improving air quality, and   The significance of world EV day   able batteries. However, the advent of
           fostering sustainable urban devel-  The transportation sector is a major   gasoline-powered vehicles in the early
           opment. Established in 2020 by sustain-  contributor to global greenhouse gas   20th century, combined with the limita-
           ability media company Green.TV and   emissions, accounting for nearly 24% of   tions of early battery technology, led to
           EV manufacturer ABB, World EV Day   direct CO2 emissions from fuel combus-  the decline of electric cars.
           aims to raise awareness, encourage the   tion. Traditional internal combustion en-  It wasn’t until the late 20th century
           adoption of EVs, and accelerate the tran-  gine (ICE) vehicles rely on fossil fuels,   that interest in EVs began to resurface,
           sition to a more sustainable transporta-  emitting carbon dioxide, nitrogen ox-  driven by concerns about air pollution,
           tion future. As the world grapples with   ides, and other pollutants that contribute   oil dependency, and the environmental
           the effects of climate change and the   to air pollution and climate change. As   impact of fossil fuels. The development

           22                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[in EV manufacturing and sales.
                                                                              In the United States, EV adoption has
                                                                           been growing steadily, with states like
                                                                           California leading the charge. Califor-
                                                                           nia’s Zero-Emission Vehicle (ZEV) pro-
                                                                           gram, along with federal tax credits and
                                                                           a growing network of charging stations,
                                                                           has contributed to the increasing pop-
                                                                           ularity of EVs across the country. Major
                                                                           automakers like Tesla, General Motors,
                                                                           and Ford have also made significant in-
                                                                           vestments in EV technology, driving in-
                                                                           novation and expanding the range of
         Charging slot in public parking                                   The role of infrastructure in EV
                                                                           electric vehicles available to consumers.

                                                                           adoption
                                                                              One of the key factors influencing
                                                                           the adoption of electric vehicles is the
                                                                           availability of charging infrastructure.
                                                                           As more people transition to EVs, the
                                                                           demand for convenient, accessible, and
                                                                           reliable charging stations has grown sig-
                                           byproduct. This diversity in electric ve-  nificantly. World EV Day emphasizes
                                           hicle technology offers consumers a   the importance of expanding EV infras-
                                           range of options to suit their needs and   tructure to support the widespread use of
                                           preferences.                    electric vehicles.
                                                                              Public and private sectors have been
                                           World EV day and global adoption   working together to build an extensive
                                           trends                          network of charging stations, including
                                             World EV Day plays a pivotal role in   fast chargers that can replenish an EV’s
                                           accelerating the global adoption of elec-  battery in minutes rather than hours. In
                                           tric vehicles. In recent years, the EV   Europe, the European Union has set am-
                                           market has experienced exponential   bitious targets to install one million pub-
                                           growth, with millions of electric cars   lic charging points by 2025 as part of its
         An EV charging in a parking lot   have recognized the potential of EVs to   2050.
                                                                           Green Deal, which aims to make Europe
                                           now on the road worldwide. Govern-
                                                                           the first climate-neutral continent by
                                           ments, automakers, and consumers alike
                                           address environmental challenges, lead-
                                                                              In the United States, the Biden ad-
                                           ing to increased investment in EV in-
                                                                           ministration has committed to building a
                                                                           national network of 500,000 EV charg-
                                           frastructure, incentives for consumers,
                                           and commitments to phase out internal
                                                                           ing stations by 2030, as part of its
                                           combustion engines.
                                                                           sions by 2050. This initiative includes
                                             Europe has been a leader in EV adop-
                                           tion, with countries like Norway, Ger-  broader goal to achieve net-zero emis-
                                                                           investments in charging infrastructure,
           of more efficient and affordable bat-  many, and the Netherlands setting ambi-  incentives for EV buyers, and support
           teries, particularly lithium-ion technol-  tious targets for the transition to electric   for domestic EV manufacturing.
           ogy, and advances in electric drivetrains   mobility. Norway, in particular, has set a   China has also made significant in-
           have revolutionized the EV market,   global example, with EVs accounting   vestments in EV infrastructure, with
           making electric vehicles a viable and at-  for over 54% of all new car sales in   over 800,000 public charging points in-
           tractive alternative to traditional cars.   2020, thanks to a combination of gov-  stalled nationwide by 2020. The Chinese
             Today, EVs come in various forms,   ernment incentives, widespread charging   government’s support for EV infrastruc-
           including battery electric vehicles   infrastructure, and a strong public com-  ture development has been instrumental
           (BEVs), plug-in hybrid electric vehicles   mitment to sustainability.   in driving the country’s rapid transition
           (PHEVs), and hydrogen fuel cell ve-  China, the world’s largest automotive   to electric mobility.
           hicles (FCEVs). BEVs run entirely on   market, has also made significant strides   In addition to public charging sta-
           electricity, storing energy in recharge-  in EV adoption, driven by government   tions, the availability of home and work-
           able batteries, while PHEVs combine a   policies aimed at reducing air pollution   place charging solutions is crucial for
           traditional internal combustion engine   and promoting domestic EV production.   EV adoption. Many EV owners charge
           with an electric motor, allowing for   The Chinese government’s “New   their vehicles overnight at home, taking
           short trips on electric power alone.   Energy Vehicle” (NEV) mandate, along   advantage of lower electricity rates and
           FCEVs generate electricity from hy-  with substantial subsidies for EV buyers,   ensuring their car is ready for the next
           drogen, emitting only water vapor as a   has positioned China as a global leader   day. Workplace charging stations pro-

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[benefits of EVs
                                                                              World EV Day highlights the numer-
                                                                           ous environmental and economic bene-
                                                                           fits of electric vehicles. By reducing or
                                                                           eliminating tailpipe emissions, EVs con-
                                                                           tribute to cleaner air and help mitigate
                                                                           the effects of climate change. In cities
                                                                           with high levels of air pollution, the
                                                                           widespread adoption of EVs can lead to
                                                                           significant improvements in public
                                                                           health, reducing the incidence of respi-
                                                                           ratory and cardiovascular diseases.
         EV charging station                                               benefits, both for consumers and for so-
                                                                              Electric vehicles also offer economic
                                                                           ciety as a whole. While the upfront cost
                                                                           of an EV may be higher than that of a
                                                                           traditional gasoline-powered car, lower
                                                                           operating costs, including reduced fuel
           vide additional convenience for employ-  new electric models by 2025. Ford has   and maintenance expenses, make EVs
           ees, encouraging more people to switch   also announced significant investments   more affordable over the long term. As
           to electric vehicles.           in EVs, including the launch of the all-  battery technology continues to improve
                                           electric Mustang Mach-E and the up-  and economies of scale drive down pro-
           The role of automakers in       coming F-150 Lightning electric pickup   duction costs, the price of electric ve-
           promoting EV adoption           truck.                          hicles is expected to become increas-
             Automakers play a critical role in the   European automakers like Volks-  ingly competitive with traditional cars.
           success of World EV Day by developing   wagen, BMW, and Mercedes-Benz have   The transition to electric mobility
           and promoting electric vehicles that   made similar commitments, with plans   also presents significant economic op-
           meet consumer needs and preferences.   to transition their entire vehicle lineups   portunities for countries that invest in
           Over the past decade, many major auto-  to electric by the end of the decade.   EV manufacturing and infrastructure.
           makers have announced ambitious plans   Volkswagen’s ID. series, BMW’s i   The EV industry is poised to create mil-
           to electrify their vehicle lineups, com-  series, and Mercedes-Benz’s EQ series   lions of new jobs in areas such as bat-
           mitting billions of dollars to EV devel-  represent the future of electric mobility   tery production, charging infrastructure
           opment and production.          in Europe, offering consumers a wide   development, and vehicle assembly. By
             Tesla has been a pioneer in the EV   range of options to suit their lifestyles.   positioning themselves as leaders in the
           market, with its innovative electric cars   Chinese automakers have also   EV market, countries can stimulate eco-
           capturing the imagination of consumers   emerged as major players in the global   nomic growth, reduce their dependence
           and setting new standards for perform-  EV market, with companies like BYD,   on imported oil, and strengthen their
           ance, range, and design. Tesla’s success   NIO, and Xpeng leading the charge.   energy security.
           has spurred other automakers to accel-  These companies have developed inno-
           erate their own EV programs, leading to   vative electric vehicles that cater to the   Challenges and the road ahead
           a wave of new electric models entering   unique needs of Chinese consumers,   Despite the progress made in recent
           the market.                     while also expanding their presence in   years, several challenges remain on the
             General Motors (GM) has committed   international markets.    road to widespread EV adoption. Battery
           to phasing out gasoline-powered ve-                             technology, while improving rapidly,
           hicles by 2035, with plans to launch 30   The environmental and economic   still faces limitations in terms of range,









         EVs charging at a modern station                                                                  Ashok Leyland electric bus














           24                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[charging time, and cost. The availability   Government initiatives and
           of raw materials, such as lithium, cobalt,   policies
           and nickel, needed for battery produc-  India's push towards electric mobility
           tion is also a concern, with potential   began with the launch of the Faster
           supply chain disruptions posing a risk to   Adoption and Manufacturing of Hybrid
           the growth of the EV market.    and Electric Vehicles (FAME) scheme in
             Infrastructure development, particu-  2015. The program, which is now in its
           larly in rural and underserved areas, is   second phase (FAME II), provides fi-
           another challenge that must be ad-  nancial incentives to consumers and
           dressed to ensure that EVs are acces-  manufacturers for the purchase and pro-
           sible to all. The expansion of charging   duction of EVs. FAME II, with an out-
           networks, the development of ultra-fast   lay of ₹10,000 crore, aims to support the
           charging technology, and the integration   deployment of electric buses, three-
           of renewable energy sources into the   wheelers, four-wheelers, and charging
           grid are essential steps toward overcom-  infrastructure across the country.
           ing these challenges.             The Indian government has also set a
             Consumer awareness and education   target to achieve 30% electric vehicle
           are also critical to driving EV adoption.   penetration by 2030 as part of its



        Top: Electric vehicles for disabled, Middle: EV assembly line



                                                                           broader efforts to combat climate
                                                                           change and reduce oil imports. This goal
                                                                           is supported by various state-level pol-
                                                                           icies that offer additional incentives,
         Bottom: Battery manufacturing for EVs                             Challenges and opportunities
                                                                           such as subsidies, tax exemptions, and
                                                                           registration fee waivers, to encourage
                                                                           the purchase of EVs.


                                                                              Despite the government's efforts,
                                                                           India faces several challenges in its jour-
                                                                           ney toward widespread EV adoption.
                                                                           One of the primary obstacles is the high
                                                                           cost of electric vehicles, which remains
                                                                           a barrier for many consumers in a price-
                                                                           sensitive market. Additionally, the lim-
                                                                           ited availability of charging infrastruc-
           Many potential buyers are still unfamil-
           iar with the benefits of electric vehicles
           or are concerned about issues such as
           range anxiety and charging availability.
           World EV Day plays a vital role in ad-
           dressing these concerns by providing ac-
           curate information, dispelling myths,
           and showcasing the real-world benefits
           of electric mobility.

           India’s role in the global EV
           movement
             India, as one of the world’s largest
           and most rapidly urbanizing nations,
           plays a crucial role in the global transi-
           tion to electric mobility. The Indian gov-
           ernment has recognized the importance
           of reducing the country’s reliance on
           fossil fuels and improving air quality in
           its cities, and has set ambitious targets to
           promote the adoption of electric vehicles
           (EVs).

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[India’s journey towards electric mo-
                                                                           bility is still in its early stages, but the
                                                                           progress made so far is promising.
                                                                           World EV Day serves as an opportunity
                                                                           to reflect on the challenges and cele-
         PM Narendra Modi launches electric bus                            able future for the country.
                                                                           brate the achievements in India’s EV
                                                                           sector, while also galvanizing further ac-
                                                                           tion to ensure a cleaner, more sustain-
                                                                              World EV Day serves as a powerful
                                                                           reminder of the urgent need to transition
                                                                           to a more sustainable and environmen-
                                                                           tally friendly transportation system. As
                                                                           the world continues to grapple with the
                                                                           effects of climate change and the chal-
                                                                           lenges of urbanization, electric vehicles
                                                                           offer a promising solution to reduce
                                                                           emissions, improve air quality, and
                                                                           create a more sustainable future for all.
                                                                              The celebration of World EV Day
                                                                           not only raises awareness about the im-
         An electric double-decker bus inducted by BEST                    makers, and consumers can work to-
                                                                           portance of electric vehicles but also
                                                                           fosters global collaboration and innova-
                                                                           tion in the EV industry. By embracing
                                                                           electric mobility, governments, auto-

                                                                           gether to build a cleaner, healthier, and
                                                                           more sustainable world.
                                                                              As we look to the future, the con-
                                                                           tinued growth of the EV market, the ex-
                                                                           pansion of charging infrastructure, and
                                                                           the development of new technologies
                                                                           will be critical to achieving the goals set
                                                                           forth by World EV Day. By supporting
                                                                           the transition to electric vehicles, we
                                                                           can pave the way for a greener, more
                                                                           sustainable transportation system that
           ture, particularly in rural and semi-urban   Motors, for instance, has introduced the   benefits everyone. ■
           areas, poses a significant challenge to   Nexon EV, which has become one of the
           the growth of the EV market.    best-selling electric cars in the country,
             Battery manufacturing is another   while Mahindra has been a pioneer in
           critical area where India is working to   the electric three-wheeler segment.
           build capacity. Currently, the country is
           heavily dependent on imports for   The road ahead
           lithium-ion batteries, which are the most   The road to electrification in India is
           expensive component of an electric ve-  complex, but the potential benefits are
           hicle. To address this, the Indian gov-  immense. The widespread adoption of
           ernment has launched initiatives to pro-  EVs could significantly reduce the
           mote domestic battery production,   country’s carbon footprint, decrease its
           including the National Mission on   dependence on imported oil, and im-
           Transformative Mobility and Battery   prove air quality in its cities, which con-
           Storage, which aims to establish large-  sistently rank among the most polluted
           scale battery manufacturing plants in the   in the world.
           country.                          To accelerate this transition, India
             The Indian automobile industry,   will need to continue its focus on ex-
           which is one of the largest in the world,   panding charging infrastructure, making
           is also playing a pivotal role in the EV   EVs more affordable, and fostering in-
           transition. Leading Indian automakers,   novation in battery technology. Public
           such as Tata Motors, Mahindra & Ma-  awareness and education campaigns will
           hindra, and Hero Electric, have been at   also be essential in dispelling myths                    Electric two-wheeler
           the forefront of developing and launch-  about EVs and encouraging more con-
           ing electric vehicles that cater to the   sumers to make the switch to electric
           unique needs of Indian consumers. Tata   vehicles.

           26                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[EXCLUSIVE  Smartphones


           Bye-bye






           memory cards







           The removal of memory card slots from smartphones

           is not just a random design choice but a calculated
           decision driven by technological advancements,

           design priorities, and the shift towards cloud-based
           storage. By Rohan Kapoor





             n the rapidly evolving world of                               crease storage capacity. This was espe-
             smartphones, features that were once                          cially valuable in an era when high-ca-
           Ideemed essential can swiftly become                            pacity smartphones were prohibitively
           relics of the past. One such feature, the                       expensive, and cloud storage was still in
           memory card slot, has seen a sharp de-                          its infancy.
           cline in prevalence among modern An-
           droid devices. For many years, the abil-                        The decline of the memory card
           ity to expand storage using a microSD                           slot
           card was a key selling point for Android                           Despite the initial popularity of
           phones, offering a flexible and cost-ef-                        memory card slots, their presence in
                                                                           smartphones has been steadily declining
                                                                           over the past few years. A growing
                                                                           number of flagship Android devices, in-
                                                                           cluding models from major manufac-
                                                                           turers like Samsung, Google, and One-
                                                                           Plus, have started to omit this feature
         MicroSD card                                                      siderable debate among consumers and
                                                                           altogether. This trend has sparked con-
                                                                           industry experts alike.
                                                                              One of the primary reasons for this
                                                                           decline is the increasing emphasis on
           fective way to enhance the storage ca-  changer when it first became common.   cloud storage solutions. As internet
           pacity of a device. However, in recent   In the early days of mobile phones, in-  speeds have improved and cloud serv-
           years, this once ubiquitous feature has   ternal storage was extremely limited.   ices have become more reliable and se-
           started to disappear from the latest   The advent of memory cards allowed   cure, many smartphone manufacturers
           smartphone models, raising questions   users to store more photos, videos,   have shifted their focus towards promot-
           about the future of expandable storage.   music, and apps than ever before, effec-  ing cloud-based storage as the preferred
                                           tively turning their phones into portable   method for managing files. Companies
           The rise of the memory card slot   media centers.               like Google, Apple, and Microsoft offer
             To fully understand the implications   MicroSD cards, in particular, became   vast amounts of cloud storage space,
           of the disappearing memory card slot,   the standard for expandable storage.   often integrated directly into the operat-
           it's important to consider its historical   They were small, affordable, and easy to   ing system, making it easy for users to
           significance. The inclusion of a memory   use, allowing users to simply insert a   back up their data and access it from any
           card slot in smartphones was a game-  card into their phone to instantly in-  device with an internet connection.

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[This shift towards cloud storage is   slot allows manufacturers to save valu-
           further supported by the proliferation of   able space inside the device, which can
           high-speed mobile networks like 4G and   be used for other components like larger
           5G, which make it easier than ever to   batteries, improved cameras, or ad-
           upload and download large files on the   ditional sensors.
           go. As a result, many users are finding   In addition, the absence of a memory
           that they no longer need to rely on phys-  card slot simplifies the manufacturing
           ical storage media like memory cards to   process, reducing the number of compo-
           keep their data safe and accessible.   nents that need to be included in the de-
                                           vice. This can help manufacturers
           The push for sleeker, more      streamline production, improve reliabil-
           integrated designs              ity, and potentially lower costs, all of
             Another factor contributing to the   which are appealing from a business
           disappearance of the memory card slot   perspective.
           is the ongoing push for sleeker, more in-                                                       A graphic of a cloud storage icon
           tegrated smartphone designs. Modern   Enhanced security and
           smartphones are designed to be as thin   performance considerations
           and lightweight as possible, with a focus   Security is another important consid-
           on maximizing screen size and minimiz-  eration in the decision to remove the
           ing bezels. Removing the memory card   memory card slot. While memory cards
                                                                           are convenient, they can also pose secu-
                                                                           rity risks. Because they are easily re-
                                                                           movable, they can be lost or stolen, po-
                                                                           tentially exposing sensitive data to
                                                                           unauthorized access. By eliminating the
         Smartphone with a visible microSD card slot                       crypted internal storage or cloud serv-
                                                                           memory card slot, manufacturers can
                                                                           encourage users to store their data in
                                                                           more secure environments, such as en-

                                                                           ices with robust security measures.
                                                                              Performance is another factor that
                                                                           cannot be overlooked. While memory
                                                                           cards offer expandable storage, they
                                                                           often cannot match the speed and reli-
                                                                           ability of internal storage. Modern
                                                                           smartphones are equipped with high-
                                                                           speed UFS (Universal Flash Storage)
                                                                           memory, which offers significantly
                                                                           faster read and write speeds compared to












         Evolution of mobile phones and smartphones



















           28                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[most microSD cards. This means that   However, in recent years, internal   higher internal storage capacities, which
           apps and files stored on internal storage   storage capacities have increased dra-  are often sold at a premium. This allows
           load more quickly and perform better   matically. It is now common for even   manufacturers to increase their profit
           than those stored on a memory card.   mid-range smartphones to come with   margins, as they can charge more for
             For high-performance tasks, such as   128GB or 256GB of storage, with high-  models with more storage.
           gaming or 4K video recording, the   end models offering 512GB or even   In addition, the removal of the mem-
           slower speeds of microSD cards can   1TB of internal space. For most users,   ory card slot creates an opportunity for
           lead to noticeable lag and performance   this is more than enough to store all   manufacturers to promote their own
           issues. By removing the memory card   their apps, photos, and videos without   cloud storage services. For example,
           slot, manufacturers can ensure a more   ever needing to worry about running out   Google offers a range of cloud storage
           consistent and reliable user experience,   of space.            options through its Google One service,
           with all data stored on high-speed inter-  The rise of larger internal storage ca-  which is closely integrated with Android
           nal storage.                    pacities has made the memory card slot   devices. By steering users towards cloud
                                           less relevant for many users. With so   storage, companies can generate ongo-
           The rise of higher internal storage   much space available on the device it-  ing revenue through subscription fees,
           capacities                      self, the need for additional storage is   creating a new and lucrative revenue
             One of the key factors that has made   greatly reduced.       stream.
           the memory card slot less essential is the
           significant increase in internal storage   Manufacturer strategies and the   The consumer perspective: pros
           capacities in modern smartphones. In   push for profitability   and cons
           the past, entry-level smartphones often   Another reason behind the disappear-  From the consumer perspective, the
           came with just 8GB or 16GB of storage,   ance of the memory card slot is the   disappearance of the memory card slot
           which was quickly filled up with apps,   strategic decisions made by smartphone   has both advantages and disadvantages.
           photos, and other media. This made ex-  manufacturers. By removing the mem-  On the one hand, the shift towards cloud
           pandable storage a necessity for many   ory card slot, companies can encourage   storage and larger internal capacities
           users.                          consumers to purchase devices with   offers greater convenience and peace of
                                                                           mind. Users no longer need to worry
                                                                           about managing physical storage media
                                                                           or transferring files between devices
                                                                           manually. Instead, everything is stored
                                                                           securely in the cloud, accessible from
                                                                           anywhere and automatically backed up.
                                                                              However, there are also drawbacks to
                                                                           this trend. One of the biggest concerns
                                                                           for consumers is the potential loss of
       Bottom: 5G mobile towers  Right: Smartphone with an open app





































           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Smartphone as a video camera                                                                      Left: Modern smartphone Internals  Bottom: Smartphone demand increasing daily













           control over their data. With cloud stor-  concerns associated with cloud storage   ory card slot is a clear sign of the evolv-
           age, users are dependent on the avail-  and the removal of the memory card   ing landscape of smartphone storage.
           ability and reliability of the service pro-  slot. For example, advancements in   While this trend offers many benefits in
           vider. If the provider experiences   wireless transfer technologies could   terms of convenience, security, and per-
           downtime, data breaches, or other is-  make it easier to move files between de-  formance, it also raises important ques-
           sues, users may be unable to access their   vices without the need for physical stor-  tions about the future of data storage and
           files. Additionally, cloud storage often   age media. Similarly, new forms of non-  the balance between cloud and physical
           requires a subscription fee, which can   volatile memory could offer faster   media. As smartphone technology con-
           add to the overall cost of owning a   speeds and greater reliability than cur-  tinues to advance, it will be interesting
           smartphone.                     rent microSD cards, potentially making   to see how manufacturers and con-
             Another concern is the loss of flex-  them a viable alternative to internal stor-  sumers adapt to these changes and what
           ibility that comes with the removal of   age.                   new innovations emerge to meet the
           the memory card slot. MicroSD cards   In conclusion, the disappearing mem-  growing demands of mobile storage. ■
           are a simple and affordable way to ex-
           pand storage, and they offer the ability
           to easily transfer files between devices
           without relying on an internet connec-
           tion. For users who frequently travel or
           work in areas with limited connectivity,
           the absence of a memory card slot can
           be a significant inconvenience.
           The future of smartphone storage:
           what lies ahead?
             As the trend towards removing the
           memory card slot continues, the future
           of smartphone storage is likely to be
           shaped by a combination of factors.
           Cloud storage will undoubtedly play a
           central role, offering users the ability to
           store and access their data from any-
           where in the world. At the same time,
           internal storage capacities will continue
           to increase, providing ample space for
           apps, photos, and videos without the
           need for external storage.
             However, it is also possible that we
           will see new innovations in storage tech-
           nology that could address some of the

           30                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Sri Krishna Janmashtami


           The divine birth                                                                                      REPORT





           that changed the world






           Krishna Janmashtami is a
           testament to the universal

           appeal of Lord Krishna and

           the power of devotion to
           transcend geographical

           and cultural boundaries.
           By Staff writer




                   rishna Janmashtami, the aus-
                   picious festival commem-
             Korating the birth of Lord
           Krishna, was celebrated with great fervor
           and devotion by Hindus across the world.
           From the birthplace of Krishna in Ma-
           thura, India to temples and communities
           in far-flung corners of the globe, this fes-                    Consciousness (ISKCON) plays a signif-
           tival transcends borders and unites devo-                       icant role in organizing large-scale Jan-
           tees in their love for the divine cowherd                       mashtami celebrations worldwide. From
           and philosopher-king.                                           Vrindavan to Vancouver, Belgium to
                                                                           Bangkok, New York to New Delhi, hun-
           India: The epicenter of Janmash-                                dreds of thousands of Krishna devotees
           tami celebrations                                               gather at ISKCON temples and centers to
             In India, Janmashtami is observed                             commemorate the divine appearance of
           with unparalleled enthusiasm. The cele-                         the Lord.These celebrations are marked
           brations are especially grand in Mathura                        by chanting the Hare Krishna mantra,
           and Vrindavan, the towns associated with                        singing devotional songs, reading about
           Krishna's early life.                                           Krishna's pastimes, worshipping His
             Temples are beautifully decorated,                            deity form, and fasting until midnight
           and devotees engage in fasting, singing                         when a sumptuous feast is enjoyed. ISK-
           devotional songs, and participating in   Nepal: A Ddevout neighbor   CON temples organize various pro-
           midnight celebrations, which is believed   As a predominantly Hindu nation,   grams, including Jhulan Seva, Laddu
           to be the time of Krishna's birth.One of   Nepal celebrates Janmashtami with equal   Gopal Abhishekam, cultural activities,
           the most popular events is the "Dahi   fervor. Devotees flock to temples, par-  and displays of paraphernalia related to
           Handi" ceremony, where teams form   ticularly the famous Krishna Mandir in   Krishna worship.
           human pyramids to break a pot of curd   Patan, Kathmandu, to offer prayers and
           suspended high in the air, symbolizing   participate in religious rituals. The entire   Celebrations around the World
           Krishna's playful nature and love for   country reverberates with the sound of   Janmashtami is celebrated by Hindu
           butter.                         devotional songs and chants, celebrating   communities worldwide, each adding its
             These celebrations are not limited to   the birth of Lord Krishna.   unique cultural touch to the festivities. In
           temples but also take place in homes,                           the United States, temples across the
           with families decorating their houses   ISKCON: A global movement   country organize special events, includ-
           with flowers and lights.          The International Society for Krishna   ing reenactments of Krishna's life, bha-

           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[jan sessions, and midnight prayers. The
           UK celebrates the festival with a blend of
           traditional Indian rituals and local cus-
           toms, with the Bhaktivedanta Manor in
           London being the focal point of celebra-
           tions.In Fiji, where a significant portion
           of the population is of Indian descent,
           Janmashtami is one of the most impor-
           tant festivals. Celebrations include fast-
           ing, singing bhajans, and performing                                                            ISKCON Temple, Vrindavan (UP)
           Raslila, a traditional dance drama depict-
           ing the life of Krishna. Mauritius, a mul-
           ticultural island nation, also witnesses
           grand Janmashtami celebrations, with
           temples adorned with flowers and lights,
           and devotees engaging in fasting and
           prayers.

           The spiritual significance
             Janmashtami is not just a cultural
           celebration but also holds profound spiri-
           tual significance. It serves as a reminder
           of Krishna's teachings in the Bhagavad
           Gita, which emphasize righteousness,
           duty, and the importance of selfless ac-                                                        Painting depicting Krishna's Rasa Lila
           tion. The festival encourages devotees to
           reflect on their lives, embodying the
           values of love, compassion, and harmony
           that Krishna exemplified.
             Krishna Janmashtami is a testament
           to the universal appeal of Lord Krishna
           and the power of devotion to transcend
           geographical and cultural boundaries. As
           devotees come together to celebrate the
           birth of Krishna, they not only honor
           their faith but also embrace the timeless
           wisdom and values that Krishna repre-
           sents, making Janmashtami a cherished
           occasion for millions around the world.■















         Child Krishna stealing butter from a pot                                                          Schoolchildren dressed as Lord Krishna
















           32                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY

             HOROSCOPES                                September 01-15, 2024






           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     The beginning of September brings a wave of new   Balance and harmony will be essential during
                     energy. This is a great time to take on new     this period. Seek out activities that bring you joy
                     challenges. Your determination will help you    and peace of mind. Collaboration and teamwork
                     overcome obstacles. In relationships, be mindful   will lead to success. In relationships, be open to
                     of others' feelings and make time for loved ones.    compromise and find common ground.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     This period encourages you to find balance in your   Your focus and determination will help you
                     life. Prioritize self-care and relaxation to recharge   achieve your goals. This is a time for taking
                     your energy. Professional matters may require   decisive action and making progress in your ca-
                     patience. In relationships, honesty and open    reer. In relationships, be open to deepening con-
                     communication will strengthen bonds.            nections with those you trust.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Your creativity and communication skills will be   Sagittarius, your adventurous spirit will lead you
                     at their peak. This is a perfect time for network-  to exciting new experiences. Embrace opportuni-
                     ing and collaborating with others. New ideas    ties for travel or learning that come your way. In
                     will flow easily, so keep an open mind. Make    your professional life, think outside the box and
                     sure to spend quality time with loved ones.     be open to exploring new possibilities.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     The beginning of September is a time for reflec-  September is a time to focus on building a solid
                     tion and inner growth. Focus on your emotional   foundation for your future. Whether in your per-
                     well-being and make time for self-care. Rela-   sonal or professional life, your hard work will
                     tionships may require patience and understand-  pay off. In relationships, offer support and stabil-
                     ing, so be gentle with yourself and others.     ity to those who need it.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     This period brings opportunities to shine in your   Your innovative ideas will inspire others during
                     professional life. Your leadership skills will be   this period. This is a great time to pursue cre-
                     recognized, and you may find yourself in the    ative projects and think outside the box. In rela-
                     spotlight. In relationships, show appreciation for   tionships, be open to new perspectives and ap-
                     your loved ones.                                preciate the diversity around you.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     September encourages you to focus on organiza-  Pisces, this period is ideal for introspection and
                     tion and efficiency. Set clear goals and work me-  self-discovery. Take time to connect with your
                     thodically towards achieving them. Your atten-  inner self and reflect on your goals and desires.
                     tion to detail will be a valuable asset in both   In relationships, seek emotional support from
                     personal and professional matters.              those you trust.


           SEPTEMBER 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in                                                    33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK  LETTERS











           A Call for Accountability
             The recent collapse of the Chhatra-
                                           BJP, has distanced itself from her state-
                                           ments, emphasizing that she is not au-
           pati Shivaji Maharaj statue in Sindhu-
           durg has sparked outrage among the   demnation. Notably, her own party, the   dissent and critical voices.
                                           thorized to speak on party policy
                                                                              Rather than investing taxpayer
           people of Maharashtra. This incident,   matters.                money in influencer marketing, the gov-
           which occurred just eight months after   This situation raises serious questions   ernment should focus on transparent
           its inauguration by Prime Minister   about the responsibility of public figures   communication and direct engagement
           Modi, raises serious concerns about the   in their discourse. Kangana's comments   with citizens. This approach would
           quality of materials and construction   not only undermine the struggles of   foster a more informed electorate and
           practices used. Allegations of using   farmers but also reflect a troubling in-  ensure that public funds are used effec-
           rusted bolts and poor construction   sensitivity to the complexities of such   tively, rather than being funneled into a
           methods have emerged, leading to an   protests. The BJP's reprimand highlights   potentially exploitative influencer econ-
           FIR against the contractor and structural   the need for accountability and a more   omy.
           consultant involved.            thoughtful approach to political dia-  Vipin Kumar, Meerut, Uttar Pradesh,
             This collapse is not merely a struc-  logue. As representatives of the people,   India
           tural failure; it is an insult to the sen-  elected officials must strive to foster
           timents of the people of Maharashtra,   unity and understanding, rather than per-
           who hold Shivaji Maharaj as a revered   petuating divisive rhetoric that can   Gujarat Floods: Demanding Urgent
           figure. Critics, including Shiv Sena   further inflame tensions in society.   Action
           leaders, are calling for accountability   Ramesh Sehgal, Delhi, India   The recent floods in Gujarat have
           and demanding the resignation of Chief                          devastated communities, claiming lives
           Minister Eknath Shinde for allowing                             and displacing thousands. As the waters
           such negligence. The government must   Concerns Over UP's Influencer   recede, the true scale of the destruction
           ensure that such a disgrace does not   Payment Policy           becomes evident. Entire villages lie sub-
           happen again, and that the legacy of Shi-  The Uttar Pradesh government's re-  merged, with homes, livelihoods, and in-
           vaji Maharaj is honored with the respect   cent announcement to pay influencers   frastructure wiped out.
           it deserves.                    up to ₹8 lakh per month under its new   The state government's efforts to pro-
           Karan Deshmukh, Pune, Maharash-  digital media policy raises significant   vide relief and rescue are commendable,
           tra, India                      concerns. While the initiative aims to   but more support is needed. Urgent aid
                                           promote government schemes through   is required to rebuild homes, restore es-
                                           social media, it risks prioritizing in-  sential services, and help affected fam-
           Kangana's Controversial         fluencers over genuine grassroots com-  ilies get back on their feet.
           Comments Spark Outrage          munication.                        This is a time for unity and compas-
             Kangana Ranaut's recent remarks fol-  This policy could lead to a distortion   sion. Let us come together as a society
           lowing her election to Parliament have   of public discourse, as influencers may   to support our fellow citizens in their
           ignited significant controversy. Her   prioritize government narratives over in-  hour of need. Only through collective
           comparison of the farmers' protests to a   dependent reporting. Additionally, the   action can we overcome this challenge
           "Bangladesh-like situation" and claims   provision for legal action against "objec-  and emerge stronger.
           of "bodies hanging and rapes" during the   tionable content" poses a threat to free-  C. Kumar Patel, Surat, Gujarat,
           agitation have drawn widespread con-  dom of expression, potentially stifling   India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: revoir@post.com





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           34                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!









































                                                                                                       36
                                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 01 2024
                                                                       www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           36                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR | SEPTEMBER 01 2024
           36
           36
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>