<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                       VOLUME: 03, ISSUE: 08 I  APRIL 16 2025  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: ENRIQUE MESEGUER





             20



                                                             5













                                                           17                                        24
















           4-Editorial: Why heritage is a future           17-The social and political role of bi-
           concern                                         cycles

           5-What happens when history is                  20-How to tune in your body clock

           erased?                                         23-The digital detox we all need

           8-Preserving the soul of civilization           24-The science of wishes
           10-Coping with grief and finding resil-         28-Horoscopes

           ience                                           29-Letters

           14-Dance as sacred language












           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                   3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Not Just the Past
     EDITORIAL  Why heritage is a                                                 Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi

                                                                                            MAGAZINE
                                                                                    Editor-in-Chief

           future concern                                                       Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                                                                  Art & Culture Editor
                                                hen monuments crumble and            Navormi Vats
                                                manuscripts vanish, what truly
                                        Wdisappears is not just stone and        Digital Strategy Editor
                                        ink, but the soul of civilizations. The loss of   Dr. Purnima Chauhan
                                        heritage is not merely a cultural tragedy; it
                                        is a quiet unraveling of collective memory,   Social Media Editor
                                        an erosion of identity stitched together over   Vikas Babbar
                                        centuries. From ancient temples razed in the
                                        name of progress to indigenous languages   Art & Graphics Editor
                                        silenced by assimilation, the erasure of     Vipin Kumar
                                        history often occurs not with fanfare, but
                                        with quiet complicity.
                                           Cultural heritage, both tangible and   EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
                                        intangible, serves as society’s connective
           tissue. It tells us who we were, shapes who we are and guides who we might become.   D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
           When it is destroyed, by war, neglect, development, or deliberate ideological purging,   Editor, United News of India, New
           we are left with voids that facts alone cannot fill. The physical destruction of Palmyra   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           in Syria or the looting of Benin Bronzes are not isolated acts; they are ruptures in a   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           global narrative, wounds that deny future generations the chance to see the full   Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
           spectrum of human expression.                                     Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
             Yet the conversation must go beyond mere preservation. Heritage is not static. It
           evolves, adapts and, in some cases, must reckon with uncomfortable truths. Statues of   Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           colonial figures, for instance, raise complex questions: does removing them erase   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           history, or correct its distortions? A nuanced approach demands that we balance   Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
           remembrance with reexamination. Contextualization, through education, museums,
           or reimagined public spaces, can illuminate rather than sanitize the past.   SUBSCRIPTIONS
             Moreover, heritage loss disproportionately affects marginalized communities
           whose histories were never fully recorded, let alone protected. When their stories are   Phone +91 20 40199102
           lost, silenced, or dismissed, it deepens historical inequities. Preserving these   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           narratives is not only about justice, it is about restoring plurality to the human story.   Baner Road,
           Recognition of this imbalance is essential if preservation efforts are to be truly   Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
           inclusive and globally representative.                           Published by Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi
             Dr. Krishan Kant Sharma, Professor and Head, Department of History at CCS   Regd. office 367, Kotla Street
           University, Meerut emphasizes the need for inclusive heritage policies, deeper   Meerut City-250 002 (UP)
           academic engagement and local community participation. His call to action reflects a   Founding year 2023
           growing consensus that heritage cannot be preserved by institutions alone; it must be   Subject Multidisciplinary
           lived, understood, and defended by those who inherit and embody it.   Frequency Fortnightly
             Technology offers hope through 3D reconstructions and digital archives, but it   Format Online
           cannot replace lived heritage, the rituals, scents, and textures that make memory   Language English
           tangible and deeply human.                                         Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
             In the end, when history is erased, we lose more than the past, we forfeit the   Website www.revoir.in
           wisdom it holds for the present and the vision it offers for the future. To protect our
           heritage is not an act of nostalgia, but of foresight. It is to declare that the stories of   Legal Advisor
           our ancestors still matter and that forgetting is never neutral.      Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)


                                                                            Copyright © 2025 REVOIR (eZine),
         Khzuberil
                                                                            all rights reserved. This publication
           Dr. Kamran H. Zuberi                                             may not be reproduced in any form
           Editor in Chief                                                        without permission.
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH




































           Heritage loss                                                         ivilizations are not only remem-
                                                                                 bered through their people, but
                                                                           Cthrough the physical echoes of
                                                                           their existence, monuments, temples,
           What happens                                                    ture that once shaped lives and beliefs.
                                                                           manuscripts, sculptures and the architec-
                                                                           These markers of heritage are more than
                                                                           aesthetic or archaeological treasures;
                                                                           they are the soul of communities, the
                                                                           collective memory of humankind etched
           when history                                                    in stone and spirit. When cultural her-
                                                                           itage is lost, whether by the hand of war,
                                                                           the slow decay of neglect, or the sudden
                                                                           force of natural disasters, we lose more
                                                                           than just structures. We lose identity,
           is erased?                                                      behind reverberates through generations.
                                                                           knowledge and continuity. The void left
                                                                              Observed annually on April 18,
                                                                           World Heritage Day, officially known as
                                                                           the International Day for Monuments
                                                                           and Sites, calls attention to this very fra-
                                                                           gility. It prompts an urgent reckoning:
           The loss of cultural heritage is not simply the removal of stone   what happens when the physical sym-
                                                                           bols of our shared past are obliterated?
           or timber, it is the theft of meaning, the erasure of chapters   And what is at stake for the global com-
           from the human story. Yet, in each act of preservation, in      munity when history, quite literally, is
                                                                           erased?
           every reconstructed shrine or digitized archive, there lies
                                                                           The silent ruin: A global crisis in
           defiance. A refusal to forget. A determination to remember,     cultural loss
                                                                              Cultural heritage loss is not a prob-
           rebuild and reclaim. By Aarav Sharma                            lem confined to any single region or era.  ►►

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                   5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Looted artifacts on black markets                                                                 Bamiyan Buddhas, Afghanistan – Cliff niches where   giant statues once stood













        ►  From the sands of Syria to the shores of
           the Indian Ocean, entire chapters of
           human civilization have been obliterated
           in moments of violence or years of inat-
           tention. It is a global crisis, unfolding in
           real-time.

           Palmyra: A city of echoes reduced
           to rubble
             Few modern cases illustrate the dev-                                                          Earthquake-damaged temples, Kathmandu, Nepal
           astation of cultural heritage loss more
           starkly than the destruction of Palmyra
           in Syria. Once a thriving caravan city on
           the Silk Road, Palmyra held a unique
           blend of Greco-Roman and Persian ar-
           chitectural styles. In 2015, this
           UNESCO World Heritage site was sys-
           tematically destroyed by the Islamic
           State (ISIS), who viewed the ruins as   nant. The empty niches where the Bud-  today may not exist tomorrow, not be-
           idolatrous and sought to use the destruc-  dhas once stood are stark reminders of   cause of bombs or bulldozers, but be-
           tion as a propaganda tool.      how intolerance annihilates not just the   cause of bureaucratic inertia and public
             The demolition of Palmyra’s 2,000-  present but the past.     neglect.
           year-old Temple of Bel and Arch of Tri-
           umph was not merely an attack on build-  Neglect: The slow violence against   Italy’s Pompeii: Weathering and
           ings, it was an assault on identity and   memory                wear
           shared history. What was lost wasn’t   While war makes headlines, the quiet   Even in the developed world, her-
           only architecture but irreplaceable in-  decay of neglect is a more insidious de-  itage suffers from environmental factors
           sight into ancient civilizations that had   stroyer of heritage. Many historical   and mismanagement. Pompeii, the
           flourished through coexistence and cul-  sites, particularly in developing regions,   Roman city buried by Mount Vesuvius
           tural exchange.                 suffer due to inadequate funding, poor   in 79 AD, faces a constant battle against
                                           maintenance, lack of expertise, or even   rain, mold and foot traffic.
           Bamiyan Buddhas: A cultural     apathy.                            Despite restoration efforts, collapses
           cleansing                                                       of ancient buildings have occurred due
             In 2001, the world watched in dis-  Hampi, India: A forgotten empire   to delays in preservation work. The
           belief as the Taliban destroyed the Ba-  crumbling              threat here isn’t ideological or militaris-
           miyan Buddhas of Afghanistan, massive   The ruins of Hampi, a UNESCO   tic, it’s indifference and misallocation of
           statues carved into a cliff face during the   World Heritage site in southern India,   resources.
           6th century. These statues had survived   once belonged to the powerful Vijayana-
           Mongol invasions and centuries of shift-  gara Empire. Despite its historical sig-  Natural disasters: The fury of the
           ing religious tides, only to fall to ex-  nificance, the site has been under in-  uncontrollable
           tremist ideology. Their destruction was   creasing threat, from urban   When nature strikes, human history
           an act of cultural cleansing, an attempt   encroachments, vandalism and lack of   can be swept away in a matter of sec-
           to erase pre-Islamic history and assert a   conservation planning. In many such   onds. Earthquakes, floods and fires are
           singular, narrow worldview.     cases, the absence of regular mainte-  particularly devastating to heritage sites,
             Ironically, the global outcry that fol-  nance and awareness programs leads to   which often lack structural reinforce-
           lowed made the void even more poig-  irreversible damage. What survives   ment due to their antiquity.   ►►

           6                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[lective narrative. The loss of a monu-
                                                                           ment in Aleppo or Timbuktu diminishes
                                                                           the cultural wealth of all. It weakens the
                                                                           threads that bind civilizations through
         Notre-Dame Cathedral fire, Paris (2019)                           The battle to preserve: A hopeful
                                                                           shared human experience, mutual under-
                                                                           standing and historical empathy.


                                                                           resistance
                                                                              Despite the grim realities, global ef-
                                                                           forts to preserve and protect heritage
                                                                           continue to grow, often in innovative
                                                                           and inspiring ways.
                                                                           Digital resurrection
                                                                              Organizations like CyArk and
                                                                           UNESCO’s Heritage Emergency Fund
                                                                           are digitizing vulnerable sites through
                                                                           3D scanning and virtual reconstructions.
         Mosul, Iraq – Site of destruction and reconstruction              and perhaps rebuilt.
                                                                           While digital heritage cannot replace the
                                                                           real thing, it ensures that a facsimile of
                                                                           the original can be studied, experienced


                                                                           Community-led conservation
                                                                              Grassroots movements and local
                                                                           stewardship are proving vital. In Mali,
                                                                           following the destruction of ancient ma-
                                                                           nuscripts and shrines in Timbuktu by Is-
       Al-Nouri Mosque,                                                    lamist rebels, communities secretly
                                                                           smuggled thousands of documents to
                                                                           safety. Today, these texts are being digi-
                                                                           tized and restored, testament to a culture
                                                                           that refused to let its history vanish.

        ►  Kathmandu valley: Quake’s       merely about aesthetics or tourism reve-  International legal frameworks
           cultural cost                   nue; it undermines identity, education,   Stronger international laws and col-
             In 2015, a massive earthquake struck   continuity and global solidarity.   laboration between nations are making it
           Nepal, killing thousands and reducing                           harder for looted artifacts to be traded or
           many of the historic temples of Kath-  Erasing identity and memory   trafficked. High-profile repatriations of
           mandu Valley to rubble. These struc-  Cultural sites embody shared mem-  stolen cultural objects, from Benin
           tures, many dating back to the 12th cen-  ory. When they are lost, so too are the   bronzes to Cambodian statues, signal a
           tury, were not just places of worship, but   stories, rituals and philosophies embed-  growing commitment to justice and rec-
           community centers, cultural landmarks   ded in them. For marginalized com-  onciliation.
           and living heritage. The loss was not just   munities, especially those recovering
           architectural but social and spiritual.   from colonial legacies or conflict, this   Rebuilding what can’t be replaced
                                           can feel like a second erasure, a silenc-  The loss of cultural heritage is not
           Notre-Dame Cathedral: A global   ing of voices and histories that never   simply the removal of stone or timber, it
           mourning                        fully healed.                   is the theft of meaning, the erasure of
             Closer to the West, the 2019 fire at                          chapters from the human story. Yet, in
           Notre-Dame Cathedral in Paris stunned   Loss of knowledge and learning   each act of preservation, in every recon-
           the world. Though most of the structure   Temples, manuscripts, paintings and   structed shrine or digitized archive,
           was eventually saved, the emotional re-  monuments serve as open-air class-  there lies defiance. A refusal to forget. A
           sponse highlighted how such monu-  rooms. They provide insights into an-  determination to remember, rebuild and
           ments transcend geography. People of   cient technologies, medical practices, re-  reclaim.
           all backgrounds mourned as flames en-  ligious syncretism and ecological   On this Day, let us move into action,
           gulfed the spire. The incident revealed   wisdom. When they are gone, the   supporting policies, institutions and
           how strongly we are tethered to these   knowledge they hold may never be re-  communities that safeguard our shared
           symbols, even when they don’t belong   covered.                 history. When history is erased, the fu-
           to our own culture directly.                                    ture becomes unmoored. But by protect-
                                           Globalization and the shared past   ing the past, we lay a foundation for dig-
           Why heritage loss hurts us all    In an interconnected world, one na-  nity, resilience and collective identity
             The destruction of heritage is not   tion’s heritage is part of humanity’s col-  that no bomb or disaster can destroy. ■

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                   7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[PERSPECTIVE  Prof. Krishan Kant Sharma                                the most heart-wrenching examples of
                                                                           heritage loss across the globe, the oblit-
                                                                           eration of Palmyra in Syria by ISIS, the
                                                                           dynamiting of the Bamiyan Buddhas in
                                                                           Afghanistan by the Taliban and the loot-
           speaks on history’s vanishing legacy
                                                                           ing of Iraq’s National Museum during
           Preserving the
                                                                           the 2003 invasion. These were not mere
                                                                           acts of vandalism; they were symbolic
                                                                           erasures of collective memory and cul-
                                                                           tural pride, intended to sever people
                                                                           from their roots.
           soul of civilization                                            India’s forgotten glories: From

                                                                           Nalanda to Kangla fort
                                                                              India, too, is not immune. While
                                                                           some losses have drawn attention, others
           Safeguarding heritage is not about preserving                   suffer in obscurity. Prof. Sharma high-
                                                                           lights the neglect of the Martand Sun
           the past, it’s about protecting the compass that                Temple in Jammu and Kashmir, once a
           guides our collective future. By Anaya Gupta                    marvel of Kashmiri temple architecture,
                                                                           now lying in partial ruins and largely ig-
                                                                           nored. The burning of Nalanda Mahavi-
                                                                           hara by Bakhtiyar Khilji in the 12th cen-  ►►

                 n the occasion of World Her-
                 itage Day, Dr. Krishan Kant
           OSharma, Professor and Head of
           the Department of History at Chaudhary
           Charan Singh University, Meerut, offers
           an illuminating perspective on what is at
           stake when we allow our historical and
           cultural legacies to erode. In a world
           hurtling toward modernization, his in-
           sights serve as both a caution and a call
           to action: the loss of heritage is not
           merely the destruction of stone and
           script but a fading of identity, memory
           and the very soul of civilization.

           The living bridge between past
           and future
             At its core, cultural heritage, as Prof.
           Sharma explains, is the dual expression
           of a nation’s identity, tangible and intan-
           gible. The former comprises physical ar-
           tifacts like monuments, temples and re-
           lics that stand as enduring witnesses to a
           society's evolution. The latter encom-
           passes traditions, folklore, language, rit-                                                          Dr. Krishan Kant Sharma, Professor and Head, Department of History, CCS University, Meerut
           uals, music and performing arts, the liv-
           ing heritage that binds generations. “It is
           essential to conserve cultural legacy,” he
           emphasizes, “because the next genera-
           tion will comprehend it only when we
           protect and pass it down.” Without these
           bridges to the past, communities lose
           their sense of origin and purpose.

           When stones fall, civilizations
           tremble
             History, when erased, reverberates
           far beyond the immediate site of de-
           struction. Prof. Sharma recalls some of

           8                                           www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[►  tury led to the destruction of one of the                       is the repatriation of artifacts looted dur-

           world’s first residential universities, an   “                  ing colonial rule. For Prof. Sharma, the
           irreplaceable center of Buddhist scholar-                       matter is clear: cultural artifacts belong
           ship. Meanwhile, historic forts like Kan-  Destroying a         with the people who have a direct, an-
           gla Fort in Manipur and the lesser-doc-                         cestral connection to them. “The local
           umented archaeological mounds of   nation’s heritage is         population takes pride in and has a close
           Western Uttar Pradesh are silently van-                         relationship with the cultural artifacts
           ishing victims of construction encroach-  like severing the     that were taken,” he asserts. Returning
           ment and nearby brick kiln extraction.                          these items is not just an act of restitu-
                                             roots of a green              tion; it is a reconnection of communities
           Erasing the roots: The cost of                                  with their histories.
           cultural amnesia                  tree, it leaves a
             What happens to a nation when its                             Guardians of memory: The role of
           cultural markers are erased, whether by   society dry and       teachers and institutions
           ideology, neglect, or war? Prof. Sharma                            Amidst the challenges, there is hope.
           compares it to cutting the roots of a   dead.”                  Prof. Sharma notes a growing commit-
           flourishing tree: “It becomes lifeless and                      ment by the Indian government to revive
           dry.” A country’s cultural identity is its                      and protect the nation’s cultural pride.
           pride and when it's obliterated, its   ories preserved in the collective con-  Awareness campaigns, heritage walks,
           people lose a vital connection to who   sciousness of a people are not so easily   museum initiatives and increased media
           they are. The effect ripples into the   erased.                 attention are beginning to change the
           younger generations, who grow up un-                            narrative. However, he believes the
           anchored, unaware of the soil from   Can technology touch the past?   greatest responsibility lies with educa-
           which they come. "Without understand-  The digital dilemma      tional institutions and those who shape
           ing ancestry, development is impos-  Still, the question arises: can technol-  young minds. “Teachers, historians and
           sible," he says poignantly, noting that   ogy rescue what is lost? Efforts like 3D   the nation's universities can play a sig-
           heritage gives youth a lens through   recreations and digital restorations are   nificant role,” he says. By organizing
           which to understand both the past and   becoming increasingly common as a re-  field visits, holding discussions and fos-
           their place in the present.     sponse to destruction. Prof. Sharma sees   tering a sense of curiosity, educators can
                                           these as symbolic gestures, useful for   empower the youth to value and defend
           Power and the past: The politics of   education and awareness, but unable to   their heritage.
           historical interpretation       substitute the visceral experience of
             In recent years, the political dimen-  standing before a centuries-old monu-  A shared legacy, a shared
           sions of heritage destruction have drawn   ment, of touching history with one's own  responsibility
           intense scrutiny. Some argue that rewrit-  hands. “In practice, the physical pres-  Looking to the future, Prof. Sharma’s
           ing history or removing cultural markers   ence of cultural heritage offers a unique   message is unequivocal: the preserva-
           is a tool of power. Prof. Sharma, ho-  experiential connection,” he notes, re-  tion of world heritage must become a
           wever, takes a nuanced stance. While he   minding us that cultural meaning lives   collective mission. It is not a task for
           acknowledges that interpretations of his-  not only in form but in the sensory and   governments or historians alone, but for
           tory can shift, he maintains that histori-  emotional interaction with space.   global citizens. “Until everyone acquires
           cal truth cannot be rewritten. “Only the                        an awareness of cultural heritage, this
           interpretation of history may be   The return home: Repatriating   effort will not be feasible,” he warns.
           changed; the facts of history cannot be   stolen history        But he also sees the potential for a
           altered,” he affirms. Monuments may   One of the most complex and conten-  global awakening, through education,
           fall and texts may burn, but the mem-  tious aspects of heritage discourse today   digital platforms and international co-
                                                                           operation. “If everyone recognizes, ap-
                                                                           preciates and beautifies the legacy
                                                                           around them, then perhaps the world's
                                                                           heritage can be conserved.”

                                                                           History as a compass: Why world
                                                                           heritage day still matters
                                                                              As World Heritage Day reminds us
         Bamiyan Buddhas, Afghanistan                                      fragile. In a world grappling with rapid
                                                                           each year, history is not static. It is dy-
                                                                           namic, layered and alive. But it is also
                                                                           urbanization, political polarization and
                                                                           cultural homogenization, voices like
                                                                           Prof. Krishan Kant Sharma’s remind us
                                                                           that safeguarding heritage is not about
                                                                           preserving the past, it’s about protecting

                                                                           future. ■

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in      the compass that guides our collective   9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Healing from loss                                               that most individuals go through as they

                                                                           process their loss. Elisabeth Kübler-
                                                                           Ross’s seminal work, On Death and
                                                                           Dying (1969), introduced a model that
     INSIGHT  Coping with grief                                            has become a foundational tool in under-
                                                                           standing grief. The five stages she out-
                                                                           lined, denial, anger, bargaining, depres-
                                                                           sion and acceptance, represent
           and finding                                                     emotional states that individuals may
                                                                           experience in various orders and inten-
                                                                           sities.
                                                                              Denial is often the first response to
                                                                           loss. The pain may feel so overwhel-
           resilience                                                      accept what has happened. This stage
                                                                           ming that the mind initially refuses to
                                                                           can provide a temporary respite, allow-
                                                                           ing individuals to absorb the news at
                                                                           their own pace.
           The journey through grief is undeniably difficult, but it          Anger often follows as a natural reac-
                                                                           tion to feeling helpless or powerless. In-
           is also a path that can lead to personal growth and             dividuals may feel angry at the circum-
           resilience. By Rajeev Khanna                                    stances, at the person who has passed   ►►



                oss is an inevitable part of life,
                but the journey through grief can
           Lfeel uniquely isolating and over-
           whelming. Whether it comes in the form
           of death, breakups, or other significant
           life changes, the emotional pain that fol-
           lows can challenge even the strongest
           individuals. The grieving process can be
           long and complex, often leaving individ-
           uals feeling lost, confused, or emo-
           tionally drained. Yet, within this painful
           journey, healing is possible. Healing
           does not mean forgetting or erasing the
           loss, but rather learning how to live with
           it in a way that fosters resilience and
           emotional growth.
             In honor of World Healing Day, this
           article explores how individuals and
           communities navigate the difficult jour-
           ney of grief, emphasizing the impor-
           tance of understanding the stages of
           grief, the role of cultural practices in the
           healing process and how dance can
           serve as a vital form of collective ex-
           pression. The article aims to provide
           comfort and guidance for those experi-
           encing grief, while also offering valu-
           able insights for caregivers, mental
           health professionals, cultural scholars
           and readers with a deep interest in
           human emotions and healing.
           The stages of grief: A universal yet
           personal experience
             Grief is a deeply personal experience
           and no two people grieve in the same
           way. However, psychologists and re-
           searchers have identified certain stages

           10                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Healing Garden – A space for peace and restoration
                                                                                                           Solitary nature scene, evoking feelings of solitude





















        ►  away, or even at themselves.
             Bargaining is characterized by a des-
           perate desire to reverse or prevent the
           loss. This might manifest as “if only”
           thoughts, as individuals wish they could
           have done something differently.
             Depression is a profound sadness that
           sets in when the reality of the loss sinks
           in. This stage can be particularly isolat-
           ing, as the weight of grief can feel too
           much to bear alone.
             Acceptance is not about forgetting                                                            A symbol of hope and resilience amidst grief
           the loss but finding a way to move for-
           ward. It represents a sense of peace and
           the understanding that life must con-
           tinue, even in the face of loss.
             It’s important to note that these
           stages are not linear. Grievers might
           move back and forth between stages, or
           skip some altogether. Healing, therefore,   ferings.            the Yoruba of West Africa, have com-
           is not about completing each stage but   In Hindu tradition, the period of   plex spiritual practices surrounding
           rather finding a personal path through   mourning is marked by rituals that may   death. The deceased are believed to
           grief.                          extend over several days. The Shraddha   enter into the realm of ancestors and
                                           ceremony, performed on the 13th day   their presence is honored through var-
           Cultural practices in grieving and   after death, is designed to ensure the de-  ious rituals. In some communities, large
           healing                         ceased’s journey to the afterlife. The   communal funerals serve as a celebra-
             While the emotional experience of   grieving process often involves com-  tion of life and the event may include
           grief is universal, the way in which grief   munity support, with extended family   music, dance and storytelling as ways of
           is expressed and processed can vary sig-  and friends coming together to offer   expressing grief and preserving the
           nificantly across cultures. Different cul-  prayers and comfort. Additionally,   memory of the deceased.
           tures have unique rituals, traditions and   Hindu beliefs around reincarnation can   These cultural practices serve as im-
           beliefs that offer support during the   offer solace, as the idea that life is cycli-  portant coping mechanisms, providing
           grieving process and facilitate healing.   cal provides hope that death is not an   individuals with structured ways to ex-
             In Mexican culture, the annual Día   end but a transition.    press their grief, celebrate the life of the
           de los Muertos (Day of the Dead) is a   Japanese culture has a tradition   deceased and, ultimately, find a sense of
           vibrant celebration of life and death.   called Obon, a festival during which   peace. The rituals and beliefs inherent in
           Families gather to honor their deceased   families welcome back the spirits of   these traditions offer a sense of com-
           loved ones, creating altars adorned with   their ancestors. Lanterns are lit and of-  munity and collective resilience, high-
           photographs, candles, food and mari-  ferings are made at the family altar to   lighting the importance of connection
           golds. This ritual is not focused on sor-  guide the spirits back. This period also   and support during times of loss.
           row but on celebrating the continuity of   serves as an opportunity for families to
           life. The belief is that the souls of the   gather and reflect on their ancestors’   The role of support systems in
           deceased return to be with their families   lives, reinforcing the connection be-  grief recovery
           for a brief time and the living express   tween the living and the deceased.   While cultural practices provide a
           their love and respect through these of-  African cultures, particularly among   framework for grieving, the presence of  ►►

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[►  strong support systems plays a critical
           role in the healing process. Individuals
           experiencing grief often feel over-
           whelmed and alone, but support from
           family, friends and professionals can
           make a significant difference.
             Emotional support: Simply having
           someone to talk to, who listens without
           judgment, can be a powerful tool for
           healing. The validation of one’s feelings                                                       A woman in conversation with a therapist
           of sorrow, anger, or confusion is impor-
           tant. Grief counselors or therapists can
           help individuals navigate the complex
           emotions that arise during mourning.
             Social support: Engaging with others
           who have experienced similar losses can
           provide comfort and validation. Grief
           support groups or online communities
           can connect individuals and allow them
           to share their experiences in a safe and
           understanding space.
             Physical support: Helping with day-
           to-day tasks can ease the burden on
           those grieving. Whether it’s preparing
           meals, assisting with household chores,
           or offering transportation, physical sup-
           port provides practical assistance that al-
           lows the individual to focus on their
           emotional recovery.
             The importance of a collective sup-                                                           People gathered for pooja
           port system cannot be overstated. In
           many cultures, mourning is a communal
           activity, with extended families, friends
           and neighbors coming together to help
           each other through the hardest times.   way of embodying grief, not as some-
           This sense of solidarity can create an en-  thing to suppress, but as an energy to be
           vironment where healing is possible.   expressed. In this sense, dance becomes
                                           a ritual of connection, healing and emo-
           Dance as collective healing     tional release.
             In addition to the emotional and   Celebratory dances: such as those
           physical support from loved ones, cer-  seen in Mexico’s Day of the Dead or
           tain forms of expression can facilitate   Brazilian Carnival, allow the community
           healing. Dance stands out as a unique   to come together to honor the lives of
           and powerful medium for both individ-  the deceased, celebrate their memories
           ual and collective healing. Across the   and affirm the continuity of life. These
           globe, dance has been a vital part of rit-  dances promote resilience, reminding                A woman grieving in front of a grave
           uals associated with grief and celebra-  participants that life and love transcend
           tion.                           death.
             In many African cultures, dance is in-
           tegral to funerals and memorial services.   Finding resilience through healing
           In Ghana, the Adowa dance is per-  The journey through grief is undeni-
           formed at funerals to express the sorrow   ably difficult, but it is also a path that
           of the community, allowing grief to be   can lead to personal growth and resil-  the resilience that comes with healing is
           shared collectively. Similarly, in the Ca-  ience. Understanding that grief is not a   the ability to live with that loss, to carry
           ribbean, the Lamentation Dance in-  linear process and that healing does not   it forward in a way that honors the
           volves the rhythmic movement of the   mean forgetting, allows individuals to   memory of those we have lost and to
           body to express grief and mourning,   give themselves permission to mourn in   find hope and joy again in life. As we
           helping individuals release their emo-  their own way and on their own time-  celebrate World Healing Day, let us re-
           tions in a communal setting.    line. The cultural practices, support sys-  member that healing is not only about
             The physical movement of dance,   tems and forms of expression, such as   overcoming pain but also about embrac-
           coupled with music, enables individuals   dance, offer invaluable tools for navigat-  ing the strength within ourselves and our
           to release pent-up emotions in a way   ing this challenging time.   communities to move forward with
           that words alone may not allow. It is a   Grief may never fully disappear, but   grace and resilience. ■

           12                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION








































           The Spiritual Connection                                        dance is a sacred act, embedded in ritual,
                                                                           worship and the pursuit of divine connec-
                                                                           tion.
           Dance as sacred                                                 Dance in worship: A cross-cultural

                                                                           spiritual thread
                                                                              Throughout human history, dance has
                                                                           played a vital role in religious cere-
                                                                           monies and spiritual practices. In many
           language                                                        traditions, it is not just a symbolic offer-
                                                                           ing to the divine, it is a path to transcen-
                                                                           dence.

                                                                           Sufi whirling: Spinning toward the
           To dance is to remember what it means to be human,              divine
                                                                              Among the most iconic examples of
           rooted in earth, reaching for the divine and moving             sacred dance is the Sufi whirling prac-
                                                                           ticed by the Mevlevi order of dervishes in
           always toward a deeper connection with each other               Turkey. With white flowing robes and
           and with something sacred. By Riya Verma                        arms outstretched, one hand turned up-
                                                                           ward to receive from God, the other
                                                                           downward to give to the earth, the der-
               rom the earliest moments of   cation. To dance is not merely to move, it   vishes spin in a meditative trance. This
               human history, when flickering   is to speak in the body’s language, often   ritual, known as the Sema, symbolizes
           Fflames cast shadows on cave walls,   in devotion, reverence and surrender.   the soul’s journey toward divine love and
           dance has been a profound form of ex-  Each year, International Dance Day   unity. It is not performance but prayer;
           pression. In the absence of words, rhythm   serves as a global reminder of the power   not spectacle but surrender.
           and movement emerged as primal ways   and universality of dance. While often   The circular motion represents the ce-
           to communicate with one another and   celebrated for its aesthetic and cultural   lestial order, mirroring the rotation of
           with the divine. Across continents and   richness, this occasion is also a moment   planets, the cycles of life and the eternal
           civilizations, dance transcends entertain-  to reflect on dance’s deeper spiritual and   flow of creation. As the dancer loses
           ment; it becomes ritual, prayer and invo-  communal meanings. For many cultures,   awareness of the self, a deeper awareness  ►►

           14                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[►  is born, one that dissolves ego and invites
           spiritual communion.
           Native American ceremonial
           dances: Earth and spirit united
             For Native American tribes, dance is
           deeply intertwined with cosmology,
           community and the land itself. The Sun
           Dance of the Plains tribes, for example, is
           a physically grueling and spiritually
           charged ritual, often involving fasting,
           piercing and days of ceremonial move-
           ment. Participants offer themselves as
           living prayers for the healing of their
           people and the harmony of the world.                                                            Christian praise dance in church
             Similarly, Powwows, though modern
           in format, are rooted in traditional dances
           like the Grass Dance or the Eagle Dance,
           which carry spiritual significance. The
           beat of the drum represents the heartbeat
           of Mother Earth and each dancer’s steps
           are considered a prayer, echoing ances-
           tral wisdom and invoking spiritual bal-
           ance.

           Hindu temple dance: Embodied
           devotion
             In India, dance has long been en-
           shrined as a divine art form. The classical
           dance Bharatanatyam, originating in
           Tamil Nadu, was historically performed
           by devadasis, female temple dancers, as a
           form of devotional offering. Every ges-
           ture (mudra), eye movement and rhythm
           carries symbolic meaning, illustrating                                                          Native American Powwow dance
           stories from Hindu epics like the Ramay-
           ana and Mahabharata.
             The dancer is not merely enacting my-
           thology but becoming the deity. The
           boundaries between the performer and
                                           the divine blur, inviting both dancer and   Dance as collective ritual: Sacred
                                           audience into a sacred experience of dar-  unity in motion
                                           shan, a glimpse of the divine presence.   Beyond individual devotion, sacred
                                                                           dance often functions as collective ritual,
                                           Balinese ritual dance: Harmony of   uniting communities in a shared act of
                                           realms                          reverence and renewal.
                                             In Bali, dance is a spiritual necessity.
                                           Traditional dances like the Legong and   African ritual dances: Communal
                                           Barong are not simply artistic displays   pulse
                                           but essential components of temple cere-  In many African spiritual traditions,
                                           monies. Dancers are trained from child-  dance is central to rites of passage, har-
                                           hood to channel divine energies, acting as   vest festivals and ancestral worship.
                                           vessels through which gods and spirits   Movements are deeply grounded, earthy
                                           may move.                       and rhythmic, often performed in circular
                                                                           formations that represent unity and conti-
         Hindu Bharatanatyam dance         munity from malevolent forces and to   dance rituals fosters not only spiritual
                                             The dances serve multiple functions:
                                           to honor deities, to protect the com-
                                                                           nuity. The collective participation in
                                                                           awakening but social cohesion.
                                           maintain the spiritual balance between
                                           humans, nature and the unseen world.
                                                                              The Yoruba religion of Nigeria, for
                                                                           example, includes dances for orishas
                                           Elaborate masks, stylized gestures and
                                                                           (deities), each with distinct movements,
                                           hypnotic gamelan music create an at-
                                           mosphere that dissolves the mundane and
                                                                           rhythms and costumes. Dancers may
                                           elevates the sacred.
                                                                                                       15
           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in      enter a trance, believed to be possessed  ►►]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[►  by the spirit of the orisha, thereby cre-
           ating a tangible encounter between the
           human and divine realms.

           Christian liturgical dance: Praise in
           motion
             Even within the often-reserved setting
           of Christian churches, liturgical dance
           has found space, especially in African-
           American congregations. Here, move-
           ment becomes a heartfelt offering of
           praise, hope and lament. In Gospel
           churches, spontaneous dance can erupt
           during worship as an overflow of spiri-
           tual ecstasy. Choreographed liturgical
           performances, meanwhile, bring biblical                                                         Sufi whirling dervishes
           narratives to life and deepen communal
           worship.
             The dancing body becomes a vessel
           through which the Holy Spirit moves, ex-
                                                                           A dance of reverence and renewal
                                                                              In an increasingly fractured world,
                                                                           where digital interactions often replace
                                                                           embodied presence, sacred dance offers a
                                                                           return to wholeness. It reminds us that the
                                                                           body is not separate from spirit, that com-
                                                                           munity is not separate from ritual and
                                                                           that movement can be a gateway to the
                                                                           eternal.
                                                                              To dance is to remember what it
                                                                           means to be human, rooted in earth,
                                                                           reaching for the divine and moving al-
                                                                           ways toward a deeper connection with
         Ancient temple dance reliefs                                      in that movement, across temples and de-
                                                                           each other and with something sacred.
                                                                              As the drum beats, the feet move. And
                                                                           serts, churches and forests, something
                                                                           timeless unfolds, a dance as old as spirit
                                                                           itself. ■



           pressing what words cannot contain, joy,   Dance and the human spirit:
           grief, awe and longing.         Bridging worlds
                                             The universality of sacred dance
           The inner journey: Dance as     speaks to a profound human need, to
           meditation and healing          bridge the seen and unseen, the body and
             For many spiritual seekers and mind-  spirit, the individual and community.
           fulness practitioners, dance offers a path   Through ritual movement, cultures ac-
           inward. Practices such as ecstatic dance,   ross time have made sense of suffering,
           five rhythms, or trance dance invite par-  celebrated life’s cycles and invoked the
           ticipants to enter a state of non-verbal   presence of the divine.
           meditation. There are no steps to follow,   While each tradition is unique in form
           only breath, beat and inner listening.   and belief, a common thread runs
             In these spaces, dance is not about   through them all: the body as sacred in-
           performance but about presence. Move-  strument, rhythm as a spiritual pulse and
           ment becomes a dialogue with the self   dance as a living prayer.
           and the universe, cathartic, liberating and   On International Dance Day, let us
           often deeply healing.           look beyond choreography and cos-
             By bypassing the analytical mind,   tumes. Let us honor dance as an ancestral                 Ecstatic dance session
           dance touches the subconscious, releas-  gift, a mirror of our spiritual longing and
           ing emotional blockages and awakening   a bridge to something greater than our-
           spiritual insight.              selves.

           16                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[From pedals to protest


                                                                           cycle Day is often celebrated for the
           The social and                                                  cling. But beneath the surface of fitness   DEEP DIVE
                                                                           health and sustainability benefits of cy-
                                                                           campaigns and urban cycling incentives
                                                                           lies a deeper story. This story is about
                                                                           how bicycles have served as instruments
                                                                           of activism, challenging authority, de-
           political role of                                               manding better public spaces and carv-
                                                                           ing out paths for freedom and reform in
                                                                           societies around the world.

                                                                           The symbolic power of the bicycle
           bicycles                                                        tonomy. It is human-powered, afford-
                                                                              At its core, the bicycle represents au-
                                                                           able, accessible and independent of fos-
                                                                           sil fuels or large infrastructures. In many
                                                                           social justice movements, these very
                                                                           qualities elevate the bicycle from a
           How two wheels became a global symbol of resistance,            mode of transport to a symbol of resist-
                                                                           ance and self-determination.
           hope and collective change. By Ishita Desai                        Cycling as a form of protest is pow-
                                                                           erful because of its accessibility; it in-
                                                                           vites participation from people across
             n the modern world, where mech-  heart of political and social movements.   gender, age and economic backgrounds.
             anized transport and high-speed con-  Whether in the form of mass protests or   A rider becomes both individual and
           Inectivity often dominate our imagi-  silent, solitary rides of defiance, bicycles   collective, both visible and mobile, em-
           nation of progress, the humble bicycle   have become emblems of resistance,   bodying freedom of movement in the
           seems almost too quiet to spark rev-  tools of empowerment and mobile plat-  most literal sense. In oppressive regimes
           olutions. Yet, history and current events   forms for environmental and social jus-  or systems that restrict freedom, simply
           reveal a surprising truth; bicycles have   tice.                riding a bike can become a rebellious
           persistently wheeled their way into the   Observed annually on April 19, Bi-  act.            ►►

















         Youth riding bicycles during a protest in New York






















           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[While bicycles were once emblem-
                                                                           atic of Chinese working-class life, the
                                                                           rapid modernization and embrace of car
                                                                           culture created stark environmental and
                                                                           social inequalities. In response, environ-
                                                                           mental activists began organizing cy-
                                                                           cling events to protest urban pollution
         Mass bicycle protest event                                        like Beijing and Shanghai quietly organ-
                                                                           and call for sustainable policies.
                                                                              During the 2010s, activists in cities
                                                                           ized group rides, often under the guise
                                                                           of fitness or community engagement.
                                                                           These rides subtly critiqued government
                                                                           negligence on pollution and public
                                                                           health without directly violating strict
                                                                           protest laws. In such contexts, the bi-
                                                                           cycle became a coded language of re-
                                                                           sistance, a way to speak out without
                                                                           speaking aloud.
         Mass cycling event in Dhaka, Bangladesh                           came a focal point of democratic aspira-
                                                                           Pedaling for democracy: Egypt’s
                                                                           revolutionary rides
                                                                              During the Arab Spring, Egypt be-

                                                                           tion and state crackdown. While the
                                                                           iconic images of Tahrir Square showed
                                                                           massive human crowds, bicycles played
                                                                           an understated but essential role in sus-
                                                                           taining the protests.
                                                                              Youth activists in Cairo used bicycles
                                                                           to navigate the congested and mili-
                                                                           tarized city, delivering supplies, organiz-
                                                                           ing meetings and mapping police move-
                                           would gather en masse to ride through   ments. In a city where surveillance was
                                           city streets, asserting their right to public   tight and public transportation unreli-
                                           space in cities dominated by cars.   able, bicycles provided speed, stealth
                                             What made Critical Mass both effec-  and freedom.
                                           tive and controversial was its non-hier-  More than just a practical tool, cy-
                                           archical, leaderless structure. Without   cling also came to represent a vision of a
                                           permits or formal organizers, it blurred   freer, more inclusive city, one not
                                           the line between celebration and civil   choked by traffic and state control. After
                                           disobedience. It was simultaneously joy-  the fall of Hosni Mubarak, some activ-
                                           ful and disruptive. In cities from London   ists began promoting cycling as part of a
                                                                           broader urban renewal and democratiza-
                                           to Buenos Aires, participants used the
         A woman riding a bicycle in Iran  frastructure, cleaner air and a rethink of   to political transformation.
                                           rides to advocate for better cycling in-
                                                                           tion effort, linking environmental justice
                                           urban priorities.
                                                                           The intersection of gender and
                                             By slowing down traffic and occupy-
                                           ing roads, Critical Mass challenged the
                                                                           pedals
                                                                              The political symbolism of bicycles
                                           automobile-centric design of modern
                                           cities. In doing so, it turned the bicycle
                                                                           extends beyond mobility into the realm
                                           into a tool for environmental advocacy,
                                                                           act of a woman riding a bicycle has been
                                           civic engagement and urban reimagina-
                                                                           seen as a radical gesture. In Iran, women
                                           tion.                           of gender equity. In many countries, the
        ►  Critical mass: Taking back the                                  defying bans by cycling in public have
           streets                         Cycling through repression:     turned their rides into viral moments of
             Perhaps the most globally recognized   China’s silent rides   protest. In India, programs like “Cycle
           example of bicycle-based protest is the   In authoritarian contexts, where pub-  Chalao” have empowered young girls in
           Critical Mass movement. Originating in   lic demonstrations can be swiftly sup-  rural areas to attend school and assert
           San Francisco in 1992, this monthly ride   pressed, bicycles offer a quieter yet po-  their independence.
           was not an organized protest in the tradi-  tent form of protest. In China, bicycles   Historically, the bicycle has been a
           tional sense, but rather an organic form   have long been both a staple of daily life   vehicle of feminist liberation. In the late
           of “protest through presence.” Cyclists   and, at times, a silent symbol of dissent.   19th century, suffragettes in the West   ►►
           18                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[►  used bicycles as a metaphor for emanci-
           pation. The American activist Susan B.
           Anthony famously said that bicycles had
           “done more to emancipate women than
           anything else in the world.”
             Today, cycling continues to be a bat-
           tleground where issues of access, safety
           and representation are negotiated, mak-
           ing it a vital lens through which to view
           intersectional justice.

           Riding against climate change
             As the planet faces an escalating cli-
           mate crisis, the bicycle has reemerged as
           a potent symbol of ecological respon-                                                           Cycle rally in ancient times
           sibility. Around the world, climate
           marches, particularly those led by youth
           movements, have featured bicycles
           prominently, not only as a sustainable
           alternative but as a symbol of the sys-
           temic change required.
             Events like “Ride for the Future” in
           the United States, or “Cycling Marches”
           in Europe and Southeast Asia, use mass
           bike rides to call attention to inadequate
           climate policy and demand action from
           governments. The bicycle, once again,
           becomes not just a protest tool but a vi-
           sion of a better, greener society.

           Urban planning and policy: The
           road ahead
             For urban planners and policy enthu-
           siasts, the message of these movements                                                          Woman cyclist in Europe
           is clear: bicycles are not just about trans-
           port, they’re about access, equity and
           community. Cities that invest in cycling
           infrastructure aren't just reducing emis-
           sions; they are actively reshaping public   frequently cited as models, but many   robi’s recent push for bike lanes, are ex-
           life.                           cities in the Global South, from Bo-  perimenting with new paradigms of
             Amsterdam and Copenhagen are   gotá’s car-free Ciclovía Sundays to Nai-  urban mobility. When citizens demand
                                                                           these changes through protest rides or
                                                                           grassroots initiatives, they not only ad-
                                                                           vocate for better transit, they redefine
                                                                           civic participation.
                                                                           The quiet power of wheels
                                                                              In an age where protests often make
                                                                           headlines through spectacle or confron-
                                                                           tation, the bicycle offers a different kind
                                                                           of resistance, silent, mobile and persist-
         A family riding during Car-Free Sunday                            promise of the future.
                                                                           ent. It moves through traffic, past check-
                                                                           points, across social barriers. It carries
                                                                           with it the weight of history and the

                                                                              On this Bicycle Day, let us look bey-
                                                                           ond the spokes and handlebars. Let us
                                                                           see the bicycle for what it truly is, a
                                                                           powerful political tool, a symbol of
                                                                           human resilience and a quiet engine of
                                                                           transformation. In its simple frame lies

                                                                           and collective hope. ■

                                                                                                       19
           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in      the complex story of freedom, resistance]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[SPECIAL STORY









































                 ave you ever noticed how your
                 energy levels rise and dip at cer-  Reset your life
           Htain times of the day, or how
           some people naturally wake up at dawn
           while others hit their stride after sunset?
           These variations aren’t just quirks; they   How to tune in
           are signs of your biological clock at
           work. Known scientifically as the circa-
           dian rhythm, this internal timer governs
           everything from sleep patterns and body
           temperature to hormone levels and me-  your body clock
           tabolism. When in sync, your body
           clock can be a powerful ally in optimiz-
           ing health, productivity and mental clar-
           ity.
             On the occasion of Biological Clock   Our ancestors rose with the sun and slept with the
           Day, it’s the perfect moment to explore
           how aligning your daily habits with your   stars, but modern life has created a disconnect
           internal rhythms can dramatically im-
           prove your overall well-being. Whether   between our internal clocks and our external
           you're a busy urban dweller, a wellness
           seeker, or someone struggling to get   schedules. By Naina Kapoor
           quality sleep, learning to tune in to your
           body’s natural cues can be a life-chang-
           ing shift.                      uses this information to regulate various   nism ensures survival by helping organ-
                                           biological functions in a roughly 24-  isms anticipate and adapt to changes in
           Unlocking the secrets of your   hour cycle. This includes your sleep-  their environment, especially the daily
           biological clock                wake schedule, digestion, alertness and   light-dark cycle.
             At the core of your body’s timekeep-  even mood.                 Modern science confirms that disrup-
           ing is the suprachiasmatic nucleus   Circadian rhythms are not exclusive   tions to this rhythm, from night shifts to
           (SCN), a small group of cells located in   to humans; almost all living organisms,   excessive screen time, can lead to long-
           the brain’s hypothalamus. The SCN re-  from plants to animals, have similar in-  term health issues such as insomnia,
           ceives light signals from your eyes and   ternal clocks. This evolutionary mecha-  obesity, diabetes, depression and heart   ►►

           20                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Airplane window with sunrise view                                                                 Graphic representation of the circadian rhythm














        ►  disease. The good news? You can recal-
           ibrate your biological clock through
           conscious lifestyle choices.

           The role of natural light in
           synchronizing your body clock
             Light is the most powerful cue in
           regulating your circadian rhythm. Spe-
           cifically, exposure to natural sunlight in
           the morning acts as a reset button for
           your biological clock. When your eyes
           detect natural light, they signal the SCN
           to suppress melatonin production (the
           sleep hormone) and increase cortisol
           (which promotes alertness). This natural                                                        Tips for maintaining healthy sleep
           progression helps set the tone for a pro-
           ductive and energized day.
             On the flip side, blue light exposure
           at night, especially from screens, tricks
           your brain into thinking it's still daytime,
           delaying melatonin release and pushing   Hormonal changes also influence
           your sleep schedule later. Over time, this   women’s internal clocks more dramati-
           misalignment between your environ-  cally, particularly during menstruation,
           ment and your internal clock can disrupt   pregnancy and menopause. These fluctu-
           everything from your sleep cycle to   ations can shift sleep patterns, affect
           metabolic functions.            energy levels and increase sensitivity to
                                           circadian disruptions.
           Tip:                              Men, meanwhile, may have slightly
             Spend at least 20–30 minutes out-  later circadian preferences, often leaning
           doors in natural light each morning and   towards "night owl" tendencies. Testos-
           reduce screen exposure at least an hour   terone levels, which peak in the morn-
           before bedtime. Opt for dim, warm   ing, play a role in influencing male alert-
           lighting in the evening to promote mela-  ness and mood.                                        A tired traveler resting in an airport lounge
           tonin release.
                                           Tip:
           How biological clocks affect men   Tune in to your personal chronotype,
           and women differently           whether you're a morning lark, night
             Circadian rhythms aren’t one-size-  owl, or somewhere in between, and tai-
           fits-all. Gender plays a significant role in   lor your schedule accordingly rather
           how biological clocks operate. Studies   than fighting your natural rhythm.
           suggest that women tend to have shorter                         tal and metabolic peaks and troughs
           circadian cycles than men, making them   Syncing daily routines with the   throughout the day. Here’s how to lever-
           natural early risers. This can partly ex-  body’s natural rhythms   age this rhythm:
           plain why women often wake up earlier   Your internal clock doesn’t just con-  Morning (6 AM – 10 AM): Ideal for
           and feel sleepier in the evening.   trol sleep; it orchestrates physical, men-  light exercise, planning and strategic   ►►

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Meditation before sleep                                                                           Woman stretching in natural morning light










                                                                           Improving sleep quality by
                                                                           honoring the clock
         Person checking mobile after stepping off a plane                 environmental factors. Rather than rely-
                                                                              Sleep is the cornerstone of circadian
                                                                           health. Yet, millions struggle with sleep
                                                                           deprivation due to poor habits, stress, or

                                                                           ing solely on sleep aids, aim to create a
                                                                           circadian-friendly sleep environment.
                                                                           Key strategies:
                                                                              Maintain a consistent sleep-wake
                                                                           schedule, even on weekends.
                                                                              Make your bedroom cool, dark and
                                                                           quiet.
                                                                              Establish a wind-down routine:
                                                                           reading, meditation, or light stretching.
                                                                              Limit naps to 20–30 minutes if
                                                                           needed during the day.
        ►  thinking. Cortisol is naturally high,   concentration and gastrointestinal is-  When sleep aligns with your internal
           boosting alertness.             sues.                           rhythm, you wake up refreshed, your
             Midday (11 AM – 2 PM): Body tem-  Jet lag is more than just inconven-  metabolism functions optimally and
           perature and reaction times peak, good   ient; it can impair immune function and   your emotional resilience improves.
           for demanding tasks.            cognitive performance, particularly in
             Afternoon (2 PM – 5 PM): Great for   frequent travelers like pilots, cabin crew   Reclaiming your rhythm in a
           collaborative work, light physical activ-  and business professionals.   digital world
           ity and social interaction.                                        Our ancestors rose with the sun and
             Evening (6 PM – 9 PM): Winding   The science:                 slept with the stars, but modern life has
           down time. Ideal for relaxation, creative   Jet lag occurs because your SCN   created a disconnect between our inter-
           hobbies and family time.        takes time to adjust to a new light-dark   nal clocks and our external schedules.
             Night (10 PM onwards): Melatonin   cycle. The mismatch between internal   Fortunately, tuning in to your body
           rises, preparing the body for sleep.   and external time cues throws off mela-  clock doesn’t require radical changes; it
           Avoid stimulants and screens to allow   tonin and cortisol secretion.   starts with small, intentional adjustments
           for quality rest.                                               that honor your biological design.
             Tip: Design your day in sync with   Tips to combat jet lag:      As we reflect on Biological Clock
           these natural cycles to boost productiv-  Gradually shift your sleep schedule a   Day, consider how your daily routines
           ity, focus and overall well-being.   few days before travel.    either support or sabotage your natural
                                             Expose yourself to bright light at   rhythm.
           Navigating jet lag in a 24/7 world   your destination's morning time.   Whether you’re chasing productivity,
             In an increasingly globalized world,   Avoid caffeine and alcohol close to   seeking better sleep, or striving for ho-
           international travel is common, but so   bedtime.               listic health, aligning with your circa-
           is jet lag, a condition caused by rapid   Stay hydrated and avoid heavy   dian rhythm is one of the most powerful
           time zone changes that misalign your   meals late in the day. Consider melato-  steps you can take.
           internal clock with local time. Symp-  nin supplements (with medical advice)   The rhythm is already within you,
           toms include fatigue, insomnia, poor   to ease the transition.   you just have to listen. ■

           22                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[►
                                            Tuning in to the rhythm within


         Vipin Agarwal, meditation expert and wellness guide
                                           The digital detox                                                     ANALYSIS





                                           we all need






                                           Even a regular morning walk in sunlight can work
                                           wonders. Align your sleep-wake cycle, eat warm meals
                                           on time and find moments of quiet. By Pooja Mehta



             n an era of digital overload, dis-  can experience change by meditating   For travelers and global professionals
             rupted routines and 24/7 lifestyles,   consistently for just 10–15 minutes   grappling with jet lag, Vipin rec-
           Ituning in to your natural body clock   daily, preferably around the same time.   ommends grounding techniques like
           is more than a health trend, it’s a per-                        mindful breathing, hydration and short
           sonal revolution. And at the heart of this   Living in cities, out of sync   meditations during flights. “When you
           shift lies a quieter wisdom, one that be-  Urban dwellers, he notes, are often   land, expose yourself to local sunlight
           gins with stillness.            the most disconnected from their circa-  and follow the local sleep cycle as soon
             Meditation expert and long-time   dian rhythms. “Artificial light, screen   as possible. The body will adjust faster.”
           wellness guide from Meerut, Vipin   exposure (blue light, known as high-
           Agarwal, believes that our inner rhythm   energy visible HEV light), late meals, all   Begin today, begin gently
           holds the power to transform our physi-  these confuse the body,” Vipin says.   For those new to the journey, his ad-
           cal, mental and emotional health. “The   “People stay awake long after their   vice is simple: “Wake up with the sun,
           body clock isn’t just a biological mecha-  minds are tired and wake up with alarms   breathe deeply, sit in silence. Start with
           nism,” he reflects. “It’s nature’s poetry   that override their natural rhythm.”   rhythm, not perfection.”
           inside us, an unseen rhythm that governs   He suggests simple corrections: dim-  Because in tuning into your body
           not just our sleep but our clarity, creativ-  ming lights after sunset, keeping screens   clock, you’re not just resetting your
           ity and calm.”                  away before bed and syncing meals and   health, you’re resetting your life. ■
             Vipin’s personal journey into under-  meditation times with natural light cues.
           standing the body clock didn’t begin in a
           lab or through theory. It started with ex-  Common mistakes, gentle fixes
           haustion. “Years ago, I was constantly   From his experience working with
           fatigued. I realized I was living against   people across age groups, he identifies
           my own rhythm. That moment was a   common rhythm-disrupting habits, ir-
           wake-up call.” Gradually, he began re-  regular sleep, skipping meals, over-caf-
           aligning his life with the natural cycles   feination and emotional burnout.
           of light, sleep, breath and mindfulness   “People try to push through fatigue with
           and the change, he says, was nothing   coffee and productivity hacks. But rest
           short of profound.              is productive too.”
                                             His remedy? Start small. “Even a
           Meditation: Your reset button   regular morning walk in sunlight can
             So how does meditation factor into   work wonders. Align your sleep-wake
           this inner alignment?           cycle, eat warm meals on time and find
             Vipin explains, “Our breath is the   moments of quiet.”
           bridge between body and mind. Specific
           techniques like anapanasati (mindful-  The inner sunrise and global lives
           ness of breathing) and yoga nidra (con-  Vipin often speaks of the “inner sun-
           scious relaxation) help reset the nervous   rise”, a metaphor for awakening to your             Circadian clock illustration
           system. Practicing meditation at sunrise   own timing. “You can feel this in the
           or sunset enhances its impact, as these   calm of early morning, when your
           are transition times for the body clock.”   energy is soft, not scattered. It’s the best
             He emphasizes that even beginners   time to meditate, reflect and align.”                   ►►

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION








































           More Than Magic                                                 alike, exploring the science of wish ful-
                                                                           fillment opens a window into how pur-
                                                                           pose can shape our lives in ways both
                                                                           subtle and profound.
           The science of                                                  The psychology of wishing: More

                                                                           than mere daydreams
                                                                              To wish is to hope and hope is a pow-
                                                                           erful psychological force. Research in
                                                                           positive psychology reveals that hope
           wishes                                                          isn't passive. It's an active cognitive pro-
                                                                           cess involving goal setting, pathway
                                                                           thinking (developing strategies to reach
                                                                           the goal) and agency thinking (the moti-
                                                                           vation to pursue it). According to psy-
           Science affirms what cultures and wisdom traditions have        chologist Charles Snyder, who pioneered
                                                                           the theory of hope, individuals with high
           always known: to dream is to live more fully. By Rohan Kapoor   hope are better problem solvers, more
                                                                           resilient under stress and exhibit greater
                                                                           overall well-being.
                here is something profoundly   deeper psychological and physiological   But the impact doesn’t stop at emo-
                human about making a wish.   transformation at play?       tions. Having a dream to pursue acti-
           TWhether whispered under shoot-   As the world observes World wish   vates specific regions of the brain, espe-
           ing stars, blown into birthday candles, or   day, it's worth diving into the fascinating   cially the prefrontal cortex, which is
           silently etched into vision boards,   intersection between science, hope and   responsible for planning, decision-mak-
           wishes tap into our deepest hopes and   human potential. This day, inspired by   ing and regulating emotions. The brain,
           longings. Across cultures and ages,   the first wish granted by the Make-A-  in essence, begins to organize around
           people have held onto dreams as both   Wish Foundation, reminds us not just of   our dreams, making strategic choices
           guiding lights and sources of resilience.   the power of a fulfilled desire but also   that inch us closer to them, often uncon-
           But what truly happens when those   the remarkable journey toward it. For   sciously.
           dreams come to life? Is wish fulfillment   general readers, young professionals,   Wishing isn’t just escapism; it’s a
           simply a pleasant emotion, or is there a   educators, parents and wellness seekers   neurological rehearsal for achievement.   ►►

           24                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[collective


                                                                             prayers

                                                                             across faiths
         Members of the Sikh community at a Gurudwara                        into collective spiritual rituals,
                                                                               Across cultures and continents,
                                                                             the act of wishing is often elevated

                                                                             where communities come together
                                                                             in hope and devotion. In Hinduism,
                                                                             devotees gather at temples to tie
                                                                             threads around sacred trees or
                                                                             make offerings at shrines, praying
                                                                             for health, prosperity, or the suc-
                                                                             cess of a loved one. In Christianity,
                                                                             prayer circles and vigils are held
                                                                             where congregants ask God to
                                                                             grant healing or guidance, believ-
                                                                             ing in the power of unified faith. In
                                                                             Islam, the concept of du'a, a per-
                                                                             sonal supplication to Allah, is often
                                                                             shared collectively during com-
                                                                             munal gatherings, especially dur-
                                                                             ing holy nights like Laylat al-Qadr.
                                                                             Buddhists chant mantras and light
                                                                             lamps in temples to manifest peace
                                                                             and enlightenment, while Judaism
                                                                             encourages the recitation of Psalms
                                                                             in groups, often for someone who
         Lighting candles to make a wish                                     uals, steeped in centuries of tradi-
                                                                             is ill or facing hardship. These rit-
                                                                             tion, serve not only as spiritual
                                                                             conduits but also as emotional an-
                                                                             chors, reminding individuals that
                                                                             they are not alone in their longing
                                                                             and that shared hope is a powerful
                                                                             force in itself.


        ►  The brain on dreams: A          focus and enhances emotional resilience.   better sleep, lower cortisol levels and
           neurochemical symphony            Moreover, the default mode network,   improved heart health.
             When a goal or wish is visualized,   a set of brain regions involved in imagi-  A study published in Psychosomatic
           the brain releases dopamine, the “feel-  nation, introspection and empathy, is   Medicine found that individuals with a
           good” neurotransmitter associated with   heavily engaged when we fantasize or   strong sense of purpose in life had sig-
           reward and motivation. This release   plan our future. This system helps indi-  nificantly lower risk of stroke and heart
           doesn’t only occur when the wish comes   viduals simulate possible realities, pav-  disease. Similarly, patients recovering
           true, it starts much earlier, during the   ing the way for creative problem-solving   from illness, particularly children
           mere act of imagining success. Neuro-  and personal growth.     granted wishes through organizations
           scientific studies have shown that men-                         like Make-A-Wish, report increased op-
           tal imagery and visualization techniques,   Wishes and the body: The mind-  timism, faster recovery and higher
           common in elite athletes and per-  body connection              compliance with medical treatments.
           formers, activate the same brain circuits   It might seem surprising, but harbor-  When the mind embraces possibility,
           as actual physical execution.   ing meaningful goals can also benefit   the body often follows suit.
             This dopaminergic activity helps   physical health. Chronic stress, often a
           people stay motivated, persevere   consequence of aimlessness or unful-  The fulfillment moment: What
           through setbacks and maintain a positive   filled desires, has been linked to inflam-  happens when a wish comes true
           outlook. It's not that dreams guarantee   mation, cardiovascular issues and weak-  The experience of achieving a long-
           success, but that the act of dreaming re-  ened immunity. On the flip side, people   held dream is both exhilarating and
           calibrates our mindset, increases mental   with clear life goals tend to experience   humbling. Psychologists note that ful-  ►►

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[►













         A temple priest making a wish                                                                     A young woman making a wish in a church














                                                                         ► fillment often brings a peak emotional
                                                                           state, a sense of joy, gratitude and con-
                                                                           nection to something larger than oneself.
                                                                           But it also brings a moment of cognitive
                                                                           integration, where the journey, the strug-
                                                                           gle and the final reward coalesce into a
                                                                           deeper understanding of self-worth and
         People gathered in prayer at a church                             show increased activity in the ventral
                                                                           capability.
                                                                              Brain scans during such moments
                                                                           striatum, part of the reward system and
                                                                           the medial prefrontal cortex, which
                                                                           plays a role in self-referential thought.
                                                                           In simpler terms, people begin to see
                                                                           themselves differently, as someone who
                                                                           is capable, worthy and empowered.
                                                                              This internal shift often leads to
                                                                           further ambition, generosity, or purpose-
                                                                           driven action. In many cases, one dream
                                                                           fulfilled becomes the stepping stone for
                                                                           another.

                                                                           The flip side: When wishes delay or
                                                                           change
                                                                              Not every wish materializes as imag-
                                                                           ined. Life detours, disappointments and
                                                                           evolving priorities can challenge even
                                                                           the most ardent dreamers. Yet science
                                                                           shows that the ability to adapt goals,
                                                                           known as “goal disengagement and re-
                                                                           engagement”, is crucial to long-term
         Muslim girls performing namaz                                     attainable dreams and refocus on new
                                                                           well-being. People who can let go of un-
                                                                           aspirations experience less distress,
                                                                           higher self-esteem and even better phys-
                                                                           ical health.
                                                                              The key is flexibility, not stubborn-
                                                                           ness. In many ways, the human spirit is
                                                                           defined not by what we achieve, but by
                                                                           how we navigate what we don’t.

           26                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025 ►►]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Colorful prayer flags fluttering in the Himalayas                                                 Tying threads on a sacred tree




















         Graduates tossing caps in the air fulfilling the wish             ple practices nurture both creativity and


                                                                           discipline, two qualities that make
                                                                           wishes more than just whimsical
                                                                           thoughts.
                                                                           Why wishes matter more than ever
                                                                              In today’s fast-paced, hyper-compet-
                                                                           itive world, it’s easy to become cynical
                                                                           or overwhelmed. But wishes act as gen-
                                                                           tle reminders of who we are and who we
                                                                           hope to become. They offer direction in
                                                                           uncertainty, meaning in routine and cou-
                                                                           rage in adversity.
                                                                              From a mental health perspective,
                                                                           cultivating dreams is an antidote to stag-
                                                                           nation and despair. Therapists often use
                                                                           future-oriented techniques, such as “mi-
                                                                           racle questions” in solution-focused
                                                                           therapy, to help clients imagine a life
                                                                           beyond their current struggles. These
                                                                           imagined futures act as emotional an-
         A child blowing a dandelion or candles                            The sacred spark of human
                                                                           chors, offering both clarity and motiva-
                                                                           tion.

                                                                           aspiration
                                                                              At its core, a wish is more than a
                                                                           fleeting desire; it is a seed of transfor-
                                                                           mation. When nurtured with intention,
                                                                           belief and action, it grows, not just into

                                                                           touches others. Science affirms what
                                                                           cultures and wisdom traditions have al-
        ►  Teaching the art of dreaming: The   role by encouraging imagination, sup-  a personal success, but into a ripple that
                                                                           ways known: to dream is to live more
           role of parents and educators   porting autonomy and modeling healthy   fully.
             Fostering the ability to wish and to   goal-setting behavior.    As we mark World Wish Day, let us
           work toward those wishes, is a vital life   In classrooms and at home, wish-  honor not just the dreams already ful-
           skill. For children and adolescents,   making can be turned into structured ex-  filled, but the ones still forming in hearts
           learning how to set realistic goals, visu-  ercises: writing “future-self” letters, cre-  and minds across the globe. For in wish-
           alize success and cope with setbacks   ating vision boards, or setting SMART   ing, we connect with our better selves
           builds emotional intelligence and resil-  goals (Specific, Measurable, Achiev-  and in striving, we inch closer to the ex-
           ience. Parents and educators play a key   able, Relevant, Time-bound). These sim-  traordinary. ■

           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                                April 16-30, 2025









           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     This period encourages bold steps in your       Your charm works wonders in both career and
                     professional life. Career growth looks promising if   personal life. A new partnership or collaboration
                     you stay focused. Romance deepens, but avoid    could blossom. Romance is peaceful, yet excit-
                     being too dominant. Financial gains are possible. A   ing. Save rather than splurge. Take breaks to
                     balanced diet will boost your energy.           avoid mental fatigue.

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     A calm and constructive period awaits you. Career   Transformation continues, let go of what no
                     moves slowly but surely. Relationships bring    longer serves you. Professionally, progress
                     comfort and warmth. Financial planning pays off,   comes through adaptability. Romance inten-
                     avoid unnecessary purchases. Relaxation and     sifies, stay open and vulnerable. Monitor your
                     nature walks are highly beneficial.             health, especially digestion and sleep patterns.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Gemini, ideas flow effortlessly, capitalize on   Sagittarius, a sense of adventure drives success
                     them for career advantage. Your charm attracts   in your work. Relationships sparkle with joy and
                     attention in love life. Financially, minor gains   spontaneity. Money flows in, but avoid risky
                     are likely. Don’t ignore sleep and hydration for   ventures. A short trip or nature escape will re-
                     overall well-being.                             juvenate you.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Emotional clarity helps in both work and rela-  You’re focused and determined, ideal for career
                     tionships. Focus on long-term goals profes-     growth. Love life feels secure, though you must
                     sionally. Romance is nurturing, but avoid cling-  make time for it. Financially, it’s a favorable
                     ing behavior. Financial status is stable.       period. Stretching and proper posture will im-
                     Meditation and journaling bring peace of mind.   prove physical health.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Recognition and appreciation come your way at   Aquarius, innovation helps you stand out profes-
                     work. Passion rises in relationships, but avoid   sionally. Romantic surprises keep things interest-
                     controlling tendencies. Finances improve, but   ing. Income is steady; think long-term in invest-
                     think before spending. Focus on flexibility exer-  ments. Take digital breaks for better mental
                     cises and deep breathing.                       clarity.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, details matter, your precision helps solve   Follow your intuition, your inner voice won’t
                     problems at work. Love life requires empathy    mislead you. Creativity brings recognition at
                     and listening. Stick to your budget to avoid fi-  work. Love is sweet and supportive. Manage fi-
                     nancial strain. Mind-body practices like yoga   nances wisely to avoid stress. Mindfulness
                     bring balance.                                  brings emotional grounding.


           28                                          www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






           Fresh death threat to Salman Khan   ED sends a strong message that no one
           raises alarming concerns        is above the law. It is important, ho-
             It is deeply concerning to learn that   wever, that investigations are carried out   ernment and industry bodies should
           Bollywood superstar Salman Khan has   fairly, free from political bias or media   work together to strengthen employment
           once again received a fresh death threat.   sensationalism.     opportunities in emerging sectors to ab-
           As a prominent public figure and   The public deserves to know the   sorb the impact of such layoffs.
           philanthropist, Salman Khan has long   facts, and due process must be followed   Let us hope affected employees re-
           been a beloved icon in Indian cinema.   to ensure justice is served. At the same   ceive the support they need during this
           Repeated threats not only endanger his life   time, such cases must not become tools   challenging time.
           but also raise serious questions about the   for political point-scoring but rather op-  Naresh Kumar Sharma, Hyderabad,
           safety of celebrities and public figures in   portunities to strengthen institutional in-  Telangana, India
           our country.                    tegrity and public trust.
             Such incidents reflect a disturbing   We hope for a thorough, impartial in-
           trend and highlight the urgent need for   vestigation.          Fire at government hospital in
           enhanced security and stronger cyber   Neeti Roy, New Delhi, India   Lucknow raises safety concerns
           surveillance mechanisms. No one should                             The recent fire incident at a govern-
           have to live under constant fear, especially                    ment hospital in Lucknow, which led to
           those who contribute to the cultural fabric   Impending Google layoffs a cause   the emergency evacuation of over 200
           of the nation.                  for concern in India            patients, is both alarming and deeply
             Authorities must act swiftly to identify   The news that Google is reportedly   distressing. While it is a relief that
           the source and ensure strict legal action.   preparing for another round of layoffs,   timely action prevented any loss of life,
           We hope for Salman Khan’s continued   with advertising, sales, and marketing   the situation highlights serious concerns
           safety and that such threats are not taken   teams in India likely to be affected, is   about fire safety and emergency prepa-
           lightly.                        deeply concerning. In an already uncer-  redness in our public healthcare institu-
           Ramesh Sehgal, Mumbai,          tain job market, such decisions by global   tions.
           Maharashtra, India              tech giants can have far-reaching impli-  Hospitals are meant to be safe havens
                                           cations on both individuals and the   for the sick and vulnerable. A fire in
                                           broader economy.                such a facility not only endangers lives
           Robert Vadra appears before ED in   India has been a significant talent   but also disrupts critical medical care. It
           Haryana land deal case          hub for Google, and layoffs in these cru-  is essential that hospitals, especially
             This is in reference to Robert Vadra's   cial departments may disrupt careers and   government-run ones, conduct regular
           recent appearance at the Enforcement   create anxiety among employees and as-  fire safety audits, ensure the mainte-
           Directorate (ED) office following a   pirants alike. While companies must   nance of electrical systems, and train
           summon related to the Haryana land   evolve and restructure to stay compet-  staff in emergency response protocols.
           deal case. Such developments underline   itive, there must also be a balanced ap-  Authorities must investigate the fire’s
           the increasing focus on transparency and   proach that considers employee welfare.   cause and take measures to prevent re-
           accountability in high-profile land trans-  It is essential for corporations to pro-  currence. Patient and healthcare worker
           actions.                        vide transparent communication, fair   safety should always remain a priority.
             As a prominent figure linked to polit-  severance, and adequate support during   Krishan Kuma Gupta, Lucknow,
           ical circles, Vadra’s questioning by the   such transitions. Additionally, the gov-  Uttar Pradesh, India



            Letters (limited to one hundred words) are welcome and should be addressed to the Editor at
            Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in





             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           APRIL 16 2025 | REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 www.revoir.in                                  29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA["Life is either a daring adventure or nothing at all."


                                                                     – Helen Keller






































































                                                                                                                Photo credit: Valeska Huyskens]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[►










































                                    YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!






































                                                                                                         ►►

                                                                                 ol. 3, No.5 |
                                                                                 REVOIR
                                                                               REVOIR
                                                                                V
                                                                                  V
                                                                                      |

                                                                                   ol. 3, No.7 |
                                                                                      |
                                                                            .in
                                                                             .in
                                                                            .in
                                                                        .revoir
                                                                         .revoir
                                                                              .in
                                                                              ol. 3, No.4 |
                                                                              REVOIR
                                                                             V
                                                                              REVOIR

                                                                                         OCT
                                                                                        FEBRUAR
                                                                                        |

                                                                                                 Y
                                                                                                   16 2025

                                                                                             APRIL
                                                                                        DECEMBER 16 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 01 2024
                                                                                       SEPTEMBER 16 2024

                                                                                      |
                                                                                       |
                                                                                       NOVEMBER 16 2024



           32
           32
           323232
           32
           32
                                                      www
                                                      .revoir
                                                  www.revoir
                                                      www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.6 | MARCH 16 2025MARCH 01 2025
           32
           AUGUST 01 2024 | REVOIR www.revoir.in
           32
           32                                     wwwwwwwww www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.8 | APRIL 16 2025 01 2025OBER 01 2024
           323232
           32
           32
           32
           32
           32
                                                                   www
                                                                    www
                                                                   www
                                                                 REVOIR Magazine
                                                                  REVOIR Magazine REVOIR | AUGUST 01 202432
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       .revoir
                                                                       REVOIR Magazine
                                                                    .in www.revoir.in
                                                                     www
                                                           .revoir
                                                           .in
                                                       www.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.3 | FEBRUARY 01 2025.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.2 | JANUARY 16 2025.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine Vol. 3, No.1 | JANUARY 01 2025www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | DECEMBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | NOVEMBER 01 2024www.revoir.in REVOIR | OCTOBER 16 2023www.revoir.in REVOIR | AUGUST 16 2024
                                                         .revoir
                                                            www
                                                                .revoir
                                                                .in
                                                              .in
                                                              REVOIR Magazine
                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>