<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="32"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Contents









                     VOLUME: 04, ISSUE: 04 I  FEBRUARY 16 2026  ON THE COVER: DESIGNING VIPIN AGARWAL I PHOTO: KARINA)





               5



                                                            15













                                                           23                                        26
















           4-Editorial: The fate of human thought          26-Why strawberries are never alone
           5-Is thinking becoming optional?                28-Horoscopes

           8-What would fill the vacuum?                   29-Letters

           11-The innovation graveyard                     31-Frame of thought

           15-The ecology of power
           18-When care breaks relationships

           21-The dates that quietly run our lives

           23-The composer who never saw the

           frame









           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Beyond Automation
     EDITORIAL  The fate of                                                         Editor-in-Chief

                                                                                            MAGAZINE


                                                                                   Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           human thought                                                        Social & Lifestyle Editor

                                                                                    Dr. Uzma Naaz

                                              here was a time when thinking de-   Art & Culture Editor
                                              manded effort. We argued over ideas,   Dr. Monika Garg
                                        Tfilled notebooks with rough drafts,
                                        changed our minds mid-sentence. Today, al-  Digital Strategy Editor
                                        gorithms suggest what to read, what to     Vishakha Sharma
                                        watch, even what to believe. On World
                                        Thinking Day, an uncomfortable question
                                        surfaces: if machines can reason, calculate   Social Media Editor
                                        and predict faster than we can, what’s left   Sushil Kumar
                                        for us?
                                           In a café recently, I watched students   Art & Graphics Director
                                        preparing a presentation. They weren’t de-   Vipin Agarwal
                                        bating concepts so much as prompting an
                                        AI tool to generate slides, summaries and
           potential questions from their professor. It was efficient. Impressive, even. But some-  EDITORIAL ADVISORY BOARD
           thing felt absent. The confusion that sharpens clarity. The slow formation of an origi-
           nal idea.                                                         D. Bisht Shandilya (Former News
             Machines now draft reports, analyse markets and assist in medical decisions. In   Editor, United News of India, New
           the knowledge economy, speed is currency and artificial intelligence provides it gen-
           erously. For young professionals racing deadlines, outsourcing mental labour seems   Delhi), Prof. Amar Garg (Former
           practical. Why spend hours interpreting data when software can surface patterns in   Vice Chancellor), Dr. Dharamveer
           seconds?                                                         Mahajan (Former Principal),  Prof.
             Yet thinking has never been only about speed. It’s about wrestling with uncer-  Archana Sharma (Pol. Science),
           tainty. It’s about questioning assumptions and resisting easy answers. Predictive sys-  Prof. P.D. Sharma (Botanist), Dr.
           tems guide us toward what is most likely. But breakthroughs often emerge from what   N.P. Saxena (Botanist), Shahid A
           seems unlikely.                                                        Siddiqui IRS (Retd.)
             There’s a subtler cost, too. The more we depend on algorithmic guidance, the
           more our intellectual stamina may weaken. Much like GPS has dulled our sense of   SUBSCRIPTIONS
           direction, constant digital assistance can soften judgment. We scroll instead of reflect.
           We skim instead of read deeply. We react instead of reason.
             Still, blaming technology is too simple. Calculators didn’t ruin mathematics.   Phone +91 20 40199102
           Search engines didn’t end curiosity. Used wisely, intelligent tools can expand our   Contact us Survey Number 12/1,
           reach and free us from routine tasks. The real issue is whether we use that freedom to   Baner Road,
           think more deeply or simply to produce more quickly.                Pune-411045 (Maharashtra)
             For educators and parents, the stakes are real. Are we teaching students how to   Email mail@magazine.revoir.in
           think critically, or merely how to craft better prompts? In many classrooms and of-  Website www.revoir.in
           fices, output is rewarded more than insight.
             Thinking is slow. It involves doubt and occasional failure. Sometimes it leads no-  Legal Advisor
           where. But that struggle builds judgment, empathy and perspective.   Anil Bakhshi (Advocate)
             As machines grow more capable, our advantage may lie not in processing power
           but in meaning-making. In asking better questions. In choosing thoughtfully rather
           than reacting instantly.
             So is thinking becoming optional? It might feel that way. But perhaps it’s becom-  Copyright © 2026 REVOIR (eZine),
           ing more valuable than ever. The next time your device completes your thought,   all rights reserved. This publication
           pause. Finish it yourself.                                       may not be reproduced in any form
                                                                                  without permission.


         Khzuberil
           Dr. Kamran Zuberi
           Editor in Chief
           zuberi@magazine.revoir.in

           4                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[COVER STORY








































           The AI surge                                                            hen was the last time you
                                                                                   struggled with a thought? Not
                                                                           Wscrolled, not skimmed, not re-
                                                                           acted. Struggled. Sat with an idea long
           Is thinking                                                     a campus library, a college student
                                                                           enough for it to push back.
                                                                              A few weeks ago, in a quiet corner of

                                                                           began drafting an assignment. She
                                                                           opened her laptop, typed a prompt into
                                                                           an AI tool and within seconds, para-
                                                                           graphs appeared on the screen. Clean.
           becoming                                                        adjusted a sentence or two and sub-
                                                                           Coherent. Cited. She skimmed the text,
                                                                           mitted it. Efficient? Absolutely. Impres-
                                                                           sive? Certainly. Yet the scene leaves be-
                                                                           hind a quieter, more unsettling question:
                                                                           Did she truly think through the subject,
                                                                           or did she merely approve what the ma-
           optional?                                                       urgent. As machines reason, calculate
                                                                           chine produced?
                                                                              It is a question that feels increasingly

                                                                           and predict with growing sophistication,
                                                                           what remains distinctly human in the
                                                                           process of thought? Is thinking grad-
                                                                           ually becoming optional?
           In some contexts, yes. You can get by without thinking
                                                                           The convenience trap
           deeply about many things. You can outsource,                       We live in a time of frictionless solu-
                                                                           tions. Autocomplete finishes our sen-
           automate, delegate to algorithms. But optional doesn’t          tences. Navigation apps decide our
                                                                           routes. Streaming platforms anticipate
           mean obsolete. By Naina Kapoor                                  our taste. Algorithms curate our news,

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[our shopping carts, even our potential   merely assist thinking. It simulates it.
           partners.                         For professionals in the knowledge
             There’s nothing inherently sinister   economy, this is both thrilling and unset-  “
           about this. In fact, it’s liberating. Why   tling. A marketing executive can gener-  The real risk isn’t
           waste mental energy remembering direc-  ate campaign ideas in minutes. A soft-
           tions when a map can guide you in real   ware developer can troubleshoot code
           time? Why draft a formal email from   faster than ever. A journalist can sift   that machines can
           scratch when a tool can suggest polished   through large data sets with unprece-
           alternatives?                   dented speed.                     think, but that we
             But convenience has a quiet side ef-  Productivity rises. Deadlines shrink.
           fect. It trains us to outsource micro-deci-  Expectations grow.   might decide we
           sions. And those micro-decisions, over   And yet, something subtle shifts.
           time, add up to something larger.   When the first draft is no longer yours,   don’t have to.”
             Consider online forms. They pre-fill   when the initial spark comes from a ma-
           your information. Suggest your address.   chine, are you still the primary thinker
           Correct your spelling. You barely need   in the room? Or are you becoming a cu-  over nuanced ones. That’s efficient, yes.
           to pause. Or social media captions. A   rator of machine-generated ideas?   But it’s also limiting.
           quick AI prompt and you have a witty                               Imagine a generation that rarely sits
           line ready to post. The process feels   The brain on standby    with confusion because a tool resolves it
           smooth, almost magical. Yet the more   There’s a growing body of research   instantly. What happens to intellectual
           we rely on automated thinking, the less   suggesting that our brains adapt to how   resilience? To patience? To the habit of
           we practice our own.            we use them. Memory, for example, has   questioning?
             It’s not that we’ve stopped thinking   changed in the age of smartphones. Why   These aren’t dramatic dystopian
           entirely. It’s that we’re thinking less   memorize phone numbers when they’re   fears. They’re quiet, cumulative shifts.
           deeply, less independently. And perhaps,   stored in your device? Why recall facts
           less often than we realize.     when a search engine is seconds away?   Education at a crossroads
                                             Psychologists call this “cognitive off-  Walk into a modern classroom and
           From calculators to cognitive   loading.” We transfer mental tasks to ex-  you’ll see the tension play out in real
           companions                      ternal tools. In moderation, it’s efficient.   time.
             Technology replacing mental effort   Our brains can focus on higher-order   Students use AI to draft essays.
           isn’t new. When calculators became   thinking instead of routine recall.   Teachers use AI to detect AI. Universi-
           common, there were fears that students   But here’s the tension. If we offload   ties debate policies. Some ban certain
           would forget basic arithmetic. To some   too much, do we weaken the very capac-  tools. Others integrate them into the cur-
           extent, they did. But education adapted.   ities we’re trying to preserve?   riculum.
           Calculators became tools, not substitutes   Critical thinking requires effort. So   The debate often centers on cheating.
           for understanding.              does reflection. They’re not instant.   But that’s only part of the story. The
             What’s different now is scale and in-  They involve wrestling with ambiguity,   deeper question is pedagogical. What
           timacy.                         holding conflicting ideas, tolerating un-  does it mean to learn in an era where an-
             Artificial intelligence isn’t just   certainty. Algorithms, by design, aim to   swers are abundant?
           crunching numbers. It’s writing essays,   reduce uncertainty. They give you the   Traditionally, education wasn’t just
           summarizing research papers, generat-  most probable answer, the most opti-  about correct answers. It was about the
           ing code, drafting legal briefs. It’s com-  mized suggestion.   process. Struggling with a math prob-
           posing music, designing logos, even   Over time, we might start preferring   lem. Revising a clumsy paragraph. De-
           suggesting therapy responses. It doesn’t   clarity over complexity. Quick answers   bating a philosophical idea with class-

           6                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[They can simulate patterns. But they
                                                                           don’t experience doubt. They don’t
                                                                           wrestle with moral responsibility. They
                                                                           don’t live with the consequences of
                                                                           decisions in the way humans do.
                                                                              Thinking, at its best, isn’t just cal-
                                                                           culation. It’s judgment. It’s ethical rea-
                                                                           soning. It’s the slow weaving of per-
                                                                           sonal experience with external
                                                                           information.
                                                                              That weaving still belongs to us.
                                                                           A choice, not a fate
                                                                              It would be easy to frame this as an
                                                                           inevitable decline. Brains shrinking. At-
                                                                           tention spans collapsing. Humanity sur-
                                                                           rendering to silicon.
                                                                              Reality is rarely that simple.
                                                                              Every technology reshapes cognition.
                                                                           Writing once externalized memory.
                                                                           Printing democratized knowledge. The
                                                                           internet exploded access to information.
                                                                           Each shift sparked anxiety. Each also
                                                                           unlocked new forms of thought.
                                                                              The difference now is speed. Change
                                                                           is accelerating. And we don’t always
                                                                           pause to ask what we’re trading for con-
                                                                           venience.
                                                                              Is thinking becoming optional? In
                                                                           some contexts, yes. You can get by with-
                                                                           out thinking deeply about many things.
                                                                           You can outsource, automate, delegate
                                                                           to algorithms.
                                                                              But optional doesn’t mean obsolete.
           mates. Those moments built cognitive   In such an environment, deep think-  The danger isn’t that machines think.
           muscles.                        ing can feel almost inefficient. Why   It’s that we might forget to. That we
             If AI can produce a near-perfect   spend an hour reading multiple perspec-  might become so comfortable with
           essay in seconds, students might skip the   tives when a 60-second video sum-  ready-made answers that we stop asking
           messy middle. They might never experi-  marizes the “truth”? Why write a long,   better questions.
           ence the discomfort that often precedes   thoughtful post when short, punchy lines   Maybe the real challenge isn’t tech-
           insight.                        get more engagement?            nological. It’s cultural. Do we value
             Of course, AI can also enhance learn-  It’s not that people have stopped car-  deep thought enough to protect it? Do
           ing. It can explain concepts in multiple   ing. Many care deeply. But the architec-  we design schools, workplaces and digi-
           ways. Provide personalized feedback.   ture of our digital spaces rewards imme-  tal platforms that reward reflection, not
           Offer simulations that bring abstract   diacy over reflection.   just speed?
           theories to life. Used wisely, it’s a pow-  And gradually, the habit of thinking   I don’t have a definitive answer.
           erful companion.                before reacting erodes.         Honestly, I’m not sure anyone does.
             But companions can quietly take                                  But I keep returning to that student
           over. The line between assistance and   What’s left for us?     and her polished, AI-generated essay. I
           substitution is thin.             So where does that leave us?   wonder what would’ve happened if
                                             If machines can analyze data faster,   she’d written it herself. It might have
           The social media mind           write more fluently and predict out-  been messier. Slower. Imperfect.
             Outside classrooms and offices,   comes with impressive accuracy, what   And perhaps, in that imperfection,
           there’s another arena where thinking   remains uniquely human?   she would’ve found something unex-
           feels increasingly optional: social media.   Creativity, some argue. But AI now   pected. A new idea. A surprising connec-
             Platforms are engineered for speed.   generates art and music that can move   tion. A thought that was truly her own.
           Scroll. React. Share. Rarely pause.   people. Empathy, perhaps. Yet even   In the end, thinking may become op-
             Algorithms decide what you see.   chatbots are trained to simulate empa-  tional in practice. But for those who
           Trending topics shape what you discuss.   thetic responses.     want depth, agency and genuine under-
           Viral posts compress complex issues   Maybe the answer isn’t in what ma-  standing, it remains essential.
           into bite-sized opinions. You’re nudged   chines can’t do, but in how we choose to   The question isn’t whether machines
           toward instant reactions. Nuance doesn’t   engage with them.    can think.
           travel as well as outrage.        Machines can generate possibilities.   It’s whether we still choose to. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[ANALYSIS


































           If Politics Went Quiet                                          and parties. Yet politics, at its core, is
                                                                           about power. Who decides? Who bene-
                                                                           fits? Who pays the price?
                                                                              Even if governments went quiet,
           What would fill                                                 decisions wouldn’t stop. They would
                                                                           simply move elsewhere.
                                                                              Take the corporate boardroom. When
                                                                           policymakers hesitate, multinational
                                                                           companies frequently step forward.
           the vacuum?                                                     chains, determine what speech is al-
                                                                           They set labor standards in supply
                                                                           lowed on digital platforms and influence
                                                                           public health through pricing and ac-
                                                                           cess. These are political decisions in ev-
                                                                           erything but name.
           Politics is not just Parliament or Congress. It’s not only         In India, we’ve seen this dynamic
                                                                           play out in subtle ways. When regu-
           manifestos and rallies. It’s the constant negotiation of        latory frameworks lag behind the rapid
                                                                           growth of digital payments or ride-shar-
           who we are and how we live together. By Arjun Patel             ing platforms, it’s often companies that
                                                                           effectively shape the rules of the road.
                                                                           Users adapt. Workers adjust. Policy-
                 o rallies. No televised shouting   temptation to imagine a world without   makers follow. The center of gravity
                 matches. No campaign slogans   politics is understandable.   shifts, but the politics remains.
           Ncreeping into dinner conver-     But here’s the uncomfortable truth:   It’s just less visible.
           sations. Just silence. It sounds almost   there is no such thing as a world without
           peaceful, doesn’t it?           politics. When formal politics retreats or   When markets take the helm
             For many professionals and urban   loses legitimacy, something else rushes   Markets are efficient allocators of re-
           readers, the phrase “I’m tired of pol-  in. Markets. Religion. Technology. Cul-  sources. They are not, however, natural
           itics” has become a reflex. It’s there in   ture. Unspoken power structures. The   guardians of equity.
           office corridors, in WhatsApp groups, in   vacuum never stays empty for long.   If formal politics weakens, markets
           airport lounges where executives scroll                         tend to expand into areas once governed
           past yet another headline. The fatigue is   The myth of neutral ground   by public debate. Education becomes a
           real. The noise feels endless. So the   Politics is often reduced to elections   private commodity. Healthcare tilts to-

           8                                                www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Algorithms
                                                                                            curate what we
                                                                                            see, what we
                                                                                            buy, even what
                                                                                            we believe. So-
                                                                                            cial media plat-
                                                                                            forms decide
                                                                                            which posts
                                                                                            trend and which
                                                                                            disappear. Artifi-
                                                                                            cial intelligence
                                                                                            systems in-
                                                                                            fluence hiring
                                                                                            decisions, credit
                                                                                            approvals and
                                                                                            predictive poli-
                                                                                            cing.
                                                                                               These sys-
                                                                                            tems are built by
                                             “                             engineers, optimized by data scientists
                                                                           and monetized by shareholders. Yet their

                                                                           impact is deeply political.
                                                                              Consider misinformation. When reg-
                                             There is no such
                                                                           platforms become the de facto referees
                                             thing as ‘no                  ulatory oversight is slow or fragmented,
                                                                           of public discourse. Their content mod-
                                             politics’, only               eration policies shape elections, public
                                                                           health campaigns and social cohesion.
                                             power operating                  In India’s massive digital ecosystem,
                                                                           with hundreds of millions of users, this
                                             without being                 is especially consequential. A rumor
                                             named.”                       travels faster than a clarification. A viral
                                                                           video can spark real-world tension.
                                                                           When formal political mechanisms fail
           ward those who can pay. Housing prices                          to build trust, people rely on what ap-
           rise according to investor logic rather   There’s reassurance in shared rituals.   pears on their screens.
           than social need.               But when politics steps back or becomes   And screens are not neutral.
             We’ve seen this in global cities from   distrusted, religious and cultural iden-
           London to Mumbai. The skyline fills   tities can take on a sharper political   Culture fills the silence
           with luxury towers while middle-class   edge.                      Sometimes, the vacuum is filled not
           families stretch budgets to stay afloat.   Across societies, from the United   by institutions but by culture.
           No one may call it “political,” but these   States to parts of Europe and South   Films, music, stand-up comedy, even
           outcomes are the result of power and   Asia, we’ve witnessed how identity   memes become vehicles for social com-
           priority.                       movements gain momentum during   mentary. In societies where political
             In India’s urban corridors, the tension   periods of political disillusionment. In   conversation feels constrained or ex-
           is palpable. Gated communities flourish   India, debates around citizenship, his-  hausting, artists carry the burden of ask-
           beside informal settlements. Metro lines   tory and cultural symbols have intensi-  ing difficult questions.
           extend into commercial hubs while pe-  fied in recent years. These are not   Think of how cinema has shaped de-
           ripheral areas wait for basic services.   merely theological conversations. They   bates around corruption, gender and so-
           When elected representatives struggle to   shape laws, public policy and the every-  cial justice. A film can humanize what
           respond swiftly, developers and finan-  day experience of minorities and major-  policy papers cannot. A song can articu-
           cial institutions often step in. They fill   ities alike.       late anger more powerfully than a mani-
           the vacuum with capital and contracts.   Even when people claim they’re   festo.
             The market doesn’t ask whether it   stepping away from politics, they’re   In India’s creative industries, story-
           should lead. It simply does.    often stepping into identity. And iden-  tellers have often stepped into contested
                                           tity, when mobilized collectively, be-  spaces. They reflect tensions that formal
           Faith and identity in the absence of   comes political.         politics struggles to resolve. The au-
           trust                             You can’t really escape it.   dience engages emotionally first, intel-
             When faith in institutions erodes,                            lectually later. It’s politics through
           people seek certainty elsewhere. Reli-  Technology as the new arbiter   narrative.
           gion, community and identity can offer   If there is one force that has quietly   Culture doesn’t replace governance.
           clarity in a confusing world.   stepped into political space over the last   But it channels frustration. It gives
             There’s comfort in belonging.   decade, it is technology.     shape to the unsaid.

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                             9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[political consequences. That technology
                                                                           encodes values. That culture shapes
                                                                           power. That religion intersects with gov-
                                                                           ernance.
                                                                              For professionals and policy ob-
                                                                           servers, this requires a shift in perspec-
                                                                           tive. Instead of saying “I’m tired of pol-
                                                                           itics,” perhaps the more useful question
                                                                           is: where has politics moved?
                                                                              Is it in the startup ecosystem? In data
           The illusion of escape          Unspoken power                  centers? In classrooms? In local housing
             So why do so many people insist   Perhaps the most important point is   associations?
           they want “no politics”?        this: when politics disappears from view,   In India, as elsewhere, the answer is
             Part of it is exhaustion. The 24-hour   it doesn’t disappear from reality.   often all of the above.
           news cycle amplifies conflict. Social   It becomes unspoken.       The vacuum is never empty. It’s
           media rewards outrage. Professional   Power shifts to corporate networks,   simply occupied by actors who may not
           lives already feel demanding. Who   religious authorities, media conglom-  call themselves political.
           wants another arena of stress?   erates, or algorithmic systems. Deci-
             But opting out is rarely neutral.   sions are made behind closed doors, jus-  A personal reckoning
           When middle-class professionals dis-  tified as technical or market-driven   I used to believe that stepping back
           engage, power often consolidates in   rather than ideological.   from political debates would bring clar-
           fewer hands. Decisions get made by   This can feel smoother, even effi-  ity. Focus on work. Family. Travel. Let
           those who show up, lobby, organize and   cient. There are fewer televised argu-  the noise pass.
           mobilize.                       ments. Less visible friction.      But the noise doesn’t really pass. It
             There’s a quiet irony here. The more   But friction, uncomfortable as it is, is   reshapes itself. It appears in a change in
           educated and globally connected a soci-  often a sign of pluralism. Open political   tax structure. In a new compliance rule.
           ety becomes, the more some of its   contestation allows grievances to sur-  In a neighborhood redevelopment plan.
           members retreat from overt political en-  face. When that space narrows, resent-  In the content my children encounter on-
           gagement. Yet their lives remain shaped   ment doesn’t vanish. It goes under-  line.
           by zoning laws, taxation, trade policy,   ground.                  Politics is not just Parliament or Con-
           environmental regulation and digital   In some countries, prolonged depolit-  gress. It’s not only manifestos and
           governance.                     icization has led to sudden, intense erup-  rallies. It’s the constant negotiation of
             In India’s metropolitan centers, you   tions of protest. Citizens who felt ig-  who we are and how we live together.
           can hear it in casual conversation. “I   nored by technocratic governance   So if politics were to disappear to-
           don’t follow politics anymore.” And yet   reassert themselves dramatically. The   morrow, something else would step in
           the same speaker worries about infla-  vacuum fills, again, but this time with   by evening. Capital. Faith. Code. Cul-
           tion, school admissions, fuel prices and   anger.               ture. Perhaps all four.
           air quality. These are political outcomes,                         The real question isn’t what fills the
           even if the word feels distasteful.   A more honest conversation   vacuum. It’s whether we’re paying at-
             Politics, in this sense, is like weather.   Maybe the goal shouldn’t be to elimi-  tention when it does.
           You may not want to discuss it, but you   nate politics but to make it more honest.   And whether, in our fatigue, we’ve
           still live in it.                 To acknowledge that markets have   mistaken silence for peace. ■

           10                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[DEEP DIVE


































                                                 Progress Interrupted


                  hat kills a brilliant idea? It’s
                  rarely incompetence. Rarely a
           Wlack of funding. And almost     The innovation
           never a shortage of imagination.
             More often, it’s something quieter. A
           closed-door meeting. A regulatory file
           that doesn’t move. A lobbyist’s phone
           call. A political calculation.
             Somewhere between the lab and the                 graveyard
           marketplace, between a prototype and a
           policy note, innovation gets buried. Not
           because it failed. But because it threat-
           ened someone.
             This is the innovation graveyard. And   The challenge for policymakers, bureaucrats and
           it’s more crowded than we like to admit.
                                           corporate leaders is simple to state, hard to practice.
           When power fears change
             Innovation is romanticized. We cele-  Don’t fear disruption. Shape it. By Aarav Sharma
           brate founders, disruptors, inventors in
           hoodies and garages. We repeat stories
           of rebellion and triumph. Yet history   Or take Stanley Meyer, who claimed   Regulation: Shield or sword?
           tells a more complicated tale.   to have developed a water-powered fuel   Regulation is necessary. No serious
             Consider Nikola Tesla. A visionary   cell vehicle. His invention was dis-  entrepreneur would argue for a world
           whose work on alternating current trans-  missed and entangled in legal disputes   without standards. Public safety, envi-
           formed modern electricity, Tesla also   over fraud. Whether flawed or ahead of   ronmental protection, consumer rights
           imagined wireless global communica-  its time, the episode reveals something   all depend on it.
           tion and free energy transmission. But   uncomfortable. Once power structures   But regulation can also become a tool
           his more radical ideas found little sup-  label an idea as threatening or inconven-  of delay. Or worse, exclusion.
           port from financiers who preferred con-  ient, it rarely receives a fair hearing.   In many industries, from pharmaceu-
           trolled, billable electricity systems. In-  Innovation doesn’t just compete in   ticals to telecom, the cost of compliance
           novation that cannot be monetized or   markets. It competes in corridors of   alone can crush a start-up before it even
           controlled often struggles to survive.   power.                 launches. Large corporations can afford

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[“



            Innovation rarely

            dies in the
            laboratory; it dies

            in the meeting

            room.”


           armies of lawyers. A two-person team
           working out of a shared office cannot.
             Take ride-sharing. When Uber ex-
           panded globally, it collided with en-
           trenched taxi unions and municipal au-
           thorities. In some cities, bans came
           swiftly. In others, regulatory reforms
           followed. The question wasn’t just about
           safety or fairness. It was about control
           of a lucrative ecosystem.
             In India, similar tensions played out
           when app-based mobility platforms dis-
           rupted traditional operators. State gov-
           ernments struggled to balance consumer
           demand with the political weight of es-
           tablished transport unions. Innovation
           moved faster than policy and policy
           often responded defensively.
             Regulation can protect society. But it
           can also protect incumbents.

           The Indian innovation paradox
             India prides itself on being a start-up
           powerhouse. It’s home to unicorns, digi-  sector innovations stall due to inter-de-  perspective, it raises uncomfortable
           tal payment revolutions and one of the   partmental rivalries. A pilot project   questions. How many transformative
           world’s most ambitious identity infras-  works beautifully in one district. It’s   ideas never reached the public because
           tructures in Aadhaar.           praised in presentations. Then it van-  they were inconvenient to a dominant
             Yet many Indian entrepreneurs   ishes into files.             platform?
           quietly admit that navigating bureau-  The idea didn’t fail. The system did.   Innovation often threatens business
           cracy can feel like navigating a maze de-                       models. And businesses, understandably,
           signed decades ago.             The corporate kill switch       protect themselves.
             Agritech start-ups have struggled   Not all innovation is crushed by gov-  Still, there’s a difference between
           with state-level mandi regulations.   ernments. Corporations have their own   competing and quietly burying.
           Health-tech innovators face overlapping   graveyards.
           compliance requirements across central   Large companies frequently acquire   Fear of disruption
           and state bodies. Drone start-ups waited   smaller competitors. Sometimes to nur-  Beyond politics and profit lies some-
           years for clear operational guidelines be-  ture them. Sometimes to neutralize   thing more human. Fear.
           fore policy liberalization arrived.   them. Economists call it killer acqui-  Innovation unsettles people. It dis-
             There’s also the subtle fear of scale.   sitions.             rupts jobs, habits, hierarchies.
           When a start-up grows too quickly, it   In the tech industry, giants like Face-  When renewable energy technologies
           may attract scrutiny not just from regu-  book and Google have bought dozens of   gained momentum, fossil fuel lobbies
           lators but from larger competitors who   start-ups. Many flourished under new   pushed back fiercely in several coun-
           feel threatened. Lobbying in India,   ownership. Others quietly disappeared.   tries. When digital news platforms
           though less visible than in some Western   Features were shelved. Teams were ab-  emerged, traditional media houses resis-
           economies, exists in different forms. In-  sorbed. Potential competitors faded   ted, sometimes dismissing them as un-
           dustry associations, sectoral committees   away.                sustainable or unethical. When artificial
           and informal influence networks all   From a strategic standpoint, this   intelligence tools began automating
           shape the rules of the game.    makes sense. Corporations are account-  tasks, entire professional communities
             And sometimes, promising public   able to shareholders. But from a societal   felt uneasy.

           12                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[A country that buries its innovators
                                                                           eventually buries its competitiveness.
                                                                           A personal reflection
                                                                              I’ve spoken to founders who describe
                                                                           their abandoned projects almost like lost
                                                                           companions. There’s grief in their
                                                                           voices. Months of work, years some-
                                                                           times, reduced to a regulatory impasse
                                                                           or an investor’s sudden withdrawal after
                                                                           “policy concerns.”
                                                                              They don’t always blame the market.
                                                                           They blame the maze.
                                                                              And yet, they try again. That’s the re-
                                                                           markable part. Innovation persists be-
                                                                           cause human curiosity persists. People
                                                                           still tinker in small labs. Students still
                                                                           sketch impossible machines in note-
             Fear isn’t irrational. Disruption can
           hurt. Workers can lose livelihoods.
           Communities can fracture.
             But fear can also delay adaptation. It
           can lead to defensive policymaking, de-
           signed more to slow change than to
           shape it responsibly.
             The result is paralysis. And paralysis
           is fertile ground for the innovation
           graveyard.

           Who decides what survives?
             Here’s the uncomfortable truth. Inno-
           vation is not a meritocracy.
             We like to believe the best idea wins.
           In reality, the best-connected idea often
           does.
             Access to policymakers. Relation-
           ships with regulators. The ability to in-
           fluence narratives. These matter as much   When decisions are opaque, when   books. Entrepreneurs still pitch ideas
           as technical brilliance.        lobbying trumps evidence, when bureau-  that make investors uncomfortable.
             A clean energy start-up without polit-  cracy values caution over curiosity,   Perhaps the innovation graveyard is
           ical backing may struggle to obtain grid   promising ideas suffocate quietly. No   inevitable. Not every idea deserves to
           access. A pharmaceutical breakthrough   headlines. No protests. Just silence.   live.
           without strong institutional allies may                            But we owe it to ourselves to ask,
           face endless trial approvals. A fintech   Escaping the graveyard   each time something promising dies,
           platform without compliance clarity   So what can policymakers and   why it died. Was it flawed? Or merely
           may burn cash while waiting for guide-  leaders do?             inconvenient?
           lines.                            First, design regulatory sandboxes   If we’re honest, we’ll admit that
             The market is not a neutral arena. It’s   that allow controlled experimentation.   power shapes progress more than we
           shaped by rules. And those rules are   India’s fintech sandbox model is a step   care to acknowledge.
           shaped by power.                in that direction. It signals openness   The challenge for policymakers, bu-
                                           without abandoning oversight.   reaucrats and corporate leaders is simple
           A balanced view                   Second, improve transparency. If an   to state, hard to practice. Don’t fear dis-
             To be fair, not every stalled innova-  innovation is rejected, explain why. Pub-  ruption. Shape it. Don’t protect systems
           tion is a victim. Some ideas fail because   lish criteria. Reduce ambiguity.   at the cost of the future. Protect the fu-
           they are poorly executed. Some are gen-  Third, protect competition. Antitrust   ture by reforming systems.
           uinely unsafe. Some are premature.   vigilance isn’t anti-business. It’s pro-in-  Because somewhere right now, in a
             Governments must weigh public in-  novation.                  modest office or a rural workshop or a
           terest. Corporations must manage risk.   Finally, cultivate institutional cou-  university dorm room, someone is build-
           Investors must allocate capital pru-  rage. That may be the hardest task. Sup-  ing something that could change the
           dently.                         porting a disruptive idea can be politi-  way we live.
             The real issue isn’t that innovation   cally risky. It can upset powerful   Whether it thrives or joins the grave-
           faces scrutiny. It’s that scrutiny is not al-  stakeholders. But avoiding that risk   yard depends less on imagination and
           ways transparent or consistent.   carries its own cost.         more on the choices we make. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[IN-DEPTH


































           Lessons from the hills



           The ecology







           of power                                                        vaji’s statecraft was rooted in a deep, al-

                                                                           most intuitive environmental literacy.
                                                                           The forests were not obstacles. The hills
                                                                           were not barriers. The monsoons were
                                                                           not inconveniences. They were allies.
                                                                              And that changes the way we think
           Shivaji’s story reminds us that power is not only about         about governance itself.
                                                                              To travel through the Western Ghats
           expansion. It’s about endurance. And endurance                  during the monsoon is to feel small. The
                                                                           mist rolls in without warning. Slopes
           requires harmony with the environment that sustains             turn slick. Paths disappear. It’s beautiful,
           you. By Pooja Mehta                                             yes. But it’s also disorienting.
                                                                              Shivaji saw possibility in that dis-
                                                                           orientation.
                  hat if the most powerful ally   at his life from a different angle. Not   Forts like Raigad, Pratapgad and Sin-
                  a ruler ever had wasn’t an   just as a warrior king or a master strate-  hagad were not chosen randomly. They
           Warmy, but a forest? That       gist, but as a leader who understood   were embedded into the geography of
           might sound poetic, even romantic. Yet   something many modern governments   the Sahyadris, rising from cliffs,
           history suggests it’s not far from the   are still struggling to grasp. Power is in-  wrapped in dense vegetation, protected
           truth. On February 19, as Maharashtra   separable from ecology.   by narrow approaches. These weren’t
           marks the birth anniversary of Chhatra-  Long before climate change became   just military installations. They were
           pati Shivaji Maharaj, it’s worth looking   a policy brief or a campaign slogan, Shi-  ecological statements. The terrain did

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Long before

                                                                             climate policy,

                                                                             power here

                                                                             listened to the

                                                                             monsoon.”



                                                                           Shivaji learned to anticipate these
                                                                           rhythms. His forces often used seasonal
                                                                           knowledge to their advantage, launching
                                                                           surprise attacks or retreating into terrain
                                                                           that became nearly impassable for ad-
                                                                           versaries during heavy rains.
                                                                              He also invested in a naval presence
                                                                           along the Konkan coast. Sea forts and
                                                                           ships weren’t just about expansion. They
                                                                           were about recognizing that power in a
                                                                           coastal, monsoon-shaped region re-
                                                                           quired maritime awareness.
                                                                              It’s tempting to view this as simple
                                                                           pragmatism. And yes, it was practical.
                                                                           But it was also ecological intelligence.
                                                                           The calendar was not just political. It
                                                                           was seasonal.
                                                                              Today, climate volatility is forcing
                                                                           governments to rethink infrastructure,
                                                                           agriculture and disaster management.
           half the defending.             from nowhere. It came from understand-  Early warning systems, adaptive crop-
             In an age when imperial powers pre-  ing how to move with the land rather   ping patterns, resilient urban design.
           ferred grand cities on plains, accessible   than against it.    These are our modern equivalents of
           and visible, Shivaji moved his capital to   There’s a lesson here for modern   reading the monsoon. Yet too often, pol-
           Raigad, perched atop a hill in the   governance. Today, environmental de-  icy lags behind science.
           Konkan region. It was harder to reach,   gradation is often framed as a trade-off.   What if we saw environmental lit-
           harder to besiege and easier to defend   Development versus forests. Growth   eracy not as a specialist skill, but as a
           with smaller forces. Geography became   versus conservation. But what if that bi-  core requirement for leadership?
           strategy.                       nary is false? What if forests are not just
             This was not environmentalism in the   resources to be extracted or preserved,   Governance beyond the battlefield
           modern sense. It was something subtler.   but systems that enable resilience?   There’s a tendency to romanticize
           It was literacy. An ability to read land   When you strip a landscape of its   warrior kings. Statues grow taller.
           the way others read maps.       ecological complexity, you also strip   Narratives grow sharper. Complexity
             And perhaps that’s where power be-  away strategic options. Floods intensify.   fades.
           gins. With attention.           Heat rises. Water vanishes. The very   But Shivaji’s legacy also includes ad-
                                           ground becomes unstable, politically   ministrative reforms, revenue systems
           Forests as intelligence networks   and literally.               and attention to agrarian stability. His
             Forests in the 17th century Deccan   Shivaji’s statecraft suggests some-  governance recognized the importance
           were not empty spaces. They were in-  thing different. Strength can be rooted in   of protecting peasantry and ensuring ag-
           habited, traversed, known intimately by   stewardship.          ricultural productivity. In a region de-
           local communities. Shivaji’s forces often                       pendent on rainfall and fragile soils, sta-
           relied on this local knowledge. Paths   The monsoon as military calendar   bility meant understanding ecological
           hidden under foliage, water sources   Anyone who has lived through an In-  limits.
           known only to villagers, seasonal   dian monsoon knows its drama. Roads   This isn’t to idealize the past. The
           changes that outsiders misjudged.   flood. Supply lines falter. Plans change.   17th century was not a green utopia.
             In many accounts, the speed and agil-  Many large armies of the time treated   Forests were used. Land was contested.
           ity of the Maratha forces baffled larger   the monsoon as a pause button. Cam-  Resources were finite. Yet there was an
           armies. But that agility did not emerge   paigns stalled. Movement slowed. But   embedded awareness that territory was

           16                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[destinations and climate policy as a
                                                                           modern challenge. But the threads con-
                                                                           nect.
                                                                              On February 19, when speeches are
                                                                           made and garlands are placed, it might
                                                                           be worth asking a quiet question. What
                                                                           would leadership look like if we truly
                                                                           treated ecology as a partner?
                                                                              Shivaji’s story reminds us that power
                                                                           is not only about expansion. It’s about
                                                                           endurance. And endurance requires har-
                                                                           mony with the environment that sustains
                                                                           you.
                                                                              We don’t need to romanticize the
                                                                           past to learn from it. We just need to
                                                                           look carefully.
                                                                              Maybe that’s the real tribute. Not just
                                                                           celebrating a birth anniversary, but re-
           not abstract. It was soil, water, forest
           cover, hill slopes.
             Contrast that with some modern de-
           velopment models that flatten hills for
           highways or drain wetlands for real es-
           tate. Efficiency today often ignores
           long-term ecological cost. And that cost
           eventually returns, usually as crisis.
             The idea that governance requires en-
           vironmental literacy may sound obvious
           now. But it’s not fully internalized.
           Budgets are still separated from bio-
           diversity. Urban planning often over-
           looks watershed logic. Political cycles
           are shorter than ecological cycles.
             In Shivaji’s time, survival demanded
           alignment with nature. Today, survival
           demands something similar, though the
           stakes are global.              orities. And priorities shape power.

           Environmental literacy as       A maharashtra lens, a global      “
           statecraft                      question                          In the Sahyadris,
             So what does environmental literacy   For readers in Maharashtra, this eco-
           really mean in governance?      logical reading of Shivaji may feel intui-  geography wasn’t
             It means understanding carrying ca-  tive. The Sahyadris are not just scenery.
           pacity before approving large projects. It   They are identity. The monsoon is not   scenery; it was
           means recognizing that deforestation up-  just weather. It’s memory.
           stream affects floods downstream. It   Yet this perspective resonates   strategy.”
           means valuing local knowledge systems   globally. In Latin America, indigenous
           alongside scientific data.      communities argue that the Amazon is a
             Shivaji’s success lay partly in inte-  living system, not just a carbon sink. In   thinking governance itself. Recognizing
           grating local networks, geography and   island nations, leaders speak of the   that forests, hills and monsoons are not
           seasonal rhythms into decision-making.   ocean as homeland, not merely territory.   footnotes in political history. They are
           He did not treat the land as a passive   In Africa’s Sahel, land restoration is   central characters.
           stage. It was an actor in the drama of   linked directly to security.   In a warming world, where floods
           power.                            Across continents, the same lesson   and fires redraw maps with unsettling
             Modern policymakers could take   surfaces. Ecological ignorance weakens   speed, this perspective feels less like
           note. Climate adaptation is not only   states. Ecological awareness strengthens   nostalgia and more like necessity.
           about technology. It’s about mindset. Do   them.                   And perhaps, standing on a rain-
           leaders see hills as obstacles to blast   Perhaps we’re only now catching up   soaked hill in the Western Ghats, watch-
           through or as buffers that protect com-  to an old truth.       ing clouds swallow a fort wall, one can
           munities? Do they see forests as revenue                        sense it. Power, at its most durable,
           streams or as infrastructure that absorbs   Power, reimagined   listens to the land.
           shocks?                           It’s easy to separate history from   The question is, are we listening
             The language we use reveals our pri-  present crises. To admire forts as tourist   now? ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[The Hidden Strain                                               sacred. We don’t talk about what it can
                                                                           cost.
     INSIGHT  When care                                                    cially in urban professional families,
                                                                              For many middle-aged adults, espe-
                                                                           caregiving arrives quietly and then takes
                                                                           over everything. A spouse develops Par-
                                                                           kinson’s. A parent’s dementia advances.
                                                                           A child’s disability requires constant su-
                                                                           pervision. At first, love carries it. Love
                                                                           explains it. Love justifies it.
           breaks                                                          comes logistics?
                                                                              But what happens when love be-

                                                                           The unspoken truth
                                                                              To admit that care has damaged a
           relationships                                                   is seen as moral failure. You’re sup-
                                                                           marriage or strained a parent–child bond
                                                                           posed to endure. You’re supposed to be
                                                                           grateful you can help. You’re supposed
                                                                           to feel honored.
                                                                              So people don’t say what they’re
           Maybe the question isn’t whether care destroys love. Maybe      really feeling.
                                                                              They don’t say that resentment some-
           it’s whether we’re willing to support the people who are        times creeps in at 2 a.m. when alarms go
           carrying love on their backs every single day. By Anaya Gupta   off again. They don’t say that they miss
                                                                           being touched as a partner rather than
                                                                           needed as a nurse. They don’t say that
               love him. I just don’t know if I still   and the slow, grinding reality of long-  sometimes they fantasize about leaving.
             like him. It’s a sentence people   term caregiving. It comes with guilt. It   Because who leaves someone who is
           Iwhisper, rarely say aloud. It usually   comes with shame. And often, it comes   sick?
           comes after years of hospital visits,   too late.                  The silence becomes part of the bur-
           medication schedules, interrupted sleep   We talk about care as noble, selfless,   den. Guilt seals it shut.








































           18                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             Love doesn’t collapse
                                                                             in a single moment; it

                                                                             thins quietly under
                                                                             the weight of

                                                                             constant
                                                                             responsibility.”


           Can romance survive
           responsibility?
             Romance thrives on choice. Caregiv-
           ing, especially long-term caregiving,
           often eliminates choice.
             When one person’s body becomes
           another person’s responsibility, the dy-
           namic shifts. A husband bathes his wife.
           A wife monitors her husband’s medicat-
           ion. Intimacy becomes clinical. Affec-
           tion becomes functional.
             Many couples try to preserve their
           former roles. They joke, they reminisce,
           they try to schedule “date nights” be-
           tween physiotherapy sessions. Some-
           times it works. Sometimes it even
           deepens connection. Shared hardship
           can bond people in profound ways.
             But often, slowly, almost invisibly,   enter a life organized around medication   advanced dementia. He quits a job
           the balance changes.            charts.                         abroad. His friends are building careers,
             Desire fades not because love dis-  Time loses ownership. Your schedule   raising children. He is navigating incon-
           appears but because exhaustion con-  is no longer yours. Even leisure feels   tinence and confusion. When she lashes
           sumes it. The caregiver is constantly   conditional. Can I leave for two hours?   out in frustration, he absorbs it. When
           alert. They are the one who anticipates   What if something happens?   she doesn’t recognize him, something
           falls, monitors sugar levels, notices sub-  Caregivers often remain physically   fractures.
           tle mood changes. It’s difficult to feel   present but psychologically eroded.   He tells no one that sometimes he
           romantic when you’re always on call.   They are there. They are functioning.   feels angry at her for forgetting him.
             Sexuality vanishes quietly. Not in   But inside, parts of them have thinned   How could he? She’s ill.
           dramatic fights, but in postponed con-  out from constant giving.   Care creates moral hierarchies. The
           versations. “Maybe next week.” “Let’s   And here’s the uncomfortable truth:   sick person’s pain is visible and legiti-
           just rest tonight.” Weeks become   love doesn’t always survive that erosion.   mate. The caregiver’s pain is often dis-
           months. Months become years.                                    missed as secondary.
             And with that, something tender be-  When duty swallows affection   But secondary pain still hurts.
           gins to thin.                     Consider a woman in her late forties
                                           caring for her husband after a spinal in-  The myth of endless strength
           The erosion of identity         jury. In the first year, she says she felt   Society loves stories of tireless care-
             Long-term care does not only alter   heroic. In the third year, she felt invisi-  givers. We celebrate sacrifice. We post
           relationships. It slowly deletes personal   ble. By the sixth, she says she felt like   inspirational quotes. We praise resil-
           identity.                       “equipment.”                    ience.
             Ambitions are paused indefinitely.   That word stays with you.   What we don’t acknowledge is that
           That promotion? It requires travel. That   She still loved him. But she no longer   resilience has limits.
           fellowship abroad? Impossible. The   felt seen as a partner. Their conver-  Research in psychology consistently
           book you meant to write? Maybe some-  sations revolved around appointments,   shows high levels of burnout, depression
           day.                            bills, pain management. He was suffer-  and anxiety among long-term care-
             Friendships fade. You cancel enough   ing physically. She was unraveling   givers. Sleep deprivation alone can alter
           dinners and invitations stop coming. It’s   quietly.            mood regulation and cognitive function-
           not malicious. People just don’t know   Or think of the adult son who moves   ing. Chronic stress elevates cortisol
           what to say. They don’t know how to   back home to care for his mother with   levels. Over time, the body keeps the

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[to family. “I sometimes wish it would   policies lag behind demographic real-
                                           end.” They immediately clarify. They   ities. Flexible hours and paid leave are
                                           don’t mean they wish harm. They mean   inconsistent. Long-term care insurance
                                           they wish the endlessness would stop.   is inaccessible for many.
                                             The taboo around these thoughts   When systems fail, families absorb
                                           keeps caregivers isolated. And isolation   the shock.
            “                              shrinks.                        ships stretch thin.
                                           corrodes relationships further.
                                                                              And within those families, relation-
                                             If you can’t speak honestly, intimacy

                                                                           What honesty might offer
            Guilt silences
                                                                              Perhaps the most radical act in care-
                                             It would be unfair and untrue, to sug-
            caregivers so                  When care and love coexist      giving is honesty.
                                           gest that caregiving always destroys
                                                                              To say, “I’m tired.”
            effectively that even          love. Many couples and families find   To say, “I miss us.”
                                                                              To say, “This is harder than I ex-
                                           new forms of connection. Some describe
            their exhaustion               a quieter, steadier bond. A love less   pected.”
                                           about excitement and more about pres-  Not as accusation. Not as abandon-
            begins to feel like            ence.                           ment. But as truth.
                                             But even in those stories, there is   Mental health professionals increas-
            betrayal.”                     grief.                          ingly advocate for caregiver support
                                             They grieve the version of their rela-  groups, structured respite and counsel-
                                           tionship that existed before illness. They   ing not only for patients but for partners
           score.                          grieve spontaneity. They grieve equality.   and family members. Naming the strain
             And yet, when caregivers admit fa-  The difference is that in healthier   does not mean withdrawing love. It
           tigue, they’re often met with platitudes.   adaptations, grief is acknowledged   means protecting it.
           “You’re so strong.” “You’re doing God’s   rather than denied. They seek respite   We need a language that allows care-
           work.” “At least you have each other.”   care. They ask for help. They allow   givers to be devoted and exhausted, lov-
             Strength becomes a trap. If you’re   themselves to admit ambivalence with-  ing and resentful, committed and griev-
           strong, you’re not allowed to break.   out shame.               ing, all at once.
             So people stay. They cope. They   Love survives not because the burden   Because that’s the reality.
           swallow resentment. They develop   is light, but because it is shared.
           headaches, back pain, hypertension.                             A final reflection
           They stop recognizing themselves.   Policy, distance and the global   If you’re caring for someone right
             Meanwhile, the relationship they’re   family                  now, you probably didn’t choose this
           fighting to preserve becomes defined by   In an increasingly mobile world,   version of your life. You stepped into it
           survival rather than joy.       many adult children live continents   because love demanded something of
                                           away from aging parents. They wire   you.
           Guilt as a silencer             money, coordinate care remotely, call   But love, if it’s going to survive, also
             Guilt is perhaps the most powerful   daily.                   demands something back. It demands
           force in caregiving.              Distance creates another kind of   boundaries. It demands rest. It demands
             It tells you that wanting space is self-  strain. The sibling who stays becomes   that your identity not disappear entirely
           ish. That feeling anger is cruel. That   the primary caregiver. Resentment   into someone else’s needs.
           grieving the life you lost is disloyal.   simmers quietly. The one abroad feels   Care can be beautiful. It can also be
             It convinces you that if love were   guilt and defensiveness. “I’m doing   brutal.
           pure enough, you wouldn’t feel de-  what I can.” “You don’t understand what   Pretending otherwise helps no one.
           pleted.                         it’s like here.”                   Maybe the question isn’t whether
             But love does not eliminate human   Urban professionals often face a sim-  care destroys love. Maybe it’s whether
           limits.                         ilar tension. They juggle demanding ca-  we’re willing to support the people who
             In therapy rooms across cities, care-  reers with caregiving duties, sometimes   are carrying love on their backs every
           givers confess things they’ve never said   without institutional support. Workplace   single day. ■

           20                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[FEATURE STORY








































                                                      The Family Calendar


                  hat’s on the calendar this
                  week? It sounds like a harm-
           Wless question. Domestic, even    The dates that
           cozy. But in many homes, the answer
           isn’t about birthdays or dinner plans. It’s
           about visa renewals, court hearings, che-
           motherapy cycles, loan repayments,
           school admissions. It’s about survival.
             Behind the fridge magnets and color-          quietly run
           coded planners lies a quieter truth. Fam-
           ilies don’t just run on love. They run on
           dates.

           The invisible architecture of time
             In a two-bedroom apartment in                           our lives
           Mumbai, Rhea keeps a wall calendar
           near the kitchen. At first glance, it looks
           ordinary. But lean closer and you’ll see
           small, tight handwriting filling the
           squares. “Dad review.” “Passport ap-  The calendar doesn’t capture the arguments, the fatigue,
           pointment.” “Hearing.” “EMI.” “School
           fee last date.”                 the occasional resentment. But it hints at them. And it also
             Each date holds weight.       reflects something steadier. By Rajeev Khanna
             Her father’s dialysis sessions fall
           every Tuesday and Friday. The court
           hearing for a property dispute, now in its   We talk about family as emotion. But   When bureaucracy becomes
           fourth year, is marked in red. Her hus-  family is also logistics. It’s coordination,   domestic
           band’s work visa renewal is circled   anticipation and a kind of low-grade   In migrant households, the calendar
           twice. Missing that deadline isn’t an in-  anxiety that hums in the background.   becomes a legal document of sorts. For
           convenience. It could mean uprooting   Someone has to remember. Someone al-  families navigating immigration sys-
           their life.                     ways does.                      tems, dates are everything. A single

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[missed biometric appointment can reset   what’s coming. It also reminds you that   Until she forgets once and the con-
           years of effort. An expired residency   time is moving.         sequences are immediate.
           permit can separate parents from chil-
           dren.                           The double-income juggle        Young adults and the first
             Ask anyone who has stood in line   For working parents, especially in   calendar
           outside a passport office before sunrise.   dual-income households, the family cal-  For many in their twenties and early
           The tension isn’t loud, but it’s there.   endar is practically a third partner.   thirties, adulthood begins the day you
           Papers are clutched carefully. WhatsApp   There’s the shared Google calendar,   start tracking your own deadlines. Rent
           groups buzz with reminders. “Don’t for-  the office planner, the school circular   due. Credit card bill. Passport renewal.
           get originals.” “Carry two photos.”   pinned to the board. Parent-teacher   Tax filing.
           “Reach early.”                  meetings. Performance appraisals. Vac-  There’s a small shock in realizing no
             These aren’t dramatic events.   cination schedules. Utility bill deadlines.   one else is keeping track.
           They’re procedural. Yet they determine   Sometimes it feels absurd. Two   You create reminders. Set alarms.
           futures.                        adults with postgraduate degrees stand-  Scribble notes. Slowly, you inherit the
             The same goes for court dates. A di-  ing in the kitchen debating whose turn it   invisible architecture your parents once
           vorce hearing. A maintenance petition. A   is to attend sports day because both have   managed for you.
           tenancy dispute. In theory, the law   client presentations.        And maybe you understand them a
           moves on its own timeline. In reality,   But this is modern family life. Co-  little better.
           families orbit around it. Work shifts are   ordinated down to the hour.
           swapped. Children are picked up by   And beneath the coordination lies   More than squares on a page
           neighbors. Hope rises and falls accord-  something tender. The effort. The quiet   It’s tempting to see the family calen-
           ing to adjournments.            decision, again and again, to show up.   dar as mundane. A grid of boxes. A dig-
             You begin to measure your year not                            ital notification.
           in festivals, but in hearings.   The emotional weight of dates     But look closer. It’s a map of respon-
                                             Not all dates are administrative.   sibility. A record of resilience.
           Hospital cycles and waiting rooms   Some are anniversaries of loss. The day   It tells the story of what a family is
             If you’ve ever accompanied someone   a parent passed away. The date of a mis-  carrying at any given moment. Legal
           through long-term treatment, you know   carriage. The morning a job offer was   battles that stretch for years. Illnesses
           how quickly life reorganizes itself   rescinded.                faced with routine courage. Dreams tied
           around hospital schedules.        These aren’t always written down,   to embassy stamps. Children growing
             Three weeks on. One week off. Re-  yet they live in the body. As the month   up between tuition schedules and vacci-
           peat.                           approaches, moods shift. A certain rest-  nation charts.
             Chemotherapy doesn’t just alter the   lessness creeps in. You might not even   The calendar doesn’t capture the ar-
           body. It reshapes the household calen-  connect it immediately. Then you glance   guments, the fatigue, the occasional re-
           dar. Vacations are postponed. Weddings   at the calendar and think, oh.   sentment. But it hints at them. And it
           attended briefly. Even joy is penciled in   Time doesn’t just move forward. It   also reflects something steadier. Com-
           cautiously. “If the blood counts are   circles back.            mitment. So the next time someone
           stable,” someone says.            In semi-urban households, where ex-  asks, “What’s on the calendar?” maybe
             In many urban families, caregiving is   tended families often live nearby, the   pause.
           squeezed between office hours and   calendar is collective. One aunt re-  Because behind that question is the
           school runs. The hospital appointment is   members the court date. A cousin tracks   quiet machinery of family life. The
           at 11 am, but traffic means leaving by 9.   the medical review. There’s comfort in   planning, the remembering, the showing
           The review might take two hours or six.   shared vigilance. It’s not just your bur-  up. It’s not glamorous. It’s rarely posted
           You carry snacks, chargers, a shawl.   den.                     online. But it’s what keeps households
           You wait.                         Still, someone usually carries the   running.
             And you count.                mental load more than others. Often a   In the end, perhaps that’s what
             Not days exactly, but milestones.   woman. She’s the one who knows the   family really is. Not just shared blood or
           “Two more cycles.” “Just one more   document expiry dates, the school dead-  shared space. But shared time. Carefully
           scan.” The calendar becomes both   lines, the medication refills. She doesn’t   marked. Carefully guarded. And, despite
           enemy and ally. It reminds you of   announce it. She just remembers.   everything, moved through together. ■

           22                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[PROFILE




























           Ravindra Jain                                                   Growing up in sound

                                                                              Aligarh in the 1940s wasn’t exactly a
                                                                           cultural capital. But Jain grew up in a
           The composer                                                    family that valued literature and music.
                                                                           His father, a Sanskrit scholar, encour-
                                                                           aged intellectual curiosity. The house-
                                                                           hold echoed with classical ragas, devo-
                                                                           tional verses and poetry recitations.
           who never saw                                                   became landscape. Voices had texture.
                                                                              For a boy who couldn’t see, sound
                                                                           Footsteps had mood. Even silence meant
                                                                           something.
                                                                              He trained in classical music early
           the frame                                                       and rhythms. Teachers noticed some-
                                                                           on, learning to internalize complex ragas
                                                                           thing unusual. He didn’t merely mem-
                                                                           orize compositions. He seemed to in-
                                                                           habit them. When he sang, it wasn’t
                                                                           mechanical. It was interpretive. You felt
           Cinema is often obsessed with what’s visible. Jain              he could “see” something others missed.
                                                                              Perhaps because when vision is ab-
           reminds us that what’s invisible can be just as                 sent, imagination grows restless.
           powerful. By Karan Malhotra                                     Mumbai and the leap of faith
                                                                              Moving to Mumbai in the 1970s was
                                                                           a gamble. The Hindi film industry, pop-
                 ow do you compose for a sun-  to answer that question in ways cinema   ularly known as Bollywood, was
                 rise you’ve never seen? For   had never quite imagined. Ravindra Jain   fiercely competitive. Studios were dom-
           Hmost film composers, music be-  entered the world without sight. Yet he   inated by established composers. Pro-
           gins with the image. A river flowing ac-  would compose melodies that millions   ducers were not exactly lining up to hire
           ross the screen, a lover’s hesitant glance,   can still hum decades later. He never   a visually impaired newcomer.
           a hero walking into battle. They watch,   saw the frame, but he shaped how gener-  Yet Jain persisted. He listened care-
           pause, rewind, scribble notes. But what   ations felt about it.   fully to scripts being narrated to him.
           if there is no image? What if the screen   His story isn’t just about talent over-  Directors would describe scenes in de-
           remains permanently dark?       coming adversity. It’s about imagination   tail. A forest at dusk. A wedding under
             On February 28, 1944, in Aligarh,   so powerful that it made vision almost   lanterns. A lonely road. He absorbed
           India, a child was born who would go on   optional.             these descriptions like someone mem-

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[“



            He never saw the


            frame, yet he


            taught millions

            how to feel it.”




           orizing a map.                  ferently. Directors described the emo-  A different kind of popular
             And then he translated them into   tional arc. Assistants narrated gestures.   The 1970s and 80s were loud dec-
           music.                          Sometimes he would ask questions that   ades in Hindi film music. Disco was ris-
             One of his early breakthroughs came   surprised them.         ing. Orchestras were expanding. Synthe-
           with the film Chor Machaye Shor. But it   “Is the light harsh or gentle?”   sizers entered the scene. Yet Jain’s
           was later collaborations with filmmaker   “Are they standing close, or is there   music often leaned toward melody-
           Rajshri Productions and especially the   distance between them?”   driven simplicity rooted in Indian classi-
           banner’s family dramas that cemented   He wasn’t asking about visuals for   cal traditions.
           his place in Indian cinema. Films such   curiosity. He was translating physical   He wasn’t trying to compete with
           as Chitchor and Ankhiyon Ke Jharokhon   cues into emotional tones. Harsh light   spectacle. He was creating intimacy.
           Se carried melodies that felt intimate, al-  might become a sharper orchestration.   Take the television epic Ramayan,
           most handcrafted.               Physical distance might be reflected in a   one of India’s most watched serials. Jain
             Listen to “Gori Tera Gaon Bada   sparse arrangement.          composed its title track and background
           Pyara” or the title track of Ankhiyon Ke   It’s fascinating, really. He composed   score. For millions, his music became
           Jharokhon Se. They don’t scream for at-  for images he’d never seen, yet his   inseparable from their understanding of
           tention. They linger. Soft. Sincere. Al-  songs fit seamlessly. The audience never   an ancient epic. Sunday mornings across
           most shy.                       felt a mismatch. If anything, his music   the country would fall silent as that fa-
             It’s tempting to say his blindness   often elevated the scene beyond its vi-  miliar melody played.
           gave him depth. That would be too sim-  sual limits.               He didn’t see the mythological cos-
           plistic. But it’s fair to say that because   He once remarked in interviews that   tumes or grand sets. But he sensed their
           he couldn’t rely on spectacle, he relied   he composed by “seeing through the   scale. His compositions balanced devo-
           on emotion.                     mind.” That phrase stays with you.   tion with accessibility. They felt sacred
                                             There’s a lesson there for filmmakers   without being distant.
           Composing without seeing        and artists everywhere. Sometimes   International audiences might com-
             Film music is usually reactive. The   we’re so bound to the literal frame that   pare his approach to composers who
           composer watches the edited sequence   we forget cinema is ultimately about   privilege leitmotif and thematic continu-
           and scores accordingly. Jain worked dif-  feeling.              ity over bombast. His work reminds us

           24                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[“



                                                                             For him, sound

                                                                             wasn’t support for

                                                                             the image; it was


                                                                             the image.”


                                                                           empathy as much as artistry.
                                                                           The emotional core
                                                                              What sets Jain apart isn’t just techni-
                                                                           cal skill. It’s emotional clarity. His songs
                                                                           often center on longing, innocence, de-
                                                                           votion. There’s very little cynicism.
                                                                              Maybe that’s why his melodies age
                                                                           well. They aren’t tied to flashy trends.
                                                                           They’re built on human feeling.
                                                                              When you listen to his work today,
                                                                           there’s a kind of gentle honesty. It does-
                                                                           n’t try to overwhelm you. It invites you
                                                                           in.
                                                                              And perhaps that’s why the phrase
                                                                           “The Composer Who Never Saw the
                                                                           Frame” feels so fitting. Cinema is often
                                                                           obsessed with what’s visible. Jain re-
                                                                           minds us that what’s invisible can be
                                                                           just as powerful.
                                                                           A final reflection
                                                                              He passed away in 2015, leaving be-
           that cultural specificity can still resonate   physical sight, public spotlight must feel   hind hundreds of compositions. But
           universally.                    secondary.                      numbers don’t capture legacy. Legacy is
                                                                           when a song plays at a wedding and
           Recognition and reality         Disability and the creative     someone hums along without remember-
             Over the years, Jain received multi-  imagination             ing who wrote it. Legacy is when a de-
           ple accolades, including the prestigious   In conversations about disability, we   votional hymn still echoes in a small-
           Filmfare Award for Best Music Director.   often default to inspiration narratives.   town temple decades later.
           But recognition in the arts is rarely lin-  “Despite his blindness…” we begin, as   Sometimes I wonder what he “saw”
           ear. Trends change. New composers   if limitation is the headline. Jain’s life   when he composed a love song. Was it a
           emerge. Industries move on quickly.   complicates that framing.   memory of a voice? A texture of si-
             What remained constant was his dis-  He didn’t compose despite blindness.   lence? A vibration in the air? We’ll
           cipline. He continued composing for   He composed with it. It shaped his   never quite know.
           films, television and devotional albums.   method. It sharpened his listening. It de-  What we do know is this. He trusted
           He mentored young singers. He wrote   manded trust in collaborators.   sound more than sight. He trusted imagi-
           lyrics as well, often weaving poetry and   His career also challenges industries   nation more than image.
           melody together in a way that felt or-  to rethink accessibility. How many tal-  In a world saturated with visuals,
           ganic.                          ented individuals are excluded simply   filters and endless scrolling, that feels
             It would be misleading to paint his   because systems aren’t designed to ac-  almost radical.
           life as a continuous triumph. The film   commodate them? Jain navigated a   Maybe the real lesson of Ravindra
           industry can be unforgiving. There were   space that wasn’t built for him. Imagine   Jain’s life isn’t about limitation at all.
           projects that failed. Songs that didn’t   what could happen if creative ecosys-  Maybe it’s about listening more care-
           chart. Periods of relative quiet.   tems were intentionally inclusive.   fully. About recognizing that art doesn’t
             Yet even in those quieter phases, he   For students of film and music, his   always begin with what we see. Some-
           kept working. Not for visibility. For   process offers a fascinating study. Strip   times, it begins with what we feel.
           music.                          away visuals. Focus on script, mood,   And that’s something every com-
             And perhaps that’s the point. When   rhythm of dialogue. Can you compose   poser, filmmaker and listener can carry
           you’ve lived your entire life without   purely from narrative? It’s an exercise in   forward. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[EXPLORATION







































                                                                              There’s something psychological
           Sweet Company                                                   here. We tend to pair intensity with com-
                                                                           fort. Think of how we add milk to coffee
                                                                           or lemon to fish. Strong flavors are often
                                                                           buffered. A plain strawberry can be sur-
           Why strawberries                                                prisingly sharp, especially if it’s not per-
                                                                           fectly ripe. Pairing it feels safer.
                                                                              And perhaps, more indulgent.

           are never alone                                                 The ritual of pairing
                                                                              In many cultures, strawberries have
                                                                           long been associated with celebration. In
                                                                           England, they are famously served with
                                                                           cream at Wimbledon. In Japan, straw-
           Maybe strawberries aren’t never alone because they need         berry shortcake is a symbol of festive
                                                                           occasions. Across Europe and North
           to be paired. Maybe it’s because we do. By Meera Reddy          America, chocolate-dipped strawberries
                                                                           have become shorthand for romance.
                                                                              Notice how rarely the fruit stands
                                                                           alone in these rituals. It’s not just about
                 ave you ever noticed that straw-  The discomfort of simplicity   taste. It’s about narrative. Strawberries
                 berries rarely arrive by them-  A strawberry on its own is a bold   with cream signal summer. With choco-
           Hselves? Order them at a café and   thing. Bright red, fragile, unapologeti-  late, they whisper intimacy. On cake,
           they come crowned with cream. Buy   cally sweet and sour at the same time. It   they promise celebration.
           them at a bakery and they’re tucked into   doesn’t hide its seeds. It doesn’t pretend   Food is never just food. It’s context.
           sponge cake. Even at home, we melt   to be subtle. Maybe that’s why we soften   It’s memory.
           chocolate, sprinkle sugar, or fold them   it with cream or sugar. Maybe simplicity,   I remember being handed a bowl of
           into yogurt. A bowl of plain strawberries   when it’s this vivid, makes us uneasy.   strawberries and sugar as a child. We’d
           on a table feels almost… incomplete. As   Cream smooths the tartness. Choco-  sprinkle the sugar, wait for the juices to
           if something is missing.        late deepens the sweetness. Cake gives it   pool at the bottom, then spoon it over
             It’s strange, isn’t it? In a world that   structure. Together, they become dessert.   vanilla ice cream. It wasn’t fancy. But it
           celebrates minimalism, strawberries re-  Alone, the strawberry feels like a state-  felt like an event. The strawberry was
           main loyal to company.          ment.                           the star, yes, but the supporting cast

           26                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[“


                                                                             We soften

                                                                             strawberries with
                                                                             cream the way we

                                                                             soften ourselves
           made it theatrical.             The metaphor we don’t admit
             Would that same bowl, unsweetened   Maybe this is why strawberries make   with company.”
           and plain, have felt as magical? I’m not   such an easy metaphor for relationships.
           sure.                           We rarely want to be consumed alone.
                                           We want context. We want to be soft-  moment. Their green caps still attached,
           Sweetness needs contrast        ened, complemented, understood.   their surfaces uneven and real. They
             From a culinary standpoint, straw-  There’s a quiet discomfort in stand-  don’t look lonely. They look abundant.
           berries are fascinating. They carry natu-  ing by oneself, unadorned. It’s true for   We’re the ones who imagine they
           ral sugars balanced by acidity. That   fruit. It’s true for people.   need company.
           acidity is what makes them refreshing,   Urban life especially encourages   There’s beauty in simplicity, even if
           but it’s also what makes them restless on   pairing. Networking events, curated   it makes us pause. A plain strawberry
           the palate. Cream introduces fat, which   dinner parties, brunch with friends.   asks you to pay attention. No sugar to
           rounds out sharpness. Chocolate brings   Even dating apps frame connection as   distract you. No cream to cushion the
           bitterness, which deepens the flavor.   essential. Being single can feel like   edges. Just flavor, direct and honest.
           Cake adds texture.              being a strawberry without cream, per-  Of course, I’ll still dip them in choc-
             In other words, strawberries invite   fectly fine but somehow perceived as   olate sometimes. I’m not immune to rit-
           conversation.                   unfinished.                     ual. And yes, strawberries and cream
             Chefs talk about balance all the time.   But here’s the thing. A strawberry   taste like summer in a way that’s hard to
           Acid, fat, salt, sweet. A perfect bite is   doesn’t lose its identity when paired. It   argue with.
           rarely one-dimensional. Perhaps straw-  doesn’t dissolve into the cake. If any-  But every now and then, I try one on
           berries are simply honest about this.   thing, it becomes more visible. The red   its own. It feels like listening to a solo
           They almost demand collaboration.   against white cream. The gloss against   instrument before the orchestra joins in.
             Yet, when you taste a perfectly ripe   dark chocolate. Pairing, at its best, high-  Clear. Slightly sharp. Surprisingly com-
           strawberry, warm from the sun, some-  lights individuality rather than erasing it.   plete.
           thing shifts. It’s complete. The sweet-  That’s a comforting thought.   Maybe strawberries aren’t never
           ness blooms slowly. The acidity feels                           alone because they need to be paired.
           bright, not aggressive. In that moment,   Rethinking the solitary bowl   Maybe it’s because we do.
           you realize the fruit never actually   The next time you see strawberries   And that says as much about us as it
           needed accompaniment. We did.   displayed alone at a market stall, take a   does about the fruit. ■

           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[ASTROLOGY  HOROSCOPES                             February 16-28, 2026










           ARIES                                           LIBRA
           March 21 - April 19                             Sept. 23 - October 22

                     You may feel the need to slow down and reflect.   Routine, health and productivity call for atten-
                     Not every battle requires action. A quiet       tion. Small changes improve your energy signifi-
                     breakthrough happens when you pause. Financial   cantly. Avoid procrastination. Relationships im-
                     matters remain steady, but avoid impulsive risks.   prove when you make space for practical
                     Rest strengthens clarity.                       support

           TAURUS                                          SCORPIO
           April 20 - May 20                               October 23 - November 21

                     Friendships and social connections uplift you. A   Scorpio, creativity, romance and self-expression
                     collaborative idea may show promise. Romance    flow freely. This is a beautiful time to reconnect
                     feels comfortable and supportive. Stay practical   with joy. Financial matters remain stable if you
                     with shared expenses and avoid lending money    avoid emotional spending but avoid careless-
                     casually.                                       ness.

           GEMINI                                          SAGITTARIUS
           May 21 - June 20                                Nov. 22 - December 21

                     Career attention increases. A responsibility may   Sagittarius, home and emotional grounding be-
                     feel demanding, but recognition follows. Choose   come priorities. Don’t worry, a family discussion
                     diplomacy over speed in conversations. Personal   may clear lingering doubts. Work progresses
                     relationships benefit when you separate work    quietly behind the scenes. Balance ambition with
                     stress from home life.                          inner peace.

           CANCER                                          CAPRICORN
           June 21 - July 22                               December 22 - January 19

                     Hope and optimism return. Travel, study, or spir-  Communication strengthens your position. Im-
                     itual exploration brings renewal. Emotional con-  portant discussions move forward productively.
                     nections deepen through meaningful discussions.   Short travel or new learning may expand your
                     Trust your instincts—they guide you toward sta-  outlook. Financial planning continues to sta-
                     bility.                                         bilize your path.

           LEO                                             AQUARIUS
           July 23 - August 22                             January 20 - February 18

                     Leo, emotional intensity rises, especially around   Aquarius, focus shifts to finances and personal
                     shared finances or commitments. Honest com-     values. Budgeting and long-term thinking bring
                     munication resolves misunderstandings. Focus    reassurance. Emotionally, you feel more
                     on long-term security rather than quick gains. Be   grounded. Choose stability over impulse. Care-
                     careful.                                        lessness may cause problem.

           VIRGO                                           PISCES
           August 23 - September 22                        February 19 - March 20

                     Virgo, partnerships remain central. Balance is   Your season begins, bringing renewed con-
                     key, neither overgiving nor withdrawing. Keep   fidence and self-awareness. Set intentions
                     in mind, professional cooperation brings suc-   clearly. Relationships deepen when you express
                     cess. Be careful, patience will prevent unnec-  your needs honestly. Trust yourself, you’re
                     essary tension.                                 stronger than you realize.


           28                                               www.revoir.in REVOIR Magazine | FEBRUARY 16 2026]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[READERS' FEEDBACK



             LETTERS






                                           K.K. Mahajan, New Delhi, India
           India-US trade deal: A costly
           compromise?                                                     in celebrity lending and bounced cheque
             The recent India-US interim trade deal,   Echoes of ancient ties: Tamil-  culture, which burdens honest creditors.
           announced amid fanfare by President   Brahmi on Egyptian tombs   Bollywood must introspect: unchecked
           Trump, has ignited fierce controversy.   Researchers have unearthed a stun-  extravagance fuels such scandals. It's
           Critics like Shashi Tharoor decry it as a   ning 2000-year-old Tamil-Brahmi in-  time stars prioritize integrity over
           "pre-committed purchase pact," alleging   scription on Egyptian tombs, bridging   image. Stronger financial literacy and
           India must buy $500 billion in US goods,   two ancient civilizations in an unprece-  legal deterrence can prevent repeats. Let
           slash tariffs to zero on items like pulses   dented way. Dating to the early Chris-  this be a deterrent for tinsel town's elite.
           and sorghum and curb Russian oil   tian era, the graffiti, featuring Tamil   Naresh K. Khanna, Delhi, India
           imports, surrendering a $45 billion trade   names like "Anthai", suggests South In-
           surplus. Opposition leaders, including   dian traders ventured deep into the Nile
           Akhilesh Yadav and Mallikarjun Kharge,   Valley, leaving linguistic footprints   End of an era: Sarla Maheshwari's
           warn it floods markets with cheap   amid pharaonic grandeur.    legacy
           American agriculture, devastating Indian   This discovery, from sites near Alex-  The passing of Sarla Maheshwari,
           farmers already reeling from price   andria, rewrites maritime history, ev-  the iconic Doordarshan newsreader, at
           crashes.                        idencing robust Indo-Egyptian ex-  71 marks the end of a golden chapter in
             Commerce Minister Piyush Goyal   changes predating Roman dominance.   Indian broadcasting. With her poised
           dismisses these as "misleading," insisting   Tamil-Brahmi, an early script from San-  diction and impeccable sari-clad pres-
           protections for dairy and local interests   gam-era Tamil Nadu, hints at seafaring   ence, she defined prime-time news for
           remain intact. Yet, opaque terms and   merchants navigating Red Sea routes,   millions in the 1980s-90s, delivering
           Trump's tariff threats expose diplomatic   fostering cultural osmosis.   updates on everything from Indira Gan-
           fragility. This isn't reciprocity; it's   Such finds challenge Eurocentric   dhi's assassination to economic liberal-
           leverage lost. India must renegotiate for   narratives, affirming India's global an-  ization.
           equitable terms, prioritizing farmers over   tiquity. Urgent excavations and interdis-  Maheshwari's measured tone, calm
           fleeting optics.                ciplinary studies are needed to illumi-  amid crises like the Bhopal gas tragedy,
           Ravi Kumar Gupta, New Delhi, India   nate these forgotten links, enriching our   made DD a national unifier when TV
                                           shared heritage.                was a novelty. She embodied dignity,
                                           Kishore Patil, Mumbai, Maharashtra,   training generations including Salma
           No-confidence motion on speaker    India                        Sultan and Tejeshwar Singh, while
             The no-confidence motion against                              breaking barriers for women in media.
           Lok Sabha Speaker Om Birla under-                                  Her demise evokes nostalgia for au-
           scores the need for unwavering imparti-  Justice beyond stardom: Rajpal   thentic journalism, unsullied by TRP
           ality in parliamentary proceedings. As   Yadav's jail term      chases. Tributes pour in; let’s honor her
           the custodian of House decorum, the   The recent jailing of Bollywood   by reviving public service broadcast-
           Speaker's role demands balanced facili-  comedian Rajpal Yadav for cheque   ing's ethos. Rest in peace, voice of the
           tation of debates, ensuring all voices,   bounce underscores a vital message: no   nation.
           government and opposition, are heard   celebrity is above the law. Once a   Savita Sharma, Dehradun, Uttarak-
           equitably.                      household name for his comic timing,   hand, India
             This motion arises from concerns   Yadav's financial impropriety, default-
           over procedural fairness, urging a re-  ing on a ₹5 crore loan, exposes the
           view to strengthen democratic norms.     darker side of fame. Courts have rightly   Letters (limited to one hundred
           7It reflects the maturity of India's Parlia-  sentenced him to six months, rejecting   words) are welcome and should
                                                                              be addressed to the Editor at
           ment, where constructive dialogue re-  bail pleas and emphasizing accountabil-  Email: mail@magazine.revoir.in
           solves differences, fostering national   ity.
           unity under constitutional mandates.   This case highlights systemic issues


             NOTICE:  The publishers regret that they cannot accept liability for error or omissions con-
             tained in this publication, however caused. The opinions and views contained in this pub-
             lication are not necessarily those of the publishers. Readers are advised to seek specialist ad-
             vice before acting on information contained in this publication, which is provided for
             general use and may not be appropriate for the readers’ particular circumstances.



           FEBRUARY 16 2026 | REVOIR Magazine www.revoir.in                                            29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Photo credit: Marcus L.




                                                          Look at the stars. See their beauty. And in
                                                          that beauty, see yourself. - Draya Mooney]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[YOUR  WINDOW   T O    THE  WORLD!











































                            UNLOCK THE WORLD WITH WWW.REVOIR.IN]]></page></pages></Search>